<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Tracer diffusion of network formers and multicomponent diffusion in dacitic and rhyolitic melts</title>
				<funder ref="#_vfWC5dB">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSF</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_Rhv4kzn">
					<orgName type="full">NSERC</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Don</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker','</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Geological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Geology and Center for Glass Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">McGill University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>H3A 2A7</postCode>
									<settlement>Montreal</settlement>
									<region>Quebec</region>
									<country>Canada &apos;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Troy</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<address>
									<postCode>180-3590</postCode>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Tracer diffusion of network formers and multicomponent diffusion in dacitic and rhyolitic melts</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">09E045C8A38100B84CFC5AF1C42F2D53</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received February 26, 199 1; accepted in revised form November 20, 199</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Tracer diffusivities of Si, B, and Ga were measured in anhydrous dacitic and rhyolitic melts at 1 .O GPa and 1300 to 1600°C. Diffusivities were fit to the following Arrhenius equations: in the dacite in the rhyolite Dsi = 5.59 X lO-2 exp(-383/RT) Dsi = 1.04 X lo-" exp(-139/RT) DB = 1.20 X lo-* exp(-319/RT) DB = 1.78 X 10-l exp(-4OO/RT) DGa = 3.08 X 10m4 exp(-268/RT) DGa = 1.40 X 10m2 exp(-347/RT)</p><p>where diffusivities and pre-exponential factors are in m2/s, and activation energies are in kJ/mol. In each melt silicon is the slowest diffusing cation followed by B and then Ga in the rhyolitic melt; in the dacitic melt B and Ga diffusivities are virtually identical. The low activation energy for Si in the rhyolitic melt ( 139 kJ/mol) is proposed to be due to reduction of the Si-0 bond strength by clustering of alkalies.</p><p>Clustering of network modifiers near Si cations is not as great in the dacitic melt because fewer of the network modifiers are alkalies, but instead are alkaline earths and transition metals. Measured difisivities of B and Ga are lower than diffusivities previously measured for nonnetwork modifiers, even the modifiers that have a similar charge and a larger ionic radius, i.e., Eu'+. Differences between B and Ga diffusion in rhyolite are related to the large proportion of B in trigonal coordination in these melts whereas Ga is only in tetrahedral coordination. Activation energies for Ga diffusion are presumed similar to those necessary for aluminum tracer diffusion. The gallium activation energies are also similar to the activation energies for viscous transport in these two melts and the activation energy for Si-Al interdiffusion between these two melts. This is suggestive evidence that aluminum transport is the rate controlling step in both viscous transport and interdiffusion in these melts.</p><p>Tracer diffusivities of these network formers were used to model interdiffusion between dacitic and rhyolitic melts previously measured at similar conditions of pressure and temperature <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(BAKER, 1990)</ref>. Using the model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">LASAGA ( 1979)</ref> with diffusivities measured in this study for network formers and diffusivities of network modifiers from other studies, diffusion profiles were calculated at 1500, 1400, and 1300°C. Additionally, the "Oxide-Molecule" model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> was also used at 1300°C. Calculated and measured profiles agree well at 15OO"C, but as temperature decreases the mismatch between experiment and model increases. Even the inclusion of nonideal activity terms ( GHIORSO et al.,  1983)  into the 1300°C model does not resolve discrepancies between calculations and experiments. The LASAGA ( 1979) model provides a better fit to experiments than the <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> model at the conditions studied. Despite discrepancies between modelled and measured diffusion profiles at 13OO"C, the differences between experiment and the LASAGA ( 1979) model are small enough that the model may be used to place constraints on the possible effects of diffusion in dacitic to rhyolitic melts.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>MEASUREMENTS OF CHEMICAL diffusion during the interdiffusion of silicate melts have demonstrated that soon after the initiation of diffusion, all nonalkalies appear to diffuse only as rapidly as Si and Al homogenize between the two melts, sometimes orders of magnitude below the measured tracer diffisivities of <ref type="bibr">Fe, Mg, and Ca (WATSON, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">BAKER and WATSON, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">KOYAGUCHI, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">BAKER, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">BAKER, , 1991))</ref>. Alkali cations, however, diffuse much more rapidly <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(WATSON, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">BAKER and WATSON, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">KOYAGUCHI, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr">BAKER, 1990, 199 1)</ref> . <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">WATSON ( 1982 )</ref> proposed that cations initially diffuse at values near their tracer diffusivities along the Si and Al diffusion gradients until a "transient two-liquid partitioning" behavior for all cations is achieved between melts of differing silica and alumina contents. Once the "transient two-liquid partitioning" has been achieved, the apparent diffusivities of the cations are only as fast as the diffusivities of Si and Al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">BAKER ( 1990)</ref> related this "transient two-liquid partitioning" to the requirement that the melts must achieve microscopic equilibrium, which is primarily controlled by local charge balance.</p><p>This observed behavior of cations during the interdiffusion of silicate melts could have conceivably been predicted from knowledge of the tracer diffusivities of all cations (Si, Ti, Al, Fe, Mg, Ca, Na, and K) in appropriate composition melts. Unfortunately, the important tracer diffusivities of network formers Si and Al are not known in geologic melts <ref type="bibr">(FREER, 198 1;</ref><ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al., 1985a)</ref>. Therefore, predictions of multicomponent diffusion from tracer diffusivities cannot be 617 made, despite the existence of the theoretical framework necessary for such predictions (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">LASAGA, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">ANDERSON, 198 1;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al., 1982)</ref>. This study was undertaken to fill the gap in knowledge of tracer diffusivities for network formers in dacitic and rhyolitic melts. With this new data and existing data on the tracer diffusivity of other cations in similar-composition silicate melts, models for multicomponent diffusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">( LASAGA, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al., 1982)</ref> during the interdiffusion of silicate melts could then be compared against measured diffusion profiles. Obviously, the important network formers in silicate melts are the composition~ly dominant Si and Al cations. It is for these cations that the tracer diffusiviti~ must be known.</p><p>A technique for Si tracer diffusion measurements was rapidly devised, but the extreme cost of 26Al and difficulties in using 26Al for diffusion measurements (E. B. <ref type="bibr">Watson, pers. comm, 1988)</ref> resulted in a compromise. Instead of measuring Al tracer diffusivities, the diffusivities of B and Ga were measured and used to estimate Al tracer diffusivity, later referred to as "Al" diffusivity. The diffusivities of B and Ga are expected to be very similar to those of Al because of the similar size and charge of the three cations. <ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al. ( 1985a)</ref> demonstrated little effect of cation size on the diffusivities of trivalent cations in basaltic, andesitic, rhyolitic, and ~ntelle~ti~ melts. All three cations, B, Al, and Ga, are also network formers and pIay a similar role in the structure of silicate melts. Aluminum and gallium are expected to be in tetrahedral coordination in these melts <ref type="bibr">(HENDERSON et al., 1985b)</ref>; however, B is expected to be in both tetrahedral and trigonal coordination (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">GEISINGER et al., 1988)</ref>. Although cation size has little effect on the diffisivity of trivalent cations, increasing size is expected to decrease diffusivity, and the Al diffusivity would be expected to be between the diffusivities of B and Ga. Therefore, measured B and Ga tracer diffusivities probably bracket the Al tracer diffusivities in these melts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL METHODS</head><p>Tracer diffusivities of Si, 8, and Ga were measured in melts of dacitic. AT1 50. and rhvolitic. LCO. comoositions (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). These melt cdmpositi&amp;s are the same as u&amp;d by 'BAKER ( 1990) for dhemical diffusion measurements during interdiffusion. AT1 50 was produced by multiple fusion at 1500°C with grinding between each fusion and FeO'--total iron as Fe0</p><p>LCO is a natural rhyolitic obsidian glass ( WATSON, 198 1). Cylinders of each glass were artfully drilled from nearly bubble-free monolithic glass pieces by E. B. Watson using a diamond-bit core drill. Glass cylinders were cut into approximately I .5 mm long pieces and one end of each cylinder polished to a 1 p finish. All B and Ga, and all but one Si, tracer diffusion experiments were performed in a piston-cylinder apparatus using NaCl-PyrexTM assemblies of 19 mm diameter. Glass samples were placed in holes drilled in a large graphite cylinder at the center of the assembly and covered with graphite lids, This graphite cylinder sat in a dehydrated pyrophyllite cup to electrically isolate the graphite plug from the graphite furnace ( JUREWICZ and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">WATSON, 1984)</ref>. Temperatures were measured with Wa7Re3-W7rRe2r thermocouples and are believed accurate to *S'C. Pressure was maintained at 1 .O + 0.05 GPa for all ex~~men~. Samples were quenched at rates approaching 2OOO"C/ min by turning off power to the furnace.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Si Tracer Diffusion Experiments</head><p>Si tracer diffusion was measured using 3oSi. This silicon isotope was obtained (from Oak Ridge National Laboratory, USA) as SiOz at an enrichment level of 95% "Si. This SiOr was mixed with isotopically normal SiOz and with NaC03, and fused twice at lOOO"C, with intermediate grinding, to make a sodium silicate glass with a nominal comwsition of 27 mol% Na,O and 73 molW SiO,. In this glass IS atom % of all Si is 3oSi. The-glass was ground in -an agate mortar and pestle to fine powder and stored in a drying oven until use. For each experiment the cylinders of AT150 and LCO were loaded into the graphite cylinders and then a thin layer, estimated thickness of less than 100 ,K, of the 3?&amp;enriched sodium silicate glass powder was placed on the polished ends of the dacitic and rhyolitic glass cylinders, followed by the graphite lids. Diffusion experiments were then performed at 1300,140O and 1500°C and 1 .O GPa (Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). After each experiment samples were mounted in epoxy, sectioned longitudinally, polished, and gold coated, in preparation for ion-microprobe analysis.</p><p>One Si tracer diffusion experiment in LCO was performed at 1 atm, 1303°C in a sealed Pt capsule to investigate the effect of pressure on Si diffusion. The sample was suspended in the hot zone of a latm furnace within a few mm of the thermocouple. The sample was quenched by the "yank and blow" technique to below red heat in under 5 s.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Boron and Gallium Tracer Diffusion Experiments</head><p>Boron and gallium tracers were added to the ends of ATI 50 and LCO glass cylinders as very dilute solutions of boric acid and Ga dissolved in dilute HCI. The solutions had normal isotopic ratios of both B and Ga. The.boric acid solution was synthesized by dissolving 0.5665 g of boric acid into 100 mL of distilled water at approximately 23°C. The resulting solution contained approximately 1000 fig B/ mL. The Ga solution was an atomic absorption standard solution containing 1010 pg/mL of Ga. The amounts of B and Ga added to each glass cylinder were calculated to yield a total of approximately IO0 ppm of B and 200 ppm of Ga, if the elements were homogeneously distributed throu~out the melts, and if the melts initially contained no B and Ga. The B and Ga solutions were added to the polished ends of the da&amp;c and rhyohtic glasses using a microsyringe; after each solution was added the samples were dried under a lamp, leaving a white residue on the ends of the glass cylinders. The cylinders of each composition were then loaded into the graphite plug, lids were added, and the diffusion experiments performed. Thus, B and Ga tracer diffusion occurred simultaneously in both compositions during the experiments. Boron and gallium tracer diffusion experiments were successfully completed at 1 .O GPa and temperatures from 1300 to 1600°C in AT I.50 melts, and Ga diffusion was measured at the same conditions in LCO melts; B diffusion, however, was only measured between 1300 and 1500°C. As with the Si tracer diffusion experiments, the B and Ga diffusion experiments were prepared for ion-microprobe analysis. ratios of %i/28Si were then used to solve the diffusion equation ag propriate for a thin source (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">HOFMANN, 1980)</ref>. For this case, where R is the '?%i/%i ratio at any distance x away from the beginning of the diffusion profile, &amp; is the same ratio at the beginning of dilfusion profile (i.e., x = 0), R' is the initial 3oSi/28Si ratio of the sample, D is the diffusivity, and t is the duration of the experiment. Linear regression of the natural log of the left side of the equation against x2 results in a straight line with a slope of -1/4D? from which the diffisivity can be easily calculated. Ion-mi~opro~ rn~umrnen~ for B and Ga di~sion were performed using similar techniques, but with a few differences. A 6.5 V offset was used for energy filtering and a 15 min sputtering time was allowed at each spot before beginning an analysis. At each point, five blocks of measurements of "B, %i, 69Ga, and %a intensities were made. Analytical travemes started at the B-and Ga-enriched ends of the samples and continued until the ratios of "B/30Si and 69Ga/30Si reached constant values, presumed to be background levels. These ratios of "B and 69Ga with %i were used in the above equation to calculate tracer diffusivities of B and Ga. Some typical measured diffusion profiles and theoretical fits for the thin source diffusion equation are given for Si, B, and Ga in Fig. <ref type="figure">I</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ion-Microprobe Analysis of Sl B, and Ga DlfIusion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diffusi~ti~ of Sii B, and Ga</head><p>Diffusion experiments of this study were analyzed with the MIT-Harvard-Brown Cameca fMS3F ion-microprobe. For all analyses a primary beam of O-ions with an accelerating voltage of 8.2 kV was used together with a secondary accelerating voltage of approximately 4500 V. The beam spot size on the sample was 10 to 20 p in diameter. In all analyses positive secondary ions were detected with an electron multiplier.</p><p>For %i diffusion measurements, energy filtering was accomplished using a voltage offset of 30 V. Each analysis spot was sputtered for 10 mitt, in excess of the 6 min empirically determined for the *%i count rate to stabilize, before beginning an analysis. At each point %i and reSi intensities were measured for five blocks. Analytical traverses were made from the end at which the %i-emiched sodium silicate glass had been deposited to where the %/*%i ratio had decreased to its natural level, approximately 0.0335. The measured Measured cli&amp;tsivities of Si, B, and Ga are tabulated (Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> ) . The correlation coefficients given in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> are for the linearized version of Eqn. (1) used to calculate the diffisivities.</p><p>The high correlation coefficients support the premise that the experiments fit the thin-source diffusion model. Replicate Si diffusion measurements (D-82 and D-83 compared to D-84 and D-85) also support the conclusion that elemental transport occurred by diffusion because experiments of different durations, by a factor of 4, yield very similar measured ditivities (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). Two different ion-mi~opro~ traverses on one experiment (D-85a and b) demonstrate the ~pr~u~bi~~ of the diffusion measurements.  calcuiations. Data points are taken from measured ratios of%i/"%i, "BI"Si, and @Ga/% in the experiments. Solid lines are theoretical fits to the data using the diffusion equation given in text.</p><p>The measured diffusivities have been fit to Arrhenius equations (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>) and plotted on Arrhenius diagrams (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). The activation energies for diffusion, E.'s, are usually correlated with the energetics of cation movement. The Es's are probably dominated by the strength of the cation-oxygen bond, but typically slightly smaller in magnitude. The preexponential factors, Do's, are related to the jump distance a cation moves during each diffusive step (e.g., <ref type="bibr">GLASSTONE et al., 1941;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">HOFMANN, 1980)</ref>.</p><p>Silicon tracer diffusivities in the dacitic melt at 1.0 GPa vary between 8 X IO-" m*/s, 1300°C to 4 X lOWi m2/s at 15WC and have an activation energy of 383 2: 93 kJfmo1. The Si tracer diffusivities in the rhyolitic melt, 2 X lo-" m2/ s to 8 X 1O-'5 m2/s, vary from approximately 1 to almost 2 orders of magnitude below the Si tracer diffusivities in the dacitic melt. The activation energy for Si tracer diffusivity in the rhyolitic melt is 139 + 40 kJ/mol, interestingly only onethird the activation energy for Si diffusion in the dacitic melt. The sole experiment performed at 1 atm, D-88, yielded a Si diffisivity of 1.66 X 1O-'5 m2/s in LCO at 13OO"C, within a factor of 2 of the measured diffusivity at 1 .O GPa, 1300°C. Based upon this one experiment, it appears that the difference in pressure between 1 atm and 1.0 GPa has little effect on Si-tracer diffusivity in rhyolitic melts.</p><p>Boron and gallium tracer diffusivities in AT 150 dacitic melt are the highest measured in this study and are virtually identical. At 1300°C the diffusivities are 4 X IO-r3 m2/s and increase to approximately 1 X IO-" m*/s at 1600°C. However, in the rhyolitic melt, B and Ga tracer diffusivities are distinctly different; at 1300°C B diffuses at 7 X 1O-15 m*/s and Ga diffuses at 4 X 1 O-l4 m* / s. Such differences between B and Ga diffusivities in the rhyolite melt exist to the highest temperatures studied, with Ga always diffusing two to five times faster than B. Activation energies for both B and Ga appear lower in the dacitic melt than in the rhyolitic one. However, in each melt the E,'s for B and Ga are almost identical; in the dacitic melt, the E, for B is 319 k 28 kJ/ mol and for Ga is 268 + 38 kJ/mol; and in the rhyolitic </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Boron and Galiium Diffusivities</head><p>The similar diffusivities and E,'s for diffusion of B and Ga cations in rbyohtic and dacitic mehs suggest that both ions play similar roles in the melt structures as te~hed~iy coordinated network formers, like Al. However, B diffusivities are depressed below Ga diffusivities in LCO and are either the same, or just slightly less, than Ga diffusivities in AT 150. Eafs for B diffusion appear higher than for Ga, although the l-sigma error bars overlap. These differences may either be due to a cation size effect or due to different structural roles for B and Ga. The greater diffusivity of the larger Cia ion is opposite to the size effect observed for alkali metals, where decreasing size increases diffisivity (e.g., <ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al., 1985a)</ref>. Instead, the decreased B diffusivity and increased I?, are suggested to be the result of the presence of some B in trigonal, as well as tetrahedral, coordination in giasses fe.g <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">GEISINGER et al., 1988)</ref>, whereas Ga is only present in tetrahedral coordination <ref type="bibr">(HENDERSON et al., 1985b)</ref>.</p><p>The presence of B in both trigonal and tetrabedral coordination in Eli-~umina~on~ning borosilicate glasses has been detected by both Raman spectroscopy <ref type="bibr">( KWIJNENDIJ~JK and STEVELS, 1976)</ref> and nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">( GEISINGER et al., 1988 )</ref> . Boron in tetrahedral coordination can substitute for Si or Al in the melt network, whereas B in trigoual coordination clusters and forms separate borate units in the glass that are not part of the SW-Al net-work. At high enough B concentrations, these borate units achieve a macroscopic size resulting in phase separation of borosilicate glasses ( KONIJNENDIJK and STEVELS, 1976) Although these spectroscopic studies and others discussed below were performed on glasses, there is good evidence that glass and melt structures are very similar, if not identical (i.e., <ref type="bibr">SEIFFZR~ et al., 1982)</ref>. Therefore, the results of structural studies on glasses wilf be applied to melts.</p><p>The mul~pli~ity of ~r~ua~on states of B in the melts results in more complicated diffusion paths for B than for Ga. Boron can diffuse between two trigonal sites, between two tetrahedraI sites, or between two sites with different coordination spheres, Ga, however, is only diffusing between tetrahedral sites. The En's for B diffusion reflect a combination of the energetics of B-O bonds in trigonal and in tetrahedral coordination. Because the strength of a B-O bond in trigonal coordination is greater than B-0 and Ga-0 bond strengths in tetrahedral coordination <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(BROWN and SHANNON, 1973)</ref>, E,'s for B diffusion would be expected to be greater than &amp;'s for Ga diffusion. Large distances between borate units, due to low B concentrations in the melt, result in possibly larger "mean" jump distances for B than for Ga and would result in the lower diffusivities and higher Do's for B diffusion than for Ga diffusion. These expectations are supported by the experimental measurements; however, similarities in the measured Ea% and Do's of B and Ga suggest these effects to be relatively minor. Because the proportion of borate units with B in trigonal coordination becomes greater with increasing silica content of the melt (KONIJNENDIJK and STEV-ELS, 1976 ), differences between B and Ga diffusion are more accentuated in the rhyolitic melt than in the da&amp;tic meit (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). although not investigated, it is suggested that at higher B concentrations the E. would increase and the DO would decrease for B diffusion because of increased abundance of borate units.</p><p>Because of the complexity of coordination states for boron in these silicate melts, it appears that Ga provides a better analog for Al than B. Therefore, "'Al" diffusivities will be considered equal to measured Ga tracer diffusivities.</p><p>indicate that the Al ions, nonbridging oxygens, and network modifying cations are not randomly distributed among the different types of melt structures, but that some clustering occws <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(SEIFERT et al., 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al., 1985b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">MURDOCH et al., 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr">JXMINE and PIRIOU, 1986)</ref>. Clustering in metaluminous melts with only small amounts of nonbridging oxygens may be expressed chemically by series of reactions proposed by <ref type="bibr">D~MINE and PIRIOU ( 1986)</ref> for aluminosilicate melts:</p><p>Silicon Diffusivities Si3M + Si2AlM = Si2M2 + SiSAl Over the temperature range investigated, tracer diffusivities of silicon in dacitic and rhyolitic melts decrease with increasing silica content, consistent with tracer diffisivities of other cations in various silicate melts and glasses <ref type="bibr">( HOFUANN, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">FREER, 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al., 1985a)</ref>. However, the Ea for Si diffusion in the rhyolitic melt ( 139 Wfmol) is much lower than in the dacitic melt (383 kJ/mol). The observed trend in E, for silicon tracer diffusion is opposite that observed for Si dilliusion in CaO-A1203-SiOz glass and SiOr glass where E, increases with increasing silica from 230 to 579 kJ/mol <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(SCHAEFFER, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">BREBEC et al., 1980)</ref>. At the same time the activation energy for Si diffusion decreases from dacite to rhyolite, the activation energy for "Al" diffusion slightly increases. Although the results of this diffusion study cannot illuminate the mechanism of the low E, for Si tracer dill&amp;ion in rhyolitic melts, spectroscopic and theoretical studies provide additional insight into these surprising results.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Si3M C SiA12M = S&amp;M2 + Si2A12 Sil( + Si2A12 = 2 Si3Al 2 Si3M = Siq + Si2M2</formula><p>Atomic relaxation phenomena for Si and Na in silicate melts presumably are related to movement of these cations in the melt <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(LIU et al., 1987</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(LIU et al., , 1988))</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">LIU et al. (1987)</ref> and FARNAN and STEBBINS ( 1990) used NMR techniques to study atomic relaxation for Si and Na in albite liquid and glass good'structural models for rhyolitic melts <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(HOCHELLA and BROWN, 1984)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">FARNAN and STEBBINS ( 1990)</ref> found that the E, for Si spin-lattice relaxation, TI, is 138 kJ/mol, virtually identical to the .E, for Si diffusion in rhyolitic melt measured in this study. These similar activation energies for Si tracer diffusion in the rhyolitic melt and for Si spin-lattice relaxation in albite melts and glasses suggest that the same mechanism is responsible for both types of movement in high-silica melts.</p><p>where the subscript of the element refers to the number of next nearest neighbors of a silicon cation that are silicon and Mrefers to a network modifier cation (e.g., SisMmeans that a silicon ion has 3 silicon ions and 1 M ion as its next nearest neighbors). <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">DOMINE and PIRIOU ( 1986)</ref> suggest that as the charge density of M (i.e., charge/ionic radius) increases, the equilibria should move further to the left. This suggestion is qualitatively supported by the interpretation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">SEIFERT et al. ( 1982)</ref>   <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al., 1985b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">DOMINE and PIRIOU, 1986)</ref>. Although the melt structure is predominantly composed of sixmembered rings of tetrahedra <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(TAYLOR and BROWN, 1979)</ref>, the six-membered rings may be subdivided into populations with two different (S&amp;Al)-0-(Si,Al) angles <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(SEIFERT et al., 1982)</ref>. Alternatively, depending upon composition, silicate melts may have six-membered, four-membered, and threemembered rings <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(TAYLOR and BROWN, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">SEIFERT et al., 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al., 1985b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">OESTRIKE et al., 1987)</ref>. Irrespective of the details of these two melt structures, all studies Because network modifiers can decrease Si-0 bond strengths (DE <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">JONG and BROWN, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr">NAVROTSKY et al., 1985)</ref>, the clustering of low-charge density network modifiers near a specific Si ion would be expected to lower its mean Si-0 bond strength and therefore lower the activation energy for Si diffusion, but not have a substantial effect on Al activation energies. However, hiSher charge density cations appear more evenly distributed between structural units in the melt and affect the bond strengths of any specific Si ion less. Thus, it is proposed that the activation energies for Si diffusion in these metaluminous melts are controlled by the weakest Si-0 bonds in the melts and that a higher proportion ofweaker bonds is present in the rhyolitic melt than is present in the dacitic melt. The higher proportion of weaker bonds in the rhyolite melt is because the majority of the network modifying cations are alkalies, instead of alkaline earths and transition metals as in the dacitic melt, Several predictions concerning transport processes can be made based upon the above hypothesis. Extension of the hypothesis to other silicate melt compositions suggests that for metaluminous melts the activation energy for Al diffusion should be approximately constant and that Si activation energy should be a function of the proportion and type of network modifying cations. Silicon relaxation studies to measure lr, values in anorthitic melts and glasses should yield higher activation energies than previous studies in albitic melts. The hypothesis also suggests that when it is technologically possible to measure T, values for Al in metaluminous, aluminosilicate melts, they will be much higher than I', values measured for Si in the same melts because Al-O bonds are not subs~nti~ly weakened by the clustering of alkali network modifiers around silicon ions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tracer Diffusion of Network Formers and Viscous Transport</head><p>Diffusion of network formers and viscous transport appears to occur by similar if not identical mechanisms (e.g., GLAS-STONE <ref type="bibr">et al., 1941;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">ANGELL et al., 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">HOCHELLA and BROWN, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">BAKER, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">FARNAN and STEBBINS, 1990)</ref>. In fact, <ref type="bibr">BAKER ( 1990, 199 1)</ref> has demonstrated that effective binary diffusion coefficients for Si-Al chemical diffusivities during the interdi~sion of silicate melts can be web predicted from melt viscosities. It is therefore of interest to compare &amp;,'s for Si and "Al" tracer diffusion with Es's for viscous transport in the same melts. Calculated activation energies for viscous transport <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">( SHAW, 1972 )</ref> in the melts investigated increase from 269 kJ/mol in the dacite to 340 kJ/mol in the rhyolite, opposite to the trend of E,,'s for Si tracer diffusion. However, these activation energies are virtually identical to the &amp;'s for Ga tracer diffusion (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>), and therefore "Al" tracer diffusion.</p><p>The correlation between activation energies for "Al" diffusion and viscous transport is related to the formation of transient, highly coordinated (5 or 6-coordinated cations) (Si,Al)-0 polyhedra postulated to occur during both diffusion and viscous transport (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">ANGELL et al., 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">HOCHELLA and BROWN, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">LIU et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">BAKER, 1990)</ref>. The similarity of the activation energies suggest that the energetics of formation of highly coordinated Al-O polyhedra, not Si-0 polyhedra, control the activation energies for viscous transport in these melts. Therefore, the formation of highly coordinated Al-0 polyhedra in the melt may be more common than similar polyhedra for Si-0. The easier formation of highly coordinated Al instead of Si would be consistent with the observation of S-coordinated Al, but not Si, in albite glasses quenched from 8 and 10 GPa <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">( STEBBINS and SYKES, 1990)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparison of Tracer Diffusivities of Network Formers and Modifiers in Silicic Melts</head><p>Tracer diffusivities of network formers Si, B, and Ga at 1 .O GPa are compared with tracer diffusivities in a pitchstone melt with 70% SiOr at 0.1 MPa <ref type="bibr">(HENDERSON et al., 1985b)</ref> in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. Despite the difference in pressure between the two studies, it is possible to make the com~~son because of the small effect of 1 .O GPa pressure on tracer diffisivities. This small pressure effect is demonstrated by Si tracer diffusivity measurements of this study at 1 atm and 1 .O GPa, 13OO"C, and by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">BAKER ( 1989)</ref> who demonstrated little pressure effect on the tracer diffusivity of Sr between 0.1 MPa and 1 .O GPa. The network-former diffusivities are lower than tracer diffusivities of any other cations in similar composition melts at temperatures below 1600°C (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> ) . Alkali metals diffuse much more rapidly than network formers, although the effect of ionic radius (cf. Diffusivities of other network formers are far below those of Co. Diffusivities of En, a network modifier with the same trivalent charge as B and Ga, are larger than B and Ga diffusivities, even though Eu has an ionic radius approximately twice as large as B and Ga. The depression of B and Ga diffusivities below Eu diffisivities, especially in the rhyolitic melt, is due to the network forming role of the former two cations and network m~ifying role of the latter. Finally, the effect of tetravalent charge and of being a network former on diffusivity is reflected in Si having the lowest measured tracer diffusivities. At temperatures below a~~ximately 16OO"C, charge e&amp;&amp;s and the role a cation plays as a network former or network modifier in melt structure exert strong effects on cation diffusivities. Tracer diffusivities in silicic melts span a range of five orders of magnitude, from alkalies like Na with rapid diffisivities to the sluggish diffusion of network-forming silicon. At temperatures above 16OO"C, compensation (WINCHELL, 1969; <ref type="bibr">HOF~AN~, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al., 1985a</ref> f occurs for all cations except Si in LCO mdt and Na in silicic melts (cf. <ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al., 1985a)</ref>. This comunction results in conve~ence of cation diffusivities. Although only speculation, the lack of compensation for Si diffusion in LCU melt is possibIy related to the proposed effect of alkali clustering on the activation energy for Si diffusion in this melt. The relationship is suggested by the fact that Na diffusion also does not demonstrate compensation in similar composition melts (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>: cf. <ref type="bibr">HENDERSON et al., 1985a)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CALCULATION OF MUL~COM~N~NT DIFFUSION DURING I~ER~I~FUSION OF DACXTIC AND RHYOLITIC MELTS</head><p>The tracer digits of network formers from this research can now be combined with muIticom~ne~t difhision models to calculate the full multicom~nent diffusion matrix for the dacitic and rhyolitic mehs studied. The ability to calcufate the full diffusion matrix for all melt compositions will eventually provide much better comprehension, and prediction, of diffusional processes in melts, such as "uphill" diffusion observed between basaltic and feldspathic melts <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(WATSON, 1982)</ref>.</p><p>The equation necessary for the calculation of multicomponent diffusion is Fiek's second law:</p><p>where Ci is the con~n~tion of species i, t is time, x is distance along the diffusion path, and D,'s are the diffusion matrix elements which reflect the effect of the flux of component ,j on component i. The summation is over .j -1 because the composition of 1 component can be fixed (ONSAGER, 193 <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">I a,b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">LASAGA, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">ANDERSON, 198 1)</ref> . In order to calculate the change in ~ncentmtion with time at any point along a diffusion profile, all the elements of the diffusion matrix must be calculated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CaIculat~n of the Diffusion Matrix</head><p>The first multi~m~nent diffusion mode1 considered for calculation of the diffusion matrix is that of LASAGA ( 1979 f ; the interested reader is referred to this paper for fuil details and the derivation of the relevant equations. This model is designed for cation diffusion in crystals and does not consider the possibility of oxygen diffision, Although oxygen diffusion occurs during the interdi~sion of dacitic and rhyolitic melts, the difference in oxygen concentration between AT1 50 and LCO is only 1.5%. Because of the similar oxygen concentrations in the two met&amp;, we will assume, at least for this first appmximation, that oxygen is not along between the melts and that cations can be treated as if they are diffusing on a fixed oxygen lattice. The resulting equation for the calculation ofeach J&amp; in the matrix is (LASAGA, i979, Eqn. 14b)</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Dij=oPsij-oPCi[(alnri/eCj)-(ainri/aC,) n</formula><p>where By is the tracer diffu~vity of cation i; also forj, k+ and n, 6, is the Kronecker delta Sij = I only if i = j and 0 in all other cases; z is the charge on the various diffusing cations, i,j, k, n. The concentration of any cation, e.g., ci , is in moles of cations per cm3, and yi is the activity coefficient for cation i. The cation denoted by n has been eliminated from the diffusion caiculations because it is a dependent variable; for the calculations performed, this cation has been chosen to be Na because its concentration is almost equal in the two melts studied. Equation 2 can be simplified by assuming the~~ynamic ideality in the mdt which removes derivatives for chemical activity coefhcients with respect to concentration (LASAGA, 1979, Eqn. I.5): k=l Equation 3 was used for the calculation of Do's for interdiffusion of AT 150 and LCO at temperatures of 1500, 1400, and 13OO"C, where tracer diffusion of all network farmers investigated has been measured. Calculation of .&amp;'s at 1300°C was also perfurmed using Eqn. (2) because nonideafity was expected to be greatest at the lowest temperature investi~ted, and the largest discrepancies between measured and calculated diffusion profiles were observed at this temperature. Activity coefhcients used in Eqn. ( 2) were cal&amp;ated using the regular solution model of <ref type="bibr">GH~ORSO et al. ( 1983)</ref> Although the <ref type="bibr">GHIORSO ( 1983 )</ref> melt model is calibrated primarily on anhydrous basalitic melt compositions, it was chosen over the silicate melt model of NEKVASIL ( <ref type="formula">1988</ref>) because the latter is only designed for simple, hydrous, felsic (only the albite-orthoclase-anoithitequartz system) melts. Simulations using the GHI~RSO ( 1983) model and Eqn. (2) are only preliminary at this time, but still provide valuable insight into the effects of nonideality on multicomponent diffusion between dacitic and rhyolitic melts.</p><p>For comparison, the diffusion matrix at 1300°C was ah0 calculated using the techniques of <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref>, which were originally designed to calculate interdiffision in CaO-Al&amp;&amp;-Si02 melts. The "Oxide-molecule" diffusion model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> together with Bqn. ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) of <ref type="bibr">OtSHt et al. ( 1982)</ref> for the calculation of the diffusion matrix were expanded to fit the number of components in the dacite-rhyolite system and the diffusion matrix calculated at 1300°C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> also propose a series of other, more comptex, diffusion models; but ~ompa~son with these more complex models is beyond the scope of this paper and must await future investigation.</p><p>To solve Eqns. ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">3</ref>), the tracer di&amp;sivities, Dp's, must be known. Tracer difhusivities for Si and Al were calculated as a linear function of Si content, or Al content for "'Al'" diffusivities, using the results of this study for Si and Ga tracer diffusivities in dacitic and rhyolitic melts. Because all divalent cation diffusivities are virtually identical at these temperatures <ref type="bibr">(HENDERSON et al., 1985a)</ref>, one diffusivity was used for Fe, Mg, and Ca. Some interdiffusion calculations assumed a constant di~~~vity for divaIent cations aIong the diffusion profIle. The d~~usivity used was calculated from WATSON'S ( 198 1) measurements of Ca tracer diffusion in LCO melt at ZOO MPa; this diffusivity is expected to be a minimum di@itsivity for divalent cations in the melts studied Other calculations of interdiffusion assumed a linear relation between silica content and diffusivity of divalent cations; the diffusivities of Mn, Co, and Ba in a pitchstone melt (HEN- <ref type="bibr">DERSON et al., 1985a)</ref> and of Ca in LCO (WATSON, 1981 f were used to predict difhrsivities along the diffusion profile between dacite (AT1 SO) and rhyolite (LCO); these diffusivities can exceed the tracer diffusivity of Ca in LCO by up to an order of magnitude and are expected to be the maximum possible difhtsivities for divalent cations in these melts. This variable divalent cation diffusivity was used in the <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> model and in calculations using Eqn. ( 2 ) . Titanium diffisivity was assumed to be 90% of the Si dilfusivity. Sodium <ref type="bibr">(HENDERSON et al., 1985a)</ref> and potassium <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">( JAMBON, 1982 )</ref> difisivities were assumed constant along the difIi.tsion profile.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>~~~~ulatjon of diffusion Profiles</head><p>Once cation Do's were calculated at each point along the diffusion profile, an explicit finite difference technique (e.g., AMES, Chap. 2, 1977 f was used to solve Bqn. ( 1) assuming infinite reservoirs of AT 150 and LCO: where c? is the composition of i at time la and position k dong the diffusion profile and X is the time step divided by the square of the spatial step used in the finite difference calculations. At each time step the diffusion matrix was calculated at every point along the diffision profile and new cumpositions at each point then calculated using Eqn. (4). After multipie time steps the calculated difFksion pr&amp;te was compared against ex~~rnen~~y determined diffusion profiles between ATI 50 and LCO at the same temperature f BAKER, 1990). For calculations using Bqn, ( 3 ) , the spatial step used was 10 or. and the time increment was 0.05 s. Simulated diffusion times were equal to, or greater than, 1000 s. Because of their added complexity, caIculations involving Eqn. (2) and the <ref type="bibr">GHIORSO et al. ( 1983)</ref> regular solution model had to use much coarser spatial steps and shorter duration simulations.</p><p>Because durations of #mputer-simulate interdiffision models were diflerent from real experimental durations, both values were no~aliz~ by division of the distance by the square root of time then multipl~ng by 1000 <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(OISHI et al., 1982 )</ref> . The results are plotted for all three temperatures investigated <ref type="bibr">(Figs. 4,</ref><ref type="bibr">5,</ref><ref type="bibr">6)</ref>. For comparison, zero positions of experimental and calculated diffusion profiles were taken to be the point of mean silica concentration (in wt %). Some differences between measured and calculated endmember com~sitions are seen in the diagrams (Figs. <ref type="figure">4,</ref><ref type="figure">5,</ref><ref type="figure">6</ref> ) because compositions were normalized in the computer program. Diffusion profiles, both experimental and simulated, for CaO and MgO are similar to Fe0 (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>), but at different backgroxmd compositions in AT I 50 and LCO, con~entmtions of FeO, MgO, and CaO are only plotted for the 1500°C data. In ex~~ments, alkalies did not have infinite reservoirs (BAKER, 1990) because of their extremely rapid diffusivities; therefore, experiments and simulations for alkali diffusion were not compared.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>COMPARISON OF CALCULATED WITH EXPERIMENTS DIFFUSION</head><formula xml:id="formula_2">PROFILE3 150o*c</formula><p>Comparison of calculated and measured 15BP difIusion profiles is excellent for the case of a constant diffusivity for divalent cations along the diffusion profile (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). The most striking aspect of the calculations is the small amount of uphi diffusion observed for alumina. This uphill diffusion of AI results in the small trough and broad, low-amplitude swelf of alumina concentration in the rhyolitic end ofthe diffusion profile. Although equivocal, some evidence for uphill diffusion can be discerned in the plotted experimental diffusion profile, as also observed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">KOYAGUCHI ( 1989)</ref> in his interdiffusion experiments. This uphill diffusion of Al also occurs in lower temperature diffusion calculations. Using constant divaient cation diffusivities, oniy a small discrepancy exists between calculated and measured diffusion profiles for FeO, MgO, and CaQ f~quen~y the di~~~ncy is within microprobe counting statistics errors. Allowing the diffusivity of divatent cations to vary along the diffusion profile has little effect on the silica diffusion profile but results in significant uphill diffusion of Al and more rapid diffusion of FeO, MgO, and CaO in the dacitic portion of the diffusion profile than is observed in the experimental profile.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1400°C</head><p>As observed at 1 SOO"C, both sets of calculations fit measured silica diffusion prokies (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>). Calculated alumina diffusion profiles display more uphill diffusion than observed at I SOO"C. The ~~~~ncy between calculated and measured alumina diffusion profiles at 14OO'C is less than 0.5 wt%, or diffusivities for divalent cations agree more closely with measured ditision profiles than calculations assuming variable difiksivities for divalent cations. The maximum difference between measured and calculated diffusion profiles is approximately a factor of 2.4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1300°C</head><p>Once again, calculated diRtsion profiles using Eqn. (3) provide an excellent match for measured diffusion profiles for silica (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>) regardless of whether divalent cation  <ref type="bibr">et al., 1983)</ref> to calculate activity coefficients and the effects of nonideal behavior of silicate melts on ditTusion. The <ref type="bibr">GHIORSO et al. ( 1983)</ref> model also uses variable divaient cation diffusivities. The "Oishi" model is the "Oxide-molecule" model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref>, also with variable divalent cation diffusivities. Further discussion of the various diffusion models is in the text.</p><p>diffusivity is held constant or allowed to vary. Calculated alumina profiles demonstrate more uphill diffusion than observed in experiments; but in contrast to the 1400°C results, the discrepancy is more easily observed in the dacitic rather than the rhyolitic end of the diffision couple. Uphill diffusion of Al is reduced when a constant diffusivity for divalent cat-ions is used and the m~imum difference between measured and calculated A&amp;O3 contents is approximately 1 .O wt%, or 6 relative percent. Using a constant diffisivity for divalent cations, the calculated diffusion profiles for divalent cations are also longer than measured profiles in the rhyolitic end, by approximately a factor of 2. The greatest discrepancy between calculated and measured Fe0 content is approximately also a factor of 2. Allowing divalent cation diffusivities to vary with melt composition increases the calculated diffusion profile to 4 times the length of the measured profile at the rhyolitic end of the diffusion couple.</p><p>Preliminary results using the a~i~~~rn~ition relations of <ref type="bibr">GHIORSO et al. f 1983)</ref> and Fqn. ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) demonstrate no observable changes in the silica diffusion profile and appear to reduce uphill diffusion of Al. Diffusion of divalent cations is affected by use of this activity-composition model resulting in slightly shorter diffusion profiles in the rhyolitic end and longer profiles in the dacitic end than in the simple case for an ideal melt with varying divalent cation diffusivities. Further, more illuminating, results of using Eqn. (2) must await calculations performed at smaller spatial steps and for longer simulated times.</p><p>Application of the <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> "Oxide-molecule" model (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>), with varying divalent cation ~ffusi~ties, works signi~~n~y less well than Eqn. f 3) for Al and divalent cation diffusion-longer diffusion profdes are calculated than observed in experiments or the previous models, although no uphill diffision of Al is observed for the <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> model. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">The OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> diffusion profile for divalent cations in the rhyolitic end is the same length as calculated using Eqn. (3)) but differences between measured and calculated Fe0 contents, a factor of approximately 4, are larger than calculated using Eqn. (3). Furthermore, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> diffision profiles deviate from measured compositions in the dacitic half of the diffusion profiles, unlike the results of Eqn. (3). Obviously, the use of the "Oxide-molecule" model of <ref type="bibr">GISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> is not a signifi~nt improvement over the <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">LASAGA ( 1979)</ref> model for inter~ffusion between dacitic and rhyolitic melts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>POSSIBLE CAUSES OF DISCREPANCIES BETWEEN MODELLED AND EXPERIMENTAL DIFFUSION PROFILES</head><p>Although discrepancies between diffusion profiles modelled using the techniques of LASAGA ( 1979) and measured in experiment are small, significant differences do exist. The possible reasons behind these differences are subdivided into three categoric failue of the model of Lam4 ( 1979) when applied to silicate melts (after all, it was designed for silicate crystals), use of incorrect tracer difliiivies for multicomponent diffusion calculations, and insufficient knowledge of activity-composition relations for silicate melts.</p><p>It seems doubtful that differences between models and experiments are substantially controlled by any failures of the LASAGA ( 1979) model. Because the LASAGA ( 1979) model assumes cation diffusion on a fixed oxygen lattice, any failure of the model would be expected to occur under conditions of highest oxygen mobility. Such conditions would be achieved in the 1500°C simulations. However, it is in these highest temperature simulations where the agreement with experimental diffusion profiles is the best. At 1500°C the least amount of uphii diffusion of Al and near-match between measured and calculated divalent cation diffusion profiles are observed when divalent cation diffusivities are held constant along the diffusion profile. However, the simplifying assumption of oxygen immobility used in the LASAGA ( 1979) model is just that, a simplifying assumption. The oxygens must be diffusing between the two melts. The diffusivities of oxygen in these two melts are probably similar to the diffusivities of the studied network formers (based upon correlations between oxygen and network-former diffusivities and melt viscosities-cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">SHIMIZU and KUSHIRO, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr">this work)</ref>. Coupling between slower oxygen and faster cation diffusion would be expected to result in slower observed cation diffusion; this is exactly what is observed in all calculations of divalent cation diffusion profiles. Thus, the LASAGA ( 1979 ) model may be not exactly predicting correct diffusion profiles because of oxygen mobility. However, the near correspondence between measured and modelled diffision profiles suggests that any failure of the LASAGA ( 1979) model is not major for the conditions investigated. A reliable assessment of failures in the LASAGA ( 1979) model cannot be made, however, until accurate tracer diffusivities of divalent cations and a~vity-com~sition relations are known for the melts studied.</p><p>Some disagreement between model and experiment is probably attributable to the lack of exact tracer diffusion for divalent cations in melts of AT 150, LCO, and intermediate compositions. The importance of these tracer diffusivities is seen in the effects different divalent cation diffusivities have on modelled diffision profiles <ref type="bibr">(Figs. 4,</ref><ref type="bibr">5,</ref><ref type="bibr">6)</ref>. At 1400°C and 1300°C discrepancies in divalent cation profiles between experiment and model seem to occur on the rhyolitic end of the diffusion profiles where few tracer diffusion studies have been performed at the temperatures of interest. However, at 15OO"C, discrepancies occur on the dacitic end. Calculations involving the slower, fixed diff~i~ties suggest that the technique used to predict the variable divalent cation tracer diffusivities may overestimate them and result in longer calculated diffusion profiles. To resolve this problem further measurements of tracer diffusivities in these melts need to be made at the temperature and pressure conditions of the interdiffusion experiments.</p><p>It is believed that most of the discrepancies between measured and calculated diffusion profiles are due to the assumption of ideal behavior for silicate melts. The fact that discrepancies become larger at lower temperature, where more nonideality is expected, is consistent with this belief. Furthermore, prelimin~ calculations using the activity-com~sition relations of <ref type="bibr">GHIORSO et al. ( 1983)</ref> with Eqn.</p><p>(3) result in smaller discrepancies between measured and calculated 1300°C diffision profiles, i.e., apparent mitigation of Al uphill diffision and shorter diffusion profiles for divalent cations (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>). Perhaps using activity-compositions relations specifically calibrated for anhydrous silicic melts, instead of basaltic melts <ref type="bibr">( GHIORSO et al., 1983)</ref>, model and experimental diffusion profiles would match each other more closely. Unfortunately, support for this proposition must await the development of such activity composition models.</p><p>The LASAGA ( 1979) model does not work perfectly; it is merely a first approximation for calculating interdiffusion between silicate melts. As a first approximation it does remarkably well in reproducing experimental interdiffusion profiles between dacitic and rhyolitic melts. This success suggests that application ofthe LASAGA ( 1979) model to diffusion in silicate melts might significantly enhance our quantitative understanding of diffusion-controlled processes in igneous petrogenesis. However, application of the LASAGA ( 1979) model is limited to melt compositions where all tracer diffusivities are known; unfortunately, few melt compositions satisfy this criterion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The first set of network-former diffusivities in dacitic and rhyolitic melts have been determined. Measurements of Si, B, and Ga diffusion (the last two as proxies for Al) have been made at 1 .O GPa and 1300 to 1600°C. Silicon is the slowest diffusing cation measured in both melts. In the rhyolitic melt, B and Ga diffuse more rapidly, with Ga always diffusing more rapidly than B. Silicon diffusivity in the dacite is more rapid than in the rhyolite. Boron and gallium in the dacite diffuse more rapidly than Si; but unlike in the rhyolite, B and Ga have similar diffusivities. The low diffusivities of the network formers are due to their structural role in silicate meltsnetwork-modifying cations with similar charge and much larger ionic radius (i.e., Eu'+) diffuse more rapidly than B and Ga. Activation energies for diffusion of network formers range from 139 to 400 kJ/ mol. Surprisingly, the gctivation energy of Si in rhyolite is the lowest-l 39 kJ/mol. This low activation energy is proposed to be due to the weakening effects of nearby alkalies on Si-0 bonds. Differences between B and Ga activation energies and diffusivities in the rhyolitic melt are related to the presence of B in both 3-fold and 4fold coordination, whereas Ga is only present in 4-fold coordination. Based upon the small difference in E,'s for B and Gain the dacitic melt, it is concluded that a smaller percentage of B is in trigonal coordination in this composition than in rhyolitic melts. As a result of the multiple coordination sites for B in these melts, diffusion measurements for Ga are better estimates of Al diffusion in silicate melts. Because activation energies for Ga, i.e., "Al," tracer diffusion are similar to calculated activation energies of viscous transport and Si-Al interdiffusion, Al diffusion appears to be the rate-limiting step for both viscous transport and chemical interdiffusion of dacitic and rhyolitic melts.</p><p>Modelling of multicomponent diffusion demonstrates that the model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">LASAGA ( 1979)</ref> for thermodynamically ideal phases provides a good simulation of 1500°C interdiffusion profiles between dacitic and rhyolitic melts. With falling temperatures, 1400 and 13OO"C, discrepancies between models and experiments become greater. Modelled diffusion profiles predict observable uphill diffusion of Al; no unambiguous evidence of Al uphill diffusion is observed in experiments. Modelled diffusion profiles are also longer than measured, but no more than a factor of 4 longer. A preliminary investigation of the effects of nonideality of the melt phase on diffusion demonstrates closer correspondence between model and experiment. The <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref> "Oxide-molecule" model demonstrates poorer correlation with experiment than either the ideal or nonideal versions of the LASAGA ( 1979) model by producing longer diffusion profiles of di-valent cations and Al, but without the uphill diffusion of Al observed in the LASAGA ( 1979) model. Currently, the lack of activity-composition relations and tracer diffusivities of all cations in the melts investigated limits the applicability of the diffusion models tested. Nevertheless, the models may still be useful for semi-quantitative prediction of multicomponent diffusion behavior in silicic melts.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. I. Measured and theoretical diffusion profiles for Si, B, and Ga in LCO rhyolitic melt. The x-axis is the distance from the beginning of the diffusion profile and the y-axis is the left-hand side of the equation used for diffusivity</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 2. Measured diffus~~ti~ of network farmers Si, B, and Ga in dacitic and rhyolitic melts at 1 .O GPa. Solid symbols are m~u~ments in the rhyolitic composition, LCO, and open symbols are me~urements in the d&amp;tic corn~s~i~a~ AT1 fo. circles are Ga diffusion measurement&amp; squares are B diffusion m~uremeuts~ and triangles are Si diffusion measurements. Error bars, 1 -ST, are smaller than most symbols and are plotted for all measurements. They can only be seen as short vertical lines inside the open symbols used for the dacitic composition.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of the differences in Raman spectra of the SiOz-NaAlOr and SiO&amp;aAlO., and Si02-MgA104 systems. These reactions indicate that when the dominant network modifying cations have low charge densities (e.g., alkalies) these cations are concentrated in the nei~~rho~ of Si ions, not Al cations, and more than one next nearest neighbor is a network modifier. Other evidence for the relative lack of network modifiers near Al comes from a study by OESTRIKE et al. ( 1987) that indicates Al ions in ~uminosilicate melts are concentrated in sites that have four bridging oxygens as nearest neighbors and four silicons as next nearest neighbors. If, however, high charge density cations (e.g., alkaline earths and transition metals) are the dominant network modifying cations they are associated with both Al and Si, but only one next nearest neighbor will be a network modifier. Differences between Si and "Al" activation energies for diffusion in the dacitic and rhyolitic melts probably are due to the types, proportions, and distribution of network modifying cations in the melts and their effects on melt structures and Si-0 and Al-O bond strengths. Numerous spectroscopic studies indicate that high-silica glasses and melts are composed of two structures differentiated by the manner in which (Si,Al)O, tetrahedra are linked in rings ( SEIFERT et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 3. Tracer diffusivities of cations in silicic melts. Measurements from this study, in dacitic and rhyolitic m&amp;s, are plotted using solid lines. Diffusivity m~u~ments of HENDERSON et al. (1985a) in a pitchstone melt, 70 w%</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 4. Measured and rnodelled interdiffision of dacitic and rhyolitic melts at 1 .O GPa and 1500°C. Measurements(data points) are from diffusion studies presented in BAKER ( 1990). Modelled diffusion profiles (lines) were. calculated using the model of<ref type="bibr" target="#b32">LASAGA ( 1979)</ref> assuming melts behave ideally. Solid lines are calculated diffusion profiles with a constant diffisivity for all divalent cations and dashed lines are for calculated diffusion profiles when diffusivities of divalent cations are allowed to vary as a function of melt composition (see text for a more complete discussion).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG.6. Measured and modelled interdiffusion at 1 .O GPa and 1300°C. "Ideal" models are the same models used to calculate diffusion profiles at higher temperatures. The "Ghiorso" model uses activity~om~sition relations (GHIORSOet al., 1983)  to calculate activity coefficients and the effects of nonideal behavior of silicate melts on ditTusion. TheGHIORSO et al. ( 1983)  model also uses variable divaient cation diffusivities. The "Oishi" model is the "Oxide-molecule" model of<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">OISHI et al. ( 1982)</ref>, also with variable divalent cation diffusivities. Further discussion of the various diffusion models is in the text.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 . Composition of Starttrig MAsterlals AT1 55 LCO</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>63.51</cell><cell>76.37</cell></row><row><cell>0.56</cell><cell>0.11</cell></row><row><cell>17.61</cell><cell>13.35</cell></row><row><cell>4.91</cell><cell>0.79</cell></row><row><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.06</cell></row><row><cell>1.60</cell><cell>0.07</cell></row><row><cell>5.24 4.67</cell><cell>0.51 4.31</cell></row><row><cell>1.77</cell><cell>4.67</cell></row><row><cell>99.55</cell><cell>100.24</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 . Silicon Tracer ~</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>D-82 1600 2.2 Q.57(K1.64)~10-'~ 0.99666 D-84 1500 8 6.56@0.91)x10'" 0.97336 D-86 1400 11 6.26&amp;0.33)~10'~ 0.99460 D-80 1300 21.03 2.27&amp;0.08)x10"' 0.99675 D-88 1303 10.1 1.66(fo.l8)x1O'" 0.98341 Notes: r, is the correlation coefficient for the linearized diffusion profile--sse text. Experiment D-85 was anaylzsd twice, D-Ma and D-85b. 1 -sigma errors given are based upon fits to linearized diffusion profiles. All experiments except D-88 performed at 1 .O GPa; D-88 performed at 0.1 MPa.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 . Boron and Gallium Tracer Difh~sivltlea</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Si02, at 0.1 MPa are plotted with dashed lines.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_1"><p>4.00</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgmennts-Experiments for this research were performed at RPI and were supported by <rs type="funder">NSF</rs> <rs type="projectName">Materials Research Group</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">DMR-85 106 17</rs>; data reduction and theoretical modelling at McGill were supported by my <rs type="funder">NSERC</rs> operating grant, <rs type="grantNumber">0GPO089662</rs>. Tracer analyses using the <rs type="projectName">MIT-Harvard-Brown ion microprobe were only possible because of the assistance of Nobu Shimizu</rs>. I benefited greatly from his knowledge and advice on ion-probe techniques and the study ofdiffision. Discussions with <rs type="person">E. B. Watson</rs>, <rs type="person">A. Hynes</rs>, <rs type="person">A. Mucci</rs>, <rs type="person">J. Brenan</rs>, and the loan of computers by <rs type="person">A. Hynes</rs> and <rs type="person">A. Mucci</rs>, were instrumental in developing some of the ideas and techniques used in this study. <rs type="person">M. Ghiorso</rs> and <rs type="person">F. J. Ryerson</rs> are also thanked for their insightful reviews. Editorial handling: <rs type="person">G. Faure</rs></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_vfWC5dB">
					<idno type="grant-number">DMR-85 106 17</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Materials Research Group</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_Rhv4kzn">
					<idno type="grant-number">0GPO089662</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">MIT-Harvard-Brown ion microprobe were only possible because of the assistance of Nobu Shimizu</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Numerical Methods ofPartial D@erential Equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ames</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in electrolyte mixtures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lasaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kirk-Patrick)</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Kinetics of Geochemical Processes</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Mineral. Sot. Amer</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">198 1</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="260" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Waterlike transport property anomalies in liquid silicates investigated at high T and P by computer simulation techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Angell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cheeseman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tamadon</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bull. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracer versus trace element diffusion: Diffusional decoupling of Sr concentration from Sr isotope composition. Geochim</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="3023" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical interdiffusion of dacite and rhyolite: Anhydrous measurements at 1 atm. and 10 kbar, application of transition state theory, and diffusion in zoned magma chambers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interdiffusion of hydrous dacitic and rhyolitic melts and the efficacy of rhyolite contamination by dacitic enclaves</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="473" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion ofmajor and trace elements in compositionally complex Cl-and F-bearing silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson E</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion du silicium dans la silice amorphe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brebec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Seguin R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bevenot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><forename type="middle">J C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Met</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="333" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empirical bond-strengthbond-length curves for oxides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Shannon R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Cryst. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polymerization of silicate and aluminate tetrahedra in glasses, melts and aqueous solutions: II. The network modifying effects of Mg</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Jong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H W S E</forename><surname>Brown G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>K+</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Na+</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Oh-</forename><surname>Li+</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1627" to="1642" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cl-, HjO, COZ, and HXO+ on silicate polymers</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Raman spectroscopic study of the Si02-A1203-K20 vitreous system: Distribution of siIicon second neighbors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Domine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Piriou B</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-temperature %i NMR investigation of solid and molten silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Farnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Chem. Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate minerals and glasses: A data digest and guide to the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Freer R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="454" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Geisinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Oestrike R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Navro~sky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kirkpatrick R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Thermochemistry and structure of glasses along the join NaAlSi,08-NaBSi308. Geochim. Cosmochim</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2405" to="2424" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ghiorso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S E</forename><surname>Carmichael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rivers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Navrotsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Geisinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mcmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gibbs</forename><forename type="middle">G V</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The tetrahedral framework in glasses and melts-inferences liquids; an expanded regular solution approximation for the calfrom molecular orbital calculations and implications for structure, culation of magmatic intensive variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol. thermodynamics and physical properties. Phys. Chem. Minerals</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983. 1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The gibbs free energy of mixing of natural silicate</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">) Theory of Rate Processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Glasstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Laidler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eyring</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1941">194 1</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">a) Structural controls and mechanisms of diffusion in natural silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lowry R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Raman spectra ofgallium and germanium substituted silicate glasses: Variations in intermediate range order</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bancroft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Fleet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rogers</forename><forename type="middle">D J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral. IO</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="946" to="960" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calculation of equilibrium crystallization paths of compositionally simple hydrous felsic melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nekvasil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="956" to="965" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution 23Na, *&apos;Al and 29Si spectroscopy of framework aluminosilicate glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yang W. -H</forename><surname>Oestrike R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kirkpatrick R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hervig R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Navrotsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Montez B</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geoihim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="2209" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and viscosity of rhyolite composition melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hochella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Brown G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="2640" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of liquid-state interdiffusion in the system CaO-A1203-Si02 using multiatomic ion models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Oishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nanba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pask J.'a</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Ceram. Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="253" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">193 1 a) Reciprocal relations in irreversible processes: I</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Onsager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="426" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in natural silicate melts: A critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics of Magmatic Processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hargraves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracer diffusion in granitic melts: Experimental results for</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jambon</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Rb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ce</forename><surname>Ba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10797" to="10108" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Eu to 13OO&apos;C and a model of calculation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distribution of partial melt in a felsic system: The importance of surface energy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jurew~cz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson E</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">1 b) Reciprocal relations in irreversible processes: II</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Onsager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2265" to="2279" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The application of silicon-30 in self-diffusion investigations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schaeffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Stat. Sol. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional network structure of quenched melts (glass) in the systems SiOz-NaA102, Si02-CaA1204 and Si02-MgA120</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Seifert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Virgo D</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="696" to="717" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure of borosilicate glasses studied by Raman scattering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Konijnendijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="224" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical gradient in diffusive interfaces in magma chambers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Koyaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicomponent exchange and diffusion in silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lasaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="469" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relaxation mechanisms and effects of motion in albite (NaAlSi,O,) liquid and glass: A high temperature NMR study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brandis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Chem. Minerals</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscosities of magmatic silicate liquids: An empirical method of prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. J. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">272</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="870" to="893" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusivity of oxygen in jadeite and diopside melts at high pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shimizu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kushiro I</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1295" to="1303" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure of NaAlSi30s liquid at high pressure: New constraints from NMR spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sykes D</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="943" to="946" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of mineral glasses: I. The feldspar glasses NaAlSi308, KAlSi308, and Ca-A12Si20R</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Brown G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusive motion in alkali silicate melts: An NMR study at high temperature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="538" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution %i NMR study of silicate and aluminosilicate glasses: The effect of network-modifying cations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Murdoch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">S E</forename><surname>Carmichael I</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="332" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in magma; at depth in the earth: The effects of pressure and dissolved H20</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">198 1</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basalt contamination by continental crust: Some experiments and models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The compensation law for diffusion in silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Winchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">High Temp. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
