<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS FOR NA, K, RB, CS, CA, SR, BA, CE, EU TO 13 00 o C AND A MODEL OF CALCULATION</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Albert</forename><surname>Jamb</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Terrestrial Magnetism</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20015</postCode>
									<settlement>Carnegie Institution of Washington Washington</settlement>
									<region>D. C</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<postCode>45046</postCode>
									<settlement>Orleans Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<address>
									<addrLine>Si02 73.01 76.87 A1203 ! 2.57 !2.20 Fe•03 1.32 FeO 1.39 0</addrLine>
									<postBox>94 MnO O.O5 O.O5 MgO O. 54 0.05 CaO 0.4 ! 0.30 NaaO 5.05 4.38 KaO 4.60 4.40 Ti02 0.20 0.07 H•O + O. 52 0.38</postBox>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cs 3.3 x 10 -14 2.50 x 10 s OIS Cs 3.0 x 10 -14 2.50 x 10 s 0IS Cs 1.1 x 10 -•3 4.23 x l0 s OIS Cs 5.2 x 10 -•3 1.0 x l0 s OIS Cs 8.6 x 10 -•3 9.0 x 104 OIS Cs 6.5 x 10 -•3 8.41 x 104 OIS Cs 8.6 x 10 -13 7.34 x 104 OIS Cs 1.2 x 10 -•2 5.52 x 104 OIS Cs 1.0 x 10 -• • 1.44 x 104 OIS Cs 6.7 x 10 -•2 1.69 x 104 OIS Cs 1.05 x 10 -• 1 1.44 x 104 OIS Cs 2.3 x 10 -• 1.44 x 104 OIS Cs 4.7 x 10 -• • 1.56 x 104 OIS Cs 8.3 x 10 -•3 1.4 x 104 OIS • Cs 4.1 x 10 -12 7.2 x 103 OIS • Cs 3.4 x 10 -• • 3.6 x 103 OIS • Cs 5.6 x 10 -• 9.0 x 102 OIS • Cs 7.84 x 10 -•2 8.5 x l0 s OVC Cs 9.54 x 10 -13 1.48 x l0 s OVD Cs 6.30 x 10 -•2 8.5 x 10 s OVD Cs 1.19 x 10 -l• 8.32 x 104 OVD Cs 3.78 x 10 -• • 1.55 x 10 s OVD Cs 1.71 x 10 -•ø 1050 9.0 x 103 OVD Cs 3.54 x 10 -lø 1097 1.86 x 103 OVD Cs 4.40 x 10 -•ø 1100 4.21 x l0 s OVDmm Cs 3.80 x 10-9 1300 5.4 x 104 OVDm • Na 2.2 x 10 -•3 5.04 x 10 s OIS Na 1.7 x 10 -• • 3.31 x 10 s OIS Na 1.1 x 10-9 7.56 x 104 OIS Na 4.2 x 10-s 1.44 x 104 OIS Na 3.0 x 10-s 9.0 x 102 OIS K 9.0 x 10 -12 4.34 x 104 OIS K 2.4 x 10 -•ø 3.6 x 103 OIS K 1.3 x 10-• 1.0 x 103 OIS K 1.2 x 10-s 1.0 x 103 OIS K 4.2 x 10-s 1.0 x 103 OIS Rb 5.3 x 10 -•3 2.5 x l0 s OIS Rb 2.1 x 10 -• 5.76 x 104 OIS Rb 3.5 x 10 -•ø 1.44 x 104 OIS Rb 2.0 x 10-s 9.0 x 102 OIS Rb 6.8 x 10-• 1.0 x 104 OIS Ca 8.5 x 10 _14 1.81 x l0 s OIS Ca 5.0 x 10 -•ø 1.8 x 103 OIS Ca 7.2 x 10 -•ø 9.0 x 102 OIS Ca 9.8 x 10 -•ø 9.0 x 102 OIS Ba 1.67 x 10 _•3 1.81 x 10 s OIS Ba 6.05 x 10 _• 1.81 x 104 OIS Pb 1.62 x 10 -lø 1.54 x 10 s OVD</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS FOR NA, K, RB, CS, CA, SR, BA, CE, EU TO 13 00 o C AND A MODEL OF CALCULATION</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E7A50DE3068135A57ACA9D0CE7D16325</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Tracer diffusivity of Na, K, Rb, Cs, Ca, Sr, Ba, Eu, and Ce has been measured in natural and dehydrated obsidians in the range 300ø-1300•C, 0-4 kbar, using radiotracers and an etching technique. The results complement and extend previous results on similar material. Diffusivity ranging from 10 -16 to 10 -? cm2/s have been observed. An Arrhenius law is observed for all species, with activation energies E ranging from 20 to 120 kcal/mol. A strong correlation of E with ionic radius and squared formal charge (Z 2) offers guidelines for model calculation of the activation energy. A mechanistic model of transport through an elastic medium is adapted to the present data. It permits a fair prediction of the activation energy as a function of r and Z according to E = 128(r-1.34) 2 + 33 Z2/(r+l.34) + 8 kcal/mol, with a misfit comparable to the experimental uncertainty. The correlation between E and the preexponential factor D o (compensation law) is discussed within the framework of the proposed model. The major conclusion is that local configuration (size, charge, coordination, etc.) is the major control for cationic diffusivity and not the properties of the matrix, such as chemical composition, viscosity, etc. about the local environment of some cations [see, et al. [1978] performed diffusion experiments for e.g., Calas, 1980]. The radial distribution functions permit one to compare different melts and give a more accurate image of their structure 1Now at Universit• d'Orl•ans, Laboratoire de G•ochimie, Min•ralogie et G•ologie Appliqu•es,</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The  <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[Taylor and Brown, 1979]</ref>. The diffusion data could complement in some ways these results if the diffusion process is better understood.</p><p>Since <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bowen [1921]</ref> first recognized that diffusion processes in natural melts could not be an efficient process for mass transport over significant distances, very little work had been done on this topic by earth scientists until recently.</p><p>On the other hand, synthetic glasses of industrial interest have been the subject of numerous studies. It is, however, very difficult for petrologists to obtain useful data from these experiments.</p><p>In the last 10 years, several earth scientists started new studies which brought about a far better knowledge of diffusion processes in natural melts, especially for basaltic and granitic composition (see review by Hofmann <ref type="bibr">[1980]</ref> and references therein).</p><p>I report here data that have been obtained in the last 8 years using essentially radiotracers and mapping diffusion profiles by sequential etching, a conventional technique.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Description of the Samples</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Starting Material</head><p>The basic material is a granitic obsidian (OIS) from a postglacial flow at Hrastinnuhrain,  <ref type="bibr">[Carron, 1969]</ref> have been performed on the same starting material. Some diffusion experiments have been reported previously for Na <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[Carron, 1968]</ref>, He [Jambon and <ref type="bibr">Shelby, 1980]</ref> and Li <ref type="bibr">[Jambon and Semet, 1978]</ref>. Several wet chemical analyses have been done over the years, and the mean is reported in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.. Chemical homogeneity any measurement with structural properties of has been checked using an electron microprobe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>melts [Mysen et al. 1980, and references therein]. Foaming occurs at 950•C, so that no experiment</head><p>New spectroscopic data have given some information can be performed at higher temperatures. Jambon destruction of the natural samples occurs at 950 ø and !000•C for OIS and OVC respectively. Below this temperature, Jambon [1 980] has shown that water loss is very slow, so that only the very surficial part of the sample is affected . The concentration profiles confirmed that this effect is negligible.</p><p>Oxidation.</p><p>According to the measurements of Muehlenbachs and Kushiro [! 974], oxygen diffusion corresponding to isotopic exchange is very slow. We may regard this as giving an upper limit to the diffusion of oxygen which will control the oxidation of the sample. This effect is therefore negligible considering the comparatively short duration of the experiments.</p><p>Because of the somewhat low iron content of the obsidian, accurate measurement of the Fe2+/Fe•+ratio failed.</p><p>Ar.gon solubility.</p><p>For the measurements performed under argon pressure in an internally heated pressure vessel, the question arose as to whether argon solubility could influence the diffusion results.</p><p>A crude estimate shows that the solubility of argon at 4 kbars does not exceed 0.1%, which is the detection limit by wheighing. Since the argon diffusivity is of the same order of magnitude as that of the cations, the conformity of the diffusion profiles shows that this phenomenon, if it exists, has no effect on tracer diffusion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Crystallisation.</head><p>In synthetic glasses,nucleation and growth of crystallites frequently occurs when the melting point is approached. Because of the volume change, this introduces stress and dislocations.</p><p>The melt-crystal interfaces could also be an easier pathway for diffusion; some of the tracer might also be trapped in crystallites.</p><p>For OIS, OVC and OVD no significant crystallization ever occured. Even after !0 days of annealing at 850•C X ray diffraction measurements do not show any characteristic diffraction peaks. Furthermore the glass samples are transparent so that any crystallization would be easily detected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Experimental Techniques</head><p>Except for minor details, the experimental technique is the same as that already described by Jambon and <ref type="bibr">Carron [1976]</ref> . Only the major characteristics are mentioned here, and the reader should refer to the prevoius paper for further details.</p><p>The samples are cut and polished   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Experimental Results</head><p>All the experimental results are reported in Table <ref type="table">2 with</ref>     is small over a pressure variation of a few kilobars. For smaller species, the effect of pressure is expected to be even less significant because of presumably smaller activation volumes .    In summary, none of the simple correlations proposed so far can describe our results satisfactorily.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Effect of the</head><p>Cationic charge.</p><p>To study conveniently the effects of the cationic charge, it follows clearly from the previous section that we have to deal with species of constant radius to remove the effects of size. Fortunately, He, Na, Ca, and Ce having similar radii can be used to investigate charge effects (Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>). As far as we know, no   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Stokes-Einstein law</head><p>From the above results, it follows that the two obvious parmueters governing diffusion rate are ionic charge and radius. Now, I will try to reconcile the experimental results with simple theoretical models. We can roughly distinguish two kinds of models:</p><p>1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The first one considers that diffusion is</head><p>comparable to the moving of a neutral sphere in a liquid; this is the well-known Stokes-Einstein law and its more sophisticated analogs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The second class of models considers that</head><p>the movement is one of a sphere moving in an elasti'e medium and thus uses elastic properties of the matrix. can be fitted reasonably well using (8) <ref type="bibr">[Shelby, 1972a,b]</ref>. On the other hand, for glasses of the systems NaaO : Si02 : and NaaO : SiOa : A1203 <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[Shelby, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Shelby and Eagan, 1976]</ref>  In our model, the elastic energy for sodium is supposed to be zero; therefore if this variation is real it implies that the electric term is affected by the addition of water. Similarly, the activation energy for Ca decreases from 68 to about 25, which is far outside analytical errors.</p><p>This confirms that both the elastic and electric components are affected by the addition of water.</p><p>If the first contribution is readily Understood, the latter is not as obvious. However, the experimental measurements of Hazen and Finger <ref type="bibr">[ 1979]</ref> showed that there is a general relationship between bulk modulus, charge of cation, and size of cation-anion polyhedra; therefore any change in the bulk modulus is expected to be correlated to a cation-anion readjustement: changing the distance between a cation and its surrounding oxygens affects both elastic and electric contributions to the activation energy. Detailed calculation of the effect is not possible yet.since the activation energies measured in hydrous melts are not very accurate and the small number of species analyzed so far do not permit an overall generalization. <ref type="bibr">Watson [1979b</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson [ , 1981] ]</ref>     </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.">Compensation Law for Obsidian</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>materials such as metals, salts, oxides, and glasses as long as a single diffusion mechanism is effective. Lacharme [1976] has shown that over a restricted temperature range (-•300øC), the overall experimental accuracy is generally insuffi-References are (1) this work, (2) this work and Carron [1968] (3) Jambon and Shelby [1980], (4) Jambon and Semet [1978], (5) Magaritz and Hofmann [1978a], (6) Magaritz and Hofmann [1978 b], (7) Reynolds [1960]. Numbers in parantheses</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Diffusion of Na and Cs in several matrices. AB2, OR2, albite and orthoclase glasses [Jambon and Carron, 1976]. BT, basalt glass [Jambon and Carron, 1978]. W, CaO:AlaO•:Si02 glass [Winchell, 1969]. The line for Na in Si02 is form Frischat[1975]. The spread in diffusivity is small compared to variations between species and even the variations with temperature.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Diffusivity for species with approximately similar radius. The line for He is from Jambon and Shelby [1980]. The fanning Arrhenius lines from a single point express the compensation law (see section 5.4) in contrast to Figures</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Correlation between activation energy E and squared valence Z 2 A similar trend was ß observed by Jambon and Delbove [1977] in feldspar glasses. He is from Jambon and Shelby [1980].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Comparison between measured activation energy (OIS: solid circles: OVD: open circles) and prediction according to equation (13) (lines). Ne is from Reynolds [1960] in a tektite glass and He from Jambon and Shelby [1980] for both OIS and OVC.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Do</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>understanding of kinetic problems and especially diffusion in natural melts is quite important in several petrological situations. The need for kinetic data is obvious in chemical mix- ing, growth from the melt, and isotopic equi- libration during anatexis or partial melting. Furthermore, quantitative data for a greater number of species should provide some insight into the structure of silicate melts. Up to very recently only qualitative information was avail- able for describing these silicate melts as a collection of more or less polymerized units [see Hess, 1971]. One can use,' for example, the ratio of bridging to nonbridging oxygens to correlate</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Rang•rvallas•sla in southern Iceland. This is an exceptionally good starting material in that bub- bles, crystals, and microcracks are almost absent. Under I mm thickness, it appears dark but still transparent. Electrical conductivity [Carron, 1968; Abelard and Cal•s, !980] and viscosity mea- surements</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>diameter. For the measurement of very slow-dif- fusing species in dehydrated obsidian (OVD), the results are greatly improved by firing the samples at !!00•C for about 15 min. The surficial melting of the sample permits healing of all the microcracks and imperfections that result from sample preparation, without deforming the disk significantly. This special preparation allowed -16 us to measure diffusivities down to 2 x !0 cma/s or profiles extending to no more than 0.5 •n. For fluid samples, e.g., OVD above !100•C, Pt tubes were used as containers. Some of these samples have been subsequently sectioned accord- ing to the technique described by Magaritz and Hofmann [!978 a]. All other samples have been sectionned by successive etching in dilute HF. Only one single tracer has been studied in each experiment. This permitted the optimization of the penetration of the tracer. Magaritz and Hofmann [1978a] showed that for obsidian there is no significant time dependence. Reproducibi- lity of the measurements was checked for the diffusion of Cs and found to be satisfactory. Linearization of the activity profiles was routi- nely done, and all the calculated diffusivities have been taken from linear plots. All nonlinear profiles have been discarded. There were very few of them, generally due to irregularity of the sample surface (especially on the edges). A simi- lar effect is observed for very short profiles if the surface is not healed before experiment. This effect precludes the measurement of the diffusi- vity of Ce in OIS and OVC because of its exceed- ingly low value at 900øC. Two replicate measurements at !!00•C on OVD by both grinding and etchinõ yielded diffusivities of 3.5 and 4.4 x !0-1øcm /s, identical within analytical uncertainty. Including all significant sources of error ( run duration, activity count- ing, weighing of slab), once can estimate a theo- retical uncertainty of +0.3 on log D (or a factor</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>as thin</cell><cell>disks</cell><cell>of 0.5</cell><cell>to 5 mm thickness</cell><cell>and 8 mm</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Eu 2.61 x 10 -•s</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">3.59 x 10 s OVD</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Eu 6.14 x 10 -•4</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.76 x l0 s OVD</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Eu 1.68 x 10 -•2 Eu 4.00 x 10 -•2 Eu 2.90 x 10 • Ce 2.5 x 10 -16 Ce 4.6 x 10 -•s Ce 5.1 x 10 -•4</cell><cell cols="3">6.48 x 104 OVD 3.44 x 10 s OVD 1050 3.60 x t04 OVD 8.5 x l0 s OVD 3.44 x 10 s OVD 1.55 x 10 s OVD</cell><cell>of 2 on D). The deviations give a mean standard deviation from Arrhenius (log D), • --0.6. lines This larger deviation includes temperature uncer-tainty, which is especially significant when tem-perature dependence is large (of the same order as all other analytical uncertainties). The over-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Ce 9.45 x 10 -•3</cell><cell>]100</cell><cell cols="2">1.86 x ]03 OVD</cell></row><row><cell>Ce 8.1</cell><cell>x 10-s</cell><cell cols="2">1300 5.4</cell><cell>x 104 OVD</cell></row><row><cell>Ce 9.3</cell><cell>x 10-s</cell><cell cols="2">1300 5.4</cell><cell>x 104 OVD</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>All data obtained using etching technique.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Institution of Washington. All other results were obtained at the University of Orleans.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 3 with standard devia- tion and temperature range. The decrease of D with temperature is strong especially for highly charged cations and heavy alkalis ( about I order of magnitude for 100•C). For the smaller alkalis Na and K, this effect is far less significant. The range of activation energy variations (a Fig. 1. Arrhenius plot for the alkalis in obsi- dians. Dehydrated obsidian (OVD), open.circles, this study. Natural obsidians (OVC), (solid squares), Magaritz and Hofmann [!978a] for two Na points and four Cs points at 800øC; (OIS) (solid circles), all this study except three measure- ments for Na by Carron [1968] above 600•C; (crosses), Cs in (OIS) 3 kbar, this study; also figured are previous measurements by Sippel [1963] for Na in an unspecified obsidian, trian- gles. 1200 1000 800 600 øC log D ••,•, , , , , i I 8 _ 10 •• Pb _ • Sr 12 14 • • - 16 6 7 8 9 10 104/T Fig. 2. Further results in obsidians. All this study. Also reported as straight lines are the results of Magaritz and Hofmann [1978a, b] for Eu and Sr in (OVC). It may be noticed that results for Ce and Eu in natural obsidian (OVC, solid circles and line) lie significantly above the corresponding lines in dehydrated obsidian (OVD, open circles). The same is observed in Figure 1. cient to reveal significant deviations from line- arity that would imply the existence of more than one mechanism. The above expression (1) can be derived from the theory of absolute reaction rate [Glasstone et al.,194!]. Application of this ex- pression to glasses has been challenged by seve- ral authors who have proposed instead equations such as D --DoT1/2exp -E1/RT (2) D = DoT exp -E2/RT (3) D = Do exp -E3/RT exp-(•/2RT) 2 (4) In the case of diffusion of He in silica glass, Shelby and Keeton [1974] have shown that (3) or (4) provided a significantly better fit of the data. The present data are not of sufficient ac- curacy to choose statistically between equations. Adding more data on other natural and synthetic material [Jambon and Carron, 1976, 1978; Jambon and Shelby, 1980; Jambon, 1980], i.e. 218 points, also does not allow resolution of this question. The usual form of the Arrhenius equation was therefore retained as adequate to describe the present data. 4.3. Pressure dependence The only measurements I have made of the ef- fect of pressure, are for Cs in OIS. The diffu- sivity at 3 kbar is very close to that at ! bar. At first sight the activation energies, 69.8 and 49.8 kcal/mol seem to be significantly different; The differences between Eu and Sr are interpreted However, the standard deviations of 9.3 and 2.0, as an effect of charge (see text). Also plotted, Ca (dots), Ba (triangles) and one Pb result. factor of 5 between sodium and cerium) makes it a useful parameter in understanding the variations of diffusion rates in these systems. The general- ly greater uncertainty in Do (or log Do) is the major reason why it has been disregarded in most previous studies. It corresponds to the intercept at the value 1/T = O. In the present experiments, the total range of 103/T is 0.7 -1.2, with an even more restricted interval for a single Arrhe- nius line; this restricted temperature interval creates uncertainties when the slope is not ac- curately determined. Because the range in Do is more than 10 orders of magnitude, it is still a possible tool for understanding diffusion proces- ses ß 4.2. Discussion of the Temperature Dependence No discontinuity was ever observed in the Arrhenius plots, in contrast with those described previously in synthetic glasses [see, e,g., John- son et al., 1951]. In the previous section it was assumed that the temperature dependence follows the Arrhenius equation: respectively, make this difference rather uncer- tain. Watson [ 1979a] has shown for the diffusion of Ca in a Na20 : CaO : AI•O•:SiO• melt, •hat tens of kilobars are necessary to see significant variations. If there is an effect of pressure, it</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>TABLE 3 . Arrhenius Parameters g• kcal/mol lo• D o Temperature cm /s Matrix range, øC Ref He 8.01 (0.32) -3.23(0.15) OIS 200-280 Li 21.5 (0.9) -1.75(0.25) OIS 300-900 Na 20.2 (0.3) -1.91 (0.18) OIS 140-850 K 25.4 (0.9) -2.46(0.24) OIS 350-850 1 Rb</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>30.4 (0.2)</cell><cell>-2.86(0.05)</cell><cell>OIS</cell><cell>400-950</cell></row><row><cell>Cs</cell><cell>49.8 (2.0)</cell><cell>-1.04(0.44)</cell><cell>OIS</cell><cell>600-920</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Cs 69.8 (9.3)</cell><cell>2.83(1.9)</cell><cell cols="3">OIS m 750-900 !</cell></row><row><cell>Ca</cell><cell>67.8 (!.1)</cell><cell>3.31 (0.22)</cell><cell>OIS</cell><cell cols="2">630-930 1</cell></row><row><cell>Ba</cell><cell>64.5 (-)</cell><cell>2.1 (-)</cell><cell>OIS</cell><cell cols="2">630-810 1</cell></row><row><cell>He</cell><cell>8.56(0.25)</cell><cell>-2.86(0.11)</cell><cell>OVC</cell><cell>190-270</cell></row><row><cell>Sr</cell><cell>42.7 (0.8)</cell><cell>-1.26</cell><cell cols="2">OVC 670-950</cell></row><row><cell>Ba</cell><cell>45.1 (1.5)</cell><cell>-1.42</cell><cell cols="2">OVC 700-950</cell></row><row><cell>Eu</cell><cell>59.1 (-)</cell><cell>-0.26(-)</cell><cell cols="2">OVC 800-950</cell></row><row><cell>Ne</cell><cell>!4.1</cell><cell>-4.54</cell><cell>xm</cell><cell>100-400</cell></row><row><cell>Cs</cell><cell>48.1 (2.9)</cell><cell>-2.01(0.45)</cell><cell cols="2">OVD 790-1300</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Ce 117.2 (5.7)</cell><cell>6.72(0.99)</cell><cell cols="2">OVD 875-1100</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Eu</cell><cell>69.0 (1.2)</cell><cell>0.89(0.22)</cell><cell cols="2">OVD 700-1050</cell><cell>I</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>concentration profile of water in their sample was poorly known, and hence the correspondence between water concentration_ and diffusivity was not accurate. Whereas the diffusivity of Cs is drastically affected by water content, Watson's [!981] results show that the effect is negligible for Na and intermediate for Ca. At this stage, it is worth noting that we have data for Eu am.d Ce in both OVC and OVD, and for Cs in OIS and OVD• In all three cases, the diffusivity is significantly lower in the dehy- drated sample, OVD (Figures 1-2). In the case of Eu one could argue that this is due to the change of the redox state of the glass (see next sec- tion); however, for Ce and Cs, this particular effect is certainly negligible. On the average, changing the water concentration from 0.3 to 0.0 wt % decreases the diffusivity by a factor of 50 to !00. This is ir• qualitative agreement with the statements of Jambon et al. [1978] that most of the increase occurs between 0 and ! wt % Since most natural obsidians have water contents between 0.1 to 0.5 wt %, the major variations in diffusivity in these glasses for a specific spe- cies will be connected to this water abundance rather than .to the chemical composition in the broader sense (SiOa concentration, for exemple). On the other hand, Arrhenius parameters show comparatively little variations. The variation of diffusivity with water con- centration is very similar to that of water it- self [Shaw,!974; Jambon, 1980; Delaney and Karsten, !98! ], for which the diffusivity increa- ses drastically between 0 and 1% water. 4.5. Effect of Diffusing...Species From the results of Figures 1-2, we can see at first glance that there is a progressive variati- on from small to large cations. This is particu- larly obvious for the alkalies. This feature can also be observed for rare gases in silica glass [Swets et al.,!961] and has been described by Jambon and Carron [!976] in feldspar glasses.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>This</cell><cell>feature</cell><cell>is not clear</cell><cell>for</cell><cell>alkaline</cell><cell>earth</cell><cell>ele-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ments,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>but these species are all smaller than K, and Ca is about as large as Na. Considering spe- cies of similar size, such as Na, Ca, Ce, and He [Jambon and Shelby, !980], we observe a progres- sive increase in the magnitude of diffusivity as well as in the activation energies with increas- ing charge ( Table 4 and Figure 4). No simple</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>TABLE 4 . Activation Energy and Diffusivity in Obsidians for Species of Similar Size but Varied Charges</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>He</cell><cell>Na</cell><cell cols="2">Ca</cell><cell>Ce</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">D 800øC, cma/s 10 -5 10 -6 5 x 10 -lø 2 x 10 -18</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">E, kcal/mol</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>20</cell><cell></cell><cell>68</cell><cell>! 17</cell></row><row><cell>Ionic</cell><cell>radius</cell><cell>1.10</cell><cell>!.24</cell><cell>1.20</cell><cell></cell><cell>1.22</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">Data for helium are extrapolated</cell><cell>from Jambon</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">and Shelby [ 1980].</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">correlation</cell><cell cols="5">with other parameters like electrone-</cell></row><row><cell>gativity</cell><cell cols="3">or ionic potential</cell><cell cols="3">has been found.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Correlation</cell><cell>with</cell><cell>ionic</cell><cell>radius</cell><cell>r.</cell><cell>As noted</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">above, the correlation</cell><cell cols="3">of diffusivity</cell><cell>and ionic</cell></row><row><cell>radius</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>is most apparent for the alkalies, since they have all the same charge and their size varies considerably. We can add to the present data those of Jambon and Semet [ 1978] on Li dif- fusion in OIS. The ionic radii are those defined by Whittaker and Muntus [ 1970] in VIII fold coor- dination. There are several reasons for this choice. One is that coordination of species in glasses is not very well known, and consequently, I chose one single coordination number. The qua- litative agreement would not be changed were it possible to choose more appropriate coordination number s.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>dif•usivity is very different from both Ce 3+ and Sr a , so an alternative explanation is needed$ A possibility is that Eu is present as both Eu • and Eu 3 , with the Eu•+/Eu •+ ratio being given by an equilibrium law. The redox state of the melt is buffered by Fea+/Fe •+ equilibrium. In this si- tuation, it can be shown [Crank, !975, chap. 14] that the measured diffusivity D will be related to the Eu•+/Eu a+ ratio. Since t• diffusivity of Eu•+(similar to that of Ce 3+) is negligible com- pared to that of Eua+(similar to that of Sra+),</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>we obtain</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>D(Eu 2+) = • (l + Eu•+/Eu 2+)</cell><cell>(7)</cell></row><row><cell>I2f as a first guess, we take D(Eu 2+) = D(Sr %), we obtain, at 900øC:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Eu•+/Eu •+ --5 x 10 a</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>This figure seems quite reasonable for a glass prepared by melting in air to allow dehydration. Further experiments conducted under controlled oxygen fugacity should confirm the present spe- culations. However, it is worth noticing that if this result and its interpretation are correct, this technique' would permit a unique determinat- ion of the Eu3+/Eu 2+ ratio, which is very dif- ficult to obtain when low concentrations are con- cerned, as is the case in natural systems.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>and r the ionic radius. As already stated by Carron [1968] and Murase [1962] and more recently in view of the many more recent data (discussed by Hofmann [1980]), this law is not appropriate in describing diffusion proper- ties of silicate melts. However, Oishi et al. [1975] have shown that there is a good agreement between diffusivity of oxygen and viscosity in the systems CaO : A120• : SiO2, Na20 :CaO : SiO2, and Na20 : SiO2. In contrast, all the cationic diffusivities determined in obsidians are far larger than D predicted by Stokes-Einstein law. A qualitative explanation could therefore be that a more efficient mechanism for diffusive transport is effective for all the cations studied so far. It is quite possible that cations with high cha- rge, like Si or A1 which are believed to have very low diffusivities, follow the Stokes-Einst- ein law. For these elements, the mechanism that</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>The Stokes-Einstein to viscosity according to the equation law relates diffusivity D• --kT/6•r where k is Boltzmann constant, T the absolute temperature (øK), is effective for other cations will not exceed that of transport by some visc6sity-related mechanism. This speculation is suggested by the quite unrealistic value obtained by extrapola-tion from cationic diffusivities toward species like Si . The disjunction between properties related to the silicate network (like viscosity) and dif-fusion suggests that this process is correlated to properties of the cation itself ( short range order) rather than the matrix ( intermediate and long range order). This view confirms qualitati-vely the fact that the chemical composition of the matrix is only a subsidiary parameter in des-cribing diffusion properties in silicate systems of geological interest. 5.3. Diffusion and Elastic-Electric Properties of Glasses Frenkel [1947] first considered the relation between diffusion and elastic properties of sol-ids. He related the activation energy to the shear modulus of the matrix. This modulus has been measured in several silicates over their</cell><cell>D</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>melting range by Murase and McBirney [1975] using ultrasonic wave propagation. For obsidians the shear modulus is constant from 1200øC to room temperature. A model for calculating the activa- tion energy of diffusion in glasses has been fir- st proposed by Anderson and Stuart [1954]. They subdivide the activation energy E into several contributions according to E = Es + Ec + Er + Ep + Ev (8) where Es is the shear energy corresponding to the elastic repulsion of the neighbors upon jumping to the next stable position. Ec is an electric energy (called Coulombian energy) which corres- ponds to the electrostatic energy involved during a jump. Er, Ep, and Ev are repulsive, polarisat- ion, and Van der Waals energy, respectively. Ep and Ev are negligible, and Er may be assimilated as a fraction of Ec and included therein. One of the obvious weakness of this model is that it implies transport via insertion like pos- itions; for transport occuring via substitution like positions, one should add one more energy term Ef, corresponding to the energy of formation of these sites. In Si02 and Si02 : TiOa glasses, activation energy for He (and other rare gases)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>suggests that the in- crease of diffusivity in hydrous melts is due to a greater number of potential sites, hence reducing the average jump distance for Cs. First, a decrease in Do and mean jump distance alone is expected to explain a decreased mobility, the</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>'</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>I</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>I</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>'</cell><cell>I</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>_</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>_</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ce</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>_</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>_</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ol</cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">.o + o.1 E _</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>E</cell><cell>-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>(o</cell><cell>_</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>_</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">•</cell><cell>0 _</cell><cell cols="8">'E Eu Li/•_r,,,,bJ,..</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>_ -</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>•</cell><cell cols="7">N•coB• •Cs</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">+ -</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="5">-5 Ne.øUs</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>5o</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>100</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>150</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>E</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="6">KCAL / MOLE</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Fig. 7.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Compensation plot for all species measured so far in obsidians. Li is from Jambon and Semet []978]. Na, Ca, and Cs in hydrated obsidians (circles) are from Watson [1979b, ]980]; all others as previously mentioned; o values are quoted for the present values and when available. The line is the visual best fit to He, Na, Ca, Ce. The alkalies in OIS are obviously not compensated (curved line). opposite of what is actually observed. Since</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>Winchell [] 969] showed that the correlation between log Do and E observed for many Arrhenian phenomena is also (approximately) valid in silicate melts and glasses. Before going into a more detailed discussion, I want to emphasize that the correlation has to be very closely observed to retain any significance. If we con- sider an Arrhenius plot bounded by temperatures of 400 ø to 1700øC and diffusivities of 10 -$ to 10 -16 cm2/s, it will contain all the diffusivi- ties measured so far, essentially because of ex-</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">perimental feasibility.</cell><cell cols="3">The transformation of</cell></row><row><cell>all</cell><cell>the lines</cell><cell>that</cell><cell>cross</cell><cell>over</cell><cell>this</cell><cell>domain with</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">negative slopes (i.e.,</cell><cell cols="3">positive activation</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">energy)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>into a compensation plot, log Do versus E, yields a truncated sector spreading along an apparent correlation line, with a half width of 47 kcal/mol at the mean value of 40 kcal/mol.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">When Winchell</cell><cell>[!969]</cell><cell cols="2">•ollected</cell><cell>diffusion</cell><cell>results</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">from all kinds of silicates,</cell><cell>including melts,</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">glasses, and crystals</cell><cell cols="3">of various compositions,</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">he obtained a correlation</cell><cell cols="2">for 134 points (o = ]5</cell></row><row><cell>kcal/mol);</cell><cell cols="5">99% of these points are expected to</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">fall within +3 •, i.e.,</cell><cell cols="2">+45 kcal/</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>mol, comparable to the width of the domain previously calculated. The point is that it requires a very high cor- relation coefficient, or a small •, for this cor- relation to have any physical significance. Such properties are observed when looking at some specific correlations, e.g., a series of glasses or a series of species in a single matrix [see Winchell and Norman, 1969; Jambon and Carron, ]978; Hart, !981]. All the data for obsidians have been plotted in Figure 7, which deserves several comments. Even though some scatter is observed, the correlation is probably real. The second point is that species, with approximately similar radii, are 'well' correlated, the remain- ing scatter being of the same order as the analytical uncertainty. This effect of compensa- tion is already clear on Figure 4, where He, Na, Ca, and Ce display Arrhenius lines fanning from a single point (= 2000øC, 2 x 10 -4 cm'/s). This property is a corollary of the compensation law. For the species with r = 1.2 •, the correlation line is approximately log Do = -4.0 + 0.] E (14) with Do in cm•/s and E in kcal/mol. It is not clear whether the data obtained for hydrous melts fall on that same line or not because of the very significant uncertainty on Do. All the larger species fall below the line, or in other words, for the same value of Do they have higher activ- ation energy and lower diffusivity than if they were compensated according to (14). Now, looking more closely at the alkalies in dry obsidians (Figure 7), we can see that they are not compensated •t all. This property is quite un--. fortunate because it precludes an accurate pre- diction by use of the compensation law. For instance, a value of log Do = -2 corresponds to E ranging 20 to 50 kcal/mol, and this is not due to an uncertainty in the data. The feature observed here for alkalies is not an overall feature of silicate glasses, since Jambon and Carron [1978] showed that in a basaltic glass the correlation is excellent. The domain of application of the compensation law will probably remain unclear until much more reliable data become available. The interpretation of the compensation law is not straightforward. Theories have been developed by Zener []952], Lazarus [!955] and R•etschi [! 958], using both mechanical and quantum 10,807 mechanical formulations. In the case of melts or glasses, only classical formulations are feasi • ble. From the present results, the compensation appears excellent for species with r = 1.2 •. From section 5.3, it follows that for these particular species, the elastic component Es is negligible, most of the activation energy stemming from the electrostatic component Ec, with the exception of He. Looking into Zener's [1950] theory of compensation is rather frustra- ting since it rests upon a formulation of the elastic energy of migration. It is possible somehow to overcome this difficulty; Hazen and Finger [1979] have shown that there exists a simple correlation between bulk modulus Kp, charge Z and anion-cation distance (r + ro). In</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>oxides and silicates</cell><cell>it yields</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">K (r + ro)3 = 7.5 Z Mbar •3 P</cell><cell>(15)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">When assuming that a similar</cell><cell>law still</cell><cell>holds in</cell></row><row><cell>glasses</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head>and because of the simple relationship between bulk and shear modulus (g -• Kp/2), we ob-</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>tain</cell><cell>for a series</cell><cell>of cations</cell><cell>with</cell><cell>constant</cell><cell>radius</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>g = • Z</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(16)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head>• being constant. This permits writing a new ex- pression of Ec, while putting (160 ) into (13). It yields for cations with r = 1.2 A: E = B g2 + 8 (17) where B, a function of the radius only, is there- fore constant in the present case. Under these conditions it may be shown (see the appendix) that a compensation relation is expected under very reasonable assumptions for isoradius spe- cies: log Do = A + B E (18) For smaller species, compensation could still hold because (17) remains still valid. The only species studied so far and corresponding to this case is Li, which is actually compensated. As long as no further confirmation from other spe- cies is available, this fit could be coincidental as well. For large= species, (17) cancels; there is an additional term of shear energy Es which affects the compensation (see the appendix). The first coefficient A in the compensation equation (18) is decreased by the addition of a negative term. This corresponds qualitatively to the variations observed for the alkalies. The order of magnitude is correct too, but the exact value depends critically on the value of r D in (9). It hoas been chosen more or less arbitrarily as 1.34 A. in addition to this we did not consider possible variations of the energy of formation of defects Ef with size. For the large cations it could be slightly different. Our conclusion is therefore that for cations with constant radius but different charge, and independently of the validity of the proposed theory, the compensation law is sufficiently well observed to be used as a predictive to91. For cations with radius of the order of 1.2 A and for smaller cations we predict that the compensation should be the same, whereas for larger cations the intercept should be de- creased and the slope remain approximately constant. If these predictions are correct, the approximate calculation of diffusivity becomes possible. Estimation of activation energy as explained in the previous section, combined with compensation effects, permits theoretically the calculation of both E and Do of the Arrhenius equation. There remains, however, some doubt about the validity of the present theory for strongly covalently bonded species, like Si. Further experimental determination will permit testing the validity of the theory and increase the accuracy of the prediction. At this point we want to emphasize that only accurate determina- tions of Arrhenius parameters are useful in delineating the theory. More approximate deter- minations may be useful to obtain a good order of magnitude for petrological calculation, but such data cannot help the development of any predic- tive theory. At the present level of knowledge, the orders of magnitude of tracer diffusivities are quite well known. The next goal is to obtain more accurate data. 6. Conclusions All previous considerations show that the diffusion process is controlled by short range order or local environment of the cation. Proper- ties of the matrix on the other hand have little or no influence on transport phenomena. Even the number of defects or available sites is rather independent of the anionic framework, as is demonstrated by the continuity over the trans- formation range. This property may not hold for less silicic systems, since in that case, some discontinuities have been observed [see, e.g., Johnson et al., 1951; Jambon and Carron, 1978]. As a consequence, study of local environments of</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>cations</cell><cell>and their</cell><cell>oxidation</cell><cell>state</cell><cell>will</cell><cell>be of</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">great interest</cell><cell cols="3">to a better understanding</cell><cell>of</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">trans port phenomena.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>and</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p></p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix</head><p>We start from a general expression of the A' = A -6.4 (r -rD) 2</p><p>For Cs the modification is A-A' = 1.6, whereas the observed variation is 2.4, surprisingly close to the predicted value.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Aknowledgements.</head><p>This </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cal•s, Mesure de la conductivit• •lectrique par la m•thode d&apos;imp•dance complexe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Abelard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Mineralogical Association Meeting</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Orleans</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Adda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Philibert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">La Diffusion dans les</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Solides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Presses Universitaires de France</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Paris</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1966-02">2. 1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calculation of activation energy of ionic conductivity in silica glasses by classical methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stuart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Ceram. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="580" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>I 954</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermal expansion and glass transition temperatures of synthetic glasses of plagioclase-like compositions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Arndt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>H•berle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="326" />
			<date type="published" when="1921">1921</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contribution • l&apos;•tude du comportement des •l•rnents de transition dans les liquides silicates magmatiques, thesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Calas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Univ. of Paris</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autodiffusion du sodium et condutivit• •lectrique dans les obsidiennes granitiques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C. R. Hebd. S•ances Acad. Sci., Ser. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">266</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="854" to="857" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Vue d&apos;ensemble sur la rh•ologie des magmas silicates natureIs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Bull. Soc. Fr</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mineral. Cristallo. gr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="446" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Mathematics of Diffusion, 2nd ed</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ion microprobe study of water in silicate melts: Concentration dependent water diffusion in obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Karsten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">634</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He migration in TiO2-SiOa glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shelby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Ceram. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He migration in glass forming oxides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shelby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3068" to="3072" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of phase separation on helium migration in sodium silicate glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shelby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Ceram. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He migration in sodium alumino silicate glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shelby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Eagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Ceram. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="420" to="425" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temperature dependence of gas diffusion in glass</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shelby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Keeton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Phys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1458" to="1460" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sodium diffusion in natural minerals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Sippel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="130" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion coefficients of helium in fused quartz</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Swets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Franck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sructure of mineral glasses: The feldspar glasses NaA1 Si308</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Brown</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">KAISi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">308</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Acta</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Calcium diffusion in a simple silicate melt to 30 kbar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geochim. Cosmochim</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Acta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="323" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of cesium ions in H20 saturated granitic melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">205</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1259" to="1260" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in magmas at depth in the earth: The effect of pressure and dissolved HaO</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">981</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ionic radii for use in geochemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J W</forename><surname>Wittaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Muntus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geochim. Cosmochim</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Acta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="945" to="956" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The compensation law for diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Winchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
