<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">OBSIDIAN COMPOSITION: AN ION-MICROPROBE DETERMINATION</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Institut de Physique du Globe</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Albert</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michel</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Semet</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Mindralogie et G~ologie Appliqude</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoires de G~ochimie</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Universitd d&apos;Orldans</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>45045</postCode>
									<settlement>Orleans Cedex (France}</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire de Gdochimie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">et Cosmochimie (L.A</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Universit~s P. et M. Curie et Paris 7</addrLine>
									<postBox>C.N.R.S. 196)</postBox>
									<postCode>75005</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris Cedex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">OBSIDIAN COMPOSITION: AN ION-MICROPROBE DETERMINATION</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">06FBC4DB485AB6EDA6186925BB0FA4BC</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received June 29, 1977 Revised version received October 4, 1977</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Tracer diffusion coefficients for Li in glasses of albite, orthoclase, and obsidian composition have been determined by a method involving deposition of a thin source on polished glass wafers, anneal under controlled temperature conditions (300-900"C), and ion-microprobe determination of the concentration profile. All results conform to an Arrhenius-type relationship, D = D O exp(-Q/RT), where Q is 23, 17, and 22 kcal mol-1;Dois 0.2, 0.003, and 0.03 cm 2 s -1 for albite and orthoclase glasses, and obsidian respectively. Lithium is thus a fast diffusing ion and behaves similarly to sodium in the same glasses. A mechanism involving jumps of the diffusing ions through oxygen hexagonal rings is suggested by consideration of ionic radii ratio of alkali (H, Li, Na, K, Rb, and Cs) ions to the oxygen anions.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Diffusion coefficients of anions and cations in silicate glasses or liquids of geological interest are prerequisite data in the interpretation of the rates at which crystals equilibrate with a magma (e.g. see Bottinga et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1 ]</ref>). The present study is an outgrowth of earlier work by our group <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref> on alkali metal diffusion in glasses of albite, orthoclase, and obsidian composition. The data for Na, K, Rb, and Ca diffusion were obtained by the conventional radioactive tracer method. Lithium, however, does not have a suitable radioactive isotope, so that a method of obtaining its concentration profile after the diffusion anneal had to be implemented.</p><p>Previous experimental work <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6]</ref> on lithium diffusion in glasses has shown that fissures appeared as I.P.G. Contribution No. 267. a result of contraction and provided fast diffusion paths. It was thus clear that this element had to be used in trace amounts before valid data could be obtained.</p><p>The ion-microprobe has been used with success in the determination of concentration or isotope ratio profiles (e.g. see Colby <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> and McHugh <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref> and has recently been specifically applied to diffusion problems of geological interest <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>. In addition, it affords a high sensitivity for lithium analysis. The analytical method described below is a direct result of these technological developments.    <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref>. Because of the relatively high diffusion coefficients the concentration profiles were spread over hundreds to thousands of microns. Therefore, direct application of the crater erosion technique under the primary beam of an ion-microprobe <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">8]</ref> for the analysis of the resulting profile was not practical.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental procedure</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Homogeneous glass wafers whose compositions are reported in</head><p>After the diffusion anneals the samples were mounted with epoxy resin in a metal ring, and polished perpendicular to the original tracer surface. A thin gold film or grid was deposited on the polished surface by vacuum evaporation.</p><p>The lithium concentration profiles were obtained with a CAMECA SMI 300 ion-microprobe. The samples are placed in the holder so that the direction of sample movement is perpendicular to the tracer surface. The Au fdm is eroded away along a traverse by the primary ion beam, which was typically of negatively charged oxygen at an energy of 14.5 keV and a current of several nanoamperes. The secondary ion current for 7Li + ions is then continuously monitored with a potentiometric recorder while moving the sample at a constant speed. The diffusion coefficient is obtained from the solution to the diffusion equation for a thin plane source (14, p. 12]:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">C(x) = C(O) exp(-x2/4Dt) (1)</formula><p>where C(x) is the concentration at a distance x from the surface, D is the diffusion coefficient, and t, the duration of the diffusion anneal.</p><p>The secondary ion current I(x), at a distance x from the tracer surface, follows from integration of the signal intensity over the primary beam spot size:</p><p>x+r</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">I(x) = a f C(p) x/r 2 -(x -p)2 dp + I(°°) (2} X--r</formula><p>where a is a constant, r is the primary beam spot size which is typically 25/2m in diameter, p is the integration variable, C(p) is given by (1), and I(~) is the signal corresponding to background concentration. For x &gt; 2r the relation: x 2 plots. The x values were corrected for the small deviation of the traverse from the perpendicular to the surface.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">I(x) -I(oo) _ exp -4D-t<label>(3)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head><p>The lithium diffusion coefficients obtained for albite, orthoclase glasses, and an obsidian of rhyolitic composition (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref>) are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>.</p><p>The data have been least-squares fitted to an Arrhenius-type relationship: <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>) and yield the activation energies, Q, and the pre-exponential factor, Do, reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">3</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">O = D o exp(-O/RT) (Fig.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>The overall linearity of the log D vs. 1/T plots (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>) indicate that a single diffusion process for Li  is operative in the temperature range studied. The diffusion rates obtained for the three glass compositions are on the same order of magnitude as for Na in M20-A1203-SiO2 glasses <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15]</ref> but differ substantially from K, Rb, and Cs behavior in being markedly faster. The rates are, however, considerably smaller than could have been predicted from Winchell's <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref> suggestion that activation energies are linearly related to ionic radii. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> presents such a diagram where our data <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4]</ref>, and this study) for Li, Na, K, Rb, and Cs in the three glass compositions are summarized.</p><p>We have chosen to attribute to those ions a coordination number equal to that found in most silicate compounds. The effective ionic sizes of the large cations (e.g. Rb and Cs mostly) in the glasses may, however, differ noticeably from the chosen value. It is readily seen that activation energies vs. ionic radius of the alkali ions follow two major trends. Ions larger than K ÷ have rapidly increasing activation energies, whereas those smaller than K ÷ show a relative constancy (15-23 kcal tool-l). These trends will not be affected in their general appearance by chosing different coordination numbers. Noteworthy also is the fact that H (H~O?) diffusion in silicate glasses is also  characterized by an activation energy on the order of 20 kcal mo1-1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>. These features suggest the following as regards to the mechanism of diffusion• The glass structure may be approximated by an oxygen close packed framework with a relatively large number of anion "vacancies"• In such a structure the anion vacancy is surrounded by a hexagonal ring of anions• The jump through the ring of alkali ions having the same size as oxygen or smaller will therefore not require the energy corresponding to the deformation of the ring but only an electrostatic component which we take to be equal to about 20 kcal mo1-1. Larger ions like Rb + or Cs ÷ will require an additional deformational energy term increasing rapidly with the size contrast between anions and cations. This is in keeping with the smaller activation energies found for the more loosely packed ortho-clase glass. Additional support for such a mechanism is found in the data of Hofmann and Magaritz <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref> who show that ionic size for divalent cations is ineffective in modifying the activation energy (approximately 40 kcal mo1-1 for Ca 2÷ and Sr 2÷ which are smaller than O 2-, and Ba 2÷ which is the same size as 02-for coordination numbers smaller than twelve). The higher activation energy for the divalent cations would be due to stronger electrostatic effects. We believe that there is a strong case for similar cation diffusion mechanisms in glasses.</p><p>Although small systematic differences in the behavior of I3, Na, and K in the glasses seem to occur a detailed mechanistic account will not be attempted here. Similarly, the data on diffusion for the other cations at hand do not warrant such an attempt more involved than is presented above• The data do, how-ever, give some experimental evidence that diffusion controlled chemical zonation in plagioclase phenocrysts (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref>) is not due to slow alkali mobility. Control must be effected by slower-moving ions and/or melt-crystal interface equilibria.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusions</head><p>We have shown that (1) the ion-microprobe is a sensitive tool for the study of lithium diffusion profiles, and (2) alkali diffusion in silicate glasses (melts?) of geological interest is dominated by processes showing relatively small activation energies and, thus, rapid rates to low temperatures for ions smaller than oxygen. The rate decreases rapidly for larger ions.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. A. Typical 7Li concentration profile. The glass-epoxy interface lies at about 1.9 mm and is indicated by the vertical stippled line. Edge effects due to polishing irregularities make the profile near the interface to depart from the theoretical profile indicated by a thin continuous line. B. Ln [I(x) -I(~)] vs. x 2 plot of the profile shown in A. x is here the distance to the glass-epoxy interface. The slope of the straight line is -(4Dt) -1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>I(0) -I(oo) is a good approximation of the prone. By plotting In [I(x) -I(oo)1 vs. x 2 one should obtain a straight line with slope -(4Dt) -1. Fig. 1A presents a typical concentration profile and Fig. 1B the corresponding In [I(x) -I(~)] vs.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Arrhenius plot of Li diffusion data in glasses of albite, orthoclase, and obsidian composition. Errors on individual determinations are approximately 0.1-0.5 log units.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig.3. Activation energies for alkali ion diffusion in glasses of albite, orthoclase, and obsidian composition plotted against ionic radii. The data are taken from Carron<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref>, Jambon and Carron<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4]</ref>, and this study• Ionic radii are from R.D. Shannon and C.T. Prewitt (Acta Crystallogr., Sect• B, 25 (1969) 925-946)• Eight-fold coordination has been arbitrarily attributed to Li + and Na ÷, • • + ÷ and twelve-fold coordmatmn to K , Rb , and Cs + (see text).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Chemical composition of the glasses used in this study (values in wt.%, except where noted otherwise)</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Obsidian</cell><cell>Albite glass</cell><cell>Orthoclase</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>glass</cell></row><row><cell>Si02</cell><cell>73.01</cell><cell>68.40</cell><cell>65.17</cell></row><row><cell>AIzO 3</cell><cell>12.57</cell><cell>19.50</cell><cell>18.20</cell></row><row><cell>Fe203</cell><cell>1.32</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>FeO</cell><cell>1.39</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MnO</cell><cell>0.05</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MgO</cell><cell>0.54</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CaO</cell><cell>0.41</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Na20</cell><cell>5.25</cell><cell>11.90</cell><cell>5.02</cell></row><row><cell>K20</cell><cell>4.60</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>11.81</cell></row><row><cell>TiO 2</cell><cell>0.20</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H20</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Li (ppm)</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>~5</cell><cell>~5</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>99.86</cell><cell>99.80</cell><cell>100.20</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">until optical flat was obtained. A thin deposit of Li</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">tracer is deposited on the polished face by evapora-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">tion of a dilute LiNO3 solution, and fusion of the</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">compound for one minute at 300°C. This results in</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">a thin plane source with lithium concentration of a</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">few tens to a few hundreds of parts per million.</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Although Li transport must be effected through an</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">interdiffusion process the use of this element in tracer</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">amounts allows determination of a diffusion coeffi-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">cient equal or close to the self-diffusion coefficient</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">[13, p. 125]. The experiments reported here are thus</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">directly comparable to determinations of diffusion</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">coefficients by radioactive tracer methods. The diffu-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">sion anneals were carried out in regulated wire-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">wound furnaces. Details of the sample preparation</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">and high-temperature anneals are reported in Jambon</cell></row><row><cell>and Carron</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE 2 Run</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">data and diffusion coefficients for lithium</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Composition</cell><cell>T</cell><cell>D</cell><cell>Anneal time</cell><cell>Number of</cell><cell>Percent</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(°C)</cell><cell>(cm 2 s -1)</cell><cell>t (s)</cell><cell>determinations</cell><cell>variation *</cell></row><row><cell>Albite glass</cell><cell>910</cell><cell>7.2 × 10 -6</cell><cell>960</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>790</cell><cell>6.8 X 10 -6</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>685</cell><cell>1.0 × 10 -6</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>582</cell><cell>2.3 × 10 -7</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>469</cell><cell>3.6 X 10 -8</cell><cell>5.76 X 104</cell><cell>6</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Orthoclase glass</cell><cell>780</cell><cell>5.3 × 10 -7</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>50</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>685</cell><cell>3.0 X 10 -7</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>582</cell><cell>1.5 X 10 -7</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>455</cell><cell>1.4 × 10 -s</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>80</cell></row><row><cell>Obsidian</cell><cell>909</cell><cell>1.7 X 10-6</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>50</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>794</cell><cell>1.0 × 10-6</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>693</cell><cell>1.9 X 10 -7</cell><cell>2.58 X 103</cell><cell>4</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>593</cell><cell>1.0 × 10-7</cell><cell>3.60 × 103</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>80</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>487</cell><cell>8.0 X 10-9</cell><cell>1.44 × 104</cell><cell>4</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>412</cell><cell>3.1 × 10-9</cell><cell>9.00 × 104</cell><cell>5</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>297</cell><cell>9.0× 10-11</cell><cell>1.76X10 s</cell><cell>6</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>* The variation is between replicate ion-microprobe profiles of a single sample. Where not indicated the variation is less or equal to 10%.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>TABLE 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Activation energies and preexponential factors for Li diffusion</cell></row><row><cell>in glasses</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Composition</cell><cell>D O</cell><cell>Q</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(cm 2 s -l)</cell><cell>(kcal mo1-1)</cell></row><row><cell>Albite glass</cell><cell>0.203 (0.150)</cell><cell>23.0 (0.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Orthoclase glass</cell><cell>2.58 (2.00) × 10 -a</cell><cell>17.2 (1.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Obsidian</cell><cell>2.52 (0.50) × 10 -2</cell><cell>22.0 (0.3)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">* The numbers in parentheses represent the standard devia-</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">tion obtained from the weighed linear least-squares fit of the</cell></row><row><cell>log D vs. 1/T plots.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The manuscript has benefited from discussions with <rs type="person">Y. Bottinga</rs>, <rs type="person">F. Albarbde</rs>, and <rs type="person">N. Shimizu</rs> and from reviews by <rs type="person">B.J. Giletti</rs> and <rs type="person">A.W. Hofmann</rs>. The reviewers should in no way be held responsible for interpretations which, in some instances, are contrary to theirs. This research was carried out under the joint financial auspices of the <rs type="institution">Universities of Orl6ans</rs>, and P. and <rs type="person">M. Curie</rs>, the <rs type="funder">Institut de Physique du Globe</rs>, and the C.N.R.S. We are grateful to <rs type="person">A. Pierre</rs> for equipment maintenance and the collection of part of the data.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some observations on ~scillatory zoning and crystallization of magmatic plagioclase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bottinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kudo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="792" to="813" />
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetic disequilibrium in trace element partitioning between phenocrysts and host lava</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Albar~de</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bottinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autodiffusion du Na et conductivit6 ~lec-trique des obsidiennes granitiques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C. R. Acad. Sci. Paris, Set. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">263</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1665" to="1668" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Etude exp~rimentale de la diffusion des ~l~ments alcalins K, Rb, Cs dans une obsidienne granitique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C.R. Acad. Sci. Paris, Ser. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3069" to="3073" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Na, K, Rb, Cs in glasses of albite and orthoclase composition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="897" to="903" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NMR study of diffusion in Li silicate glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Svanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Johanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Chem. Scand</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="755" to="774" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Frischat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Ionic Diffusion in Oxide Glasses</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bay Village, Ohio</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">182</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ion microprobe mass analysis, in : Practical Scanning Electron Microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Colby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>J.l. Goldstein and H. Yakowitz</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Plenum Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="572" />
			<pubPlace>New York, N.Y.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors that influence an elemental depth concentration profile</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mchugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Natl. Bur. Stand. Spec. Publ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">427</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An ion-microprobe study of the self-diffusion of Li + in lithium fluoride</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Coles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V P</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">471</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ion microprobe analysis of a potassium self-diffusion experiment in biotite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Giletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hinthorne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Comaford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-diffusion of potassium in low albite using an ion microprobe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gilctti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Semet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kasper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geol. Soc. Am., Abstr. Progr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">754</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studies in diffusion, III. Oxygen in feldspars, an ion microprobe determination (submitted to Geochim</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Giletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Semet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cosmochim. Acta)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shewmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Diffusion in Solids</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, N.Y.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">203</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Mathematics of Diffusion</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed., 414 pp</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion measurements using fast deuterons for in situ production of radioactive tracers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rep. Carnegie Inst. Washington</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="263" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The compensation law for diffusion in silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Winchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">High-Temp. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Diffusion of H20 in granitic liquids. Part I: Experimental data. Part II: Mass transfer in magma chambers</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Geochemical</forename><surname>Transport</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kinetics</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Giletti</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yoder</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Yund</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Carnegie Inst. Washington Publ</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">634</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">170</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts and glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rep. Carnegie Inst. Washington</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="259" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The zoned plagioclases of different magmatic environments: a preliminary ion microprobe study (submitted to Earth Planet</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shimizu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sei. Lett</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
