<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">[5] LITHIUM TRACER-DIFFUSION IN AN ALKALI-BASALTIC MELT -AN ION-MICROPROBE DETERMINATION</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lowry</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Prince Consort Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>SW7 2BP</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country>U.K.</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cambrdige</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Downing Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>CB2 3EQ</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<country>U.K.</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J B</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Nolan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mineralogy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">BriHsh Museum (Natural History)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cromwell Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>SW7 5BD</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">U.K</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V P</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">[5] LITHIUM TRACER-DIFFUSION IN AN ALKALI-BASALTIC MELT -AN ION-MICROPROBE DETERMINATION</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4F44FE037FB5E44BA43CB26E75AF31C2</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received September 15, 1980 Revised version received December 11, 1980</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>An ion-microprobe-based technique has been used to measure lithium tracer-diffusion coefficients (DLi) in an alkali-basaltic melt at 1300, 1350 and 1400°C. The results can be expressed in the form: DLi = 7.5 X 10 -2 exp(-27,600/RT) cm 2 s -1</p><p>The results show significantly faster diffusion rates than those previously recorded for other monovalent, divalent and trivalent cations in a tholeiitic melt. Consequently, diffusive transport of ions acting over a given time in a basaltic melt can produce a wider range of transport distance values than hitherto supposed. Hence, it is concluded that great care should be exercised when applying diffusion data to petrological problems.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>16.55 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1 ]</ref>); however, such a method is not applicable to all Fe2Oa 10.67 cations of geological interest, including Li. An alter-FeO 1.91 native procedure is to use an artificially enriched MnO 0.18 stable isotope (e.g. 6Li) as the tracer, whose distri-MgO 6.30 bution can readily be measured with the ion micro-CaO 9.62 probe. Indeed, two previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref> have Na20 3.79 K20</p><p>1.73 successfully used the ion microprobe for the deter-P205 0.52 mination of Li self-diffusion or tracer-diffusion coeffi-Total 100.88 cients in crystalline and glassy solids. This paper presents the results of a feasibility study on the extension of the technique to determinations in silicate melts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental procedure</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) by a method which is similar to that described by Hofmann and Magaritz <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[ 1 ]</ref>. After annealing for 3-4 days at the run temperature, a thin deposit of LiC1 * was precipitated from solution onto one end of Narrow platinum capillaries (1.5 mm nominal ID) were Filled with a natural alkaLi-basaltic melt (see * 0.98 6Li; A.E.R.E., Harwell.</p><p>0012-821X/81/0000-0000/$ 02.50 © 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company the charge. The tracer was incorporated into the glass for 5-10 minutes at 800°C and any excess removed with dilute HC1. The experiments were run for up to 6 hours at 1300, 1350 and 1400°C in a SiC tube resistance furnace to produce a diffusion profile 1-2 cm in length. The experiment durations were selected on the basis of two criteria. First, as Hofmann and Magaritz <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[ 1 ]</ref> have shown, diffusion experiments in basaltic melts for which Dt &lt; 3 X 10 -2 cm 2 are prone to error caused by transport processes other than volume diffusion. In this work the Dt values were always &gt;7 × 10 -z cm 2. Secondly, it was deemed necessary to show that the diffusion coefficient was independent of experiment duration. Consequently, the durations of the experiments at each isotherm were varied by a factor of between 1.7 and 2.0. Unfortunately, the variation could not be increased as the durations were constrained at the lower bound by the minimum desirable Dt value and at the upper by the length of profile which can be accommodated by the ion microprobe. After quenching (~30  seconds) in compressed air, the charges were mounted in epoxy resin. The resultant block was then partially ground away to expose glass along a complete longitudinal section of each charge, and subsequently polished.</p><p>The instrument used for profile determination was a modified version of the AEI IM-20 ion microprobe <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. The primary beam consisted of 160-ions accelerated to 30 kV and focused to a spot of about 15 #m diameter. The Li isotope intensities were measured by ion counting at points along the centre-line of each sample, enabling 6El/TEl to be plotted as a function of distance (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</p><p>The measured 6Li/Tti ratios must be transformed into tracer concentrations before the tracer-diffusion coefficient can be obtained using the equation below, which is derived in Appendix 1 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">B -RC tracer concentration (c) = R (1 -X) -X<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where B = 6Li concentration in the matrix, R = measured 6Li/Tti ratio, C = 7Li concentration in the matrix, and X = 6ti fraction in the tracer.</p><p>The effect of the transform can be assessed from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The relevant solution of Fick's second law for the diffusion from an instantaneous plane source into  . 1</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">C(x, t) -~ exp 4~-<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where C(x, t) = concentration at a distance x (cm) from the plane source after a diffusion time t (s), M = mass of tracer added per unit area, and D = diffusion coefficient (cm 2 s-l).</p><p>If this is rewritten in the form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">M in c = ln[~]- [~Dt ]<label>(3)</label></formula><p>it can be seen that a plot ofln c against x 2 should be linear with a slope of -(4Dt) -] . The transformed data from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head><p>The measured tracer-diffusion coefficients are given together with the relevant experimental data in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>, and are presented graphically in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. A least-squares fit of the data to the Arrhenius equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">D = Do exp(-Q/RT) (4)</formula><p>gives an activation energy (Q) of 27.6 + 2.5 kcal </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>Two features of the data set obtained here are of particular interest and are discussed below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Activation energy of diffusion</head><p>The significance of the parameter Q in equation ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) is unclear. Magaritz and Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> argue that the slope of the Arrhenius line obtained from diffusion determinations should not be considered as an activation energy, because the liquid does not have a fixed structure. Watson <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> postulates that Q is dependent upon melt microstructure (cation coordination polyhedra geometry) which is largely insensitive to temperature4nduced charges in the melt structure. Moreover, he successfully applied the concept to Ca 2+ diffusion data in a simple silicate melt. It, therefore, appears that whilst Q may not be an activation energy "sensu stricto" it is nevertheless a parameter which can be used to relate diffusion behaviour to certain aspects of silicate melt structure.</p><p>Published data for tracer diffusion in a tholeiitic melt <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref> show a range of only 8 kcal mo1-1 in the activation energies of several divalent and trivalent cations, which is within the bounds of experimental error. However, the value obtained in the present study on a melt of alkali-basaltic composition is 8 kcal mo1-1 lower than the lowest value measured in the tholeiitic melt, suggesting that significant variation may be encountered if a wider range of cations is studied.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Isothermal diffusion coefficients</head><p>The isothermal tracer diffusion coefficients exhibit two remarkable features. First, if the data of Jambon and Semet <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> for Li ÷ tracer diffusion in obsidian glass are extrapolated to 1350°C, they fall within a factor of two of our measured value for Li ÷ in an alkali-basaltic melt. However, such an extrapolation is fraught with sources of error resulting from changes in the diffusion matrix, and therefore it seems probable that the coincidence of values is fortuitous. Nevertheless, the possibility that the similarity is real provides impetus for further experiments.</p><p>Secondly, the values in Table <ref type="table">2</ref> are all significantly faster than the highest yet recorded for cations in a natural silicate liquid at 1300°C (D = 2.5 × 10 -6 cm 2 s -1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>) and therefore bring the range of observed diffusion coefficients in basaltic melts at this temperature to two and a half orders of magnitude. The value for Li ÷ is believed to represent the upper limit for diffusion of cations of geological relevance (with the possible exception of hydrogen)but the lower limit may not yet have been reached. It is tentatively proposed that such a limit may be represented by the diffusion of hexavalent uranium which may be as low as 10 -9 cm 2 s -1. This hypothesis is currently being tested experimentally.</p><p>It is interesting to note the geological relevance of a four orders of magnitude variation in D for different cations in a single melt composition. Hofmann and Magaritz <ref type="bibr">[I ]</ref> give the times taken for characteristic diffusional transport distances ((Dt) 1/2) of 5.6 cm, 56 cm and 1.8 km as i, 10 6 and 109 years respectively, assuming a diffusion coefficient of 10 -6 cm 2 s -1 . If the calculation is repeated for the data range suggested above, the results obtained are: From the above it can be clearly seen that the value for D used in mathematical models should be selected with some care. Hofmann and Magaritz <ref type="bibr">[I ]</ref> and Magaritz and Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> have used tracerdiffusion coefficients for a variety of different concentration regimes. Whilst this is a valid first approximation (and indeed all that is possible with the data currently available), it should be realised that, strictly speaking, these coefficients should only be applied to regimes where the concentration gradient is extremely small. Otherwise, the effective diffusion coefficients are termed chemical diffusion coefficients or interdiffusion coefficients. Although these are linked mathematically to the tracer-diffusion coefficients (for the equations see Wei and Wuensch [ 10] ; Cooper <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>) they may deviate from them by several orders of magnitude.</p><p>The application of tracer-diffusion coefficients to geological problems therefore requires careful consideration of the concentration regimes present in the system. As a general rule of thumb, tracer-diffusion coefficients cannot be applied directly to geological problems which involve the transport of major or minor elements in silicate melts. However, the application of tracer-diffusion data to trace element transport is probably justified as the concentration differences (i.e. the difference in concentration between the two ends of a concentration gradient) are constrained, by definition, to tens or possibly hundreds of parts per million.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>The ion microprobe provides an excellent method for the measurement of otherwise unobtainable lithium diffusion data in melts. The results for Li ÷ show an activation energy of 27.6 kcal mol-1 and a value for D1296 of 1.08 X l0 -5 cm 2 s -1 . These values are lower and faster respectively than any data previously reported for basaltic melts. For such a melt at 1300°C it is postulated that the tracer-diffusion coefficients for different cations may span a range as large as 10 -s to 10 -9 cm 2 s -1 and therefore the values used in numerical models of petrological processes need to be selected with care.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Plot of the measured 6Li/TLi ratios and derived tracer concentrations against distance for experiment D88. The values in each data set have been divided by the largest value in it to facilitate comparison of the two prof'tles.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Log-square transform of the tracer-concentration profile shown in Fig. 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1 Analysis</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>of experimental charge, alkali basalt 2266</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>One of us (R.K.L.) gratefully acknowledges the receipt of a N.E.R.C. research studentship at Chelsea</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>and Imperial Colleges, London. We are also indebted to N.E.R.C. for grants in support of the ion-microprobe unit, Department of Earth Sciences, University of Cambridge, where the diffusion-profile determinations were carried out. Critical comments by Dr. R. Freer, Dr. A. Hofmann and an anonymous referee greatly improved the final version of the manuscript. Mr. P. Watkins analysed the starting compositions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix 1. Derivation of equation (1)</head><p>Let A be the number of moles of 6Li in the tracer, let B be the number of moles of 6Li in the matrix, let C be the number of moles of 7Li in the matrix, let D be the number of moles of 7Li in the tracer. At any point the measured 6Li/TLi ratio (R) will given by: A+B R --(A-l)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C+D</head><p>If the fraction of 6Li in the tracer is X then:</p><p>where c = number of moles of tracer (tracer concentration). Substituting A-2 and A-3 into A-1 gives:</p><p>Xc +B R (1-X) c+d (A-4)</p><p>Rearranging for c:</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Ca, Sr, Ba and Co in a basalt melt : implications for the geochemistry of the mantle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5432</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An ion-microprobe study of the self diffusion of Li ÷ in LiF</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Coles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V P</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">457</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lithium diffusion in silicate glasses of albite, orthoclase and obsidian composition: an ion-microprobe determination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Semet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">445</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A combined ion probe/ spark source analysis system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Banner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Stimpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vacuum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">511</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Mathematics of Diffusion</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd ed., 414 pp</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Diffusion of Eu and Gd in basalt and obsidian</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">847</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium diffusion in a simple silicate melt to 30 kbar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">313</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diffusion measurements using fast deuterons for in-situ production of radioactive tracers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<publisher>Carnegie Inst. Washington Yearb</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">259</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model for multicomponent diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Chem. Glasses</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">55</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracer concentration gradients for diffusion coefficients exponentially dependent on concentration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C T</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wuensch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Ceram. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">295</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
