<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Trace element diffusion in jadeite and diopside melts at high pressures and its geochemical implication</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eizo</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Study of the Earth&apos;s Interior</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Okayama University at Misasa</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>682-0193</postCode>
									<settlement>Tottori</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ikuo</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Study of the Earth&apos;s Interior</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Okayama University at Misasa</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>682-0193</postCode>
									<settlement>Tottori</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Trace element diffusion in jadeite and diopside melts at high pressures and its geochemical implication</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">0EBE2CF881ECF73E5BEBEF11C504601C</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received December 15, 1997; accepted in revised form June 22, 1998</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Diffusivities of geochemically important trace elements (eleven rare earth elements (REE), Rb, Sr, Ba, and Y) in jadeite and diopside melts and those of Zr, Nb, Th, and U in jadeite melt have been measured at pressures between 7.5 and 20 kbar and at temperatures 50 -200°above the liquidus, using diffusion couples and ion microprobe analysis. The concentrations of these elements in the experimental charges are close to those in natural igneous rocks. In the jadeite melt which is nearly fully polymerized (NBO/T ϳ 0), (1) diffusivities of REE increase with increasing ionic radii, (2) diffusivities of tri-and tetravalent elements increase with increasing pressure at constant temperature, whereas those of mono-and divalent elements do not change significantly with pressure, and (3) diffusivities of these elements decrease with increasing their ionic charge at constant pressure and temperature. In the diopside melt which is considerably less polymerized (NBO/T ϳ 2), (1) diffusivities of these trace elements depend mainly on their ionic radii rather than ionic charges; the diffusivities of mono-and divalent ions decrease with increasing ionic radii at constant pressure and temperature, and (2) diffusivities of REE are nearly the same as that of Ca and decrease with increasing pressure at constant temperature. The behavior of these trace elements is correlated with that of major elements; in the jadeite melt, tri-and tetravalent elements behave similarly to network-forming cations Al and Si, whereas mono-and divalent elements behave as network-modifying cations similarly to Na. In the diopside melt, the diffusion behavior of all these trace elements is similar to that of network-modifying cations Ca and Mg.</p><p>The results of the present experiments suggest that the abundance of some trace elements in igneous rocks may have been affected by diffusion process at the magmatic stage. In the case of REE, for example, if two different magmas with high and low REE concentrations become in contact one another by multiple intrusion, and a zoned magma chamber is formed, diffusion begins to take place between them, and near the interface, the REE-enriched magma will become more light REE-depleted, whereas REE-depleted magma will become more light REE-enriched, and in addition, if magmas are reduced, the former will show a negative Eu anomaly, whereas the latter will show a positive Eu anomaly.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Magmatic processes relevant to the origin of magmas have been often inferred or discussed based on the abundance of various trace elements in igneous rocks. In many magmatic processes such as partial melting, crystallization, magma mixing, and assimilation, diffusion is involved, and the abundance of trace elements as well as those of major elements in magmas changes during such diffusion-involved magmatic processes. For quantitative evaluation of diffusion of trace elements in these magmatic processes, diffusion coefficients for trace elements in magmas over a wide pressure-temperature range must be known. Diffusion coefficients for trace elements in simple and natural magmatic melts have been measured by a number of investigators (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hofmann, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Watson and Baker, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chakraborty, 1995)</ref>. Recently, diffusion coefficients for a wide variety of elements in a haplobasaltic melt were measured at 1 atm <ref type="bibr">(LaTourrett et al., 1996)</ref>. However, the diffusivities of many geochemically important trace elements in magmas over a wide pressure-temperature range are still not known. It is also desirable to understand the mechanism of diffusion of trace elements in magmatic melts and their relations to the diffusivi-ties of major elements and to the structure and viscosity of those melts.</p><p>In the present study, the diffusion coefficients for geochemically important trace elements, eleven REE, Rb, Sr, Ba, and Y in jadeite (NaAlSi 2 O 6 ) and diopside (CaMgSi 2 O 6 ) melts have been measured at pressures between 7.5 and 20 kbar. In addition, those of Zr, Nb, Th, and U in jadeite melt were also measured at pressures between 12.5 and 20 kbar. Preliminary results on the diffusivities of REE and Ba in jadeite and diopside melts have been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Nakamura and Kushiro, 1997)</ref>. Jadeite and diopside melts were chosen because these melts are representative polymerized and depolymerized magmatic silicate melts, respectively; the former has number of nonbridging oxygen (NBO)/number of tetrahedral cation (T) ϳ 0 at least at low pressures, whereas the latter has NBO/T ϳ 2. Most natural magmas have NBO/T between 1.6 and 0 with the highest frequency at about 0.8 <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Mysen, 1987)</ref>. Also, the diffusion coefficients for major elements in these melts as well as their viscosities have been determined or calculated <ref type="bibr">(Shimizu and</ref><ref type="bibr">Kushiro, 1984, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Angell et al., 1982</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Angell et al., , 1987;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Kushiro, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Scarfe et al., 1979)</ref>. The results of the present experimental study partly confirmed previous measurements, but revealed unexpected behavior of trace elements, particularly REE, which would affect interpretation of the REE abundance data of igneous rocks. An attempt was made to explain the changes of diffusivities of above trace elements with pressure, taking account of the diffusivities of major elements and the structures of the melts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">EXPERIMENTAL AND ANALYTICAL METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Starting Materials</head><p>Starting materials of the experiments were glasses of pure jadeite (NaAlSi 2 O 6 ) and diopside (CaMgSi 2 O 6 ) compositions. Those glasses were doped with trace elements by the following procedures. Fine powders of jadeite or diopside glass and oxides of the trace elements were mixed thoroughly and melted in a sealed Pt tube at 15 kbar and 1450°C for 2 h for jadeite glass and at 10 kbar and 1600°C for 1 h for diopside glass. Two different glasses were prepared for jadeite composition; one contained REE, Rb, Ba, Sr, and Y and the other contained Zr, Nb, Th, U, and Eu. The reason for adding Eu to the latter glass is to check independently the analytical calibration for Eu as described below. These glasses as well as the doped diopside glass were examined by the ion microprobe analysis and were shown to be satisfactorily homogeneous. The concentrations of the trace elements in these glasses were determined with ICP-MS following <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Makishima and Nakamura (1997)</ref> and are all ppm levels as shown in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and<ref type="table">2</ref>. For the measurements of diffusivities, we used diffusion couples consisting of pure jadeite glass or diopside glass and the trace element-doped glasses. The charges were heated to about 800°C to remove any possible H 2 O and sealed in Pt capsule 2 mm i.d. diameter and about 8 mm long. The procedures of making these diffusion couples are the same as those described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Kushiro, 1983)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Experimental Method</head><p>The diffusion couple experiments were carried out at pressures between 7.5 and 20 kar. All the experiments were carried out with a solid-media, piston-cylinder apparatus. The hot piston-out method with 4% correction for friction was applied. The uncertainty of the pressure measurements is less than 5% near or above 10 kbar. Furnace assemblies of 3/4 inch in diameter with a tapered graphite heater <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Kushiro, 1976)</ref> were used. The temperature gradient in an 8 mm long capsule would be less than 10°. Temperature was measured and controlled with a Pt/Pt10%Rh thermocouple without correction for the effect of pressure on the emf, except the run at 7.5 kbar which was measured and controlled with a W5%Re/W26%Re thermocouple. The run durations were 4 h at 1400°and 1450°C and 8 h at 1300°C for jadeite melt and 15 and 30 min for diopside melt at 1590°C. The time required for heating from the liquidus temperatures to the run temperatures were less than 1 min for the jadeite runs and less than 30 s for the diopside runs. These heating times were not considered in the diffusion time for calculating the diffusion coefficients. In the case of jadeite runs, it causes less than 0.5% errors, whereas in the case of diopside runs, it does up to 2% errors. To examine the effect of higher oxygen fugacity, one experiment on jadeite composition was made with a crimped Pt capsule which was surrounded by hematite powder and sealed in a 5 mm-diameter Pt tube. At the end of the runs, pressure was released first and immediately (1-2 s) after the pressure release, power was cut off. The quenching rate is about 100°/s near the liquidus temperatures. By this quenching method, the charges were found to be all glass and free After the runs, the charges were mounted in epoxy and polished along the vertical axis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Analytical Method</head><p>Analyses of all the charges were made with a Cameca ims-5f ion microprobe at Misasa. Samples were sputtered with an O Ϫ primary beam of 10 nA intensity resulting in a beam size of about 10 m in diameter. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> is a secondary electron microscope (SEM) image of a polished charge of jadeite glass near the initial interface after the analyses (A), together with a close-up view of an ion probe crater (B). Positive secondary ions were collected by ion counting using an energy offset of Ϫ60 V from 4500 V acceleration with an energy bandpass of Ϯ10 V. These operating conditions resulted in secondary ion intensities of 30 Si to be 1-1.5 ϫ 10 5 cps for diopside and jadeite glasses. The secondary ion intensities of concerned masses were normalized to 30 Si. The intensity ratios are proportional to the concentration of measured trace elements in the jadeite and diopside glasses.</p><p>An energy filtering method <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Shimizu and Hart, 1982)</ref> was applied to reduce matrix effect to the secondary ions, and correction factors for large isobaric mass interferences were used. In the diffusion couple applied in this study, the matrix effect of major elements on the ionization of trace elements is canceled out because the major element composition, and melt structure are nearly identical between the doped and undoped melts. However, if diffusion rates are different among the elements studied, the matrix effect appears especially for Eu, Gd, and Dy analyses. Even if the above analytical conditions with energy filtering are applied to the REE analysis, it is difficult to eliminate properly the isobaric interference of oxide ions of in particular 135 Ba 16 O, 141 Pr 16 O and 147 Sm 16 O to 151 Eu, 157 Gd and 163 Dy, respectively. The correction factors used to subtract the isobaric oxide interference were obtained empirically by measuring oxide/metal ion ratios (i.e., 135 Ba 16 O/ 135 Ba, 141 Pr 16 O/ 141 Pr and 147 Sm 16 O/ 147 Sm for Eu, Gd, and Dy, respectively) in jadeite and diopside glasses doped only with Ba, Pr, and Sm made under the same conditions as the starting materials. We also measured a diffusivity of Eu in an Eu-doped jadeite melt without other trace elements. The diffusivity obtained was identical within the analytical error to that from multielement-doped jadeite melt at the same experimental conditions. This observation firmly supports the conclusion that the interference corrections for Eu, Gd, and Dy adopted in this study worked properly in the ion microprobe analyses. Analytical reproducibilities given by 1 relative standard deviation for the elements concerned were better than 3% in the analyses made after the experiments near the end of doped jadeite and diopside glasses, which are far from the diffusive zones and keep the initial concentrations. The relative concentrations along a diffusion profile ranged from 1 (doped level) to 0.05. It is, therefore, difficult to evaluate simply the analytical errors in this case. Analytical reproducibilities obtained for our glass standards which contain approximately two orders of magnitude lower concentrations of the doped jadeite and diopside glasses (see Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and<ref type="table">2</ref>) were better than 10%. Our analytical errors in the present study, thus, may be expressed to be 10 to a few %. Analyses were made at ten to twenty-one points along the vertical section of the charges at intervals of 50 -100 m.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Jadeite Melt</head><p>Diffusivities of REE, Rb, Sr, Ba, Y, Zr, Nb, Th, and U in jadeite melt were measured at 7.5, 12.5, 15, and 20 kbar at 1400°C (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). At 15 kbar, the measurements were also made at 1300°and 1450°C to examine the effect of temperature at constant pressure. These temperatures are 50 -200°above the liquidus temperature of jadeite. The diffusion profiles of REE and Ba in jadeite melt at 15 kbar and 1450°C are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>. The profiles of REE except Eu and Ba are close together; however, there are distinct differences. The slopes of the profiles for heavy REE such as Er, Yb, and Lu are steeper than those for light REE such as La and Ce, as shown in the enlarged diagram (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref>). Apparently, diffusivities of light REE are larger than those of heavy REE. The profiles for Ba and Eu are significantly less steep and extend for much longer distances than those for other REE.</p><p>Diffusion coefficients for all of these elements were calculated applying a diffusion model with a composite semi-infinite media by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Crank (1975)</ref> and using the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">C͑ x,t͒ ϭ C 0 / 2͓1 Ϫ erf͑ x/ 2 ͱDt͔͒</formula><p>where C(x,t) is concentration at distance x from the interface after run time t, C o is initial doped concentration, D is diffusion coefficient, and erf is error function. The results of the calculations of the diffusion coefficient are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. It is evident from the Table that at each pressure, the diffusion coefficient of REE, except Eu, increases gradually from Lu to La with decreasing atomic number or increasing ionic radius. For example, at 15 kbar at 1400°C, the diffusion coefficient increases from 0.70 Ϯ 0.12 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 cm 2 /s for Lu to 1.13 Ϯ 0.06 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 cm 2 /s for La. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> shows the diffusion coefficients of REE at 7.5, 12.5, 15, and 20 kbar at 1400°C as function of their ionic radii given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Whittaker and Muntus (1970)</ref>. The rate of increase does not appear to be constant, but appears to decrease with increasing ionic radius and have a kink in the middle (near Gd and Sm). The difference in diffusivity between La and Lu ranges from 29 to 46%. Eu has much larger diffusivities (almost one order of magnitude) than other REE under the present experimental conditions. This is most likely due to the predominance of Eu 2ϩ relative to Eu 3ϩ in the melts as discussed later. The diffusivities of Rb and Sr are larger than those of REE by more than one order of magnitude at pressures lower than 15 kbar, and Ba has diffusivity close to that of Eu. On the other hand, the diffusivities of Zr, Nb, Th, and U are much smaller (by factors of 3-10) than those of REE in the pressure range from 12.5 to 20 kbar (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>; Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</p><p>The diffusivities of REE increase with increasing pressure, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. The rate of increase is relatively small at pressures lower than 12.5 kbar, but becomes larger in the pressure range between 12.5 and 20 kbar. The effect of pressure on the diffusivities of Rb, Sr, Eu, and Ba are small. The overall trends for Eu and Ba in the pressure range from 7.5 to 20 kbar have a slightly negative pressure dependence. The diffusivities of Zr, Nb, Th and U increase with increasing pressure. The rate of increase is larger at pressures higher than 15 kbar similar to REE.</p><p>It is clear from Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> that the diffusivity decreases with increasing ionic charge of these elements from monovalent Rb to tetravalent Zr. The diffusivity of Eu is between those of Sr and Ba, suggesting that Eu would be mostly divalent. In the experiment made at 15 kbar and 1450°C with a crimped Pt capsule surrounded by hematite powder, the diffusivity of Eu relative to those of other REE was significantly reduced (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). The ratios of Eu/Sm and Eu/Gd are 10.0 and 8.95, respectively, for the run made at 1400°C with sealed Pt capsule, whereas they are 3.51 and 3.54, respectively, at 1450°C with crimped Pt capsule surrounded by hematite. A trace of graphite powder put in one of the experiments made with sealed Pt capsule persisted at least for 8 h at 1400°C. Although the values of oxygen fugacities (fo 2 ) of these runs were not exactly known, the fo 2 of the charge with sealed Pt capsule is estimated to be close to that of the C-CO-CO 2 buffer which has a slightly higher fo 2 than the quartz-fayalite-iron buffer at 15 kbar and 1450°C, whereas the fo 2 of the charge with a crimped capsule would be close to that of the magnetite-hematite buffer. Although the oxygen equilibrium may not have completely achieved in the latter experiment, it is suggested that a significant part of divalent Eu was converted to trivalent Eu during this experiment.</p><p>The effect of temperature on the diffusivities of REE and Ba is examined at 15 kbar. Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> shows the plot of lnD of representative REE (La, Gd, Eu, Dy, and Lu) and Ba as function of 1/T. The data obtained at 1450°C with crimped  capsule, except Eu, are also plotted. The data for four REE and Ba at 1300°, 1400°, and 1450°C can be fitted approximately by straight lines. The activation energies for diffusion can be calculated from the slope of these lines; they are 297.5 Ϯ 24.3 kJ/mole for or La, 345.6 Ϯ 43.9 kJ/mol for Lu and 188.3 Ϯ 17.6 kJ/mole for Ba. The value for Eu obtained from only two points is 185.8 Ϯ 26.4 kJ/mol. The error for La is large due to relatively large standard deviation in the measurement at 1300°C.</p><p>The diffusivities of Sr, Nd, and Pb in a natural rhyolitic melt with less than 1 wt% H 2 O have been measured at 10 kbar by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Perez and Dunn (1996)</ref>. The reported diffusion coefficients for Sr and Nd at 1400°C at 10 kbar are 1.24 (Ϯ0.11) ϫ 10 Ϫ7 and 8.18 (Ϯ1.42) ϫ 10 Ϫ9 cm 2 /s, respectively, which are very close to those of Sr and Nd in jadeite melt at 1400°C at 12.5 kbar [1.50 (Ϯ0.08) ϫ 10 Ϫ7 and 7.67 (Ϯ0.25) ϫ 10 Ϫ9 cm 2 /s, respectively] obtained in the present experiments. Such an agreement indicates that the diffusivities of other elements in jadeite melt would be applied to those in natural rhyolitic melts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Diopside Melt</head><p>Diffusivities of REE, Rb, Sr, Ba, and Y in diopside melt were measured at 10 and 12.5 kbar at 1590°C which is 40 -60°a bove the liquidus temperature of diopside. The diffusion coefficients calculated for these elements are given in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. As shown in the table, the diffusion coefficients of REE range from 2.15 Ϯ 0.06 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 cm 2 /s for Lu to 2.93 Ϯ 0.67 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 cm 2 /s for Eu; however, the variations are not simple as compared with those in the jadeite melt. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref> shows the diffusion coefficients of REE as a function of ionic radius at 10 and 12.5 kbar. Europium, which is assumed to be all divalent, is plotted outside the range of this figure. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>, it appears that the diffusivity increases slightly from Lu to Nd with increasing ionic radius, but becomes nearly constant or even decreases from Nd to La. The diffusion coefficient of Ca measured at 10 kbar and 1600°C is 2.77 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 cm 2 /s <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Shimizu and Kushiro, 1991)</ref>. The diffusion coefficient at 1590°C, calculated using the activation energy for diffusion of Ca in diopside melt at 10 kbar (142.7 kJ/mol.) given by the same authors, is 2.62 Ϯ 0.30 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 cm 2 /s. The value is nearly identical to that of Pr which has an ionic radius nearly the same as that of Ca (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>).</p><p>The diffusivities of REE at 12.5 kbar are smaller than those at 10 kbar, indicating that the effect of pressure is opposite to that on the jadeite melt. The diffusivities of Rb, Sr, Ba, and Y also decrease from 10 to 12.5 kbar; the rate of their decrease is smaller for Rb, Sr, and Ba than that for REE and Y. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref> shows the changes of the diffusion coefficients of these elements from 10 to 12.5 kbar at 1590°C. For comparison, the changes of diffusion coefficients of Mg and Ca from 10 to 14 kbar at 1650°C <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Shimizu and Kushiro, 1991)</ref>   The diffusion coefficients for these elements at 1590°C and 10 kbar are plotted against their ionic radii (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref>). The diffusion coefficient for Mg at this temperature was calculated based on the data at 1600°C and the activation energy for diffusion of Mg in diopside melt at 10 kbar <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Shimizu and Kushiro, 1991)</ref>. The diffusion coefficients for divalent and monovalent ions Mg, Ca, Sr, Ba, and Rb plot on a smooth curve from Mg to Rb, indicating that the diffusivity in diopside melt depends essentially on ionic radius of diffusing ions at constant pressure and temperature. A similar trend was shown for divalent ions Mg, Ca, and Ba in a melt with composition Fo 15 Di 40 An 45 <ref type="bibr">(LaTourrett et al., 1996)</ref>. The diffusivities of trivalent REE do not fit this general trend; the diffusivity slightly increases from Lu to Nd. Europium, when assumed to be divalent, is plotted off the smooth trend. If part of Eu is trivalent, the bulk ionic radius is shifted toward a position of smaller ionic radius and it would plot closer to the smooth curve, although it has a large uncertainty of measurement. The diffusivities of trivalent ions REE and Y are slightly off the curve; however, considering the uncertainties of the measurements, they are reasonably close to the curve for divalent and monovalent ions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Relation in Diffusivity between Trace Elements and Major Elements</head><p>The most interesting result of the present experiments is that the diffusivities of REE increase with increasing their ionic radii. This contradicts the general rule of diffusion that the diffusivity decreases with increasing ionic radius <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Hofmann, 1980)</ref>. To understand the cause of this anomalous behavior of REE, the diffusivities of REE and other trace elements are compared with those of major elements. The diffusivities of Si and O in jadeite melt and Si, O, Ca, and Mg in diopside melt have been measured at high pressures <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Shimizu and Kushiro, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr">1991)</ref>. The diffusivity of Al in melts along the join NaAlSi 2 O 6 -NaGaSi 2 O 6 at high pressures was also measured <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Kushiro, 1983)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Angell et al. (1982</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Angell et al. ( , 1987</ref>) calculated diffusivities of major ions in both jadeite and diopside melts up to 40 GPa (400 kbar) using molecular dynamics computer simulations. These studies demonstrated that in jadeite melt, the diffusivities of network-forming cations Si 4ϩ , Al 3ϩ , and O 2Ϫ increase, whereas that of network-modifying ion Na ϩ decreases with increasing pressure at constant temperature. On the other hand, the diffusivities of Si 4ϩ , O 2Ϫ , Ca 2ϩ , and Mg 2ϩ in diopside melt all decrease with increasing pressure at constant temperature. Increase of diffusivities of Si, Al, and O in jadeite melt and decrease of those ions in diopside melt with increasing pressure are associated with respective decrease and increase of viscosity of these melts at high pressures <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Kushiro, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Scarfe et al., 1979)</ref>.</p><p>The diffusivities of REE, Y, Zr, Nb, Th, and U in jadeite melt increase with increasing pressure similarly to network-forming ions Si 4ϩ , Al 3ϩ , and O 2Ϫ , whereas those of Rb, Sr, Ba, and Eu do not change or slightly decrease with increasing pressure. It appears that trivalent REE and Y and tetravalent Zr, Nb, and Th and U (may be partly U 5ϩ ) behave like network-forming ions, whereas monovalent and divalent ions behave similarly to network-modifying ion Na ϩ . As shown above, the activation energies for diffusion of REE in jadeite melt are 290 -350 kJ/mole, whereas those of Eu and Ba are about 190 kJ/mole. The activation energy for Si in jadeite melt is 301 kJ/mole <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Shimizu and Kushiro, 1991)</ref>, which is rather close to the activation energies for most REE, supporting the above argument.</p><p>The above trivalent and tetravalent ions are, however, too large to be incorporated in the tetrahedral sites in jadeite melt, and they might take five-coordination for oxygen ions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Fiske and Stebbins (1994)</ref>    Coefficients for Mg and Ca were calculated based on the data at 10 kbar and 1600°C given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Shimizu and Kushiro (1991)</ref>.</p><p>(1995) demonstrated based on the XAFS studies that Ti 4ϩ exists partly in five-coordinated sites and suggested that it can act simultaneously as network-former and network-modifier in silicate melts and that U 4ϩ may play a structural role similar to Ti 4ϩ . It may be possible that REE behave similarly to Mg or Ti; that is, they exist in five-coordinated sites or in both four-and six-coordinated sites. If REE behave partly as network-former, the observed decrease in their diffusivities with decreasing ionic radii may be explained; that is, the smaller REE exist more in four-or five-coordinated sites than the larger REE and show smaller bulk diffusivities. The diffusivities of networkforming ions are much smaller than those of network-modifying ions.</p><p>In diopside melt, the diffusivities of both network-forming Si and O and those of network-modifying Ca and Mg decrease with increasing pressure at constant temperature. The diffusivities of REE, Y, Rb, Sr, and Ba also decrease with increasing pressure. The rates of the decrease are, however, variable as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref>. More remarkable observation is that the diffusivities of these ions decrease almost monotonously with increasing ionic radius along a smooth curve at constant pressure and temperature as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref> for 10 kbar and 1590°C. Network-forming Si and O plot far below this curve. It is most likely that all of these ions behave as networkmodifiers, and contrary to the behavior in jadeite melt, their diffusivities do not depend on their ionic charges but depend mainly on their ionic radii. It should be noted that the diffusion coefficients for Mg and Ca were obtained by inter-diffusion of different isotopes <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Shimizu and Kushiro, 1991)</ref>, whereas those for Sr and Ba were obtained by tracer diffusion. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Lesher (1990)</ref> demonstrated that isotopic exchange (inter-diffusion of different isotopes) proceeds much more quickly than chemical homogenization. The fact that both the data for Mg, Ca, Sr, and Ba plot on a smooth curve indicates that the mechanism of diffusion of trace amounts of Sr and Ba is similar to that of inter-diffusion of magnesium and calcium isotopes; that is, tracer diffusion does not need significant structural reorganization of melt at least in case of diopside melt. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Hofmann (1980)</ref> showed a negative linear relation between the diffusivity and log(Z 2 r) for tracer diffusion in basalt melt, where Z and r are ionic charge and ionic radius, respectively. In jadeite melt, there is a broad trend showing such a log-linear relation for divalent-tetravalent ions, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9</ref>. However, such a relation does not hold among ions with the same charge. Particularly, REE except Eu show a positive relation as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9</ref>. In this case, other factors such as the proportion of different coordination of ions may be taken into account, as discussed above.   <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(1976</ref><ref type="bibr">( , 1980). Fig. 11). Fig. 11</ref>. Relation between viscosity and diffusivity for REE and Ba in jadeite and diopside melts. Viscosity data for diopside melt are from <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Scarfe et al. (1979)</ref>. Thick cross denotes the diffusivities of Gd and Eu 3ϩ in olivine tholeiite melt at about 1300°C at 1 atm given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Magaritz and Hofmann (1978)</ref>. 3157 Trace element diffusion in melts at high-pressure</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Relation between Diffusivity and Viscosity</head><p>Generally speaking, there is an inverse relation between the diffusivity and viscosity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Shimizu and Kushiro (1984)</ref> demonstrated that the diffusivity of oxygen and viscosity have an inverse relation for both jadeite and diopside melts which is fitted by the Eyring's equation. The diffusivities of REE and other elements in both jadeite and diopside melts obtained in the present experiments are related to the viscosities of these melts. Viscosity of jadeite melt was measured at pressures between 5 and 24 kbar and at temperatures between 1200°and 1500°C and activation energy for viscous flow was obtained at 7.5 and 20.7 kbar <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Kushiro, 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr">1980)</ref>. Viscosity of diopside melt was measured at 10 and 12.5 kbar at 1640°C and activation energy for viscous flow was obtained at 1 atm <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Scarfe et al., 1979)</ref>. Using these data, the viscosities of both jadeite and diopside melts at pressures and temperatures of the present experiments were calculated. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">10</ref> shows the relation be-tween the viscosity and diffusion coefficient of some of REE and Ba in jadeite melt at 15 kbar and at 1300°, 1400°and 1450°C. As discussed above Eu is most probably all divalent in the runs made at 1300°and 1400°C. As shown in the figure, there is a linear relation between the viscosity and diffusion coefficient of these elements in this log-log plot. If data at different pressures are included, the points become scattered. However, there is an approximately linear correlation between viscosity and diffusivity even if the data for diopside melt are included, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">11</ref>. The slopes for divalent Ba and Eu are steeper than those for trivalent REE. These linear relations may hold for natural magmas. The diffusion coefficients for Gd and Eu (mostly Eu 3ϩ ) in an olivine tholeiite melt are (1.4 Ϯ 0.4) ϫ 10 Ϫ7 cm 2 /s at temperatures near 1300°C <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Magaritz and Hofmann, 1978)</ref>. The viscosity of olivine tholeiite melt at this temperature is about 10 2 poise, and their data plot closely to the line for trivalent REE in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">11</ref>. The difference between the diffusivities of trivalent REE and those of divalent Eu becomes smaller with lowering viscosity; however, the latter is still larger than the former by factor of more than 3 for melts having viscosities similar to those of basalt magmas. The diffusion-induced Eu anomaly would, therefore, be produced in basalt magmas under reducing conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Application</head><p>The present results are first applied to the diffusion process in a zoned magma chamber where two different magmas with different REE concentrations are in contact with one another. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12b</ref> is a schematic diagram of such a zoned magma chamber consisting of a lower layer of heavier magma with relatively low REE concentration and an upper layer of lighter magma with high REE concentration. This zoned magma chamber would be formed if a more mafic magma intrudes into a magma chamber filled with a fractionated, more felsic magma. Such a density stratified, layered magma system is stable and can be maintained for a long time (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Oldenburg et al., 1990)</ref>. In this case, magma mixing starts at the boundary between the two layers and a boundary layer or a diffusive layer is formed, where diffusion process proceeds. The REE abundances in the boundary layer change with time, and if the magmas are reduced, Eu anomalies will be induced. The chondrite-normalized REE patterns of the upper and lower parts of the boundary layers were calculated, assuming that the chondrite-normalized concentrations of REE are 100 and 10 for upper and lower layers, respectively, and that the diffusivities of REE are the same as those in jadeite melt at 15 kbar and 1400°C. These unrealistic flat patterns are used for the simplicity of calculation. The calculated chondrite-normalized patterns after 5000 years for both the upper and lower diffusive zones at 50 cm from the original interface are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">12a</ref>. These two patterns are mirror images. The pattern for the upper diffusive zone is slightly light REE depleted and shows a negative Eu anomaly, whereas that for the lower diffusive zone has an opposite feature.</p><p>The diffusive layer thickens with time. If the diffusivities of REE are an order of 10 Ϫ7 cm 2 /s (assuming viscosities of an order of 10 2 poise for basaltic melts), the thickness of the boundary layer becomes about 50 m in 5 ϫ 10 4 years. In melts with such a viscosity, the difference in diffusivity between trivalent REE and divalent Eu is smaller than those in jadeite melt; however, there is still a significant difference between them as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">11</ref>.</p><p>Another possible case where the abundance patterns of trace elements may be affected by diffusion is partial melting. If there is a temperature gradient in a partially molten zone in the upper mantle or in the lower crust, the gradients in melt fraction and composition of melt would be produced. Melts formed in the lower-melt fraction region are more enriched in REE and other incompatible elements than those formed in the highermelt fraction region. Diffusion of the elements would take place between the melts in such different regions and a mixed zone with different trace element abundances may be formed in the partially molten zone similarly to that in a zoned magma chamber described above.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. SEM image of a part of a polished charge of jadeite glass after a diffusion experiment made at 10 kbar and 1400°C and analysis with an ion microprobe. Photo A indicates analyzed spots near the initial interface of the diffusion couple, and photo B shows a close-up view of a crater formed by sputtering of the O Ϫ ion beam during analysis for approximately 40 min.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,65.30,67.00,223.15,158.69" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Concentration profiles for REE and Ba in jadeite melt from a diffusion experiment made at 15 kbar and 1450°C. (a) Profiles for REE and Ba near the initial interface. (b) Expanded profiles for REE in the lower right portion of (a). Two solid lines denote the range of diffusion profiles of REE excluding Eu.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,63.17,67.00,227.16,572.34" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig.3. Diffusion coefficients (D, cm 2 /s) for REE in jadeite melt at 7.5, 12.5, 15, and 20 kbar at 1400°C, plotted against their ionic radii. Solid curves are polynominal best fits for the data, whereas dashed curves with a kink near Gd and Sm fit the data better.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,336.40,67.00,184.80,235.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Changes of diffusion coefficients with pressure for Rb, Sr, Ba, REE, Nb, U, Th, and Zr in jadeite melt at 1400°C.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,63.00,67.00,228.48,215.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig.6. Diffusion coefficients for REE in diopside melt at 10 and 12.5 kbar and 1590°C plotted against their ionic radii. Eu 2ϩ is plotted outside the range of this figure. Solid lines represent approximate median lines for the data points.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,337.00,519.16,183.60,160.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>suggested based on the NMR measurements that Mg 2ϩ in Na 0.28 Mg 0.18 Si 0.54 O 1.54 melt at 1400°C is either [5]Mg or a mixture of [4]Mg and [6]Mg. Brown et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Changes of diffusion coefficients with pressure for Rb, Ba, and REE in diopside melt at 1590°C. Data for Mg and Ca at 1600°C are from Shimizu and Kushiro (1991).</figDesc><graphic coords="6,85.06,67.00,183.48,205.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Changes of diffusion coefficients for REE, Y, Sr, Ba, and Rb in diopside melt at 10 kbar and 1590°C as a function of their ionic radii.Coefficients for Mg and Ca were calculated based on the data at 10 kbar and 1600°C given by<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Shimizu and Kushiro (1991)</ref>.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,63.00,506.12,228.84,174.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Relation between diffusion coefficients (D) and log(Z 2 r), where Z is ionic charge and r ionic radius, for Rb, Sr, Ba, REE, Nb, Zr, U, and Th in jadeite melt at 15 kbar and 1400°C.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,63.00,470.44,232.20,218.58" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Relation between viscosity and diffusivity for REE and Ba in jadeite melt at 15 kbar. Only four REE (La, Gd, Eu, and Lu) are plotted for simplicity of illustration. Data for other REE plot between those for La and Lu. Viscosity data for jadeite melt are from Kushiro(1976, 1980).</figDesc><graphic coords="7,316.13,67.00,225.24,160.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Changes in chondrite-normalized abundance of REE (a) by mixing of upper and lower magma layers with different REE concentrations in a zoned magma chamber (b). Initial chondrite normalized REE concentrations of the upper and lower magma layers are 100 and 10, respectively, and the time of mixing is 5000 years. Europium is assumed to be mostly divalent, as in the present experiments.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,118.45,67.00,368.28,396.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Diffusion coefficients for 19 trace elements in jadeite melt at high pressures (cm 2 /s)</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Initial</cell><cell>7.5 kbar</cell><cell>12.5 kbar</cell><cell></cell><cell>15 kbar</cell><cell></cell><cell>20 kbar</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">concentration</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(ppm)</cell><cell>1400°C, 4 Hours</cell><cell>1400°C, 4 Hours</cell><cell>1300°C, 8 Hours</cell><cell cols="2">1400°C, 4 Hours</cell><cell>1450°C, 4 Hours</cell><cell>1400°C, 4 Hours</cell></row><row><cell>La Ce Pr Nd Sm Eu GD Dy Er Yb Lu Ba Sr Rb Y Zr Nb Th U</cell><cell>(248) (245) (123) (256) (131) (25.9) (257) (283) (141) (139) (27.9) (1310) (4960) (123) (1240) (559) (56.0) (117) (100)</cell><cell cols="6">6.88 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.14) 2 8.36 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.13) 2.91 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.18) 1.13 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.56 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.46 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.09) 6.83 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.25) 8.19 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.12) 2.84 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.06) 1.04 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.44 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.41 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.03) 6.62 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.28) 8.05 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.14) 2.87 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.07) 1.00 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.04) 2.42 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.35 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.08) 6.29 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.19) 7.67 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.25) 2.71 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.06) 1.08 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.31 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.19) 2.36 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.11) 6.04 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.13) 6.82 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.12) 2.66 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.10) 0.86 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.17 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.18) 2.19 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.05) 1.12 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.12) 1.22 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.12) 4.20 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.30) 8.59 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.62) 7.61 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (1.08) 9.05 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.42) 4.89 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.37) 5.70 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.15) 1.99 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.10) 0.96 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.15 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.22) 2.18 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.11) 4.45 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.12) 5.40 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.15) 1.77 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.10) 0.85 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.04) 1.97 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.05 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.13) 4.59 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.17) 5.47 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.14) 1.69 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.14) 0.84 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.03) 2.00 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.06) 2.00 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.13) 4.64 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.13) 5.05 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.06) 1.59 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.08) 0.74 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.03) 1.85 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.03) 1.87 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.10) 4.01 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.19) 4.53 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.30) 1.44 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.06) 0.70 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.12) 1.81 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.11) 1.75 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.07) 1.03 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.04) 7.85 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.24) 2.66 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.09) 6.33 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.20) 1.07 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.07) 8.74 ϫ 10 Ϫ8 (0.46) 1.50 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.08) 1.67 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.04) 1.66 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.04) 1.74 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.09) 1.72 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.06) 1.93 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.12) 4.88 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.13) 5.31 ϫ 10 Ϫ7 (0.03) 1.54 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.38) 1.60 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.05) 2.32 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.11) 2.16 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.15) 2.50 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.08) 5.33 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.28) 1.80 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.07) 2.09 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.09) 3.80 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.29) 2.32 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.05) 2.47 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.12) 3.70 ϫ 10 Ϫ9 (0.14)</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">1) This run was made with Fe 2 O 3 powder surrounding a crimped Pt capsule</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">2) Number in parenthesis indicates 1 of individual analytical precision</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Table 2. Diffusion coefficients for 15 trace elements in diopdide</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">melt at high pressures (cm 2 /s)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Initial</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">concentration</cell><cell></cell><cell>10 kbar</cell><cell>12.5 kbar</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(ppm)</cell><cell></cell><cell>1590°C, 15 Min.</cell><cell>1590°C, 30 Min.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>La Ce Pr Nd Sm Eu Gd Dy Er Yb</cell><cell>(217) (214) (107) (223) (114) (22.6) (223) (246) (123) (121)</cell><cell cols="2">2.45 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.19) 1 2.69 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.17) 2.67 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.22) 2.67 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.17) 2.61 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.35) 2.93 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.67) 2.59 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.19) 2.48 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.15) 2.42 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.15) 2.48 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.14)</cell><cell>1.75 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.04) 1.62 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.09) 1.72 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.05) 1.87 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.22) 1.89 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.07) 2.15 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.14) 1.70 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.15) 1.46 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.09) 1.42 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.07) 1.57 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.07)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Lu</cell><cell>(24.4)</cell><cell cols="2">2.15 ϫ 10</cell></row></table><note><p>Ϫ6 (0.06) 1.22 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.08) Y (1090) 2.67 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.21) 1.75 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.08) Ba (1140) 1.21 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.08) 1.11 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.08) Sr (4340) 2.24 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.30) 2.09 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.16) Rb (109) 0.43 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.09) 0.39 ϫ 10 Ϫ6 (0.04) 1 Number in parenthesis indicates 1 of individual analytical precision 3152 E. Nakamura and I. Kushiro from cracks.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgments-The authors are grateful to <rs type="person">A. Makishima</rs>, <rs type="person">K. Kobayashi</rs>, <rs type="person">Y. Iizuka</rs> and <rs type="person">C. Sakaguchi</rs> for trace element analysis of the starting materials with ICP-MS, data reduction of ion-probe results, and preparation of SEM images, and to <rs type="person">M. J. Walter</rs> and <rs type="person">D. G. Fraser</rs> for helpful comments and improving the manuscript. We also thank <rs type="person">B. Mysen</rs> and an anonymous reviewer for criticism on this paper.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pressure enhancement of ion mobilities in liquid silicates from computer simulation studies to 800 kbar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Angell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cheeseman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tamaddon</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">218</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="885" to="887" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusivity and thermodynamic properties of diopside and jadeite melts by computer simulation studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Angell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cheeseman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kadiyala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">X-ray scattering and X-ray spectroscopy studies of silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Farges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Calas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Structure, Dynamics and Properties of Silicate Melts</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="317" to="410" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Structure, Dynamics and Properties of Silicate Melts</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="503" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Mathematics of Diffusion. 2nd edition</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structural role of magnesium in silicate liquids: A high-temperature 25 Mg, 23 Na, and 29 Si NMR study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fiske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="848" to="861" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in natural silicate melts: A critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics of Magmatic Processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hargraves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="417" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in viscosity and structure of melt of NaAlSi 2 O 6 composition at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6347" to="6350" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscosity, density, and structure of silicate melts at high pressures and their petrological applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics of Magmatic Processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hargraves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="120" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of pressure on the diffusivity of networkforming cations in melts of jadeitic compositions. Geochim. Cosmochim</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1415" to="1422" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self diffusion of magnesium, calcium, barium, neodymium, ytterbium, titanium, zirconium, and uranium in haplobasaltic melt. Geochim. Cosmochim</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Latourrette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wasserburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fahey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1329" to="1340" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decoupling of chemical and isotopic exchange during magma mixing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of europium and gadolinium in basalt and obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="847" to="858" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suppression of matrix effect in ICP-MS by high power operation of ICP: Application to precise determination of rubidium, strontium, yttrium, barium, REE, lead, throium, and uranium at ng g Ϫ1 levels in milligram silicate samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Makishima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geostand. News Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="319" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magmatic silicate melts: Relations between bulk composition, structure and properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Magmatic Processes: Physicochemical Principles</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geochemical Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="399" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusivities of rare earth elements and Ba in magmatic silicate melts at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Japan Acad</title>
		<meeting>Japan Acad</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="47" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-organization in convective magma mixing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Oldenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yuen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Sci. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusivity of strontium, neodymium, and lead in natural rhyolite melt at 1.0 GPa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Perez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1387" to="1397" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in viscosity and density of melts of sodium disilicate, sodium metasilicate, and diopside composition with pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scarfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Virgo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carnegie Inst. Wash. Yearb</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="547" to="551" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Applications of the ion microprobe to geochemistry and cosmochemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shimizu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Rev. Earth Planet. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="526" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusivity of oxygen in jadeite and 3159 Trace element diffusion in melts at high-pressure diopside melts at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shimizu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1295" to="1303" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mobility of magnesium, calcium, and silicon in diopside-jadeite liquids at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shimizu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physical Chemistry of Magmas</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="212" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical diffusion in magmas: An overview of experimental results and geochemical applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physical Chemistry of Magmas</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="151" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ionic radii for use in geochemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J W</forename><surname>Whittaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Muntus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="945" to="956" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
