<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Diffusivity of strontium, neodymium, and lead in natural rhyolite melt at 1.0 GPa WALDO</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perez ','</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of New Brunswick</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E3B 5A3</postCode>
									<settlement>Fredericton</settlement>
									<region>New Brunswick</region>
									<country>Canada &apos;Consejo</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">National de Investigaciones Cientificas y Tecnicas</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pabell&amp; INGEIS, Ciudad Universitaria</addrLine>
									<postCode>1428</postCode>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Todd</forename><surname>Dunn'</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of New Brunswick</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E3B 5A3</postCode>
									<settlement>Fredericton</settlement>
									<region>New Brunswick</region>
									<country>Canada &apos;Consejo</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">National de Investigaciones Cientificas y Tecnicas</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pabell&amp; INGEIS, Ciudad Universitaria</addrLine>
									<postCode>1428</postCode>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Edmonton</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of New Brunswick</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E3B 5A3</postCode>
									<settlement>Fredericton</settlement>
									<region>New Brunswick</region>
									<country>Canada &apos;Consejo</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">National de Investigaciones Cientificas y Tecnicas</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pabell&amp; INGEIS, Ciudad Universitaria</addrLine>
									<postCode>1428</postCode>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Alberta</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<address>
									<postCode>T6G 2E3</postCode>
									<region>AL</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Diffusivity of strontium, neodymium, and lead in natural rhyolite melt at 1.0 GPa WALDO</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">07FFE34323E67430B2049518287ADB08</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received January 9, 1995; accepted in revised form January 4, 1996</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemical diffusivities approximating</head><p>tracer diffusivities of Sr, Nd, and Pb have been measured in a natural rhyolite melt at 1.0 GPa and temperatures from 1000 to 1450°C using the diffusion couple technique. Diffusivities for all three elements were determined under nominally anhydrous conditions. Lead diffusivities were also determined at -1 and 2.5 wt% dissolved Hz0 in the melt. The results are described by the following Arrhenius equations (D in m'/s, activation energy in Jlmol, Tin Kelvin): D cSr,dryj = 1.58 X lo-' em(262200'RT) DCNd,+,,) = 1.28 X lo-' em(33"200'RT' D tPb,dry, = 1.92 X 10e7 em('48400'RT' DCPb,-,%) = 1.18 x lo-' e-('3'700'RTi DCPb,--z.5Bj = 2.18 X 10m9 e~(72600'RT).</p><p>The results are consistent to within an order of magnitude with previously reported Sr, Nd, and Pb tracer diffusivities.</p><p>Under anhydrous conditions, the relative magnitudes of the diffusion coefficients are Dsr = DPb &gt; D,, . DNd determined in this work is similar to previously reported Ds, The implication of these results is that Pb and Sr diffusion-controlled isotopic and chemical exchange can occur at a faster rate than major element chemical exchange, but that Nd exchange occurs at about the same rate as major element exchange. The consequences of this process are illustrated with a model of isotopic exchange in a basaltic-granitic, double-diffusive, convecting magma chamber. The diffusivity of Pb increases with increasing dissolved water more than that of Si increases suggesting that, at least for Pb, isotopic homogenization also occurs faster than chemical homogenization under hydrous conditions.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Diffusion is a process of transport of matter. Chemical diffusion occurs as a result of chemical potential gradients in a system and self-diffusion as a result of "random-walk." Diffusion was not considered to be an important petrogenetic process during the early years of this century when thermal diffusivities were known to be several order of magnitude larger that chemical diffusivities and most igneous systems were considered to be chemically closed systems <ref type="bibr">(Bowen, 1921)</ref> However, modem chemical and isotopic studies, applied to both whole rocks and minerals in several suites, indicate that the evolution of magmas in closed systems is the exception rather than the rule in nature (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Eichelberger, 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr">Grove et al., 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">Reagan et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hildreth and Moorbath, 1988)</ref>. The chemical and isotopic diversity of igneous rocks is now thought to be the product of different simultaneous processes such as assimilation, fractional crystallization, magma mixing, and magma replenishment <ref type="bibr">(Taylor, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr">DePaolo, 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr">O'Hara and Matthews, 1981)</ref>. In this "open system' ' paradigm, diffusion is a fundamental parameter, which controls chemical and isotopic homogenization during magma mixing, contamination of the magma by assimilation of wall rock, and affects the kinetics of crystal growth during fractional crystallization and the kinetics of xenocryst dissolution during partial melting.</p><p>In recent years, a large diffusivity dataset has been produced for network-former and network-modifier elements in natural melts, both at 1 atmosphere and higher pressures <ref type="bibr">(e.g., Hofmann, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jambon, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lowry et al., 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dunn, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dunn and Ratliffe, 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson and Baker, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr">Baker, 1989</ref><ref type="bibr">Baker, , 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">Baker, , 1991</ref><ref type="bibr">Baker, , 1992;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lesher, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">Lesher, , 1994))</ref>. Surprisingly, the diffusivities of Sr, Pb, and Nd, the most common elements used as isotopic tracers, have not been measured at high pressure in the same melt. To address this shortcoming, we have measured chemical diffusivities of Pb, Nd, and Sr at low concentration levels in order to approach tracer diffusivities.</p><p>The experiments were run under nominally dry conditions between 1450 and 1175°C using the diffusion couple technique. Lead diffusivities were also determined in melts with water contents of approximately 1.0 and 2.5 wt%, at temperatures between 1400 and 1000°C. Rhyolite was chosen as the starting material because highly polymerized high-silica melts have been shown to have the lowest diffusivities <ref type="bibr">(Baker, 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">Henderson et al., 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr">Jambon, 1982)</ref>. Thus, those diffusivities will, most likely, be rate limiting in diffusion-controlled processes involving silicic melts <ref type="bibr">(Lasaga, 1983)</ref>.  Detection limits were: 190 ppm (Sr), 300 ppm (Nd) and 220 ppm (Pb) ##II -number of analyses and models of diffusion-fractional crystallization (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Stewart and DePaolo, 1992)</ref>. As an example, we develop a hypothetical model to show how diffusion can affect the isotopic composition of a stratified, compositionally zoned magma chamber.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">EXPERIMENTAL AND ANALYTICAL PROCEDURES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Starting Material</head><p>A rhyolitic obsidian from Newberry Caldera, Oregon, USA. was used as the starting material. The obsidian was powdered in an agate mortar and split into several aliquots. Two aliquots were doped with approximately 0.36 wtY&amp; PbO and 1.24 wts SrO, respectively. Three other aliquots were doped with Nd at concentrations of 0.1, 0.5, and 1 .O wts Nd,O,.</p><p>A final aliquot was undoped. The splits were fused in a controlled atmosphere furnace (1400°C; 0.1 MPa; Fayalite-Magnetite-Quartz (FMQ) buffer imposed by CO-CO2 gas mixtures) and crushed 4 times to produce homogeneous glass. Compositions of the doped and undoped glasses, determined by electron microprobe as described below, are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. The glasses were crushed in an agate mortar to a grain size of less than 50 p and used to prepare diffusion couples.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">High-Pressure Experiments</head><p>The experiments were done by the diffusion couple technique using a cylindrical geometry (Dunn and <ref type="bibr">Ratliffe, 1990)</ref>. Graphite capsules were used for all runs. The graphite capsules were not further encapsulated for most nominally anhydrous runs and were encased in welded Pt capsules for water-bearing runs. Capsules were loaded by tightly packing the doped glass powder into the bottom of the graphite capsule with a polished steel rod. The undoped glass powder was packed into the top of the capsule and the capsule was closed with a layer of graphite powder.</p><p>Combined Sr-Nd diffusion experiments were done by tilling the bottom of the capsule with Nddoped glass and the top of the capsule with Sr-doped glass. Water was added to the hydrous experiments with a microsyringe. The graphite capsule was then placed in a Pt capsule, which was crimped and welded shut.</p><p>The experiments were done at I .O GPa in a non-end-loaded pistoncylinder apparatus using NaCl/Pyrex/crushable-MgO sample assemblies. The hot-piston-out method was used for all runs. Tempera-tures were monitored with uncalibrated Pt-Pts,Rhiz thermocouples separated from the tops of the capsules by 0.5 mm thick alumina spacers. Temperatures are estimated to be accurate to within 2 10°C. Pressure was monitored with a Bourdon tube gauge and reported pressures are thought to be accurate to within kO.05 GPa based on determinations of the melting point of NaCl at 1 .O GPa. During short duration runs (t c 1 h) at high temperature (7 2 13OO"C), the sample was heated over a period of 1 to 2 min to 1100°C and then rapidly heated (t &lt; 5 s) to the run temperature. The temperature controller was set to minimize temperature overshoot, which was always less than 5°C. Runs were terminated by turning off the heater power. Cooling during the first 1 to 2 s of the quench occurred at -3Oo"C/s.</p><p>All samples quenched to bubble-and crystal-free glass. After the experiment, the capsule was cast in epoxy and cut in half perpendicular to the original interface.</p><p>One half of the capsule was mounted for electron microprobe analysis and the other half was used to prepare a doubly polished glass plate for water and carbon dioxide analysis.</p><p>The oxygen fugacity of the experiments is controlled by the furnace assembly and capsule materials.</p><p>At the conditions and composition of our experiments, the oxygen fugacity is expected to be close to FMQ for the graphite-Pt capsules and below FMQ in graphiteonly capsules <ref type="bibr">(Holloway et al., 1992)</ref>. At these oxygen fugacity conditions and the range of temperatures used for the runs, basic thermodynamic data <ref type="bibr">(Robie et al., 1979)</ref> indicates that the Pb in the samples will be present as Pb*'. The fact that our Pb diffusivity results compare favorably to diffusivities of other divalent cations and not with those of tetravalent cations <ref type="bibr">(Hofmann, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson, 1994)</ref>  -not analyzed yses of glasses were done with the UNB JEOL 733 electron microprobe by combined EDS and WDS methods, using an accelerating potential of 15 keV, a sample current of 0.5 nA, and a detector live time of 100 s for EDS analysis of nominal major elements.</p><p>Trace element (Sr, Nd, and Pb) data were acquired by WDS methods at 15 keV, 50 nA sample current, and counting times from 60 to 200 s. EDS data were acquired first, then the points were reoccupied for the high current trace element analyses.</p><p>The EDS and WDS data were merged and reduced relative to mineral (albite-Na, Al, Si; bytownite-Ca; otthoclase-K; garnet-Fe: olivine-Mg; celestine-Sr). inorganic fluoride (NdF,-Nd) and metal (Ti, Mn, and Pb) standards.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Water and Carbon Dioxide Analyses</head><p>The water and carbon dioxide contents were determined for twenty-three of the forty-two samples by infrared spectroscopy (Tables 2 and 3). All of the samples to which water was added were analyzed, as were selected nominally anhydrous samples.  <ref type="bibr">(1986)</ref> showed that the density of andesite glass quenched from high pressure is intermediate between the densities of glass quenched from the same temperature at 1 bar and the density of melt at high pressure.</p><p>At 1200°C. the computed densities of the anhydrous starting glass (Table <ref type="table">I</ref> ) are 2.34 and 2.52 g/cm3 at 0.1 MPa and 1 GPa, respectively <ref type="bibr">(Lange and</ref><ref type="bibr">Carmichael, 1987, 1989: Kress and</ref><ref type="bibr">Carmichael, 199 I )</ref>. If the density of glass quenched from 1200°C and 1 GPa is -2.4 g/cm2 (cf. <ref type="bibr">Dunn and Scarfe, 1986)</ref>. then using the one bar glass density will result in an over-estimation of the water and CO? contents of the glass by approximately 2.6% and a similar magnitude underestimation will occur when the high pressure melt density is used. Thus, glass densities, calculated for the run conditions assuming an oxygen fugacity on the FMQ buffer, were used, noting that this introduces a systematic error of --4% to the water and CO? determinations.  The total uncertainties in the measured water and carbon dioxide contents are difficult to evaluate since they depend on the respective accuracies of the measured thickness, the density calculation, the extinction coefficients, and the spectroscopic measurements. Considering those factors, the uncertainties in the CO2 and water determinations are estimated to be ?20'?&amp;%.  <ref type="table"></ref>and<ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). Representative data sets from Pb and Nd-Sr diffusion runs and the concentration profiles calculated from the measured diffusion coefficients are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Time series experiments were done to demonstrate that diffusion is the dominant mass transfer process operating during the experiments <ref type="bibr">(Dunn, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dunn and Ratliffe, 1990)</ref>. With four exceptions (Pb at 1175°C and 1450°C anhydrous and Pb at 1000 and 1400°C at 2.5 wt% water; Table <ref type="table">2</ref>), at least two and as many as six experiments were run for each element at each temperature. Run durations for replicate experiments varied by factors from 1.5 to 6. The results (Tables <ref type="table">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>), which are independent of experimental duration, within analytical uncertainty, are consistent with diffusion being the dominant mass transfer process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">RESULTS</head><p>The forty-two diffusion experiments yielded thirteen Sr, sixteen Nd, and twenty-five Pb diffusivities. The Pb diffusion experiments included fifteen nominally anhydrous runs, six runs with -1 wt% dissolved water, and four runs with -3 wt% dissolved water (Table <ref type="table">2;</ref><ref type="table"></ref>  where the activation energies are in Jlmol, T is in Kelvin, and uncertainties are reported at the 95% confidence level.</p><p>Although the bulk of the experiments were nominally anhydrous, infrared spectroscopic measurements of the water contents of selected nominally dry samples demonstrate that all measured samples, run in welded platinum capsules or open graphite capsules, have water contents between 0.2 and 0.7 wt% (Tables <ref type="table">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). <ref type="bibr">Stolper et al. (1987)</ref> measured similar water contents in "nominally dry' ' piston-cylinder experiments and suggested that, independent of the techniques used to assure dry conditions, there is always some dissolved water in piston-cylinder experiments, because it is impossible to keep Hz out of the furnace assembly. The HZ reacts with FeZOX and CO:-in the melt and produces HZ0 <ref type="bibr">(Holloway et al., 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fine and Stolper, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr">Stolper et al., 1987)</ref>. Therefore, although our "dry" runs actually contain -0.5% water, we believe that the results are comparable to other '&lt;dry" high pressure diffusion data (where dissolved water was not measured). Consequently, for the purpose of the present discussion (and mainly for comparative reasons), the nominally anhydrous data set of the present study is referred to as "dry."</p><p>The carbon dioxide contents of the samples are positively correlated with the water contents independent of run temperature (with the exception of samples 30 and 46, Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). In general, the carbon dioxide contents of the samples are comparable to the carbon dioxide contents of melt inclusions in quartz crystals from the Bishop Tuff <ref type="bibr">(Anderson et al., 1989)</ref>. This similarity in carbon dioxide contents suggests that our diffusion results can be applied to natural rhyolites with carbon dioxide contents similar to Bishop Tuff magmas without concern for the effects of dissolved carbon dioxide on diffusivities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">DISCUSSION</head><p>Strictly speaking, the experiments reported here are multicomponent chemical diffusion experiments. Thus, the total flux of a diffusing species (J, ) is given by the Onsager extension to Fick's Law: Ji = C -D,j (dpj/dx), Because the doping levels used in this study are small (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> ), the relative magnitudes of the chemical potential gradients of components other than the dopant species are small compared to the gradient for the dopant spe- ties. Thus, contributions to the total flux of the dopant species due to [ Di,,( dpjqildx); i # j] terms in Eqn. 8 are expected to be small relative to the dopant species term [D,,,( dp,/ ax); i = j] as long as the on-diagonal D,,j is not much smaller than the off-diagonal D,, . Furthermore, the chemical potential gradients for species (j) other than the dopant species (i) are opposite in sign to the dopant species term. Therefore, if the contributions of those terms to the total flux of the dopant species are significant compared to the dopant species term, they will cause uphill diffusion of the dopant species <ref type="bibr">(cf. Richter, 1993)</ref>. The lack of evidence for uphill diffusion (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>) suggests that the off-diagonal terms are not dominant.</p><p>If the i # j terms in Eqn. 8 make significant contributions to the total flux of dopant component i (J, ) , then decreasing the concentration level of the dopant component should decrease those contributions and result in a corresponding increase in J, and the value of D,,, determined from Eqn. 2. This possibility was tested by doing Nd diffusion experiments at different doping levels (0.1, 0.5 and 1 .O wt%; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) The results (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> ) show that the diffusivity of Nd is independent of concentration up to at least 1.0 wt% Nd203. These results are in agreement with those of <ref type="bibr">Wei and Wuensch ( 1976)</ref> who found that chemical diffusivities, measured in atomic concentration gradients up to a few atom percent, differed from tracer diffusivities by less than 20% absolute. That level of uncertainty is comparable to the average two standard deviation uncertainties for the diffusivities measured in this study (27%, Pb; 1 l%, Sr, 22%, Nd; Tables <ref type="table">2</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). Thus, we conclude that the chemical diffusivities reported here are within analytical uncertainty of tracer diffusivities.</p><p>A comparison of our results with previously published data for tracer diffusivity in silicic melts is shown in Fig.  <ref type="bibr">SiOZ (Lesher, 1994)</ref>; (i, j) Si diffusion at 75 wt% SiOZ dry and with 3 wt% water <ref type="bibr">(Baker, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">(Baker, , 1991))</ref>; (k, 1, m, n) Eu and Ba in pitchstone and panterllerite, respectively <ref type="bibr">(Henderson et al., 1985)</ref>; (0) Sr in dry rhyolite <ref type="bibr">(Baker, 1989)</ref>. assuming 74 wt% SiO,; point Sr", determined by Baker, 1989, by thin source experiments using x5SrCl). The diffusivity of Sr obtained in this paper intersects or is slightly lower than results for Ba in silicic melts <ref type="bibr">(lines BaL and Ba", Henderson et al., 1985 )</ref> Our Nd results (line NdE) are also similar to but slightly smaller than previous high temperature determinations of the diffusivity of Nd (line Nd*, calculated from Eqn. 7b of Lesher, 1994, assuming 74 wt% SiO*) and Eu <ref type="bibr">(lines EuK and EuU, Henderson et al., 1985)</ref>. Our results for Pb diffusion are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> as lines PbA ("dry"), Pb" ( 1 wt% water) and PbC (2.5 wt% water). Jambon ( 1982) made a single determination of the diffusivity of Pb at 1 bar (Point PbF) His data point lies three fourths of an order of magnitude lower than the extrapolation of our "dry" data set (line Pb"). In contrast, our "dry" Pb results are virtually identical to the Sr diffusivity of Lesher ( 1994) (line SrG), the Sr diffusivity of Baker (1989) (point Sr"), and the Ba results of <ref type="bibr">Henderson et al. (1985)</ref> (lines Ba', and Ba'). Those results are consistent with the prediction by <ref type="bibr">Lesher ( 1994)</ref> that Pb diffusivities should be similar to Sr diffusivities.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> also shows Si chemical diffusivities at 75% silica in dry melt and in a melt with 3 wt% dissolved water (lines Si <ref type="bibr">' and Si", respectively)</ref> from <ref type="bibr">Baker (1990</ref><ref type="bibr">Baker ( , 1991))</ref>. The diffusivities of Sr and Pb in dry melt are larger than the diffusivity of Si under dry conditions, whereas the diffusivity of Nd is smaller than that of Si. The implication of these results is that lead and strontium isotopic and chemical exchange can occur at a faster rate than major element chemical exchange, but that Nd exchange occurs at about the same rate as major element exchange. Under hydrous conditions, the diffusivity of Pb remains larger than that of Si, thus lead isotopic and chemical exchange will continue to be faster than major element chemical exchange.</p><p>The effect of increasing the dissolved water content of the melt is to increase the diffusivity of Pb in rhyolitic melt at 1.0 GPa (Figs. <ref type="figure">2</ref> and<ref type="figure">3</ref>). The magnitude of this effect decreases with increasing temperature because the activation energy for Pb diffusion decreases from 148400 J/mol under nominally dry conditions to 72600 J/mol at 2.5 wt% dissolved water (Eqns. 3, 4, and 5). Overall the effect of dissolved water on the diffusivity of Pb is the same as that observed for Zr and P diffusion by <ref type="bibr">Harrison and</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson (1983, 1984)</ref> and for Si diffusion by <ref type="bibr">Baker (1990</ref><ref type="bibr">Baker ( , 1991))</ref>.</p><p>The effect of dissolved carbon dioxide on the measured diffusivities cannot be resolved. Experiments with similar water contents run under similar conditions but with different carbon dioxide contents (e.g., experiments 46 and 41 Table <ref type="table">2</ref>, and experiments 73 and 79, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>) yield diffusivities that are within analytical uncertainty.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Applications</head><p>As discussed previously, this study determined chemical diffusivities that approximate tracer diffusivities. The validity of this approximation is illustrated by the fact that the differences between true tracer diffusivities reported by other authors and the present results are less than one order of magnitude (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>). Since our diffusivities are all slightly smaller than the true tracer diffusivities, our data provide lower limits for the tracer diffusivities of Sr, Nd, and Pb in rhyolitic melts. Strontium, lead, and neodymium tracer diffusivities in igneous melts can be used to model a variety of petrologic problems. Recently, <ref type="bibr">Stewart and DePaolo (1992)</ref> showed that the isotopic and chemical signatures of the tops of some mafic layered intrusions can be controlled by a combined process of diffusion and fractional crystallization (DFC) . Other applications include modelling the extent of isotopic homogenization expected for mafic enclaves enclosed in granitic magma (Baker, 199 I), and modelling isotopic homogenization in a composite mafic-felsic layered magma chamber <ref type="bibr">(Baker, 1990)</ref>.</p><p>In order to illustrate the magnitude of diffusive exchange in igneous systems and the differences between the Sr, Nd, and Pb systems, we developed a simple model of isotopic homogenization in a layered magma chamber (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Huppert et al., 1988)</ref>. Our model is similar to that discussed by <ref type="bibr">Baker ( 1990)</ref> for Sr, but we have applied it to three isotopic systems. Following Baker ( <ref type="formula">1990</ref>)) we assumed a cylindrical magma chamber containing equal volumes of basaltic and granitic magma. In such a system, mass and heat transfer occur via double-diffusion across a thin static boundary layer between layers that are themselves well mixed by convection <ref type="bibr">(Turner, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr">Turner and Campbell, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr">Spera et al.. 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr">Clark et al., 1987)</ref>. We model diffusive exchange across the static boundary layer between the two halves of a double-diffusive convecting magma chamber. A sketch of the model and the starting conditions are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4a</ref>. The thicknesses of the chemical boundary layers between the two convecting magmas in our model magma chambers were calculated using Eqn. 22 of <ref type="bibr">Clark et al. (1987)</ref>. For chamber heights of 500, 5000, and 10000 m, the calculated thicknesses of the chemical boundary layers are 0.0042, 0.0087, and 0.0108 m, respectively. The parameters used in those calculations are given in Table <ref type="table">4</ref>. It is worth noting that the thicknesses of the chemical boundary layers in this study are much less than the 0.2 m thickness calculated by <ref type="bibr">Clark et al. (1987)</ref> for a 5 km thick magma chamber. The smaller thicknesses here are a consequence of the fact that the present model is for anhydrous magmas. <ref type="bibr">Clark et al. ( 1987)</ref> did their calculations for a hydrous system in which the silicon diffusivity is much larger and the viscosity of the silicic melt is much smaller. The basaltic magma was assumed to be at a temperature of 1300°C and the temperature of the granitic magma was assumed to be 1200°C. These temperatures are thought to be representative of the dry liquidii of basaltic and granitic magmas, respectively, at 1.0 GPa <ref type="bibr">( Wyllie, 1988)</ref>. Diffusivities of Pb, Sr, and Nd for the models were calculated from Eqns. 3, 6, and 7, respectively, assuming a double-diffusive boundary layer temperature of 1250°C.</p><p>The conditions described above closely approximate diffusion across a membrane separating two compositionally uniform reservoirs. <ref type="bibr">Crank (1979)</ref> presents a solution to the diffusion equation for that geometry <ref type="bibr">(Eqn. 4.24: Crank, 1979)</ref> where the concentrations of the diffusant in the two reservoirs are constant. We have used that equation, calculating in 1000 year time steps out to 2 million years, to model diffusive exchange in the composite magma chambers de- In order to model the change in the isotopic composition of the system, we followed Baker (1990) and computed fluxes of the individual isotopes of each element across the boundary layer. Figure <ref type="figure">4b</ref>, c, and d show the results of the isotopic transfer models for Sr, Nd, and Pb under the assumed conditions. For the smallest magma chamber modelled ( 1000 m diameter, 500 m height), significant chemical and isotopic exchange begins after approximately 400 years for Pb and 900 years for Sr. This time range is well within the expected thermal lifetime of small magma chambers according to heat flux calculations <ref type="bibr">(Furlong and Myers, 1985)</ref>. Neodymium, on the other hand, would take more than 10,000 years to suffer significant modification, and thermal death of the chamber will likely terminate the homogenization process. Since the diffusivity of Nd is comparable to that of Si (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>), the time required for neodymium isotopic homogenization is indicative of the time the entire chamber would take to chemically homogenize via major element diffusion across the boundary layer.</p><p>The models shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4b,</ref><ref type="figure">c</ref>. and d are easy to compute since isotopic homogenization is only dependant on selfdiffusion. Chemical homogenization though is dependant on the activity of the element in the couple <ref type="bibr">(Richter, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lesher, 1994)</ref>. If the diffusivity of the element is much faster than the diffusivities of the network-former elements (as is the case for &amp; and Dpb) then isotopic homogenization could be achieved while concentration differences persist for the particular element on the two sides of the couple. Lesher (1994) determined the activity coefficients of Sr in basaltic and rhyolitic melts. This information allows us to model the Sr chemical homogenization across the couple and to compare the result with the model of strontium isotope homogenization. The activity coefficient for the rhyolite was calculated from the composition of the undoped rhyolite (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) We used the 1300°C partial melt composition from the peridotite melting study of <ref type="bibr">Baker and Stolper ( 1994)</ref> to compute the activity coefficient for the basalt.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4e</ref> shows the results of the models of chemical transfer of Sr under the same conditions as those used for the isotopic homogenization models shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4d</ref>. The models show an apparent decoupling of the chemical and isotopic compositions of Sr resulting from the differences in the activity coefficients for the trace elements in the two magmas (i.e., isotopic equilibration occurs when there are still significant chemical concentration differences between the two magmas)</p><p>The models in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> are useful to understand the nature of the "decoupling" of isotopic exchange from chemical exchange in a stratified system and warn us that finding chemical differences across an interface in such a system does not mean there was limited isotopic exchange. Although these models are illustrative of the extent to which diffusion can affect isotopic and chemical exchange in composite magma chambers, they are not directly applicable to natural systems. They ignore cooling of the chamber, major element mass transfer across the boundary layer, and other concurrent natural processes that we know affect the evolution of magmas, such as fractional crystallization, assimilation, mixing, and magma withdrawal from the chamber. Crystallization will change the compositions of the magmas, which will change diffusivities and activities in the residual melts and increase the viscosities of the melts, seriously compromising magma convection. In addition, crystallization of phases in which the elements of interest are compatible will effectively remove those elements from the reservoir in which the crystallization occurs. For example, crystallization of plagioclase in the basaltic or granitic melt will deplete the melts in Sr and Pb and will tie up isotopically primitive (i.e., less exchanged) Sr and Pb. The effect will be to reduce the extent of isotopic equilibration of the melts relative to that predicted by models in which crystals are not a factor. Such a process would also produce plagioclase crystals with strontium isotopic signatures lower (basalt) or higher (granite) than the whole rock value, as was found by <ref type="bibr">Wasserburg et al. ( 1964)</ref> in a sill in Warm Spring Canyon and by <ref type="bibr">Stewart and DePaolo (1992)</ref> in the basal&amp; of the Muskox intrusion.</p><p>The extent of isotopic perturbation in a composite magma chamber is, at best, very difficult to estimate. As discussed above, it will be controlled by several factors, such as the longevity, size, and shape of the magma chamber, the rate of replenishment and the extent of fractional crystallization. However, based on the measured diffusivities, is important to stress that strontium and lead isotopic signatures of silicic melts (and crystals, if concurrent fractional crystallization occurs) can be perturbed in geologically short periods of time, particularly if the magma chamber is convecting in a double-diffusive regime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Under anhydrous conditions the diffusivity of Sr in rhyolite melt at 1 GPa is comparable to that of Pb, but the diffusivity of Nd is from one to one and a half orders of magnitude smaller. The measured diffusivities of Sr, Pb, and Nd compare favorably with previous determinations of Sr, Ba, Nd, and other REE diffusivities. The diffusivity of Nd is similar to that of Si in melts of approximately the same composition. Thus, the rate of change of the neodymium isotopic composition of a melt will be similar to that of the major elements for processes that are rate limited by diffusion. In contrast, due to their larger diffusivities, strontium and lead isotopic exchange in the same systems will occur at rates faster than those of neodymium isotopic exchange or major element compositional change. Thus, Nd is a more reliable isotopic tool to trace processes of bulk assimilation, magma mixing and, where the extents of assimilation and mixing are either small or can be quantified, to determine the isotopic composition of the source region of the magma.</p><p>The diffusivities of Sr and Pb are large enough to produce significant perturbations of the isotopic signatures of compositionally contrasting magmas that are in diffusive contact. The cases in which such perturbations would be more obvious are stratified magma chambers under a convecting regime and small magmatic enclaves in a compositionally distinct magma chamber.</p><p>The complexity of diffusion-controlled isotope exchange processes makes it very difficult to determine the relative importance of such processes in magmatic systems. Consequently, it is equally difficult to determine if such processes have occurred. Thus, we must be very cautious when estimates of the mantle and crustal components of a magma source are done using only the strontium and lead isotopic signatures of derivative melts. Differences between the isotopic composition of bulk rock and early crystallized minerals may constitute the only proof that diffusion-controlled isotopic exchange occurred.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(fo.51)~10-" 3.41(*0.33)~lV'~ 4.35(+0.32)~10-~~ 2.23(*0.46)x10-I4 5.56(M.69)xlO-" 1.56(*0.29)x10-I4 * 6.99(+0.62)~10"~ 1.43(+0.15)x10-'2 6.22(*3.28)x10-I4 l.13(M.18)x10-'2 8.06(*2.96)x10-" 1.46(M.l5)xlO-'* 9.17(*2.84)x10-I4 1.60(M.l4)~10~'~ 1.34(*0.25)x10-" 3.08(iO.37)~10-'* 1.8O(kO.38)~10-'~ * 2.17(~.22)~10"~ 2.62(iO.34)~10~'~ 1.63(M.26)~10-'~ 5.26(*0.70)x10-" 4.22(ti.86)~1@'~ 3.89(*0.42)~10"~ 2.30@0.22)xlO-" l 8.18(+1.42)x10-" 1.24(!~0.11)~10-" l.Ol(~.72)xlO-" 4.26(*0.65)~10"~ 3.17(*0.26)~10~'~ 6.82(*0.67)x10-'* 5.77(*0.53)x10-'" ln.8. -*-capsules were either graphite (Gr) or graphite lined Pt (Pt-Gr) not analyzed sample was not Sr doped</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the diffusion equation for concentrationindependent diffusion under the boundary conditions imposed by the sample geometry is (Crank, 1979) C(x, t) = (C,/2) erfC(XI(2J(Dt)), (1) where D is the diffusion coefficient, t is the experimental duration, erfc(z) is the converse error function of z, C(x, t) is the concentration of the diffusing species at distance (x) from the original interface after time (t), and C,, is the initial concentration in the x &lt; 0 end of the diffusion couple (C = 0 for x &gt; 0 at t = 0). Noting that erfc(z) = 1 erf(z), and that the diffusing element is initially present in both halves of the diffusion couple at concentrations C, (x &lt; 0) and C,(x &gt; 0), leads to a linear form of Eqn. 1 that can be fit to diffusion profiles: xl(2d(Dt)) = erf-'( -(2C(x, t) -c, + C2)/(C, -C,)}. (2) At least forty data points were collected along the length of each sample. Raw counts from the doped and undoped ends of the diffusion profiles were used to define values of C, and Cz, respectively. Equation 2 was fit to the data from the central portion of the couple (where [(C(x, t) -C2)/(C, -C,)] 5 0.95), in the form of raw counts vs. distance, using least squares. The slopes of the equations were used to compute the diffusivities. The uncertainties in the regressed slopes and in the experimental durations were used to compute the uncertainties in the diffusion coefficients (Tables 2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 1. Representative diffusion profiles for (a) Pb and (b) Nd-Sr. Error bars on the data points are based on counting statistics and are reported at the 95% confidence level. The solid lines are concentration profiles calculated from the derived diffusion coefficients.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>is the diffusion coefficient of component (i) in response to the chemical potential gradient of component j (dpj/dX).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 2. Plots of the diffusion results for (a) Sr and Nd and (b) Pb. Lines are regression fits of Arrhenius equations to the data. The equations are given in the text. The Arrhenius line for Pb diffusion in rhyolite with 2.5 wt% water is shown as a dashed line because the slope of that line is determined almost entirely by the location of the single data point at 1000°C.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 3. Arrhenius plot comparing the results of this study (thick lines) with literature data for Sr, Nd, Pb, and other divalent cations and rare earths (thin lines) and Si (dashed lines). Data sources are (a) Pb in dry rhyolite; (b) Pb in rhyolite with 1 wt% water; (c) Pb in rhyolite with 2.5 wt% water; (d) Sr in dry rhyolite; (e) Nd in dry rhyolite; (f ) Pb in obsidian at 0.1 MPa in air (Jambon, 1982); (g, h) Sr and Nd at 74 wt%SiOZ (Lesher, 1994); (i, j) Si diffusion at 75 wt% SiOZ dry and with 3 wt% water(Baker, 1990(Baker,  , 1991)); (k, 1, m, n) Eu and Ba in pitchstone and panterllerite, respectively(Henderson et al., 1985); (0) Sr in dry rhyolite(Baker, 1989).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 4. (a) Schematic model of a double-diffusing magma chamber showing the initial chemical and isotopic compositions of the endmembers. (b), (c), and (d) Results of model calculations for isotopic exchange of Nd, Pb, and Sr across the boundary separating the two halves of a double-diffusing composite magma chamber. (e) Result of the model of Sr chemical exchange using the activity coefficient formula of Lesher ( 1994). Curves in (b), (c), (d), and (e) indicate the size of the magma chamber: ( 1) I km diameter, 0.5 km height; ( 10) 10 km diameter, 5 km height; (50) 50 km diameter, 10 km height.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Electron microprobe analyses of starting glasses (wt.%).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Analyses</cell><cell>have been</cell></row></table><note><p>nd. -not detected.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Experimental conditions and results of the Sr and Nd diffusion experiments. Uncertainties are reported at the two standard deviation level.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Run</cell><cell>T"C</cell><cell>Cap'</cell><cell>t</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(s)</cell></row><row><cell>83</cell><cell>1175</cell><cell cols="2">Pt-Gr 36000</cell></row><row><cell>71</cell><cell>1175</cell><cell>Pt-Gr</cell><cell>36000</cell></row><row><cell>81</cell><cell>1175</cell><cell cols="2">Pt-Gr 23520</cell></row><row><cell>62</cell><cell>1275</cell><cell>Gr</cell><cell>3600</cell></row><row><cell>67</cell><cell>1275</cell><cell>Gr</cell><cell>3600</cell></row><row><cell>68</cell><cell>1275</cell><cell>Gr</cell><cell>3600</cell></row><row><cell>78</cell><cell>1275</cell><cell>Pt-Gr</cell><cell>5400</cell></row><row><cell>76</cell><cell>1275</cell><cell>Pt-Gr</cell><cell>3600</cell></row><row><cell>85</cell><cell>1275</cell><cell>Pt-Gr</cell><cell>3600</cell></row><row><cell>63</cell><cell>1350</cell><cell>Gr</cell><cell>3600</cell></row><row><cell>77</cell><cell>1350</cell><cell>Pt-Gr</cell><cell>2700</cell></row><row><cell>72</cell><cell>1350</cell><cell>Pt-Gr</cell><cell>1800</cell></row><row><cell>84</cell><cell>1350</cell><cell>Pt-Gr</cell><cell>1500</cell></row><row><cell>64</cell><cell>1400</cell><cell>Gr</cell><cell>1630</cell></row><row><cell>73</cell><cell>1400</cell><cell>Gr</cell><cell>1800</cell></row><row><cell>70</cell><cell>1400</cell><cell cols="2">Pt-Gr 2700</cell></row><row><cell>79</cell><cell cols="2">1400 Gr</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>AcknowledRnzents-We</head><p>thank <rs type="person">Don Baker</rs>, <rs type="person">Robert Creaser</rs>, <rs type="person">Robert Luth</rs>, <rs type="person">Colin Macpherson</rs>, <rs type="person">Frank Spera</rs>, and Yuanming</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Mineral.</p><p>Petrol. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
