<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">[6] DIFFUSION IN MAGMAS AT DEPTH IN THE EARTH: THE EFFECTS OF PRESSURE AND DISSOLVED H20</title>
				<funder ref="#_tQbGJsK #_N8PDKr9 #_BNRtFm7">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSF</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Research Corporation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Earth Sciences Section, National Science Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Bruce</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>12181</postCode>
									<settlement>Troy</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">U.S.A</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">[6] DIFFUSION IN MAGMAS AT DEPTH IN THE EARTH: THE EFFECTS OF PRESSURE AND DISSOLVED H20</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">14FDA9C7C7987FA763FC5D3AC64C8FF7</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received September 11, 1980 Revised version received October 27, 1980</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Experimental data on cation diffusion in silicate melts and glasses at atmospheric pressure cannot be quantitatively applied to diffusion in magmas at depth because pressure and dissolved H20 have significant effects. Diffusivities of Ca and Cs in soda-lime aluminosilieate melt are reduced by roughly an order of magnitude as pressure increases from 1 to 30 kbar at 1100°C (in the case of calcium, the pressure effect is smaller at higher temperatures). The influence of dissolved H20 is opposite to and (for some ions) far more important than that of pressure: at 700°C, Cs diffusion in granitic obsidian is enhanced by four orders of magnitude by the addition of 6 wt.% H20, and Ca diffusivity increases by 2.5 orders of magnitude. Sodium diffusion, on the other hand, is relatively immune to changes in H20 content.</p><p>The retarding effect of pressure on diffusion in deep-seated magmas is largely compensated by higher magmatic temperatures, such that overall "depth" effects on diffusion are of secondary importance -diffusion rates in mantle melts are probably well approximated by 1-atm, neaxqiquidus values. Diffusion rates in crustal magmas, however, are extremely sensitive to H20 content, so that models of rate-controlled processes in hydrous magmas may be grossly in error if 1-atm diffusivity values are used.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The potential significance of ionic diffusion as a rate-controlling factor in magmatic processes was recognized some time ago by Bowen <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. Curiously, Bowen's early diffusion measurements (interdiffusion of diopside and plagioclase melts) were not widely applied to models of igneous processes, perhaps because their general validity was unknown and because instruments were not available to measure diffusion gradients in natural samples. In the past 10-I 2 years, renewed and widespread interest in ionic transport in magmas has arisen, stimulated largely by the realization that many igneous systems, ranging in scale from volcanic-rock thin sections to the Earth's mantle, do not represent complete chemical equilibrium.</p><p>The recent interest in diffusion in magmas has prompted several experimental investigations, among which are the studies by Sippel <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, Carron <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, Jambon and Carron <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and Magaritz and Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref> on granitic obsidian, and by Medford <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, Hofmann and Magaritz <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and Magaritz and Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> on basaltic melts. The combined efforts of these workers have yielded diffusion data for alkali, alkaline earth, rare earth, and transition elements in melts or glasses that encompass the normal compositional range of magmas. The results, which are summarized by Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, are now complete enough that estimates of diffusivities (D's) can be made for many cations at all geologically reasonable temperatures. In fact, because of the systematic dependence of diffusion rates upon cation size and charge (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>), approximate diffusion rates can be assigned to some cations not yet studied experimentally.</p><p>The main limitation of the existing body of diffusion data is that the values are strictly applicable only to magmas near the surface of the Earth. 0012-821X/81/0000-0000/$ 02.50 © 1981 Elsevier Scientific Publishing Company Although allowance can usually be made for the increase in magmatic temperatures with depth, any effects of other petrologic variables, such as pressure and dissolved volatiles, are difficult to predict. The purpose of this paper is to provide a basis for extrapolation of 1 -arm diffusion data to depth in the Earth. I will consider pressure and dissolved H20 content as the main variables of interest, although other volatiles clearly may have some influence in specific cases. I will draw from the small amount of published data on the effects of pressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[ 11 ]</ref> and dissolved H20 <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref> on Ca and Cs diffusion, respectively, but I will also present new data on diffusion of Cs at upper mantle pressures and of Na and Ca in granitic melts of varying H20 content. The emphasis will be upon experimental results, although simple theoretical considerations will be discussed where appropriate as aids to generalization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The effect of pressure in the absence of volatiles</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">General theoretical considerations</head><p>For pure substances in which self-diffusion rates have been measured as a function of pressure, a relation of the following form usually holds:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Dp, T = Do,Texp(-PVa/RT) (1)</formula><p>where Dv, T is the diffusivity at pressure P and absolute temperature T, Do, T is the diffusivity at zero pressure and the same temperature, R is the gas constant, and Va is a constant that has the units of volume and is generally termed the "activation volume". The physical significance of the activation volume necessarily varies with diffusion mechanism: In crystalline solids where a vacancy mechanism applies, V a can be resolved into two components, Vv and Vm, which are the partial molar volume of vacant sites and the volume increase per mole of activated species, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. In melts, where the concept of a v.acant site loses significance <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>, it is reasonable to suppose that Va ~ Vm. In no material should the activation volume be regarded as independent of temperature <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> or of diffusing species. Naghizadeh and Rice <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[ 17]</ref> explained variations in activation volumes for self-diffusion in several van der Waals liquids in terms of compressibility: the more corn-pressible the fluid, the greater the decrease in diffusion rate with applied pressure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Diffusion of calcium and cesium in molten silicate at high pressures</head><p>The only previous measurements of the effect of pressure on diffusion in materials resembling magmas are those I reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> for Ca diffusion in a sodiumcalcium-aluminosilicate melt (29% Na20, 5% CaO, 10% Al203, 56% SiO2). Although some geological relevance was lost by use of this composition, it was chosen in order to maximize the P-T range over which diffusion data could be obtained. Because I believe that the measured pressure effects on diffusion are at least qualitatively applicable to basic magmas (diffusion systematics in amorphous silicates appear to be generally insensitive to bulk compositional changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>), the same melt was used for the cesium experiments reported here. Beta-emitting radiotracers were used for both elements (4SCa and 134Cs), so that dif- fusion profiles could be directly mapped on nuclear emulsion plates. The specific experimental techniques used for the Ca experiments, along with a discussion of the sources of error in the data, are given by Watson <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[ 11 ]</ref>. The only differences introduced in the present experiments on Cs diffusion are that (1) all runs were made in a solid-media, pistonCylinder apparatus, and (2) the soft AgC1 pressure medium used in the Ca experiments was replaced by harder but tight-fitting boron nitride that resulted in equally good preservation of the sample geometry at run conditions.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">--- [', J4°°° " E 3oo° E ,o'\,</formula><p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>, Ca diffusivity is most sensitive to variations in pressure at the lowest temperature studied (1100 ° C), and becomes progressively less sensitive with increasing temperature. At 1100°C, Dca decreases by a factor of "7 as pressure is increased from 1 to 20 kbar;at 1400°C, Dca changes by a factor of only 1.4 over the same pressure interval. Isothermal equations for the pressure dependence of Dca are as follows: at 1100°C,Dca = 5.15 X 10 -7 exp(-ll.9P/RT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> at 1200°C, Dca = 9.73 X 10 -7 exp(-6.3P/RT)</p><p>(3) at 1300°C,Dca = 1.5 X 10 -6 exp(~-.71P/RT) (4) at 1400°C,Dca = 2.4 × 10 -6 exp(-2.24P/RT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> (In these equations, the units of pressure are dyne/ cm 2 and R = 8.3157 × 107 dyne cm/deg mole). Equations (2) to ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) have the same form as equation ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>); note the systematic negative dependence of activation volume, Fa, upon temperature. The data shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> can be re-plotted to illustrate the isobaric temperature dependence of Dca (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). The isobars in this figure are given by the following equations:  Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. Isothermal pressure dependence of cesium diffusivity in a sodium-calcium-aluminosilicate melt. The 2o error estimates (-+ 17%) are taken from observed variance among 5 replicate Ca diffusion experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[ 11 ]</ref>, and assumed to apply to these measurements. The "fit" to the 1200 ° data points is obviously speculative; it is based on the slopes of the 1100 ° and 1300 ° lines. See text for equations of lines. </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">D = Do exp(-EffRT) (<label>9</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">)</formula><p>where R is the gas constant in cal/deg mole, and Do and E a are constants, the latter having the units kcal/ mole and the designation "activation energy". From the observation that the slopes of the lines in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> are equivalent to -Ea/R, it is clear that E a increases markedly with increasing pressure (cf. values in equations ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) to ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>)).</p><p>Because it has been found that the retarding effect of pressure on diffusion of alkalies in solid alkali sill-cate glasses is proportional to the size of the diffusing species <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, it was expected <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11 ]</ref> that Cs diffusion in silicate melt would be more sensitive to pressure than Ca diffusion, as Cs ÷ is considerably larger than Ca 2÷. Although the data for Cs are not as complete as those for Ca, it is apparent from a comparison of Figs. 1 and 3 that increased pressure has similar effects on the diffusivities of the two elements at 1100°C, but that Cs mobility is more effectively reduced by increases in pressure at 1300°C (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> for a summary of data). Given in the form of equation ( <ref type="formula">1</ref> • 18 kbar X 15</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">• 6 I • ' ] i | | i • 0 . i | | i | | • . , • 6 -?</formula><p>104/T°K Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. Data of Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> re-plotted to show isobaric dependence of cesium diffusivity upon temperature. See equations ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>).</p><p>the pressure dependence of Dcs is: at llO0°C,Dcs = 8.02 × 10 -7 exp(-9.9P/RT) (10)* at 1300°C,Dcs = 5.17 × 10 -6 exp(-12.9P/RT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>*</p><p>where the units are the same as in equations ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) to (5).</p><p>In agreement with previous studies, the activation energy for Cs diffusion at low pressure is larger than that for Ca (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>), but it is also apparently less sensitive to changes in pressure: From the similarity in the pressure dependencies of Dca and Dcs at low temperature (1100°C), it might be deduced that it is primarily the compressibility of the bulk diffusion medium, not the compressibility of the individual cation-oxygen bonds <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[ 11 ]</ref>, that determines the activation volume for diffusion. However, because the activation volumes for Cs and Ca diffusion differ significantly at higher temperatures, no general conclusion regarding the interrelationship between ion or melt compressibilities and Va can be drawn at the present time. Calcium and cesium diffusion systematics are obviously dissimilar (cf. sub-parallel lines in Figs. <ref type="figure">3</ref> and<ref type="figure">4</ref> with "fanning" lines of Figs. <ref type="figure">1</ref> and<ref type="figure">2</ref>), which may indicate that the structural role of Ca in the melt is temperature and pressure dependent, while that of Cs is not. It is possible, for example, that Ca participates in the formation of anorthite-like molecules at lower temperatures, which reduces its mobility in the melt.</p><p>From the data presented above, the following conclusions can be drawn regarding the effect of pressure on diffusion in magmas: (1) changes in pressure have only a minor effect on Dca at temperatures appropriate for melting in the mantle; (2) Ca diffusion in more silicic (and therefore generally cooler) magmas of the deep continental crust is slower by as much as an order of magnitude than 1-atm diffusivity data would indicate (see <ref type="bibr">Watson [11,</ref><ref type="bibr">fig. 9]</ref>;(3) the rate of Cs transport is affected by pressure in a manner similar to that observed for Ca, but is more sensitive to changes in pressure at upper mantle melting temperatures; and (4) in general, the effects of temperature and pressure on Cs and Ca diffusion are compensatory, so the diffusive transport rate is relatively constant along the liquidus of a magma in P-T space.</p><p>These conclusions can probably be generalized to include all alkali and alkaline earth elements, but their applicability to other species, especially networkforming cations such as Si 4÷ and A13÷, cannot be evaluated at the present time.</p><p>* Because each of equations ( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) to ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) is defined on the basis of only three experimental data points, the possible error in the diffusion parameters is substantial. Considering the error bars shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">3</ref> and<ref type="figure">4</ref>, the activation volumes from equations ( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>) can be assigned a probable error of_+13% and _+16% (2a), respectively; the 20 errors for the activation energies in equations ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) are _+29% and _*21%, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The effect of dissolved H20</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">General theoretical considerations</head><p>Compared with the case of pressure effects, there is relatively little basis for predicting the influence of dissolved H20 on diffusion of cations in silicate melts.</p><p>Although the dramatic reduction in viscosity of magmas by solution of water is well documented <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, the general inapplicability of the Stokes-Einstein relation precludes calculation of concurrent changes in diffusivities <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p><p>Two lines of evidence suggest that high H20 concentrations should result in high diffusivities of constituent ions. First, Shaw <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> has shown that the diffusion rate of H20 itself is "2 orders of magnitude faster in granitic melt containing ~6 wt.% H20 than it is in "dry" obsidian of the same composition. Diffusion of any component that assumes a structural role similar to that of H20 (e.g. alkali oxides? <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21 ]</ref>) might, therefore, be similarly enhanced by the addition of H20.</p><p>The second line of evidence for enhancement of diffusion rates by addition of H20 stems from the generally "compensated" nature of diffusion in molten silicates -that is, the linear relation between log Do and E a (constants in equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">9</ref>)) for diffusion of many different ions in a variety of melts <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Winchell <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> noted that diffusion in compositions having low melting temperatures is generally characterized by low values of Do and E a. Solution of H20 is very effective in melting point reduction of silicates, so it may, if Winchell's generalization is valid, also substantially reduce Do and Ea for diffusion of other components. Because of the specific compensation relation that applies to silicate melts (see Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and Winchell and Norman <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>), such a reduction in Do and Ea amounts to an increase in diffusion rate at temperatures below ~1500°C. The next section will show that this prediction is borne out by experimental data for some elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Diffusion of Cs, Na, and Ca in H20-bearing granitic melt</head><p>Experimental measurements. I recently reported experimental data on diffusion of Cs ÷ in granitic melt containing ~6 wt.% H20 <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. The data are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> in comparison with Dcs values for "dry" obsidian <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> of similar composition (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>). Also included in the figure are values for Cs diffusivity in the same melt at lower H20 concentration (3.5 wt.%). In Figs. <ref type="figure">6</ref> and<ref type="figure">7</ref>, respectively, new results on diffusion of Ca and Na in granitic melt containing 0, 3.5, and 6.2 wt.% H20 are presented. (See Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> for a Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>. Arrhenius plot of Cs diffusivity in granitic melts containing 6.2 and 3.5 wt.% of H20 compared with previous measurements (solid line) on dry granitic glass <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>Least-squares equations for the H 2 O-free and 6.2% H20 times are, respectively: DCs = 8.12 × 10 -2 exp(-49.9 × IO3/RT);Dcs = 7.19 × 10 -5 exp(-19.5 × 103/RT). Additional data are required at the 3.5% H20 level before a meaningful linear fit can be made. See text for an estimate of the probable error in the measurements.</p><p>summary of run information and diffusivity values.) All the new data were obtained in thin-source experiments similar to those described by Watson <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[ 13]</ref>, in which H-emitting 4 SCa and ~,-emitting 2 2Na  Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>. Arrhenius plot of Ca diffusivity in granitic obsidian containing 0, 3.5, and 6.2 wt.% H20. The least-squares equation for the 6.2% H20 line is: DCa = 0.0055 exp(-25.50 × 103/R T). The 0% H20 line is given by DCa = 0.00012 exp(-30.23 X 103/RT), but is subject to revision when more data have been aquired. The line for 3.5 wt.% H20 is obviously speculative; an activation energy intermediate between the 0% and 6.2% H20 values was assumed. Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. Arrhenius plot of Na diffusivity in granitic obsidian containing 0% and 3.5 wt.% H20. The solid line for 0% H20 and 1 bar is from Magaritz and Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, and is given by DNa = 0.044 exp(-22.90/RT). The single value for 0% H20 and ~2 kbar (diamond symbol) is from the present work and probably falls below the solid line because of the 2-kbar difference in pressure. The 3.5-wt.% H20 line is given by DNa = 0.0033 exp(-16.31/RT). served as radiotracers. The experiments were carried out on dry or pre-hydrated obsidian cylinders encapsulated in 1.8-mm-diameter Pt tubes that were sealed by welding cylindrical noble metal plugs in the recessed ends. All diffusion runs were made in coldseat vessels at the same pressure (2.1-2.2 kbar), so as to standardize any possible pressure effects. Sodium diffusion profiles were determined by the "residual activity" technique of Magaritz and Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> ; Ca profdes were directly mapped on/~-sensitive nuclear emulsions <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, and the diffusivity values were calculated from microdensitometer scans (see <ref type="bibr">Watson [111)</ref>.</p><p>Because the experiments on H20-bearing melts were carried out on larger samples than the dry, highpressure runs (1B mm vs. 1 mm diameter) and were run in different apparatus, some discussion of the possible sources of error in the data seems necessary. Short of performing the same experiment many times over, there is no way to obtain an accurate measure of the uncertainty in any single result. The data presented in Figs. <ref type="figure">5</ref><ref type="figure">6</ref><ref type="figure">7</ref>include several duplications, each of which represents a small time study. There are, for example, three determinations of Dcs in melt con-taining 6% H20 at 800°C. The points represent experiments of 2, 3, and 4 days duration, and the values agree within a factor of two, with no systematic variation with run duration. This is the largest discrepancy I have observed in replicate experiments -the two Dca points at 800°C and 6% H20 show results of runs 12 hours and 2 days long, and the agreement is within a factor of 1.3. Possibly significant sources of error include (1) imperfections in nuclear emulsions or uneven exposure and development procedures, (2) the non-negligible range of /3 particles in the quenched glasses, (3) error in estimates of H20 content, (4) deformation of the diffusion capsule and thin-source geometry. I find that densitometer scans of separate emulsions exposed to the same sample give the same diffusion coefficient to within 10%; furthermore, the correlation coefficients of the linearized diffusion profiles (in C vs. x 2, where C is proportional to tracer concentration and x = distance) are always &gt;0.988.</p><p>The/~-particle range question was indirectly addressed in the "dry" Ca diffusion experiments (see Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>). These runs yielded diffusion profiles much shorter than those obtained in the "wet" experiments, and yet the resulting diffusivities are consistent with the Ba and Sr data published by Magaritz and Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. If the ~ range is unimportant in short diffusion profiles ('200/am), as it appears to be, then it will be insignificant in long (1-3 mm) ones.</p><p>The water contents of the samples were estimated by weight loss at 1100°C from pieces of the hydrated glasses separated prior to the diffusion runs. The values were occasionally low for the 6% H20 hydrations, in which cases the samples were discarded. The H20 contents of several glasses were checked after diffusion runs and found to be close to (usually slightly higher than) the predicted values.</p><p>I believe that the largest source of error in the experiments is sample deformation. Despite the hydrostatic pressure conditions in the cold-seal vessels, the platinum diffusion capsules were generally slightly distorted from their initial cylindrical form; in particular, the inner surface of the Pt plug at the thin-source end sometimes acquired a slightly convex shape, thus invalidating the utilization of a strictly thin-source model. On the whole, however, the results are consistently reproducible, and a factor of two can probably be taken as the maximum uncertainty in any diffusion coefficient obtained from a single run.</p><p>Systematics of the data. The data summarized in Figs. <ref type="figure">5</ref><ref type="figure">6</ref><ref type="figure">7</ref>show that H20 has two effects on diffusion in granitic melts at the temperatures studied: (1) the diffusion coefficients generally increase with increasing H20 content;and (2) the activation energies for diffusion generally decrease. In the case of Na, the effect is small (and conceivably within the limits of uncertainty in the data), but for Cs diffusion at 700°C, Dcs is almost 4 orders of magnitude higher for melt containing "6 wt.% H20 than for dry glass. The "hydrous" activation energy is less than half the "dry" value. For Ca, the difference in diffusion coefficient is about 21 orders of magnitude and the activation energies differ by 16%. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8</ref>, the 700°C results are re-plotted to show the dependence of diffusion coefficients on H20 content for all three elements. It should be noted that the data for Cs are in qualitative agreement with those of Jambonet al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, but that the present results indicate a less pronounced positive dependence of Dcs upon H20 content. The one value reported here for diffusion of Na in dry obsidian (700°C) is a factor of wt% H20 in melt 2 lower than previously reported values <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>, a discrepancy that can be attributed either to the uncertainty in the present result or to the 2.2-kbar difference in pressure (previous experiments were carried out at 1 atm). I favor the latter interpretation because sample deformation was slight in the dry experiments of the study. Although the data are too few at the present time for valid generalization, two tendencies seem apparent: (1) ions with very low diffusion rates in dry obsidian undergo the greatest enhancement of diffusivity (and reduction in activation energy) upon addition of H20; and (2) the variations in diffusion parameters attributable to solution of H20 are consistent with the general compensation law of Winchell <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> -that is, the observed decreases in Ea with increasing H20 content are accompanied by decreases in log Do. A corollary to the first observation above is that ions with high diffusivities in dry obsidian (e.g., Na*) are enhanced very little by addition of H20, perhaps suggesting that there is an upper limit to cation diffusion rates in amorphous silicates. Finally, it seems clear that enhancement of diffusion rates by dissolved H20 is not restricted to ions of any particular chemical affinity, since both an alkali element (Cs) and an alkaline earth (Ca) are much more mobil in H20-bearing melts than in dry glass.</p><p>When I first presented the data for Cs diffusion in an H20-saturated melt <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, I proposed a simple atomistic explanation for the enhanced mobility in H20-rich compositions: Because the solution of H20 amounts to widespread creation of non-bridging oxygens <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, the number of structural positions favorable for occupation by Cs ÷ is greatly increased as H2 O is added. This creation of potential sites results in a reduction of the average diffusive jump distance for Cs ÷, so the diffusivity increases. The additional data now available support this simple conceptualization in that the pre-exponential factor, Do, generally decreases with addition of H~O to the melt. In atomistic theories of diffusion, the jump distance (or, in crystals, the lattice spacing) is a primary component term in Do <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Thus, the general decrease in Do that characterizes the effect of H20 on diffusion in melts may reflect the hypothesized reduction in average diffusive jump distance.</p><p>Alternatively, the changes in ionic diffusion rates upon addition of H20 might be viewed simply as the difference between diffusion in a solid and diffusion in a liquid: Dry obsidian is a metastable, essentially solid substance that is characterized by well-defined sites <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, whereas the H20-bearing compositions are stable fluids that by definition lack fixed sites.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Summary of petrologic implications</head><p>In magmas at depth in the earth, the effect of pressure on ionic diffusion is always operative, whereas that of H20 is obviously dependent upon its presence and concentration. In hydrous magmas, the two effects are simultaneous and opposite. In spite of the fact that pressure and H20 content were varied essentially independently in the experiments reported here (so as to isolate their effects), it is possible to draw some general conclusions about diffusion in magmas at various levels in the crust and upper mantle:</p><p>(1) In magmas of the upper crust, the retarding effects of pressure on diffusion are probably unimportant for most ions. However, enhancement of diffusion rates by dissolved H20 may be extremely important, especially for ions whose 1-arm diffusivities are low. If the magma is dry, then 1-atm diffusion data can be applied with confidence, but such data may be entirely inappropriate if H20 is present.</p><p>(2) In magmas of the lower continental crust (especially cooler felsic compositions), the effects of both pressure and H20 content on diffusion are probably substantial. For calcium and cesium in dry magmas at "--40 km depth, a factor of ~5 reduction in diffusion rate relative to the 1-arm value is likely. However, if even 1 wt.% H20 is present, the inhibiting effects of pressure on diffusion may be more than counteracted. Existing experimental data are insufficient to allow confident prediction of diffusion rates in lower-crustal magmas, but it should be noted that quantitative relevance of 1 -arm data would be fortuitous.</p><p>(3) In magmas at upper mantle pressures, diffusion rates may be as much as an order of magnitude lower than 1-atm values at the same temperature. It should be realized; however, that the higher temperatures of magmas at great depth will at least partially compensate the pressure effect. Even the presence of H20 in mantle melts may be of relatively little consequence compared with its effects in crustal magmas. In the 700-800°C range over which the enhancing effect of H20 on diffusion has been documented, a decrease in the activation energies for diffusion is also observed, especially for the alkalies. This implies that the "dry" and "wet" diffusivities converge at high temperature (see, for example, Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>). Thus, on the whole, diffusion rates in mantle magmas are probably surprisingly well represented by available 1-atm values.</p><p>From the foregoing observations, it appears likely that the conclusions of Hofmann and Magaritz <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and Hofmann and Hart <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> concerning the time scales of trace element and isotopic mixing in a partially molten mantle are valid. However, previous conclusions regarding crustal magmatic and geochemical processes drawn on the basis of diffusion data for dry obsidian <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> are subject to revision in light of the marked enhancement of diffusion rates that accompanies solution of H20 in magmas. For example, the estimate of Magaritz and Hofmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> of the diffusive transport distance of Sr during a million-year-long crustal migmatization episode is probably unrealisti-cally low. Their assumed temperature of 700°C may be appropriate for incipient melting of crustal rocks if H20 is present, but it is well below the solidus under the water-free circumstances for which their Dsr value of 10 -1 t cm2/s was selected. On the basis of the Ca diffusion data presented here, the predicted value for Dsr in a melt containing 6% dissolved H20 is ~10 -a cm2/s. This 3-order-of-magnitude difference in Dsr would result in a 30-fotd (i.e., x/103) increase in the estimated diffusive transport distance for Sr. This change does not affect the conclusion of Magaritz and Hofmann that Sr isotopic equilibration cannot occur on a regional scale in 106 years, but it does increase from centimeters to meters the scale of sampling required for Rb-Sr whole rock dating of the partial melting event.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Isothermal pressure dependence of calcium diffusivity in a sodinm-calcium-aluminosilicate melt. Equations of the least-squares lines are given in the text. The 2a error bars are estimates based on 5 replications of a single experiment (see Watson [111).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>1</head><label></label><figDesc>kbar: Dca = 5.0 × 10 -3 exp(-25.4/RT) (6) 10 kbar: Dca = 5.2 × 10 -2 exp(-33.7/RT) (7) 20 kbar: Dca = 6.2 exp(--49.8/RT)(8)which have the standard form:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figs.1 and 3that increased pressure has similar effects on the diffusivities of the two elements at 1100°C, but that Cs mobility is more effectively reduced by increases in pressure at 1300°C (see Table1for a summary of data). Given in the form of equation (1),</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>at 6 kbar,Dcs = 4.2 X 10 -1 exp(-37.8/RT) (12)* at 18 kbar, Dcs = 7.4 X 10 -2 exp(-35.3/RT) (13)*</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Diagram illustrating the dependence of Na, Ca, and Cs dfffusivities (D's) upon the H20 content of granitic melt (700°C, 2.2 kbar confining pressure).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 1 Summary</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Ion</cell><cell>Melt*</cell><cell>T</cell><cell>P</cell><cell>H 20 content</cell><cell>Run duration</cell><cell>Diffusivity</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(°C)</cell><cell>(kbar)</cell><cell>(wt.%)</cell><cell>(s)</cell><cell>(cm2/s)</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>1100</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>20 280</cell><cell>4.60 X 10 -7</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>1100</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>23820</cell><cell>3.10 X 10 -7</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>1100</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>18 300</cell><cell>1.62 x 10 -7</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>1200</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>7 320</cell><cell>8.08 X 10 -7</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>1200</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>7 200</cell><cell>5.03 X 10 -7</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>1300</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>3 600</cell><cell>2.72 × 10 --6</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>1300</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>3 120</cell><cell>1.74 x 10 -6</cell></row><row><cell>Cs +</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>1300</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>3 600</cell><cell>8.15 × 10 -7</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>s</cell><cell>1400</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2 160</cell><cell>2.19 x 10 -6</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>700</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>507 600</cell><cell>3.30 x 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷"</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>700</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>690 180</cell><cell>2.96 X 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>800</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>172400</cell><cell>6.43 x 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>800</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>262 800</cell><cell>5.29 X 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell>Cs +</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>800</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>350 100</cell><cell>1.29 × 10 -8</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>700</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>165 000</cell><cell>7.47 × 10 -l°</cell></row><row><cell>Cs ÷</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>800</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>85 140</cell><cell>2.15 × 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell>Ca 2+</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>700</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>172 200</cell><cell>9.18 × 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell>Ca 2+</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>750</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>87 720</cell><cell>1.96 × 10 -8</cell></row><row><cell>Ca ~</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>750</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>172 080</cell><cell>2.38 × 10 -8</cell></row><row><cell>Ca 2+</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>800</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>43 860</cell><cell>2.93 × 10 -8</cell></row><row><cell>Ca 2+</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>800</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>6.2</cell><cell>167 280</cell><cell>3.72 × 10 -8</cell></row><row><cell>Ca 2+</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>700</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>165 000</cell><cell>1.55 × 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell>Ca ~</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>800</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>85 140</cell><cell>2.27 × 10-9</cell></row><row><cell>Ca ~</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>700</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>941400</cell><cell>2.4 × 10 -11</cell></row><row><cell>Ca 2+</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>800</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>330 840</cell><cell>5.2 × 10 -11</cell></row><row><cell>Ca 2.</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>268 812</cell><cell>3.6 × 10 -1°</cell></row><row><cell>Na ÷</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>700</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>3 200</cell><cell>8.30 × 10 -7</cell></row><row><cell>Na ÷</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>700</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>6 900</cell><cell>6.06 × 10 -7</cell></row><row><cell>Na +</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>800</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>4650</cell><cell>1.63 × 10-6</cell></row><row><cell>Na ÷</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>3 540</cell><cell>2.95 X 10-6</cell></row><row><cell>Na ÷</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>3 540</cell><cell>1.41 × 10-6</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>of run conditions and diffusivity values (excluding the high-pressure Ca diffusion experiments, which are tabulated in Watson</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref></p>) * s = simple soda-lime-aluminosilicate melt; o = obsidian (see text).</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 2 Electron</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>microprobe analysis of obsidian used in "dry"</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">experiments of this study. This glass was pre-hydrated for</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">use in diffusion experiments on H20-bearing melts</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Obsidian (wt.%)</cell></row><row><cell>SiO2</cell><cell>76.01</cell></row><row><cell>TiO2</cell><cell>0.11</cell></row><row><cell>A12 O3</cell><cell>13.00</cell></row><row><cell>FeO *</cell><cell>0.70</cell></row><row><cell>MgO</cell><cell>0.09</cell></row><row><cell>CaO</cell><cell>0.52</cell></row><row><cell>Na20</cell><cell>3.65</cell></row><row><cell>K20</cell><cell>4.81</cell></row><row><cell>MnO</cell><cell>0.08</cell></row><row><cell>H20 **</cell><cell>0.17</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>99.14</cell></row></table><note><p>* Iron as FeO. ** Weight loss upon heating at 1100°C.</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The microdensitometry for the 4SCa diffusion experiments on dry obsidian was performed by <rs type="person">F.J. Ryerson</rs>, with whom I have had many beneficial discussions. The manuscript was improved by the constructive review of K.E. Davis. The work was supported by the <rs type="funder">Earth Sciences Section, National Science Foundation</rs>, under <rs type="funder">NSF</rs> grants <rs type="grantNumber">EAR76-15836</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">EAR78-12980</rs>, and <rs type="grantNumber">EAR78-21812</rs>. Funds for the construction of a piston-cylinder apparatus at R.P.I. were granted by the <rs type="funder">Research Corporation</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_tQbGJsK">
					<idno type="grant-number">EAR76-15836</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_N8PDKr9">
					<idno type="grant-number">EAR78-12980</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_BNRtFm7">
					<idno type="grant-number">EAR78-21812</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="1921">1921</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Evolution of the Igneous Rocks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1928">1928</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sodium self diffusion in natural minerals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Sippel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autodiffusion du sodium et conductivit6 ~lectrique dans les obsidiennes granitiques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C.R. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">266</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="854" to="856" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">t~tude exp~rimentale de la diffusion des ~16ments alcalins K, Rb, Cs dans une obsidiene granitique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C.R. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3069" to="3072" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
			<publisher>S~r. D</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Sr, Ba and Na in obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="605" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Diffusion of Eu and Gd in basalt and obsidian</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="847" to="858" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium diffusion in a mugearite melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Medford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Can. J. Earth Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Ca, Sr, Ba, and Co in a basalt melt: implications for the geochemistry of the mantle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5432" to="5440" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in natural silicate melts: a critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Physics of Magmatic Processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hargraves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University, Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium diffusion in a simple silicate melt to 30 kbar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Donn6es pr6-liminaires sur la diffusion dans les magmas hydrates: le c~sium dans une liquide granitique a 3 kbar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Delbove</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C. R. Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">287</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of cesium ions in H20-saturated granitic melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">205</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1259" to="1260" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shewmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Diffusion in Solids</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, N.Y.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">203</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nachtrieb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Transport properties in pur liquid metals</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Society of Metals</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="55" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Liquid Metals and Solidification</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temperaturedependent activation volumes of self-diffusion in cadmium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Buescher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gilder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shea</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2261" to="2268" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetic theory of dense fluids, X. Measurement and interpretation of self-diffusion in liquid Ar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Naghizadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rice</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kr, Xe, and CH</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2710" to="2720" />
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J. Chem. Phys.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of pressure on electrolytic conduction in alkali silicate glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aust. J. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Obsidian-H20 viscosities at 1000 and 2000 bars in the temperature range 700 ° to 900°C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6337" to="6343" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diffusion of H20 in granitic liquids, I. Experimental data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Geochemical Transport and Kinetics, A.W. Hofmann, B.J. Giletti, H.S. Yoder, Jr. and R.A. Yund</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<publisher>Carnegie Inst. Washington Publ</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">634</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="154" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the nature of silicate melt and its significance in magma genesis: regularities in the shift of liquidus boundaries involving olivine, pyroxene, and silica minerals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The compensation law for diffusion in silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Winchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">High Temp. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study of the diffusion of radioactive nuclides in molten silicates at high temperatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Winchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">High Temperature Technology, Third International Symposium at Asilomar 1967</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="479" to="492" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trace element partitioning determined by beta track mapping: an experimental study using carbon and samarium as examples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Seitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J, Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2627" to="2635" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Water and magmas: a mixing model, Geochim</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Burnham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1077" to="1084" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Doremus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Glass Science</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, N.Y.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley and Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">349</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An assessment of local and 301 regional isotopic equilibrium in the mantle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Least-squares fitting of a straight line</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>York</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Can. J. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1079" to="1086" />
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
