<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">DIFFUSION IN VOLATILE-BEARING MAGMAS</title>
				<funder ref="#_dmMZZvr #_zEUhudP #_MuwWkuz">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Bruce</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute Troy</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>12180</postCode>
									<region>New York</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">DIFFUSION IN VOLATILE-BEARING MAGMAS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2F58130A5FFBA9685CD20D3DA8CEBA54</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>The role of volatiles in determining the phase equilibria, physical properties and eruption dynamics of magmas has been an area of intensive investigation for several decades. Indeed, this "Reviews" volume is a testimonial not only to the perceived importance of magmatic volatiles, but also to the magnitude of the intellectual effort put toward their understanding.</p><p>In the context of the long history of research into the nature and effects of magmatic volatiles, investigations focusing specifically upon diffusion came on the scene relatively recently, beginning with a ground-breaking effort by H.R. <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Shaw (1974)</ref> published just twenty years ago. This late attention to diffusion can probably be attributed in part to the former tendency among experimentalists to concentrate upon strictly equilibrium phenomena, and perhaps also to the limited availability of analytical instruments suitable for high-resolution, in-situ characterization of dissolved volatile concentrations. Despite a general paucity of volatile-related diffusion data prior to the late 1970s, theorists and experimentalists alike had developed a strong suspicion that dissolved volatiles (water in particular) have a strong enhancing effect on diffusion-theorists because they appreciated the inverse correlation between viscosity and diffusion embodied in the Stokes-Einstein equation, and experimentalists because they routinely observed that crystals grew bigger and faster in hydrous melts than in dry melts of the same composition at the same temperature.</p><p>The purpose of this chapter is to summarize the results of experimental studies that have contributed to our present understanding of diffusion in magmas containing dissolved volatiles. Two kinds of investigation are recognized here and treated in separate sections: those focusing on diffusion of volatiles themselves, and those addressing the effects of dissolved volatiles upon diffusion of other magmatic components. In order to keep the scope of the chapter manageable, only passing references are made to diffusion of volatiles in solid glasses, though a sizable literature on this topic does exist (especially for water in Si0 2 ). To assist readers who may be unfamiliar with basic diffusion theory or with experimental techniques used in characterizing diffusion in melts containing dissolved volatiles, a brief, practical overview of these subjects is provided in the sections immediately following.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OVERVIEW OF BASIC DIFFUSION THEORY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nature and theoretical conceptualizations of diffusion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definitions.</head><p>In this chapter and in most correct usages of the word, "diffusion" refers to the translational motion of atoms or molecules dissolved in a phase; in general, the reference frame for gauging motion is the lattice or structure of the phase of interest.</p><p>Relatively inexplicit volatile-related magmatic processes such as "vapor-phase transport" and "volatile streaming" fall outside the realm of what can be called strictly diffusion, and so are not discussed in this chapter.</p><p>Diffusion theory is typically put forth in separate but complementary approaches: atomistics (deductions based upon consideration of the random motion of individual atoms) and phenomenology (presentation of the empirical equations governing diffusion in a continuum). Available space in this chapter (and expertise of the writer!) precludes comprehensive treatment of these approaches, but a brief and selective overview will expedite the clear presentation of data and concepts later in the chapter. For a more indepth review of diffusion theory, the reader is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Manning (1968)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Shewmon (1989)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Cussler (1984)</ref>. This last volume is an especially readable presentation of theory and applications of diffusion to mass transport in liquid and/or gas systems; it is laden with interesting examples and solved problems on topics ranging from ion-exchange columns to artificial kidneys (no geology, unfortunately).</p><p>Atomistics. Classic atomistic treatments of diffusion are based upon a crystalline lattice characterized by a limited number of site types (usually just one). This framework is not very realistic for magmatic liquids, in which long-range structure is lacking and site characteristics are determined at least in part by the identity of the occupying atom. Nevertheless, certain aspects of atomistic diffusion theory are readily transferable to molten silicates. It is still appropriate, for example, to consider a dissolved ion oscillating in a (momentarily) fixed position, at frequency D, as having the potential in any given oscillation cycle to leave its original position and "relocate" a small distance away. This displacement would constitute a diffusive "jump", and would amount to a net motion of the ion in the melt. Even in liquids, the fraction of oscillations that result in jumps is small, being given by exp(-E/fcT), where E is the energy barrier that must be surmounted to achieve a jump (contributions to E include the breaking of bonds at the original site, as well as the transient, close approach to neighboring ions that accompanies a jump). In general, then, the jump frequency of a dissolved ion (in sec -1 ) from a given position or site is given by r= 1) exp (-E/kT) (1)</p><p>where u is the oscillation frequency (typically ~10 14 Hz), k is Boltzmann's constant and T is temperature in kelvins.</p><p>Equation (1) applies to the totally random translational motion of an atom, ion or molecule in its host phase. If one could tag a specific atom and follow its progress, that atom would make periodic jumps in random directions, possibly even revisiting sites it occupied previously. This process is sometimes referred to as "random walk" diffusion, and it occurs in all substances regardless of the degree of initial heterogeneity (i.e., no concentration gradient is required). The values of E and u, of course, are affected not only by the identity of the diffusing species of interest, but also by its immediate atomic environment and the general structural (lattice) characteristics of the host phase. Recognizing the existence of random-walk diffusion is critical to appreciating the meanings and distinctions among the terms chemical diffusion, self diffusion, isotopic diffusion and tracer diffusion (see section on "Kinds" of diffusion).</p><p>In crystalline solids, the random atomic-jump process described above may involve one of several possible mechanisms, the most important of which are probably the vacancy (where the species of interest jumps into a near-neighbor vacant site), the interstial (where the diffusant is small enough to occupy a position between or among normal lattice sites) and the ring mechanism (in which simultaneous rotation of a cluster of atoms results in net motion of all of them). In cases where the vacancy mechanism operates, it is clear that the otherwise random-directional aspect of any single diffusive jump can be heavily biased by the presence of a neighboring vacancy. It is also clear that the frequency of jumps (hence the rate of diffusion) may be strongly dependent upon the concentration of vacancies. In magmas and other complex liquids, the conceptualization of diffusion as mechanismspecific may be a little tricky to defend; in fact, it seems likely that for network-modifying species in magmatic liquids (which most dissolved volatiles are), a variety of atomic migration mechanisms can operate, because there is some local flexibility in the way in which atoms fill space. In silicate melts, the main determinant of available diffusion mechanisms may well be the requirement that local charge balance be recovered once a jump has occurred.</p><p>Atomistic models of diffusion take on directionality when a concentration gradient is introduced. Consider a series of closely-spaced planes (in a crystal, these would be lattice planes) perpendicular to a one-dimensional gradient (along x) in the concentration of B atoms (solid circles in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). The flux of atoms from plane 1 to plane 2 can be described in terms of the jump frequency, r, introduced previously. Recalling that the units of flux are atoms-area^-time 1 (the area being perpendicular to the flux direction), and avoiding reference to any diffusion mechanism, the net flux, J, from (1) to ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">2</ref>) is simply the number of atoms jumping from l-&gt; 2 minus the number jumping back (2-&gt;1):</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Ji-»2 = ni(r/N) -na(r/N)<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where ni,2 represent the densities of diffusant atoms on the specified plane and N is the number of possible jump directions (i.e., only one jump in N would move an atom from l-»2 or vice versa; in a metal, N would be six-the coordination number). Converting atom densities to concentrations (c = n/a, where a is the distance between planes), we have Assuming that concentration is a continuous function of x, so that c 2 = c 1 + a(dc/dx), we arrive at an equation relating the flux to the concentration gradient:</p><p>where the term in brackets is a collection of constants characteristic of the diffusant of interest and the diffusion medium. In general, we would expect this term, ra 2 /N, to be constant for diffusion of a specific species in a specific medium; its actual value, of course, would be impossible to estimate a priori for a substance as complex as a silicate melt.</p><p>In the interest of saving space, the above analysis will not be extended to address the question of how a concentration gradient would evolve over time as a consequence of "random-jump" diffusion. The extension is straightforward, though, and is presented in a lucid manner by <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Shewmon (1989)</ref>.</p><p>The conclusions that emerge from the foregoing atomistic analysis are that:</p><p>(1) reduced to its simplest terms, diffusion involves inherently random motions of atoms, ions or molecules in their host media; and (2) diffusion manifests itself as a net flux only when there is a pre-existing concentration gradient in the species of interest. Armed with these conclusions, we can be appropriately skeptical about the conventional wisdom that "a gradient in concentration (or chemical potential) is required for diffusion." In reality, diffusion is an unavoidable consequence of atomic vibrations in any substance at high temperature, and does not require a concentration gradient to occur. Under most circumstances, however, we can observe the results of diffusion only when a preexisting concentration gradient is present.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phenomenology: diffusion equations.</head><p>It can be shown by experiment (and predicted on the basis of intuition) that an initially inhomogeneous phase, if annealed at sufficiently high temperature, will eventually reach a state of homogeneity. This state is achieved by migration of atoms from high-to low-concentration regions. In 1855 Adolph Fick recognized this behavior (see <ref type="bibr">Cussler, 1984, p. 18)</ref> and noted the mathematical parallels between diffusion of matter and the conduction of heat (Fourier's law) and electricity (Ohm's law). As aids in developing intuition about diffusion, these parallels are still worth emphasizing today, supplemented by the additional analogy with Darcy's law for fluid flow. Fick stated (but did not actually prove) that the one-dimensional flux of a component (/) is proportional to the gradient in its concentration through a constant, D ; , which we now recognize as the diffusion coefficient or diffusivity (units = m 2 /s). Equation (5) has the expected property that, as the concentration gradient goes to zero, so does the flux. This equation has come to be referred to as Fick's first law-or the steady-state diffusion equation-and its equivalence to Equation (4) is clear. Fick went on to develop a more general mass-conservation equation, now written (for onedimensional diffusion) as (4) </p><p>This second-order partial differential equation describes the time evolution of concentration, and so is referred to as the nonsteady-state diffusion equation (and also as Fick's second law). Solutions to this equation have been obtained for many different boundary conditions; a summary can be found in the classic reference work by <ref type="bibr">Crank (1979)</ref>. As we will show shortly, experimental studies of diffusion in volatile-bearing magmas usually incorporate one of three relatively simple solutions to Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">7</ref>), because only a small number of sample geometries and initial concentration distributions are experimentally tractable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Complications.</head><p>This discussion would be incomplete to the point of negligence without a few additional observations concerning the diffusion equations above. First, the diffusivity, D,, cannot generally be considered independent of c, over large changes in concentration. As we shall see, dissolved water provides a good example of concentrationdependent diffusion. Dependence of D, upon concentration can be due to effects intrinsic to the diffusant of interest, or it may be attributable to changing influences of other components (or both; see section on "kinds" of diffusion). Diffusion of dissolved C0 2 , sulfur and chlorine, as well as most cations, is strongly dependent upon the water content of a magma.</p><p>A second and not unrelated observation is that, contrary to the simple formulation embodied in Equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>)-which could be stated in words as "a concentration gradient will lead to an observable flux"-chemical thermodynamics suggests a more correct statement: "a gradient in chemical potential (jj,,-) will lead to an observable flux." Since |i, is not independent of the concentrations of other system components, the implications of this alternative phrasing are profound for systems characterized by strong gradients in most or all components, and the complexity of rigorous treatment rapidly escalates beyond the scope of this practical primer (but see discussion of chemical diffusion in the next section).</p><p>A final note concerning the diffusion equations is that concentration gradients in natural magmas rarely exist in one dimension only. The more general statements of Equations ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">7</ref>), for D, independent of position, are:</p><p>For ease in extracting diffusivities from laboratory samples, experiments are usually designed so that diffusion occurs in one dimension only. In melts, of course, because of their isotropic structure, the resulting diffusivities are appropriate for modeling more complicated diffusion processes in magmas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>"Kinds" of diffusion</head><p>The preceding discussion should provide a good basis for appreciating the significance of the various adjectives used to modify the word "diffusion"-e.g., "self, "isotope", "tracer", "chemical", and "multicomponent", among others. The distinctions among these can be very significant to geologists concerned with volatiles in magmas, who routinely consider transport processes involving major elements, trace elements and isotopes. Definitions of the kinds of diffusion seem to vary somewhat among authorities and among J, = -D,Vc, where J,-is a vector quantity, and disciplines, but we can probably write down interpretations that would be generally agreed upon. Inasmuch as this chapter deals with diffusion specifically in melts, we can omit discussion of terms such as "grain-boundary", "surface", "intrinsic", "extrinsic" and "defect" diffusion, all of which are significant only in crystals or polycrystals.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(3c,/ dt) = D ( V 2 c, (nonsteady-state) (steady-state)<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Strictly speaking, self diffusion refers to diffusion of the constituent atoms of a pure or nearly-pure substance; however, the term has also been applied to diffusion of components at any concentration level (e.g., major or trace elements), as long as it occurs in the absence of a concentration gradient. Characterizing self diffusion necessitates distinguishing among different atoms of the same element, so an isotopic tracer must be used, and the assumption made that the mass difference among isotopes is unimportant (which is valid for high-Z elements). The random-walk process described earlier represents self diffusion. Geochemists tend to use the term "isotopic diffusion" for the same phenomenon, in reference to a process that involves the exchange of isotopes with an implied absence of a gradient in chemical potential of the element of interest. This usage is reasonable, but in geological systems it is probably rare (and definitely fortuitous) that disequilibrium or heterogeneity in the isotopic composition of an element could exist in the absence of disequilibrium in total abundance of that element. In the context of volatiles in magmas, examples of self-or isotopic diffusion include: homogenization of the isotopes of carbon or sulfur in dissolved C0 2 or S0 2 ; and the effects of dissolved water upon homogenization of radiogenic isotope ratios (e.g., for Pb, Sr, Nd, or Hf).</p><p>Because isotopic tracers are needed to characterize self diffusion, the term "tracer diffusion" is often equated with self diffusion. There is little risk in doing this, but it is worth noting that virtually all tracer diffusion studies on geologic melts are done by introducing an isotope (usually radioactive) at one end of an experimental sampletechnically, this introduces a small chemical concentration gradient in the species of interest even if the sample already contains a high concentration of other isotopes of that species. However, because very small quantities of tracer are used, the chemical concentration gradient is diminishingly small, and the resulting diffusivities are indistinguishable from self-diffusion coefficients.</p><p>Chemical diffusion refers to diffusion in a chemical potential gradient, for which conditions are rife in magmas. The chemical or interdiffusion coefficient for a binary system is often defined simply in terms of Fick's first law: D = -J / (dc/5x). This interdiffusion coefficient generally varies with concentration (hence with distance across the interdiffusion zone), but a solution to Fick's second law exists that will accommodate where dx/dc is evaluated at c' (a concentration of interest along the interdiffusion profile) and x is the distance from the zero-net-flux plane at x=0 (this plane is referred to as the Matano interface). Implementation of Equation 10 is referred to as Boltzmann-Matano analysis (see <ref type="bibr">Shewmon, 1989, p. 34-37)</ref>; formerly done graphically, it can now be accomplished more easily by fitting a functional form to c vs. x data, and performing the differentiation and integration at various concentrations along the curve. Here X represents the mole fraction of the component indicated by the subscript and y is the activity coefficient. Although it strictly applies only to diffusion in two-component systems in which charge-balance considerations do not arise (i.e., not to magmas), the Darken equation is useful here in making the point that in ideal (or dilute ideal) binary solutions the chemical diffusion coefficient is given simply by the weighted sum of the endmember tracer diffusivities. Equations analogous to no. 11 have been derived for simple ionic materials as well (see <ref type="bibr">Manning, 1968, p. 21;</ref><ref type="bibr">Brady, 1975, p. 980)</ref>. For complex systems, some researchers have resorted to use of effective binary diffusion coefficients (EBDCs; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Cooper 1968)</ref> for cases in which one component is imagined as interdiffusing with a mixture of other components-the system is treated as binary, even though one "endmember" is itself really a mixture. For some studies described later involving diffusion of highly-soluble volatile components in magmas (e.g., H 2 0), the diffusivities extracted are actually EBDCs. The same is true of diffusivities for major or minor components obtained by analysis of concentration gradients produced upon dissolution of a simple mineral into a melt. The only disadvantage of these values is that they are valid only for the specific system, conditions, and range of concentrations directly investigated. <ref type="bibr">Lesher (1994)</ref> applied the Darken equation (Eqn. 11) to volatile-free magmas using EBDCs in combination with y-X relationships extracted from Soret diffusion experiments. To the author's knowledge, no similar attempt has been made for volatilebearing magmas, probably because y-X data are generally lacking.</p><p>Rigorous treatment of multicomponent (chemical) diffusion in systems of more than two components begins with <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Onsager's (1945)</ref> extended version of Fick's first law: J, = -X D,-. (dc, /dx) (12) j=i where n is the number of components in the system (n-1 of the diffusivities are independent). Not only are the Dy values composition dependent, the flux of one component also depends upon the concentration gradients in all other components, leading to the possibility of "uphill" diffusion-i.e., migration of a component up a gradient in its concentration. Obtaining D¡j s for a complex system requires precise and accurate analysis of diffusion profiles for all components followed by rigorous statistical treatment of data; no such analysis has been attempted for magmas or even simple analog melts containing dissolved volatiles. For in-depth discussion of multicomponent diffusion, with applications to simple melts, the reader is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b74">Zhang (1993)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Richter (1993)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Kress and Ghiorso (1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">1994</ref><ref type="bibr">), Lesher (1993) )</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Trial and Spera (1994)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Temperature and pressure dependence of diffusion</head><p>Effect of temperature. From the glimpse into the atomistics of diffusion provided earlier in this chapter, it is expected that diffusion is a temperature-dependent process. Empirically, D depends on temperature according to</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">D = D 0 exp(-Q/RT) (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">)</formula><p>where D 0 and Q are temperature-independent constants characteristic of the diffusant and the medium, and R is the gas constant. The so-called activation energy for diffusion, Q, can be readily obtained from an Arrhenius plot (InD vs. 1/T), on which the slope is -Q/R.</p><p>There are examples in the literature involving diffusion in crystalline materials where the expected linear relation between InD and 1/T fails (usually at low temperature), but no such cases have been documented for diffusion in magmatic liquids. The possibility may exist, in the case of dissolved volatiles whose speciation in the melt depends upon temperature, for apparent deviations from Arrhenius behavior. If a composite diffusivity is measured by a technique that does not distinguish different dissolved species (e.g., molecular C0 2 or C0 3 2 "), the measured value conceivably could reflect changes in speciation with temperature. This topic will surface later in reference to water diffusion in melts.</p><p>Pressure dependence of D. Theories addressing the pressure dependence of D are well developed for simple crystals and van der Waals liquids (see <ref type="bibr">Watson, 1979a</ref> for some classic references). In general, it has been shown that</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">D tp = DT€X P (-PV/RT) (14)</formula><p>where D T P is the diffusivity at some temperature and pressure, D T is the "zero-pressure" diffusivity at the same temperature (given by Eqn. 13) and V a is a constant characteristic of the diffusant and the medium, having the units of volume. The atomistic significance of V a (called the activation volume) depends upon the operative diffusion mechanism. For a vacancy mechanism, it has been equated with the sum of the partial molar volumes of vacancies and activated complexes (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Shewmon, 1989)</ref>. Tlie significance of V a in complex melts is open to debate. For alkali diffusion in alkali silicate glasses, it has been shown to approach the molar volume of the diffusant (which implies that the effects of pressure on diffusion will be greatest for large ions; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Hamann, 1965)</ref>. Existing interpretations of the activation volume imply that it will be positive in sign, which is consistent with the intuitively-reasonable prediction that compressing a material should restrict interatomic space (perhaps "squeezing out" vacancies) and thus slow diffusion.</p><p>There do exist cases involving diffusion in molten silicates where V a is close to zero (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Watson and Bender, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Dingwell and Scarfe, 1984)</ref> or demonstrably negative (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baker, 1990)</ref>. A reasonable interpretation of a negative activation volume is that the melt structure itself-and also, perhaps, the diffusion mechanism-is pressure dependent. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Baker (1990)</ref> hypothesized the formation of transient, high-coordination complexes (e.g., Si v or Si^) during the diffusive jump as an alternative explanation of the negative V a . As we shall see, data concerning pressure effects on diffusion in volatile-bearing magmas are relatively sparse.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL AND ANALYTICAL APPROACHES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General considerations</head><p>There are basically two constraints upon the design of experiments involving diffusion in volatile-bearing magmas: (1) usually (though not always) the experiments must be done at high pressures, because most volatiles of petrologic interest are either too insoluble in melts or too fugitive at atmospheric pressure; and (2) the experiments must produce diffusion gradients that can be accurately characterized and readily manipulated mathematically to extract a diffusivity.</p><p>High-pressure diffusion experiments on liquids presented new problems to experimentalists because of the need to worry about not only the usual petrologic variables (P, T, and possibly /q 2 ), but also sample geometry (which must remain constant over the course of an experiment). The first experiments on diffusion in volatile-bearing magmas <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Jambon et al., 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson, 1979b)</ref> were performed in fluid-medium pressure devices, which have the advantage of maintaining hydrostatic pressure throughout a diffusion anneal, thus minimizing sample deformation. In most laboratories, however, pressures achievable in fluid-medium pressure devices are limited to less than about 0.6 GPa, so for higher-pressure studies, solid-media (piston-cylinder) techniques were eventually developed. Strategies to combat the sample-deforming tendency of the piston-cylinder Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM have included surrounding the sample with a weak solid incapable of supporting shear stresses <ref type="bibr">(Watson, 1979a)</ref>, or using the opposite approach of encapsulating the melt in a container strong enough to resist deformation during pressurization <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">(Watson, 1991)</ref>.</p><p>In most cases, diffusion in melts is sufficiently fast to generate diffusion gradients on the order of at least 100 |im (sometimes much more) in a practical laboratory time frame of hours to weeks. This means that the spatial resolution of the analysis method rarely needs to be better than -10 Jim, which opens up the possibility of applying a wide range of analytical techniques, including: Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR; for H 2 0 and C0 2 ); serial sectioning for radiotracer counting; B-track mapping; and electron-, proton-, x-ray, or ion-microprobe (in traversing mode).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The thin-source geometry</head><p>Experimental technique. A technique popular for its simplicity is that involving the deposition of a thin, planar layer of diffusant, usually a radiotracer, on one end of the experimental sample. In typical studies of diffusion in volatile-bearing melts, a prefabricated glass cylinder is polished at one end and the radiotracer added as an aqueous solution (subsequently dried off) or by vapor deposition (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>). Prevention of the escape of volatiles during the diffusion anneal necessitates an impermeable container, usually a noble metal tube. Rather than retrofit a container to a glass specimen, it may be more convenient to draw a melt into a platinum tube at atmospheric conditions and slice up the resulting glass-filled tube into lengths suitable for high-pressure diffusion experiments (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Hofmann and Magaritz, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson, 1979a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Watson et al" 1982)</ref>. Alternatively, some workers have found it easier to pre-fabricate glass specimens at high pressure, especially if initially uniform dissolved volatile contents are desired (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Jambon et al., 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson, 1979b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Watson, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Watson et al., 1993)</ref>. The pre-synthesis step is followed by polishing the quenched glass sample at one end, addition of tracer, and returning the sample to the high-pressure apparatus for the diffusion anneal. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>thin-source experiment</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The diffusion couple and related approaches</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental configuration.</head><p>In the context of diffusion studies on volatilebearing magmas, diffusion couples have been popular mainly (but not exclusively) in the determination of cation diffusivities in melts containing dissolved water. In this case, the strategy is to juxtapose, along a planar interface, two melt reservoirs having different concentrations of the element(s) of interest (see Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>). As with thin-source experiments, Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM cylindrical samples are generally used for convenience in fabrication and encapsulation. Two cylinders are polished at one end, the polished faces placed in contact to form a diffusion couple, and the assembly annealed at the conditions of interest, causing a diffusive flux across the original interface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Extraction of diffusivity.</head><p>Given a composition-independent D and a diffusion couple that is effectively infinite in length, the flux resulting from the configuration described above leads to a distribution of diffusant described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Crank, 1975)</ref> where x is the distance from the original interface at x = 0, c, is the initial concentration at negative x, c 2 is the initial concentration at positive x, and erfc denotes the error function complement. The diffusivity is extracted either from a nonlinear fit of c x t vs. x data to Equation ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) or by inverting the data through the error function in a'plot of x vs.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">erfc _1 {2(c x l -c 2 )/(c 1 -c 2 )};</formula><p>in the ideal case, this plot is linear, with slope (4Dt)~1 /2 . Instances of 1 a composition-dependent D are revealed by a non-linear plot, which might necessitate an alternative treatment to that represented by Equation ( <ref type="formula">17</ref>) (see earlier section dealing with chemical diffusion).</p><p>A useful characteristic of the "diffusion-couple" solution discussed above is that the concentration at x = 0 is constant [at c 2 + l/2(c¡ -c 2 )] for all t &gt; 0, so essentially the same solution to the nonsteady-state diffusion equation applies to cases in which diffusion occurs from a surface held at constant concentration into a medium that is infinite in just one direction (i.e., semi-infinite). The relation describing concentration as a function of distance for this "constant surface" boundary condition is where q is the initial concentration of diffusant in the sample of interest and c 0 is the surface concentration. This solution has been implemented for diffusion in volatile-bearing melts in several ways, including: (1) exposing an initially volatile-free specimen to an effectively infinite reservoir of fluid, thus generating uptake profiles in which the surface concentration of the dissolved volatile is equal to its solubility (and therefore constant over time); (2) annealing samples initially containing dissolved volatiles at conditions conducive to diffusive loss; and (3) partially dissolving minerals into volatile-bearing melts to evaluate the effect of dissolved volatiles on diffusion of the components of the dissolving mineral.</p><p>In the last case above, the diffusant concentration is held constant at the surface of the dissolving mineral (x = 0) as dictated by the solubility of that mineral in the melt (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). The process of mineral dissolution actually results in a moving mineral/melt interface, thus invalidating Equation ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>) as a rigorous description of c x t vs. x in the melt. For highly insoluble minerals (e.g., apatite and zircon in silicic melts), the interface displacements involved in dissolution may have an insignificant effect on the diffusion gradient in the contacting melt, so the solution above is still serviceable for extracting diffusivities. (Strictly speaking, the volatile-uptake and -loss approaches also involve a moving interface if a change in volume accompanies dissolution or volatilization, but such effects are likely to be negligibly small). In the context of moving boundaries, it should be noted that analytical solutions to the nonsteady-state diffusion equation do exist for some moving-boundary situations (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Crank, 1975)</ref>, and almost any degree of complication can be modeled numerically using finite-difference techniques. In most situations, of course, it is the objective of the experimenter to design his or her experiments around the simplest possible data acquisition and reduction, keeping the number of variables to a minimum. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>mineral I melt distance Diffusion in more than one dimension</head><p>For certain problems in volatile diffusion, it is convenient to use what are best described as bulk-gain or bulk-loss experiments-i.e., ones in which a volatile component diffuses into or out of a sample over its entire surface area. Prior to the advent of in situ analytical techniques, this approach was necessary (as in Shaw's pioneering work on H 2 0 diffusion in granitic melt) because, even though concentration profiles could not be determined, bulk loss or gain of a component could be gauged gravimetrically. Appropriate solutions to Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">9</ref>) exist for dealing with situations in which diffusion occurs, for example, radial to the axis of a cylinder or the center of a sphere, and the only quantity that can be measured is the total amount of material diffused in or out (see <ref type="bibr">Crank, 1975, pp. 90ff</ref>). In general, the diffusivity is assumed to be independent of concentration in applying such solutions, but characterization of the shape of sorption (or desorption) vs. (time) 1 ^ curves can permit an assessment of the existence of any concentration dependence (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Shaw, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Jambon et al., 1992)</ref>. Depending upon the uncertainty in measuring gain or loss of volatiles, and also upon the degree to which the sample approaches an ideal shape (sphere, cylinder, etc.), D values resulting from bulk sorption or desorption can have relatively high uncertainties.</p><p>Even if an in situ analytical technique is available for a component of interest, it may still be convenient to use a spherical sample geometry-e.g., a melt droplet in contact with an atmosphere that serves as a source or sink for the volatile of interest. Such a case involves radial diffusion, and the resulting concentration profiles differ from those caused by diffusion in one dimension only. The experimenter is faced with the choice of fitting measured profiles to a slightly more complex equation for spherical diffusion <ref type="bibr">(Crank, 1975, p. 91)</ref>, or ignoring the radial aspect and invoking Equation ( <ref type="formula">18</ref>). The latter approach is perfectly acceptable when the total length of the diffusion profile is a small fraction of the sample radius.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DIFFUSION OF DISSOLVED VOLATILES IN MAGMATIC LIQUIDS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The strategy in this section is to review, in chronological order of publication (as far as is practical), experimental studies of dissolved volatile diffusion in magmas. The various magmatic volatiles are discussed independently, more or less in order of abundance, beginning with water and progressing to C0 2 , sulfur species, halogens, and eventually to noble gases. An attempt is made to present enough details of the experimental techniques Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM used in each study for the reader to appreciate the general quality and range of applicability of the data. For clarity in presentation and ease of interstudy comparison, available data for a given volatile are presented on a single Arrhenius diagram, omitting actual data points in most cases. A comparative summary diagram of available data on diffusion of all dissolved volatiles appears at the end of the section (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">13</ref>, below). For ease in comparison among various diffusants, Arrhenius equations taken from the numerous sources of data are standardized to SI units, and lines appearing on the summary figures are keyed to equations in the text. Many readers are probably more familiar with the now unfashionable units of calories and centimeters, so the following conversion </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Water and related species</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Silicic melt compositions.</head><p>As noted previously, the first study of H 2 0 diffusion in a magmatic liquid was that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Shaw (1974)</ref>, who investigated the rate of H 2 0 uptake by cylinders of granitic obsidian. Although much more is known today about the details and mechanisms of dissolved H 2 0 transport in melts, Shaw brought to light the general systematics of the diffusion process, and his data and interpretations, as well as the applications he discussed, still stand as fundamental contributions.</p><p>Shaw's bulk-uptake approach was simple and appropriate to the general unavailability (at the time) of in situ analytical techniques for hydrogen and/or oxygen. Cylinders of granitic obsidian (Valles Caldera, NM, USA; 77% Si0 2 ) were milled to -2.5 mm in diameter and sealed in gold capsules with an amount of water just sufficient for saturation of the obsidian at run conditions. Using cold-seal pressure vessels, the capsules were subjected to water pressures of 10 to 200 MPa at temperatures of 750° to 850°C for durations of 1 to 150 hours. At any given pressure and temperature, water diffused into the obsidian cylinders to an extent determined by the run duration. Upon quenching, the total water uptake was gauged both by the weight gained during the high P-T hydration and the weight lost upon subsequent complete dehydration at 1000°C in air.</p><p>Shaw recognized the possibility that water diffusivity would depend upon water content, but his bulk-uptake technique limited his ability to quantitatively determine D water * as a function of XH2O By inspection of the form of weight-gain vs. hydration-time curves for specific conditions, and by analogy with concentration-dependent diffusion in other materials, he was able to deduce the general sense of D water variation with concentration, which is reproduced in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> in comparison with results from later studies. The diffusivity ranges from ~10 13 m 2 /s at vanishingly small H 2 0 content to ~10 u m 2 /s at 6 wt % dissolved H 2 0. Shaw's best estimate of the activation energy, Q, for diffusion was ~6Q±20 kJ/mole (see lines 19 and 20 in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>), which, he noted, compared favorably with previously-determined values for hydrogen and water diffusion in silica  <ref type="bibr">(1979)</ref>, which pertain to 850°C. Note that Jambon's value plotted at 3% water actually represents melts containing 1 to 5% water-an average water content is shown here for clarity. Note also that his value at -0.1% water is shown as corrected by the later work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Jambon et al. (1992)</ref>. The dashed or dotted lines show envelopes of uncertainty proposed by the authors of each study, except for those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Karsten et al. (1982)</ref>, which were estimated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Lapham et al. (1984)</ref>. 1500 1100 900 700  <ref type="bibr">(20)</ref> where the diffusivity and pre-exponential term are in m 2 /s and R is 8.3143 J/deg-mole (the activation energy therefore being in J/mole).</p><p>Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM An interesting aspect of Shaw's study, and one that is shared with most subsequent investigations of diffusion in H 2 0-bearing granitic compositions, is that the diffusion medium varied from glass containing a small amount of dissolved water to hydrous granitic melt. At 750°-850°C and 200 MPa, nominally dry obsidian is metastable (possibly even below the glass transition temperature, Tg), whereas water-saturated obsidian is a stable, superliquidus melt. Perhaps the change in D water with increasing water content (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>) occurs as the diffusion medium varies from a rigid glass to a low-viscosity melt. Clearly, this is a circumstance in which the diffusant of interest has a profound effect upon the stability and physical properties of the diffusion medium. Indeed, it seems to have been Shaw's own earlier work on obsidian-H 2 0 viscosities <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Shaw, 1963)</ref> that stimulated his interest in diffusion.</p><p>Shortly after the Shaw's paper appeared, a study of diffusion in obsidian at low temperatures (-100° to 250°C) was published by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Friedman and Long (1976)</ref>. Because this review concerns diffusion specifically in magmas, this study of glasses is mentioned only in passing; it is worth noting, however, that the up-temperature extension of the hydrationrate data acquired by Friedman and Long passes in the general vicinity of Shaw's inferred values for diffusion in hydrous obsidian melt. As we shall see, this coincidence presaged a later conclusion: diffusion of water in amorphous silicates is insensitive to the rigidity of the medium.</p><p>Following that of Shaw, the next study to yield data on water diffusion in magmas was that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Arzi (1978)</ref>, who examined the melting kinetics of water-bearing rocks, with emphasis on the Westerly granite. In an internally-heated, gas-medium pressure vessel, Arzi exposed large (~l-cm) samples of natural rock to water pressures of 0.2 GPa and temperatures up to 1060°C; this treatment resulted in the migration of a melting front from the exposed surface of the sample inward. He hypothesized that the migration rate of this front was rate-limited by diffusion of H 2 0 through the melt, and on this basis deduced information on H 2 0 diffusion by measuring melt-front position as a function of time in a series of five experiments at ~1020°C (actually 980° to 1060°C). Arzi also applied his technique for extracting D water to an earlier set of experimental data on melt-front penetration in granulite at 760° and 0.2 GPa <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Mehnert et al., 1973)</ref>. Combined with his own value for 1020°, the resulting lower-temperature diffusivity enabled him to estimate the activation energy for H 2 0 diffusion at -140 kJ/mole. Although his data are qualitatively similar to those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Shaw (1974;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> see Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>), it seems clear, in the light of more recent data, that Arzi's indirectly calculated activation energy is almost certainly too high. Moreover, his additional conclusion that D water is independent of H 2 0 concentration has been called into question by later work (see below), in which Shaw's strongly concentration-dependent D is confirmed. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Jambon (1979)</ref> performed dehydration and hydration experiments on a natural obsidian (Valles Caldera, NM, U.S.A.; 76.9% Si0 2 ) to determine D water at low (&lt;0.4 wt %) and high (1 to 5 wt %) water concentrations, respectively. The dehydration runs involved simple heating of obsidian slabs in air at 500° to 980°C, and the diffusivities were computed from bulk weight-loss measurements. The hydration runs, like those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Shaw (1974)</ref>, were made in cold-seal pressure vessels (0.1 GPa; 800° to 900°C), but Jambon was able to characterize actual diffusive uptake profiles (rather than just bulk uptake), by making weight-loss measurements on microsectioned wafers. Another innovation in Jambon's study was the addition of obsidian powder to the water reservoir in the hydration experiments. Rapid cation exchange between the water and the glass powder established chemical equilibrium between the reservoir and the diffusion sample for all components except H z O. The results of the study reveal a 3-order-of-magnitude difference in D water Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM between obsidians with low and high water contents. The "water rich" values resemble those of Shaw (-10 11 m 2 /s; see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>), and the "water-poor" data define an Arrhenius line giving lower diffusivities: Dwater = 1.3-10" 11 exp(-47,100/RT)* (21) The activation energy for H 2 0 diffusion in the water-poor samples (-47 kJ/mole) is within the overall range of 60±20 kJ/mole suggested by Shaw (cf. line 21 with lines 19 and 20 in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Delaney and Karsten (1981)</ref> were the first to employ a truly in situ analytical technique to determine D water . They used an ion microprobe to characterize the concentration gradients in H 2 0 across axial sections of some of Shaw's original obsidian samples that had been partially hydrated at 850°C and 70 MPa water pressure. (The ion microprobe actually measures H concentration in the glass, which was assumed to represent dissolved H 2 0.) Armed with "H 2 0" concentration vs. distance curves, Delaney and Karsten could calculate D water more precisely than Shaw was able to do from his bulk weight-gain data. The shapes of the uptake profiles necessitated a concentration-dependent diffusivity to achieve good fits; in the final analysis, however, Shaw's original estimates for D water -and even its dependence upon H 2 0 concentration-held up remarkably well (see Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref> and<ref type="figure">6</ref>). Delaney and Karsten concluded that D water increases exponentially with H 2 0 content in the 0.2 to 3.7 wt % range represented in their study. <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Karsten et al. (1982)</ref> later extended the work just described to cover a 300° range in temperature (650° to 950°C), with the aim of accurately determining the activation energy for water diffusion. They ran a new series of experiments on the same obsidian originally used by Shaw, but modified the experimental technique so that H 2 0 diffused only into the exposed, polished ends of 2.5 mm-diameter, platinum-jacketed cylinders encapsulated in Ag 70 Pd 30 tubes. The diffusion anneals were done in an argon-medium, internally-heated pressure vessel at 70 MPa pressure, f 0j between FMQ and NNO, for durations of 1 to 6 hours. The resulting diffusivities confirmed both the marked dependence of D water upon water content (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>) and the activation energy for diffusion originally suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Shaw (1974)</ref>: at a constant water content of 2 wt %, the diffusivity ranged from -10~1 2 m 2 /s at 650°C to ~10 _11 m 2 /s at 950°C, which translates into an activation energy of -80 kJ/mole (see Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>).</p><p>The first study aimed at determining the effect of pressure on diffusion of water in a geologic melt was that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Lapham et al. (1984)</ref>. In preference to the hydration technique used in earlier studies, these workers chose a diffusion-couple configuration for their experiments so they could vary pressure without also causing major changes in the concentration of dissolved water (water solubility in melts is strongly pressure-dependent; see Chapter 3, 4, 6). In a gas-medium pressure vessel, they prepared uniformly hydrated cylinders (-3.7 wt % H 2 0) of the same obsidian originally used by Shaw, and subsequently juxtaposed these with nominally dry cylinders of the natural obsidian. The couples were run at 850°C and pressures of 70 to 500 MPa for 3 or 6 hours. The resulting "H 2 0" diffusion profiles were characterized by ion microprobe analysis for H, and diffusivities were extracted using Boltzmann-Matano analysis (see Eqn. 10). Concerning the main effect they were investigating-that of pressure-Lapham et al. concluded that it is too small to see within the uncertainty of their data, but placed the maximum allowable activation volume at -4 cm 3 /mole. Their overall data set is in excellent agreement with earlier results (see Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>), with D water again showing a strong dependence upon concentration (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>). A useful additional piece of information provided in the study is that the alkali concentrations remain constant across the diffusion couples even in the face of extensive water diffusion, thus eliminating the possibility that the diffusion process involves exchange of H+ with Na + and/or K + (and perhaps suggesting that water diffuses as a neutral species...?).</p><p>Lapham et al. also included in their study some experiments involving D 2 0 diffusion. These were done using the techniques employed earlier by <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Karsten et al. (1982)</ref>, except that, because the source reservoir was 99.9% D 2 0, gold rather than AgPd was used for the outer container (gold is less permeable to H 2 and D 2 ). Deuterium-uptake profiles were characterized with the ion microprobe. The systematics of D 2 0 diffusion were found to be very similar to those for water, the Arrhenius parameters being the same as those determined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Karsten et al. (1982)</ref> except for the pre-exponential constant, D 0 , which was a factor of two lower for D 2 0. The pilot study of <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Lapham et al. (1984)</ref> on D 2 0 diffusion was followed by additional data from the ASU group <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Stanton et al., 1985)</ref> obtained from experiments on the same obsidian using a similar D 2 0-uptake approach. The main improvement seems to have been in analytical procedure: Stanton et al. obtained previously unavailable standards of known D 2 0 content for use in the ion microprobe analysis. The resulting diffusivities differed somewhat from the preliminary results of Lapham et al., but were indistinguishable from the earlier D water values obtained by <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Karsten et al. (1982)</ref>. The coincidence in diffusion behavior of water and heavy water was cited by Stanton et al. as a demonstration that water diffuses as something other than free protons or H 2 molecules [the factor-of-two difference in mass between H and D would have resulted in a significantly lower pre-exponential term (by a factor of V2) for diffusion of D 2 0 relative to H 2 0 if protons and deuterons (or H 2 and D 2 ) were the diffusing species].</p><p>Several years elapsed before further advances were made in our understanding of water diffusion in magmas. The crucial foundation for further progress was laid by Stolper and co-workers in the early 1980s, who investigated the speciation of dissolved water in a variety of silicate melts and glasses using infrared (IR) spectroscopy. Briefly summarized, the principal conclusion of these studies was that H2O dissolves as both hydroxyl groups (OH") and molecular water, the former dominating at low total H2O content (~0 to 2 wt %), the latter becoming increasing important at higher concentrations (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Stolper 1982</ref>; see also <ref type="bibr">Chapters 3,</ref><ref type="bibr">4,</ref><ref type="bibr">6)</ref>. Recognizing the potential significance of speciation to diffusion, and applying a mathematical formulation for diffusion of a multi-species component, <ref type="bibr">Zhang et al. (1991)</ref> published a definitive study of water diffusion in rhyolitic glass. They worked with polished slabs of natural glass from Mono Craters, California, initially containing 0.2 to 1.7 wt % H2O. These slabs were partially dehydrated by heating in N2 at 403° to 550°C, and water-loss profiles were characterized by FTIR spectroscopy in terms of both OH" and molecular H2O. The resulting profiles were used to model diffusion governed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">flwater] 3 3[H 2 Q] , ^ 3[OH]/2 n dt = 3x1-20 ^c h 3x J (22)</formula><p>which the reader will recognize as the one-dimensional, nonsteady-state diffusion equation (cf. Eqn. 6) describing the change in concentration of "bulk" water at some point in the sample as a consequence of the mobilities of two dissolved species (OH" and H2O). <ref type="bibr">Zhang et al. (1991)</ref> were able to show that at water contents exceeding ~1 wt % (depending somewhat on temperature and whether the experiment involved hydration or dehydration), speciation equilibrium was achieved at all points along the H 2 0 diffusion gradients. They used both a forward finite difference model and inversion of the measured profiles (a Boltzmann-Matano type of analysis) to show convincingly that D 0 h _ /Dh20 is close to zero. In other words, diffusion of dissolved water occurs by migration of the molecular species, the hydroxyls being effectively immobile. This means that the concentration of OH groups along a diffusion gradient is not attributable to diffusion but to local conversion from H 2 0 molecules-a finding consistent with earlier models for simple glasses (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Doremus, 1969)</ref>. An important conclusion of the Zhang et al. study is that earlier data on water diffusion in obsidian (see above) pertain to an apparent diffusivity that results from rapid diffusion of H 2 0 and local H 2 0 + 0 = 2 OH" equilibrium (they refer to this diffusivity as the "apparent total water diffusivity"). Using calculated equilibrium values for [H 2 0]/[0H~], Zhang et. al. were able to extract DH2O f rom the published apparent values and show that a down-temperature extrapolation of previous data (i.e., those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Karsten et al., 1982 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Lapham et al., 1984)</ref> is entirely consistent with the new lowertemperature data (see Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>). Interestingly, as noted by <ref type="bibr">Zhang et al.,</ref> this means that the transition from hydrous melt at ~950°C to water-bearing glass at 400°C is transparent to diffusion of water. The Arrhenius relation proposed by <ref type="bibr">Zhang et al.</ref> to describe diffusion of molecular water in rhyolitic melts or glasses containing 1 to 3 wt % H 2 0 is</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">d h 2 0 = 4.6^3 3 -10-7 exp(-103,000±5,000)/RT (<label>23</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">)</formula><p>where the units are as indicated for Equations ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">20</ref>). The authors noted that the activation energy for diffusion of H 2 0 molecules falls on a monotonic trend of Q vs. atomic (molecular) radius of neutral species (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">11,</ref><ref type="figure">below</ref>).</p><p>In a re-visitation of the earlier work by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Jambon (1979)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Jambon et al. (1992)</ref> extended the data base on DH2O in obsidian to low, natural water contents of -0.114 wt % [this concentration represents a re-determination of the 0.38% originally used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Jambon (1979)</ref>]. As noted previously, the experiments consisted of simple dehydration of wafers of obsidian from Valles Caldera (76.9 wt % Si0 2 ). Because the 1979 run products were lost, the 1992 re-examination involved no new analytical determinations. Rather, the original, bulk-loss data were re-interpreted using the newly-determined initial water content (0.114 wt %) and the "mobile molecular water" model described above. The results were found to be consistent with extrapolation of existing data for wetter samples.</p><p>A final paper concerning transport of water-related species in silicic melts is that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Chekhmir et al. (1985)</ref> on hydrogen (H 2 ) diffusion in dry albitic glass (NaAlSi 3 Og) and water-saturated albitic melt. This study is discussed outside of the chronological progression just completed because it addresses geologically unusual circumstances of extremely reducing conditions.</p><p>The authors used a technique quite different from those implemented in the studies described above: basically, they used redox color indicators to estimate the extent of hydrogen penetration into their experimental samples. Albite glasses were prepared in a methane-oxygen flame, which resulted in dissolved C0 2 concentrations of -0.05 wt %. Monitoring diffusion of hydrogen is made possible by the fact that dissolved C0 2 imparts no color to the specimens, but C produced by reaction with diffusing hydrogen causes the sample to turn grey. Diffusion experiments were performed by placing the pre-melted glass specimens in Pt containers open to an atmosphere of pure H 2 at a pressure of 180 MPa. The extent of hydrogen penetration was assessed by measuring the thickness of the darkened outer zone; the diffusivity could be calculated directly from this measurement because the concentration of C0 2 was not high enough to consume a significant amount of the inward diffusing hydrogen. Over the temperature range 750° to 880°C, <ref type="bibr">Chekhmir et</ref>  which has been included on Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> for comparison with water diffusion systematics in obsidian. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Chekhmir et al. (1985)</ref> used a similar technique for additional experiments on hydrous, molten albite. In this case, the starting specimens for the diffusion experiments were prepared at P H 0 = 50 MPa, T = 1000°C (giving X H2 Q ~ 1.7 wt %) in a gas-medium pressure vessel. Included in the albite was 7 wt % Mn 2 0 7 to serve as a hydrogen trap and redox indicator. The hydrogen diffusion experiments were performed by returning the Mn oxide-doped glasses to the pressure vessel in open Pt tubes, so at run conditions they were exposed to a buffered atmosphere with P Hz ~ 500 kPa. Inward-diffusing hydrogen reduced the Mn to the +2 state, causing a color change and allowing the depth of H 2 penetration to be determined. Taking into account the consumption of mobile hydrogen by the reduction reaction, the authors estimated D H2 in hydrous albite melt at 8-10" 8 m 2 /s, which is much higher than any diffusivity in a silicate melt measured before or since. Assuming no melt-composition effects on hydrogen transport and extrapolating to basalt liquidus temperatures, Chekhmir et al. suggested a value of MO -6 m 2 /s for D Hz in molten basalt, which is comparable with diffusion of heat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Basaltic melt.</head><p>The only published data on diffusion of water-related species in basaltic melt are those of <ref type="bibr">Zhang and Stolper (1991)</ref>. Their starting material was a basaltic glass from the Juan de Fuca Ridge containing 50.6 wt % Si0 2 and having a natural water content of -0.4 wt %. Pieces of this glass were dehydrated at 1 atmosphere pressure, ground into disks, and juxtaposed in diffusion couples against similar disks of pristine, water-bearing glass. The couples were run in graphite-lined Pt containers at 1 GPa and 1300° to 1500°C using a piston-cylinder apparatus. Upon quenching and depressurization, the samples were cut into wafers and the concentration profiles of OH" groups and molecular H 2 0 were determined by FTIR spectroscopy, stepping across the region perpendicular to the interface of each couple. Diffusivities were determined by Boltzmann-Matano analysis and by modeling the gradients as resulting from diffusion of molecular H 2 0 only, with the additional assumption that local equilibrium is maintained between H 2 0 and OH" groups. As in the case of the much more silicic melts discussed earlier, the apparent total water diffusivity varies with water content, and is significantly higher than the up-temperature extrapolation from previous data for more silicic melts (see Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>). The governing Arrhenius equation is: D water = 3 -8 *3.4 -10 " 6 exp(-126,000±32,000/RT) (25)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Carbon dioxide</head><p>The first study of dissolved C0 2 diffusion in silicate melts was that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Watson et al. (1982)</ref>, who acquired data for two melts: (1) a simple, sodium aluminosilicate melt (60 wt % Si0 2 ), for which diffusion was characterized over a broad temperature-pressure range (800° to 1500°C; 0.05 to 1.8 GPa); and (2) an iron-free, haplobasaltic melt (-53 wt % Si0 2 ), investigated at 1.5 GPa and 1350° to 1500°C. All experiments were made using a thin-source, radiotracer technique in which 14 C (in the form of sodium carbonate) was deposited on one end of cylindrical glass samples. Runs above 0.2 GPa were made in a piston-cylinder apparatus; those at 0.2 GPa and below were made in either cold-seal pressure vessels or an internally-heated, argon-medium apparatus. that melt could be studied without encountering the liquidus. The temperature dependence of C0 2 diffusion in the sodium aluminosilicate melt at 50 MPa is well constrained by: (see Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>), and the pressure dependence-characterized at 1200°C only-is given by: where the pre-exponential term is the diffusivity (m 2 /s) at 1200 and "zero" pressure, and the activation volume (cf. V a in Eqn. 14) is in m 3 /mole [these units require that pressure be expressed in dyne/m 2 (Pa) and R in dyne-m/deg-mole (J/deg-mole)]. The pressure effect amounts to roughly an order-of-magnitude decrease in D cc&gt;2 over a 2.5-GPa increase in pressure.</p><p>In the course of a general study of C0 2 solubility in a rhyolitic melt, <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Fogel and Rutherford (1990)</ref> obtained the first value for D cc . in a highly silicic composition (76.5 wt % Si0 2 ). Their technique involved sealing of polished obsidian slabs in Ag-Pd tubes along with sufficient Ag 2 C 2 0 4 to saturate the melt in C0 2 at run conditions (50 to 660 MPa; 950° to 1150°C). Using FTIR spectroscopy, they characterized C0 2 uptake profiles in some of the samples run at 1050°C, and were able to convert these into diffusivities by assuming a constant surface concentration of C0 2 and implementing a solution for diffusion in a cylindrical sample. The resulting mean diffusivity of 2.4(±0.5)*10" 12 m 2 /s differs by only about a factor of two from the value given by the Arrhenius relation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Watson et al. (1982;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> see Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>), foretelling an insensitivity of D cc&gt;2 to melt composition that would be borne out by future studies. [This insensitivity to large variations in melt composition is now a wellestablished characteristic of C0 2 diffusion; it is also somewhat enigmatic, because C0 2 dissolves primarily as carbonate anions in basic melts and as C0 2 molecules in polymerized, silicic melts <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Fine and Stolper 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr">1986)</ref> The topic of C0 2 diffusion was revisited by <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Watson (1991)</ref> with the specific objective of determining diffusivities in more silicic melts and characterizing the effect of dissolved water on C0 2 diffusion. The melts chosen for study were a metaluminous, rhyolitic obsidian from Lake county, Oregon (76.4 wt % Si0 2 ), and a natural dacite from the Aleutians (63.5 wt % Si0 2 ). A radiotracer technique similar to that employed earlier by <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Watson et al. (1982)</ref> was used, but the melts were contained in thick-walled Ni capsules lined with Au or Ag-Pd sleeves. All experiments were run at 1 GPa, over a temperature range of 800° to 1100°C. The main findings of the study are that: (1) there is little melt composition dependence of C0 2 diffusion, as indicated by the general similarity among Arrhenius parameters for dry melts of widely varying composition, including not only the sodium aluminosilicate and haplobasaltic compositions studied earlier, but also the new values for granitic and dacitic melts; and (2) dissolved water has a major effect on C0 2 diffusion, causing a three-order-of-magnitude increase in Dco 2 as water content is increased from 0 to 8 wt % at 800 (the effect is smaller at higher temperatures). For a granitic melt containing 8 wt % dissolved H 2 0, diffusion of dissolved carbonate is described by: D CQ2 (8%H 2 0) = 6.5-10" 8 exp(-75,000+21,000/RT) (28)</p><p>In general, the effect of dissolved H 2 0 on C0 2 diffusion is to decrease both the activation energy and the pre-exponential constant (cf. Eqns. 28 and 26), which results in an increase in diffusivity at magmatically realistic temperatures (see Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref> and also later section on the effects of dissolved water on cation diffusion). Interestingly, this pattern is typical of the effects of dissolved water on diffusion of cations, as we will show later in this chapter.</p><p>As a "by-product" of their study of water diffusion in basaltic melt, <ref type="bibr">Zhang and Stolper (1991)</ref> also obtained one value for diffusion of C0 2 at 1300°C. The volatile-free half of each of their diffusion couples experienced uptake of C0 2 produced by oxidation of the contacting graphite container. The authors were able to characterize one of these uptake profiles by FTIR spectroscopy, and obtained a diffusivity almost identical to that determined earlier by <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Watson et al. (1982)</ref> for their simpler melt compositions. This result was encouraging not only in that it provided additional confirmation of the insensitivity of D C Q 2 to melt composition, but also because it demonstrated that different labs using different experimental and analytical approaches (6-track radiography vs. FTIR spectroscopy) could produce results in substantial agreement (see Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>).</p><p>Stolper's group at Caltech followed up their initial foray into C0 2 diffusion with an indepth study of diffusion in a granitic obsidian <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Blank et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Blank, 1993)</ref>, using a technique similar to that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Fogel and Rutherford (1990)</ref>. Cylinders or rectangular prisms of natural, water-poor obsidian were exposed to elevated pressures of C0 2 (50 to 105 MPa) over a broad range in temperature (450° to 1050°C) for periods ranging from ~1 day to 6 weeks. Following these diffusive-uptake experiments, wafers were cut from the samples and polished in preparation for analytical traverses with a focusing FTIR. The measured concentration profiles of dissolved C0 2 (all in molecular form) were inverted through error-function solutions for diffusion in a cylinder or slab to obtain diffusivities. Remarkably, the resulting data fall on a single Arrhenius line over the entire temperature range examined (see Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>):</p><p>D CO 2 = 6.2^2.6 "10 -7 exp(-144,60Q±4100/RT) (29)</p><p>This line applies to C0 2 diffusion in a material of granitic composition spanning the range from solid glass on the low-temperature end to viscous melt at 1050°C, and passes close to the previous data of both <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Fogel and Rutherford (1990)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Watson (1991)</ref>. The small Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM range in pressure covered by Blank's experiments precluded calculation of a wellconstrained activation volume, but a tentative value of at least 25 cm 3 /mole was suggested. If V a really is that large [in contrast with the value of ~11 cm 3 /mole determined earlier by <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Watson et al. (1982;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> see above) for a more basic melt], then the coincidence of Blank's "low-pressure" Arrhenius line with the earlier 1-GPa data of <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Watson (1991)</ref> must be fortuitous-an activation volume of 25 cm 3 /mole translates into a nearly 10-fold decrease in D C02 between 0.1 and 1 GPa. Either V a is smaller than proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Blank (1993)</ref> or the agreement between data sets is not quite as good as one would conclude at first glance. [A strong dependence of diffusivity upon pressure is by no means unreasonable, and has been observed in studies of volatile-free melts-e.g., ferrous iron in sodium aluminosilicate melts <ref type="bibr">(Dunn and Radiffe, 1990</ref>).]</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sulfur-related species</head><p>We now turn from what are generally accepted as the two most abundant magmatic volatiles (H 2 0 and CO2) to one that is relatively specific in (volumetric) importance to the late-stage evolution of calcalkaline magmas: i.e., S0 2 and its more reduced counterparts. Diffusion studies of sulfur-related species have been undertaken so recently that the only published data are those found in two abstracts <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">(Watson et al., 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Baker and Rutherford, 1994)</ref>; accordingly, this part of the present review is really more of a preview of coming attractions.</p><p>Like H 2 0, sulfur dissolves in magmas in more than one form. In contrast to the case of H 2 0, however, sulfur speciation is determined primarily by the oxidation state of the magma, with sulfide dominant at low fo 2 (&lt;FMQ, roughly speaking) and sulfate at high f Q (&gt;2 log fo 2 units above FMQ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[Carroll and Rutherford, 1988</ref>; see also Chapter 7]. Thus, the transition from sulfide-to sulfate-dominated melts occurs over a relatively small range in / 02 that encompasses typical values for calcalkaline magmas. As we shall see, the studies described below do not answer definitively the question of speciation-dependence of D su if ur , but they do provide a preliminary data set indicative of a relatively small /q 2 effect. <ref type="bibr" target="#b72">Watson et al. (1993)</ref> performed three types of experiments on a variety of melt compositions, including natural obsidian (76 wt % Si0 2 ) and dacite (68 % Si0 2 ) as well as synthetic (Fe-free) dacite, synthetic low-K andesite (61% Si0 2 ) and a lunar ultramafic composition (44 % Si0 2 ). The "lunar" melt was doped with 3000 ppm S and loaded on Pt wire loops for low-pressure, sulfur-loss experiments at 1300°C and log /o 2 = IW-0.7. Sulfur loss from the roughly spherical melt droplets (~1 mm dia.) was characterized by electron microprobe traverses on the quenched glasses, and D su if ur was estimated by matching the measured concentration profiles with those predicted for diffusion in a sphere governed by various assumed values of D. Diffusion in the other melts was investigated by techniques more similar to those described earlier in this chapter for other volatiles. Specifically, two types of samples were run in a piston-cylinder apparatus at 1 GPa: (1) diffusion couples consisting of presynthesized, S-doped and S-free halves; and (2) thinsource, radiotracer experiments in which 35 S was deposited (as aqueous Na 2 S0 4 ) at the end of prefabricated glass cylinders. Diffusion gradients in the quenched couples were characterized by electron microprobe traverses along axial sections, and chemical diffusivities were extracted by fitting the profiles to Equation (17). Tracer diffusivities were obtained from the thin-source experiments by making 6-track maps of the sectioned specimens, scanning these with a photodensitometer, and fitting the absorption vs. distance curves to Equation ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Watson, 1991)</ref>. The total range in temperature of the experiments was 1100° to 1500°C, although no single melt has been investigated over so large a range. The effect of up to 8.5 wt % dissolved H 2 0 on sulfur diffusion in the obsidian, dacite and andesite melts was assessed using the radiotracer technique.</p><p>Two low-pressure experiments on the lunar melt composition at 1300°C, of 40 and 180 minutes duration, returned the same diffusivity of 6.6-10" 12 m 2 /s. At the time of this writing, data at other temperatures are not available, so the temperature dependence of Dsulfur in ultramafic melts is unconstrained (but note that the activation energy for diffusion appears to decrease with decreasing Si0 2 content for the other melts; Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>). It can probably be assumed that dissolved S is present as sulfide in the lunar melt <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Carroll and Rutherford, 1988)</ref>, so the diffusivity reported above might be considered an endmember value for very reduced magmas.</p><p>Sporadic coverage of T-/ 0 . space has been achieved for the more silicic terrestrial melt compositions. Most of the diffusion-couple and radiotracer experiments run to date were made in Mo capsules, which impose very reducing conditions (near IW) on the contained melts. The body of data for sulfur diffusion in these reduced melts points to several general conclusions: (1) there is a systematic melt composition effect manifested as lower Dsulfur values and higher activation energies for diffusion as the Si0 2 content of the melt increases (the one value for the ultramafic lunar melt is consistent with this trend); (2) the effect of dissolved water is to significantly enhance sulfur diffusion, especially in highly silicic melts; and (3) D su if ur in all but the lunar melt is significantly lower than the D C Q 2 values summarized in the previous section, and markedly lower than D H20 , especially in silicic melts at typical liquidus temperatures. These general characteristics can be seen in the summary diagram presented as Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>, which include actual data points because the values are not yet published elsewhere. For dry Fe-free dacite and low-K andesite, Arrhenius equations based on 3 data points each (spanning 1300° to 1500°C) are as follows: The apparent high quality of the loglinear fit (except for the "dry" values) is considered fortuitous in view of the estimated -factor-of-2 uncertainty in each thin-source data point; however, the overall of influence of dissolved H2O is thought to be accurately represented.</p><p>It is emphasized that these equations are preliminary, with uncertainties of at least 10% in Q and much greater in D 0 . There are too few data at present to compute Arrhenius parameters for diffusion in dry obsidian melt, but it is clear that the trend represented by Equations ( <ref type="formula">30</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula">31</ref>)-toward lower D and higher Q with increasing Si0 2 content-continues up to the high-Si0 2 obsidian (see Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effect of Water.</head><p>The influence of water on D su ]f ur has been characterized most thoroughly for the low-K andesite: As water content increases from 0 to 5.5 wt %, the enhancement in diffusivity exceeds an order of magnitude at temperatures below ~1100°C (see Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>). On the basis of two data points (at 1300° and 1500°C), diffusion of sulfur in molten andesite containing -5.5 wt % H 2 0 is described approximately by: Dsulfur-3.2-10 8 exp(-115,000/RT) (32)</p><p>At 1300, where the data are most complete, D su if ur appears to increase roughly linearly with added H z O (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">9</ref>). The effect of dissolved H 2 0 appears to be even more pronounced in the obsidian melt, where an increase in D su if ur by more than an order of magnitude occurs just in the interval 3.1 to 8.5 wt % H 2 0 at 1100°C (a reliable value for dry obsidian at this temperature is not yet available). The general systematics of the effect of H 2 0 on D su if ur are similar to its effect on D cc , 2 (and cation diffusion in general; see last section of this chapter)-specifically, added H 2 0 results in higher D at any given temperature and lower Q overall.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Role of oxygen fugacity.</head><p>Although the picture concerning the influence of S oxidation state on D su if ur is not fully developed, it can be tentatively concluded that the effect is significant but not large. Two sets of information point to this conclusion. First, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Baker and Rutherford (1994)</ref> extracted D su ifar values for rhyolite melt at 800° and 900°C (200 MPa water pressure) from anhydrite dissolution experiments made under highly oxidizing conditions (Mn0-Mn 3 0 4 ); their values appear to be a factor of 5 to 10 higher than the down-temperature extrapolation of the <ref type="bibr">Watson et al. data</ref>  Rutherford are switched in their abstract). However, it is important to bear in mind that at least some of the difference is attributable to the 0.8-GPa difference in pressure between the two sets of data. The other indication of a relatively small effect on D^ifur comes from additional data acquired by <ref type="bibr">Watson et al.</ref> since the publication of their abstract. Several radiotracer experiments were made in which 5% hematite powder was added to the starting glasses as an internal /Q 2 control, and the runs were made in Pt rather than Mo capsules. After both the presynthesis step and the actual diffusion anneal, the glasses contained small, dispersed euhedra of Fe-oxide-in some cases both hematite and magnetite. The diffusivities resulting from these experiments appear to be only slightly higher than D^f^ values for reduced melts at similar conditions (see Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>More experiments on S diffusion systematically incorporating</head><p>as a variable should eventually clarify the role of changes in S speciation; for now, however, it appears that the effect of oxidation is to enhance D^fm-somewhat but not dramatically. A relatively small effect may imply that the diffusing species and/or diffusion mechanism is relatively independent of f Qr</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Halogens</head><p>Relatively little information exists on diffusion of dissolved halogens in magmas, and much of the available data base pertains to dry, simple-system analogs over restricted ranges in temperature. To the author's knowledge, only fluorine and chlorine have been studied to date.</p><p>Fluorine. The first study of F diffusion in melts was that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Johnston et al. (1974)</ref>, who used a radiotracer technique to measure Dp in a basic slag composition in the system Ca0-Al 2 0 3 -Si0 2 (-40 wt % each of CaO and Si0 2 ) at -1300° to 1600°C. Neglecting for the moment the questionable suitability of this depolymerized melt as a magma analog, the results of this study were intriguing in the respect that F was found to diffuse significantly faster-and with a lower activation energy-than any other melt component, including oxygen: Dp(tracer) ranged from -1-10" 9 to -4-10 9 m 2 /s over the temperature range investigated, which translates into an activation energy of -80 kJ/mole (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">10</ref>).</p><p>Using diffusion couples run in a piston-cylinder at 1200° to 1400°C and 1.0 to 1.5 GPa, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Dingwell and Scarfe (1984)</ref> examined chemical diffusion of fluorine in a more geologically-relevant melt of jadeite (NaAlSi 2 0 6 ) composition. One of the juxtaposed melts was of stoichiometric jadeite composition, the other jadeite in which some of the oxygen was replaced by fluorine (6 wt %). Diffusion couples were prepared by tightly packing glass powders of the two compositions into platinum tubes and sealing the tubes with welds. The couples were run with the denser, fluorine-free melt on the bottom, usually for 60 minutes. The extent of fluorine-oxygen interdiffusion was characterized by electron microprobe traverses on the quenched and sectioned samples. The authors were able to draw several important conclusions from their data: (1) the chemical diffusivity of fluorine (D F _ 0 ) in a relatively polymerized melt (-60 wt % Si0 2 ) is significantly lowerand the activation energy for diffusion significantly higher-than the tracer values reported earlier for basic slags; (2) over the range of F/O ratios studied, there is no dependence of Dp. 0 upon concentration of F (i.e., the interdiffusion gradients conformed well to Eqn. 17); and (3) any effect of pressure on F-0 interdiffusion is small (calculated activation volumes at 1200, 1300 and 1400°C are not statistically different from zero). Averaged over 1.0 to 1.5 GPa, fluorine-oxygen interdiffusion in jadeitic melt (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">10</ref>). Dingwell and Scarfe followed up their initial paper on F diffusion in jadeite melts at high pressures with a study of other melts in the Na 2 0-Al 2 0 3 -Si0 2 system at near-atmospheric pressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Dingwell and Scarfe, 1985)</ref>. These studies involved suspension of F-enriched glass spheres of albite, jadeite, and peraluminous haplogranite composition (75 wt % Si0 2 ) from Pt loops in an oxygen-flow furnace. At 1200° to 1400°C, these spheres exchanged fluorine for ambient oxygen at a rate determined by the F-0 interdiffusion coefficient. As in the previous high-pressure study of F diffusion in jadeite melt, F-0 interdiffusion was again found to be independent of F concentration, with D F . 0 increasing in the order albite &lt; peraluminous melt &lt; jadeite. For the range in temperature covered, all diffusivities fall between IO 11 and 10 13 m 2 /s, and activation energies between -120 and 180 kJ/mole. For albite melt, F-0 interdiffusion conforms to Dp. 0 = 2.3-10" 9 exp(-124,000/RT) (34)</p><p>Chlorine. The data base on chlorine diffusion is comparable with that on fluorine, being represented by just one abstract and two published papers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Watson and Bender (1980)</ref> measured tracer diffusivities for a variety of elements-including CI-in a sodalime aluminosilicate melt (56 wt % Si0 2 ) at 1100° to 1300°C and 0.6 to 1.8 GPa. As in radiotracer studies described earlier (e.g., of C0 2 ), the thin-source technique was used. Glass rods were prepared at atmospheric pressure by drawing the melt into a Pt capillary, which was subsequently cut into 6 to 8 mm lengths; one end of each length was polished and 36 C1 was introduced as aqueous NaCl. After drying off the solution, the sample was inserted in a graphite or boron nitride sleeve, which was plugged at the ends and run in a piston-cylinder apparatus. Diffusivities were calculated from photodensitometer scans of Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM track maps made from axial sections of the samples. At the lowest pressure studied (0.6 GPa), the following Arrhenius relation was determined for CI tracer diffusion in the Na 2 0-Ca0-Al 2 0 3 -Si0 2 melt: D Cl (tracer) = 3.4-10 4 exp(-207,000/RT) (</p><p>As in the case of F-0 interdiffusion studied by <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Dingwell and Scarfe (1984)</ref>, D C1 is unaffected by changes in pressure: Watson and Bender reported an activation volume of ~1 cm 3 /mole, which is not statistically different from zero.</p><p>The subject of chlorine diffusion was revisited by <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Watson (1991)</ref>, who sought to characterize the effects of dissolved H 2 0 on D C1 in rhyolitic and dacitic melts using techniques identical to those described for C0 2 in the same paper (see above). The part of the study devoted to CI diffusion was not entirely successful in that reliable data could not be obtained for melts containing less than 8 wt % dissolved H 2 0-in drier melts, the radiotracer tended to penetrate down the melt/capsule interface. One value was reported for the dacite (1100°C) and four for the obsidian (800° to 1100°C), all pertaining to melts with 8 wt % dissolved H 2 0. Scatter in the data precludes an estimate of the Arrhenius parameters, but it is clear that D C1 is lower than D CG2 in melts of similar composition and water content (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">10</ref>). Beta-track maps of the failed experiments (in which 36 C1 penetrated along the capsule wall) indicated, furthermore, that D C1 decreases sharply in melts containing less than 8% water.</p><p>Bai and Koster van Groos (1994) made a comprehensive study of CI chemical diffusion in a haplogranitic melt (74.6 wt % Si0 2 ) and a natural obsidian (77.9 wt % Si0 2 ) that addressed the effects not only of temperature (650° to 1400°C) but also of pressure (to 0.46 GPa) and water content (0-7 wt %). The study incorporated three different experimental approaches: Nominally dry, high-temperature (850° to 1400°C) experiments were performed at atmospheric pressure by immersing spheres of the rhyolitic obsidian in molten NaCl sealed in Pt capsules. Higher pressure, hydrous runs in which NaCl-rich brines served as the CI source were made in cold-seal pressure vessels at 850°C and 20 to 200 MPa, again using the natural glass as starting material. A final series of experiments was made at 0.1 to 0.46 GPa and 650° to 900°C on the haplogranitic melt in internallyheated or cold-seal pressure vessels. Chlorine uptake profiles, typically hundreds of microns long, were characterized by electron microprobe, and D C1 values were calculated using the standard approach of inverting the c-x data through the error function.</p><p>For their low-pressure series of experiments at 850° to 1400°C, Bai and Koster van Groos (1994) report the following well-constrained Arrhenius relation for chemical diffusion of CI in dry obsidian:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">D cl (chemical) = 3.16'10" 9 exp(-86,190/RT)<label>(36)</label></formula><p>The temperature effect on D C1 in hydrous haplogranitic melts (coexisting with NaClrich brine at 0.2 GPa) is given by Dctfchemical) = 6.46-10' 7 exp(-l 10,900/RT) (37)</p><p>Comparison of Equations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">36</ref>) and (37) indicates a substantial effect of dissolved water upon CI diffusion (see also Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">15a</ref>, below). Note that Equation ( <ref type="formula">37</ref>) is consistent with the isolated tracer diffusivity values reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">Watson (1991)</ref>, but the newer data are of higher quality and provide a much better indication of the temperature dependence of D C1 in hydrous silicic melts (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">10</ref>).</p><p>Bai and Koster van Groos were able to estimate activation volumes for CI diffusion in both dry and hydrous granitic melts as 27±10 and 22±7 cm 3 /mole, respectively. These Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM differ significantly from the near-zero V a value reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">Watson and Bender (1980)</ref>, but the melt compositions and pressure regimes of the two studies are also markedly different.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Noble gases</head><p>Most studies of noble gas diffusion in amorphous silicates have been conducted on solid glasses [see <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Doremus (1994)</ref> for an up-to-date review; also <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Carroll and Stolper, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr">1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">and Carroll et al., 1993]</ref>, so there exists only a tenuous basis upon which to draw conclusions about magmas. The one study devoted (in part) to diffusion in molten silicate is that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Lux (1987)</ref>, who presented preliminary data for diffusion of He, Ne, Ar, Kr, and Xe in tholeiitic basalt (49.7 wt % Si0 2 ) at 1350°C and near-atmospheric pressure.</p><p>The technique used by Lux involved initial purging of natural tholeiite melt of its noble gases, loading the resulting glass fragments into a Pt tube (~3 cm long, 0.5 cm dia.), and re-heating the tube to 1350°C in a noble-gas atmosphere for 8 hours. The bulk uptake of each gas was determined by isotope-dilution mass spectrometry, and diffusivities were calculated by applying a solution for diffusion in a semi-infinite medium in which the surface concentration is constant over time (given by the gas solubility at the pressure of the experiment). Lux considered the resulting diffusivities to be preliminary because the experiments were not repeated, but the data are very systematic in showing a monotonic (though modest) decrease in diffusivity with increasing atomic radius, from D He ~5±M0 9 m 2 /s, to D Xe ~2.5±M0 10 m 2 /s. This relationship is good evidence that the results were not affected by convection in the melt-the main pitfall to which experiments of this type are prone.</p><p>Lux noted that the calculated diffusivities are higher than would be expected from uptemperature extrapolation of values measured on basaltic glasses, and also that the 20-fold change in D from the smallest (He) to the largest (Xe) rare gas is much smaller than the 8order-of-magnitude difference reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Hiyagon (1984)</ref> for diffusion in basaltic glass at 900°C. The apparent major differences between noble gas diffusion in basaltic glasses and melts led Lux to conclude that D values cannot be extrapolated through the glass transition temperature. This conclusion is quite different from that reached by <ref type="bibr">Zhang et al. (1991)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Jambon et al. (1992)</ref> for diffusion of molecular H 2 0-and by <ref type="bibr">Blank (1994)</ref> for diffusion of C0 2 -in obsidian, which obey single Arrhenius relations over a large range in temperature spanning the glass transition. Note also that the Arrhenius relation for He diffusion determined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Jambon and Shelby (1980)</ref> for basaltic glass at 200° to 300°C does extrapolate to a value generally consistent with Lux' data for diffusion of other noble gases in basalt melt at 1350°C (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">12,</ref><ref type="figure">below</ref>). These divergent views concerning glass/melt similarity with respect to diffusion of neutral species are especially interesting in view of the fact that molecular H 2 0, rare gases and C0 2 all fall on a smooth curve relating activation energy for diffusion in obsidian (glass) to molecular or atomic radius <ref type="bibr">(Zhang et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr">Blank, 1994</ref>; see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">11</ref>). In obsidian, neutral H 2 0 and C0 2 molecules (and, by inference, rare gas atoms) seem to show consistent diffusion behavior through the glass transition; it is not yet clear, however, whether the same can be said of basalt. From studies of rare gas solubilities in natural melts, Lux concluded that solubility is negatively correlated with melt density, so perhaps the difference in diffusion properties of the two materials is due simply to structural differences between obsidian and basaltic glasses and melts.</p><p>A reasonable data base exists for rare gas diffusion in various solid glasses, including obsidian and basalt. However, because of the uncertain relevance of the information to magmas-and because other summaries exist-a comprehensive review is not attempted here. Selected noble-gas diffusivities for glasses do appear in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">12</ref> for comparison with Lux's values for basaltic melts. For information on geologically-relevant glasses, the reader is referred to Reynolds (I960), <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Jambon and Shelby (1980)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Carroll (1991), and</ref><ref type="bibr">Carroll et al. (1993)</ref>. Noble-gas diffusivities for basaltic melts only <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Lux, 1987)</ref> appear in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">13</ref>, which is a comprehensive summary diagram for diffusion of dissolved volatiles in magmatic liquids.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EFFECTS OF DISSOLVED VOLATILES (H 2 0) ON CATION DIFFUSION Introduction</head><p>The last topic taken up in this review concerns the effect of dissolved volatiles upon diffusion of other, non-volatile melt components. In almost all cases "dissolved volatiles" really means "water" here-only isolated data are available for the effects of other volatiles (and these are restricted to F and CI). Having seen the changes in D su ifur and D CQ2 brought about by adding water to a melt (see above), the reader is in a good position to anticipate the consequences of dissolved water for diffusion in general. Interestingly, even before any diffusion measurements on hydrous melts were available, there existed a widespread expectation (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Fenn, 1977)</ref> that water might have profound effects on diffusion, since a dramatic effect on melt viscosity had already been documented <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Shaw, 1963)</ref>.</p><p>Because H 2 0 is regarded as a common or even necessary component of most crustal magmas, numerous studies have been made of cation diffusion in water-bearing melts. In relatively few cases, however, has diffusion been examined specifically as a function of dissolved water content. For the sake of brevity, this review will focus on those studies in which the effects of water are specifically targeted, though other information will be brought in where relevant. The vast majority of data apply to melts of granitic composition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tracer diffusion</head><p>The first published results concerning the effects of water on diffusion were those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Jambon et al. (1978)</ref> for Cs in granitic melt (-73 wt % Si0 2 , anhydrous). This study involved thin-source experiments on obsidian cylinders that had been pre-hydrated in openended Pt tubes at 800°C and a water pressure of 200 MPa (resulting in 5.5 wt % dissolved H 2 0). After deposition of 134 Cs radiotracer at one end, a sample was returned to the pressure vessel (still in an open tube), pressurized with Ar to 300 MPa, and annealed at -750° to 900°C. During this thermal treatment, the Cs radiotracer diffused into the hydrated glass, and, simultaneously, some water was lost to the dry Ar atmosphere. Profiles of tracer activity vs. penetration depth were determined by serial "sectioning" (with HF) and gamma-ray counting. Cesium diffusivities were computed for different water contents from the combined knowledge of 134 Cs-uptake and H 2 0-loss profiles. The resulting values revealed a dramatic enhancement of Cs diffusion by the presence of dissolved water, amounting to a 4-order-of-magnitude increase in D between 0 and 2 wt % H 2 0 at 750°C (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">14a</ref>). Over this same water content interval, the activation energy for Cs diffusion was observed to drop from -290 to -70 kJ/mole. Note that if the Zr, P, and Si lines were extended down-temperature to geologically-plausible temperatures (for granitic melts), the effect of H 2 0 on diffusion would be much greater for these highly-charged diffusants than for the alkalies and alkaline earths. This is consistent with the broad observation that the slowestmoving species in dry melts are "accelerated" most by the addition of H z O to the system.</p><p>Shortly after publication of the study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Jambon et al. (1978)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Watson (1979b)</ref> reported qualitatively similar results for a nearly-identical system. Watson's thin-source technique was slightly different in that, after depositing radiotracer ( 134 Cs) at one end of a pre-hydrated obsidian cylinder (76 wt % Si0 2 , anhydrous), he resealed the container and annealed the sample in a cold-seal pressure vessel at 200 MPa. Diffusivities were extracted not by serial sectioning but from densitometer scans of B-track maps of the axiallysectioned samples. Watson referenced his results for melts containing -6 wt % dissolved H 2 0 to values for dry obsidian reported earlier by <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Jambon and Carron (1973)</ref>. The observed difference in D Cs was about 3.5 orders of magnitude at 700°C, and the activation energy for diffusion in the "wet" melt-at -82 kJ/mole-was 2.5 smaller than the "dry" value of <ref type="bibr">Jambon and Carron (see Figs. 14a and 15a)</ref>. Thus, there is reasonable qualitative agreement with the Jambon et al. study, but significant differences in the details: relative to dry obsidian, Watson observed about the same enhancement in D Cs for -6% added water that Jambon et al. produced with only 2%. This qualitative discrepancy may be attributed to the possible "open-system" nature of the experiments by <ref type="bibr">Jambon et al.</ref>-their samples may have lost water to the Ar pressure medium. However, the consequences of water loss would seem more likely to cause an wiiferestimation of the effect of water.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Watson (1981)</ref> followed up his initial study of Cs diffusion in granitic melt containing ~6 wt % water with a more detailed investigation of Cs, combined with a first look at the effects of H 2 0 on Ca and Na tracer diffusion in the same melt. The results of 45 Ca radiotracer experiments on granitic obsidian containing ~0, 3.5 and 6.2 wt % H 2 0, run at 200 MPa and 700° to 900°C, revealed strong enhancement of calcium diffusion by dissolved water, amounting to an increase in D Ca by 2.5 orders of magnitude over the -6% increase in water content. Although qualitatively similar, the effects of water on D Cs and on D Ca were noticeably different in several respects: (1) the overall enhancement of calcium diffusion was less pronounced; (2) within the uncertainties in the data, the activation energy for Ca diffusion (-110 to 120 kJ/mole) was unaffected by melt H 2 0 content; and (3) the effect of H 2 0 on logD Ca is close to linear, in contrast with the exponential effect on logD Cs (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">15a</ref>).</p><p>Sodium diffusion in granitic obsidian was examined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Watson (1981)</ref> for ~0 and 3.5 wt % H 2 0 using techniques identical to those employed for Cs and Ca, except that diffusion profiles were characterized by serial sectioning and counting the y-activity of 22 Na radiotracer. At the data-reduction stage in this study, the results for Na were anticipated with some excitement, because enhancement in D Na to the same degree as observed for Cs and Ca would lead to unprecedentedly high diffusivities (since Na diffusion is fast-at -10" 10 m 2 /s-even in dry obsidian at 700° to 900°C). The results were disappointing in the respect that H 2 0 had little influence on D Na : relative to the dry case, 3.5% H 2 0 resulted in an increase in diffusivity by only about 10% at 700, and at higher temperatures the effect was even smaller (see Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">14a</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">15a</ref>). Dissolution of H 2 0 does cause a significant decrease in the activation energy for Na diffusion, from -96 to -68 kJ/mole. Although only 3 elements were examined in the study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">Watson (1981)</ref>, the results provided the first glimpse of what would become a recognizable characteristic of the effects of H 2 0 on diffusion in granitic melts; namely, the lower the diffusivity in the dry melt (or glass), the greater the enhancement in diffusivity-and reduction in activation energy-by the addition of water. This amounts to saying that the effect of H 2 0 on diffusion in granitic melts is to cause Arrhenius lines of highly variable slope (radiating from some hightemperature point?; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Hart, 1981)</ref> to collapse into a relatively narrow band near the high end of the "dry" range (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">14</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemical diffusion</head><p>Most studies aimed at characterizing the effects of changes in H 2 0 content on chemical diffusion have involved the "mineral dissolution" technique described previously in the section devoted to experimental approaches. If chemically simple minerals can be used, partial dissolution is a convenient way to obtain effective binary diffusion coefficients of the mineral components in the contacting melt (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). The technique works especially well for minerals that are relatively insoluble in the melt, because the changes in absolute abundance of melt components in the diffusion field surrounding the dissolving mineral will be small. Low solubility also means that the developing diffusion field can be modeled simply and accurately as a stationary-boundary process.</p><p>High field-strength elements. Information concerning the effects of dissolved H 2 0 on diffusion of high field-strength elements in granitic melts (~76.4 wt % Si0 2 , anhydrous) was obtained by Watson and co-workers in studies of accessory mineral dissolution kinetics. By characterizing Zr concentration gradients against partiallydissolved zircons, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Harrison and Watson (1983)</ref> characterized Zr diffusion in granitic melts containing -0.1 to 6 wt % H 2 0 at 1020° to 1500°C and 0.8 GPa (over this temperature range, the solubility of zircon varies from -1200 ppm to -15,000 ppm Zr). Arrhenius lines were obtained for -0.1% and 6% H 2 0, and a systematic study of the effect of water was made at 1200°C, incorporating experiments with 0.1, 1.0, 2.3, 4.2, 6.0 and 6.3 wt % H 2 0. Zirconium diffusion is slow in nominally dry granitic melts, and is enhanced considerably by addition of H 2 0 (see Fig. </p><p>As in the case of Cs, logD^ varies with water content in a decidedly non-linear fashion: most of the "acceleration" of Zr occurs over the first 2% or so of dissolved H 2 0 (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">15b</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Harrison and Watson (1984)</ref> used the same partial-dissolution technique (this time with apatite) to obtain information on diffusion of phosphorus in granitic melts at 1100°-1500°C. Again, for a change in water content from -0.1 to -6 wt % H 2 0, dramatic changes in P diffusivity are observed (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">14b</ref>): Dp (dry) = 2.2\ 2 3 9 -10 5 exp(-601,000±12,000/RT) (40)</p><p>Dp (6% H 2 0) -10" 9 exp(-105,000/RT) (41) (Eqn. 41 is approximate because it is based upon only two points-at 1100° and 1300°C).</p><p>To the author's knowledge, Equation ( <ref type="formula">40</ref>) contains the highest activation energy (-600 kJ/mole) that has ever been reported for diffusion in a melt (Remarkably, it is also higher than most values for lattice diffusion in crystals!). The high Q and D 0 combine to make P the slowest-diffusing melt component thus far characterized at temperatures below about 1300°C (Zr is slower above this temperature). In keeping with the tendency for the slowest-moving species to be most affected by dissolved H 2 0, D p increases by many orders of magnitude (depending upon temperature) for even modest additions of H 2 0 (see Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">14b</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">15b</ref>). Significantly, parallel increases in the diffusivity of Ca-which, like phosphorus, is "released" during apatite dissolution-were not observed: because of its inherently higher diffusivity, Ca far outdistanced P in all experiments, but enhancement of D Ca by added H 2 0 did not approach the effect observed for P.</p><p>In a study paralleling the earlier efforts by <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Harrison and Watson (1983;</ref><ref type="bibr">1984)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Rapp and Watson (1986)</ref> examined the dissolution kinetics of monazite ([LREE]P0 4 ) in granitic melts containing 1 to 6 wt % H 2 0. Chemical diffusion of both P and REE was shown to be significantly enhanced by the presence of H 2 0. In contrast to the case of Ca and P diffusing away from dissolving apatite, however, REE and P exhibited parallel diffusion gradients along which the stoichiometry of monazite was maintained at all concentration levels. The authors took this to mean that diffusion of REE and P is strongly coupled, and so did not associate the effect of H 2 0 specifically with either REE or P. It seems likely, however, that P was the rate-limiting diffusant, inasmuch as D P from the monazite dissolution experiments was not greatly different from the values reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Harrison and Watson (1984)</ref> in their study of apatite.</p><p>Silica. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Chekhmir (1984)</ref> also made extensive use of the mineral dissolution technique for characterizing chemical diffusion, and incorporated H 2 0 content as a variable in some of his experiments (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Chekhmir and Epel'baum, 1991</ref> for a summary in English). Of particular significance was his study (at 1000°C and 1 atm to 0.6 GPa pressure) of quartz dissolution in albite melts containing variable amounts of H 2 0, in which he showed that logD Si increases exponentially with increasing H 2 0 content, with most of the increase occurring over the first -4% H 2 0 (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">15b</ref>).</p><p>Additional information concerning the effect of H 2 0 on chemical diffusion of Si was provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baker (1991)</ref>, who examined interdiffusion of dacite and rhyolite melts at both 3 and 6 wt % dissolved H 2 0. The study covered a significant temperature range (1100° to 1400°C; all at 1 GPa), so the Arrhenius parameters for Si0 2 effective binary diffusion in silicic melts could be estimated for two different water contents:</p><p>Baker emphasized that the uncertainties in D 0 and Q are large for the 6% H 2 0 case (80% in Q), but that the activation energy for Si0 2 diffusion in hydrous melts is clearly about half that for dry melts (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">14b</ref>). The dependence of logD Si upon water content appears to be roughly linear at 1200°C (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">15b</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effects of H2O: Recap and final observations</head><p>With rare exceptions, the effect of dissolved H 2 0 on both tracer and chemical diffusion in magmas is large-sometimes amounting to several orders of magnitude at a given temperature-and it is always positive. Two systematic trends seem to emerge:</p><p>(1) diffusants that are particularly sluggish in dry melts or glasses exhibit the greatest enhancement by added water (e.g., Cs, Zr, P, Si); and (2) the addition of water to a melt lowers both D 0 and Q for all diffusants. Graphically, this latter trend means that a family of Arrhenius lines for diffusion in melts of differing H 2 0 content will be fan-shaped in overall appearance, with all lines intersecting at some high-temperature point (see  <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Hart, 1981)</ref>. Of the elements studied to date, diffusion of Na is least affected by addition of H 2 0. The reader should bear in mind, however, that this conclusion can be strictly applied only to tracer diffusion. In chemical diffusion, the behavior of Na is known to be strongly coupled to that of Si0 2 (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Watson, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baker, 1991)</ref>, so during interdiffusion of dissimilar melts, any effect of H 2 0 on Si0 2 diffusion will also impact on Na.</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">D Si (3%H 2 0) = 2.</formula><p>At a given temperature, the increase in logD with increasing water content may be approximately linear (as in the cases of C0 2 , S and Si0 2 in natural melts at 1200°C) or clearly exponential (as for Cs, Zr, P and Si0 2 in albite melt at 1000°C). However, a cautionary note is probably warranted here, also: In those cases where the "H 2 0 effect" appears to be log-linear, the uncertainties in the data are sufficiently large that some other functional form is also permitted. The "fanning-Arrhenius" character of the H z O effect (see above) means that changes in logD with H 2 0 content are smaller at high temperatures. It may not be a coincidence that most of the apparently linear relationships between logD and dissolved H 2 0 content (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">15</ref>) apply to relatively high temperatures, where the inherent uncertainties in the measured D values can obscure the functional form of a relatively weak dependence. The manner in which D varies with melt H 2 0 content is of interest not only for predicting D values beyond the range of actual measurement, but also because of the obvious significance to melt structure and physical properties (see Chapter 9). In granitic melts at least, viscosity is known to depend strongly upon water content, and several authors have made a connection between the changes in diffusivity and in viscosity brought about by added water (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Chekhmir and Epel'baum, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baker, 1991)</ref>. The form of logD vs. H 2 0 content is also interesting from the standpoint of water speciation in the melt: a rapid initial increase in diffusivity with small amounts of added H 2 0 (dissolved mainly as OH"), followed by a more asymptotic increase in D at higher H z O content (where molecular H 2 0 becomes important), may indicate that it is dissolution of OH"-and concomitant disruption of Si-O-Si bonds-that enhances diffusion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effects of other volatiles: Preliminary information on fluorine and chlorine</head><p>In an attempt to paint a general picture of chemical diffusion in silicic melts containing geologically-realistic levels of halogens, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baker and Watson (1988)</ref> executed 15 diffusioncouple experiments on halogenated natural and synthetic glasses. A fluorine-doped granitic obsidian (0.68 wt % F, 73.6% Si0 2 ) was juxtaposed against either a Cl-rich obsidian (0.53 wt % CI; 71.6% Si0 2 ) or a synthetic Ca-Na-K-aluminosilicate glass (0.68 wt % F; 68.3% Si0 2 ). The couples were run in gas-or solid-medium pressure vessels at 0.01 to 1.0 GPa and 900° to 1400°C, and the resulting chemical diffusion profiles were characterized using an electron microprobe for the major elements and Synchrotron XRF for the minor and trace elements. Because systematic variations in halogen content were not included in the study, the effects of F and CI could be assessed mainly by comparison with previous studies of diffusion in similar but halogen-free materials. The most direct comparison possible was between D^ in the halogenated melts and D Zr values reported earlier by <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Harrison and Watson (1983)</ref> for the same melt lacking F and CI. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baker and Watson (1988)</ref> noted a -100-fold enhancement of Zr diffusion in the halogenated melt and a reduction in activation energy by -36%-effects qualitatively similar to that of H 2 0. The observed increase in diffusivity is consistent with the decrease in viscosity of albite melt caused by addition of fluorine <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Dingwell and Mysen 1985)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker (1993)</ref> followed up the exploratory study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Baker and Watson (1988)</ref> with a more detailed investigation of the effects of F and CI (at the -1 wt % level) upon chemical diffusion of major elements in peralkaline rhyolitic and dacitic melts. As in previous Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM studies of chemical diffusion in volatile-free magmas, the non-alkali elements (Al, Ti, Fe, Mg, and Ca) were found to diffuse at essentially the same rate as Si, so Baker focused his effort upon characterization of Si diffusion as a function of temperature and Si0 2 content of the melts. Interestingly, he found only minor differences-basically within experimental uncertainty-between D si in halogen-bearing and volatile-free melts. The data also suggested, however, that F causes a slight reduction in the activation energy for diffusion (relative to the volatile-absent case), whereas CI causes a slight increase. The overall effects of halogens on major-element diffusion in peralkaline melts appear to be minor. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baker and Boss&amp;nyi (1994)</ref> examined the combined effects of F and H 2 0 on Si diffusion in the same melts investigated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker (1993)</ref>. They showed that in melts containing ~3 wt % dissolved H 2 0, the addition of 1.3 wt % F further enhances diffusion by a factor of ~5 to 10 (depending on temperature) and causes a decrease in activation energy by -30%. This finding indicates that, at least under some circumstances, the effects of H 2 0 and F are additive. In more hydrous melts (6 wt % H 2 0), the effect of added F is small, however, the only perceptible change being a -12% reduction in activation energy.</p><p>No other studies of the effects of halogens on diffusion in melts are known to the author, but this area looks very promising for future research. Although halogens rarely, if ever, achieve the abundance levels sometimes reached by water (but see <ref type="bibr" target="#b73">Webster and Duffield, 1994</ref>; see also Chapter 7), it is clear from the initial work by Baker and colleagues that the effects may be important nevertheless. In terms of the significance to magmatic processes and to deciphering the mechanism of diffusion enhancement by halogens and H 2 0, a further exploration of the additive nature of their effects would be especially interesting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SIGNIFICANCE AND APPLICATIONS</head><p>The interrelationships among volatile abundance, transport properties and phase equilibria of magmatic melts lead to several key areas of application for data on diffusion. Many of these have been at least hinted at in the preceding review of experimental studies, because most experimenters have in mind specific uses of their data or specific hypotheses to test. The studies of Zr and P diffusion by <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Harrison and Watson (1983;</ref><ref type="bibr">1984)</ref>, for example-which were discussed above in the context of the effects of H 2 0 on high fieldstrength element diffusion-were actually conceived to test the survivability of accessory minerals under various circumstances of crustal melting. Thus it is already clear that the kinetics of crystal/liquid processes is one broad area to which diffusion in volatile-bearing magmas is highly germane. In the paragraphs below, this and other key areas of relevance are briefly discussed. On the grounds of impracticality, an exhaustive treatment is not attempted: the subject of diffusion in volatile-bearing magmas bears, in fact, on any and all magmatic processes that involve diffusion in the melt, and discussing all of these would require a chapter in itself.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Crystal/liquid processes</head><p>Growth and dissolution rates. Most experimentalists engaged in igneous phase equilibrium studies subscribe to a general view that crystals grow better in hydrous melts than in dry ones. Actual proof of a correlation between growth rate and melt H 2 0 content at a single temperature is elusive, but in light of what is now known about diffusion in H 2 0-bearing melts, the experimentalists' preconception is almost certainly accurate: H 2 0 (and halogens?) can enhance the supply rate of components required for growth to a crystal surface, thus accelerating the growth process. As shown by <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Harrison and Watson (1983;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM 1984), the reverse of crystal growth-dissolution-can also be strongly influenced by volatile-induced changes to diffusion in the melt. A general understanding of the role of volatiles in diffusion is thus crucial to addressing a host of problems related to interaction between crystals and contacting melt</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Boundary-layer processes.</head><p>A class of processes sometimes accompanying crystal growth might be best described as "boundary-layer phenomena." In general, these are interdependent with the process of growth just described. If a crystal grows rapidly (e.g., due to undercooling), incompatible components of the growth medium can accumulate ahead of the advancing crystal interface. The extent of accumulation depends upon the efficiency of diffusion in the melt at dispersing the component in question, so the extent of "pile-up" is related to the competition between the growth rate of the crystal (governed by diffusion of crystal-forming components in the melt) and diffusion of the incompatible component in the melt. It is easy to imagine that rapid growth of a crystal could also result in a boundary layer depleted in some slow-diffusing component, if that component were highly compatible in the crystal. For constant crystal growth rates, the mathematics of these phenomena are well understood, having been worked out, mainly in the 1950s, by researchers interested in the growth of semiconductor crystals (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Smith et al. 1955)</ref>. Complications may arise if boundary-layer depletion or accumulation of a particular component has a feedback effect on the growth rate or stability of the crystal. In such a case the complexity of the problem escalates rapidly (see, for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Lasaga 1982)</ref>. For the present purposes, it will suffice to point out simply that any changes in diffusivities of melt components-either absolute or relative-could markedly affect the behavior of the system. As we have seen, variations in H 2 0 content can have profound effects on diffusion of many components.</p><p>Even a brief discussion of boundary-layer phenomena would be incomplete without the observation that dissolved volatiles themselves may be subject to accumulation in advance of a growing crystal. <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Watson et al. (1982)</ref> called attention to this possibility in the context of H 2 0/C0 2 values in glass inclusions. Because glass (melt) inclusions are thought to result from rapid crystal growth, it is conceivable that the abundances and ratios of volatile components in them may not reflect those of the bulk melt. In retrospect, and with the present advantage of considerably more information on diffusion of dissolved volatiles, it now appears that any effect on H 2 0/C0 2 values in glass inclusions is likely to be minor unless crystal growth rates are extremely high. The case is by no means as clear for dissolved sulfur species, because these are now known to diffuse slowly in relation to other dissolved volatiles. It is even possible in this case that local, boundary-layer saturation in sulfide or sulfate could be induced by relatively rapid growth of a major mineral phase. These and related topics will be taken up in detail by <ref type="bibr">Watson et al. (in prep.)</ref> as the data base for sulfur diffusion nears completion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bubble growth</head><p>The kinetics of bubble growth in magmas is a very promising area of application for data pertaining specifically to diffusion of dissolved volatiles. Once a bubble has nucleated in a magma (due to oversaturation resulting from decompression or crystallization or both), subsequent growth occurs by two mechanisms: (1) diffusion of volatile species into the bubble from the surrounding melt; and (2) expansion. In most cases, these operate simultaneously because both are inevitable responses to further decompression. Modeling bubble growth by expansion of a constant mass of vapor is relatively straightforward, requiring knowledge only of the P-V-T relations of the vapor of interest and the viscosity of the melt. Growth resulting from addition of mass to a bubble, on the other hand, Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM requires detailed knowledge of the diffusivities in the melt of all volatiles contributing to the vapor-including any interplay among the various diffusivities (as in the case of H 2 0 affecting D C02 and D sulfur ). One of the first papers to incorporate measured diffusivities of dissolved volatiles into a bubble growth model is that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Sparks (1978)</ref>, who applied Shaw's original data for D H2 Q to make general predictions of growth rates. <ref type="bibr" target="#b71">Watson et al. (1982)</ref> used their newly-acquired data on D C02 to model growth of C0 2 bubbles in basaltic magmas, invoking the "bubble stability" equation derived much earlier by <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Epstein and Plesset (1950)</ref>. Watson et al. also pointed out that disequilibrium vapor compositions (i.e., failure to achieve partitioning equilibrium between melt and vapor) could result if the diffusivities of contributing volatiles are markedly different. An important recent paper addressing growth of C0 2 -rich bubbles in MORB is that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Bottinga and Javoy (1990)</ref>, who solved numerically the transport equations for multicomponent bubble growth involving diffusion of C0 2 , H 2 0, He and Ar under both static and dynamic magma conditions. Even in its thoroughness, this last paper does not exhaust the problems to which volatile diffusivities can be applied, because it addresses a specific magma type and decompression path. Additional data for diffusion of H 2 0, C0 2 , and sulfur that have become available since 1990 also increase the level of detail with which behavior of volatiles during bubble growth can be modeled. For a broad review and perspective of magma degassing, the reader is referred to Chapter 11 of this volume.</p><p>Larger-scale magmatic processes N.L. <ref type="bibr">Bowen (1928, p. 22)</ref> justifiably concluded that diffusion is unimportant to magmatic processes occurring on a scale greater than meters, simply because heat conduction is orders of magnitude faster than diffusion, so a magma would freeze before diffusion could accomplish anything. Despite the pronounced effect of dissolved H 2 0 on diffusion-of which Bowen was unaware-his assessment is still largely accurate. What, then, is left to say about the role of diffusion in large-scale processes occurring in volatilebearing magmas?</p><p>One of H.R. Shaw's principal interests in undertaking his study of H 2 0 diffusion in granitic magmas was to provide the data needed to assess the efficacy of diffusive transport on the scale of magma chambers. He was concerned, in particular, with such questions as the migration rates of hydration fronts and the influence of chemical and thermal boundary layers. Shaw did the first simple calculation to show convincingly that water cannot get deep into a magma body solely by diffusion from a wall-rock source (This was Bowen's point, and it later proved to be true of all other volatiles as well-the governing diffusivities are simply too low). It now appears that the only way a magma can take up H 2 0 and/or C0 2 from the crust is by assimilation of dispersed, volatile-bearing xenoliths (containing, for example, mica or carbonate).</p><p>More open to debate and future research are questions concerning the interplay between convection and diffusion in magma bodies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Shaw (1974)</ref> recognized that a marginal influx of water into a granitic magma body could generate a low-viscosity, lowdensity boundary layer that would be prone to buoyant rise, despite the influence of the broader thermal (cooler) boundary layer tending to sink. We now know, in addition, that diffusion rates of melt components in a wet boundary layer could be significantly accelerated relative to those in drier parts of the magma body. Since 1974, a large and diverse effort has been devoted to studies of convection/diffusion processes in magmas. To a great degree these seem to have been stimulated by the field and analytical work of <ref type="bibr">Hildreth (e.g., 1979)</ref>, whose reconstruction of a chemically-zoned magma chamber focused the attention of petrologists, geochemists, fluid dynamicists and numerical Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM modelers on the plausibility and efficacy of various transport processes. Suffice it to say here that situations can arise where diffusion becomes important in large-scale processes despite its general ineffectiveness relative to magma advection and heat conduction (e.g., in cases where intra-layer convection in stably stratified bodies persists long enough for diffusive mass exchange between layers to be effective). We are now in a reasonably good position to include in models of such processes both the diffusion of dissolved volatiles themselves and their effects on diffusion of other magma components.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Atomistic representation of diffusion in the presence of a concentration gradient. Planes 1, 2, and 3 are separated by one atomic jump distance, a (in a crystal, this would be the lattice spacing), and are oriented perpendicular to a 1-dimensional gradient in the concentration of B atoms (1), which decreases in the x direction (i.e., from left to right). Because the medium of interest is a melt, the atoms in each plane exhibit no long-range order. See text for discussion. Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>or, if D, is not a function of x (i.e., of concentration) Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM , d 2 C, '3x2</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The relationship between the two diffusivities just discussed-i.e., the tracer diffusivity (D*) and the chemical interdiffusion coefficient (D)-is relatively simple for binary metallic systems, as shown by Darken (1948): variation in D with x: (10) Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM D = pyV + XA*](1 + dlny/dlnX^ (11)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Schematic representation of a typical thin-source experiment. A cylindrical sample is depicted because melts generally are contained in noble metal tubes (not shown), with the tracer introduced at one end. Annealing for time t produces a gradient in radiotracer activity (c) described by Equation (15), which is linearized by plotting lnc vs. x 2 (Eqn. 16). Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 4. Schematic representation of chemical diffusion in a melt resulting from partial dissolution of a simple mineral. See text and Equation (18).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>uFigure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure5. Dependence of apparent total water diffusivity (D water ) upon HjO concentration, according to several research groups. All information applies to 800°C except for the data of<ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Jambon (1979)</ref>, which pertain to 850°C. Note that Jambon's value plotted at 3% water actually represents melts containing 1 to 5% water-an average water content is shown here for clarity. Note also that his value at -0.1% water is shown as corrected by the later work of<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Jambon et al. (1992)</ref>. The dashed or dotted lines show envelopes of uncertainty proposed by the authors of each study, except for those of<ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Karsten et al. (1982)</ref>, which were estimated by<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Lapham et al. (1984)</ref>.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 7. Summary of data on diffusion of dissolved CO2 in various melts and glasses. The numbers identify equations in the text. Lines 28 and 29, along with the data of both Watson (1991) and Fogel and Rutherford (1990), are for granitic compositions. Lines 26 and 27 refer to a sodium aluminosilicate melt (60% Si02), and the datum of Zhang and Stolper (1991) is for molten basalt. See text for details and discussion.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 8. Summary of data on diffusion of sulfur in magmatic melts. The numbers identify Arrhenius equations in the text. Data on the left (hightemperature) side of the diagram are from Watson et al. (1993) and generally represent experiments performed under reducing conditions at 1 GPa ("wet" andesite contains -5.5 wt % H2O). The lunar melt was run under reducing conditions at near-atmospheric conditions. The values of Baker and Rutherford (1994) represent oxidizing conditions at 200 MPa water pressure (The values are switched in their published abstract; they appear correctly in this figure). See text for details.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Effect of dissolved H2O on sulfur diffusion in molten andesite at 1300°C (previously unpublished data of Watson, D A. Wark and J. W. Delano).The apparent high quality of the loglinear fit (except for the "dry" values) is considered fortuitous in view of the estimated -factor-of-2 uncertainty in each thin-source data point; however, the overall of influence of dissolved H2O is thought to be accurately represented.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>for reduced rhyolite melt of similar H 2 0 content (see Fig. 8; note that the two diffusivities published by Baker and Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Summary of halogen (F and CI) diffusivities in molten silicates. The "wet" CI data of Watson (1991) are radiotracer values for molten obsidian (1) or dacite (n) containing ~8 wt % dissolved H2O. Other diffusivities and diffusion media represented are: CI tracer diffusion in soda-lime aluminosilicate melt with 56% Si0 2 (Watson and Bender 1980); F tracer diffusion in basic slag with 40% SiC&gt;2 (Johnston et al. 1974); F-0 interdiffusion in albite melt (Dingwell and Scarfe 1985); F-0 interdiffusion in jadeite melt (Dingwell and Scarfe 1984); and CI chemical diffusion in wet haplogranitic melt and in dry obsidian (Bai and Koster van Groos 1994). Hie numbered lines refer to Arrhenius equations in the text.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 11. Diagram showing the correlation between atomic or molecular radius of neutral diffusants and the activation energy (Q) for diffusion in rhyolitic glass.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 13. Overall summary/comparison diagrams for diffusion of various dissolved volatiles in magmatic liquids.(A) nominally dry melts (&lt;0.4 wt % H 2 0); (B) melts with 3 to 8 wt % dissolved H2O. Numbers in parentheses refer to Arrhenius equations in the text.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Figure 14. Comparison of diffusion in dry granitic melt (or glass) with diffusion in the same melt containing 6 wt % H 2 0. (A) tracer diffusivities for Cs, Ca, and Na at relatively low temperatures (700° to 900°C); (B) effective binary diffusion coefficients (EBDCs) for Zr, P, and Si at relatively high temperatures (1100° to 1500°C). In general, Arrhenius lines are shown for the temperature range actually investigated.Note that if the Zr, P, and Si lines were extended down-temperature to geologically-plausible temperatures (for granitic melts), the effect of H 2 0 on diffusion would be much greater for these highly-charged diffusants than for the alkalies and alkaline earths. This is consistent with the broad observation that the slowestmoving species in dry melts are "accelerated" most by the addition of H z O to the system.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 15. Diagram illustrating the dependence of diffusivities upon dissolved water content of granitic melt at low temperatures (A) 700° to 850°C, and high temperatures (B) 1000° to 1300°C. The 800°C curves for Zr and P were estimated by down-temperature extension of the Arrhenius lines for these elements shown in Figure 14 (see also Eqns. 38-41). Note the difference in the logD scales for (A) and (B), and that the influence of dissolved HjO is much greater at low temperature. Note also that for highly-charged diffusants in particular, most of the increase in logD occurs over the first 2 to 3% of dissolved H2O. Differences in pressure among the various studies represented in this diagram are ignored: In (A), all curves represent data acquired at 0.1 to 0.2 GPa, except for those marked Zr and P, which pertain to 0.8 GPa. In (B), all curves represent data acquired at 0.8 to 1.0 GPa. See text for further discussion.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>14b): Dz, (dry) = 0.098: o 1 6 exp(-409,000±12,000/RT) (38) D a &lt;6%H 2 0) = S.O^f-lO 6 exp(-198,000±7,950/RT)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>58-10 8 exp(126,500/RT) D Si (6%H 2 0) = 2.69-10 -7 exp(-131,400/RT) Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM discussion of diffusion "compensation" by</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>table may be helpful.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">units used in this chapter</cell><cell cols="2">conversion factors</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>parameter</cell><cell>units</cell><cell cols="3">to convert from to multiply by</cell></row><row><cell>D D 0 0 R</cell><cell>m 2 /s m 2 /s J/mole J/deg-mole (8.3143)</cell><cell>cm 2 /s calories</cell><cell>m 2 /s joules</cell><cell>IO' 4 4.184</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>glass. Arrhenius equations for D water at high and low water contents are given approxi- mately by</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>• •</cell><cell>•</cell><cell>•</cell><cell></cell><cell>500</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-i</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>r</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">i=&gt; Arzi '78</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>\25</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">Karsten et ai. '82 Lapham et at. '84</cell></row><row><cell>specific Arrhenius lines refer to numbered equations in the text; other data are identified in the legend. The glasses. The numbers associated with of water-related species in melts and Figure 6. Summary of data on diffusion</cell><cell>e 12 .9 "a M 10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">Chekhmir et al. '85</cell></row><row><cell>indicated percentages denote water content in wt %. Most information</cell><cell>a o i-&lt;</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>pertains to granitic compositions except</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>for the lines labeled 24 and 25, which refer to hydrogen diffusion in dry albite</cell><cell>14</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>glass and total water diffusion in basalt</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>melt, respectively. Line 23 represents</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>diffusion specifically of molecular H2O; all other lines depict total water diffusivities (except #24). See text for</cell><cell>16</cell><cell></cell><cell>_L 9</cell><cell>_1_ 11</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>15</cell></row><row><cell>details and discussion.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">1/T(K)X10 4</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p>: 1.8-10-8 exp(-65,000/RT) 1.6-10 10 exp(-74,000/RT) D, water D u (6wt%H 2 0) (nominally dry) (19)</p>"'water ~ i-"' 1 "" cApv.-/«t,vAA*R.i;</p>[nominally ary/</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>al. obtained the following Arrhenius relation for hydrogen diffusion in (initially) dry albite glass D</figDesc><table /><note><p>H = 3.7-10-7 exp(-113,000/RT) (24) Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>* This is a corrected version of the relation originally published by Jambon (1979), which follows from a more accurate estimate of the initial water content of the obsidian. Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1"><p>Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The initial manuscript leading to this paper benefited from unofficial reviews by <rs type="person">Dave Wark</rs>, <rs type="person">Daniele Cherniak</rs>, <rs type="person">John Hanchar</rs>, <rs type="person">Dan Moore</rs>, <rs type="person">Tobi Cohen</rs> and <rs type="person">Sumit Chakraborty</rs>. Formal reviews by <rs type="person">Don Baker</rs>, <rs type="person">Todd Dunn</rs> and <rs type="person">Youxue Zhang</rs> were extremely helpful in producing a more thorough and accurate final draft, and are greatly appreciated. Over the years, research on diffusion in melts at Rensselaer has been supported by the <rs type="funder">National Science Foundation</rs>, initially under grants <rs type="grantNumber">EAR78-12980</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">EAR80-25887</rs>, and most recently by <rs type="grantNumber">EAR-9105055</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_dmMZZvr">
					<idno type="grant-number">EAR78-12980</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_zEUhudP">
					<idno type="grant-number">EAR80-25887</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_MuwWkuz">
					<idno type="grant-number">EAR-9105055</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fusion kinetics, water pressure, water diffusion and electrical conductivity in melting rock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Arzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>interrelated</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of chlorine in granitic melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Koster Van Groos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geocbim Cosmocbim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical interdiffusion of dacite and rbyolite: anhydrous measurements at 1 atm and 10 kbar, application of transition state theory, and diffusion in zoned magma chambers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interdiffusion of hydrous dacitic and rhyolitic melts and the efficacy of rhyolite contamination of dacitic enclaves</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="473" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of F and CI on the interdiffusion of peralkaline intermediate and silicic melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="316" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The combined effect of F and H 2 0 on interdiffusion between peralkaline dacitic and rhyolitic melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Boss&amp;nyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of major and trace elements in compositionally complex CI-and F-bearing silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Non-Cryst Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion rates of sulfur (S 6+ ) in hydrous silicic melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rutherford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans Am Geopbys Union</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">353</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An experimental investigation of the behavior of carbon dioxide in rhyolitic melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Blank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
			<pubPlace>Pasadena, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>California Institute of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of C0 2 in rhyolitic melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Blank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans Am Geophys Union</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">312</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MORB degassing: Bubble growth and ascent</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bottinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Javoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reference frames and diffusion coefficients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="954" to="983" />
			<date type="published" when="1928">1928. 1975</date>
			<publisher>Dover Publications</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York Brady JB</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Evolution of the Igneous Rocks</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Ar in rhyolite, albite, and orthoclase composition glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sci Leu</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sulfur speciation in hydrous experimental glasses of varying oxidation state: Results from measured wavelength shifts of sulfur X-rays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rutherford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="845" to="849" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Argon solubility and diffusion in silica glass: Implications for the solution behavior of molecular gases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geocbim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Noble gas solubilities in silicate melts and glasses: New experimental results for argon and the relationship between solubility and ionic porosity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5039" to="5051" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An experimental study of krypton diffusion and solubility in silicic glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rivers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Woolum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental study of diffusion processes in magmatic melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chekhmir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vernadskii Inst of Geochemistry and Analytical Chemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<pubPlace>Moscow, USSR</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Physical Chemistry of Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM Magmas (Advances in Physical Geochemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chekhmir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">'baum</forename><surname>Epel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mb</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Persikov ES, Epelljaum MB, Bukhtiyarov PG</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ll Perchuk</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="594" to="598" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1991. 1985</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York Chekhmir AS</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Geokhimiya</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use and limitation of the concept of an effective binary diffusion coefficient for multi-component diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mass Transport in Oxides</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Jb Wachtman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Franklin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>National Bureau of Standards Publication</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">296</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="84" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion, mobility and their interrelation through free energy in binary metallic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Diffusion: Mass Transfer in Fluid Systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York Darken LS</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1948">1975. 1984. 1948</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">175</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="201" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Mathematics of Diffusion (2nd edn)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ion microprobe studies of water in silicate melts: concentration-dependent diffusion in obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Karsten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sei Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of water and fluorine on the viscosity of albite melt at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dingwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sei Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical diffusion of fluorine in jadeite melt at high pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dingwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scarfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2517" to="2525" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical diffusion of fluorine in melts in the system Na20-Al203-Si0 2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dingwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scarfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sei Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="384" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical diffusion of ferrous iron in a peraluminous sodium aluminosilicate melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Doremus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Glass Science</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York Doremus RH; New York Dunn JT, Ratliffe WA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley Interscience</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969. 1994. 1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">673</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J Geophys Res</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the stability of gas bubbles in liquid-gas solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Epstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Plesset</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Chem Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1505" to="1509" />
			<date type="published" when="1950">1950</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The nucleation and growth of alkali feldspars from hydrous melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fenn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Can Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The speciation of carbon dioxide in sodium aluminosilicate glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dissolved carbon dioxide in basaltic glasses: concentration and speciation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sei Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The solubility of carbon dioxide in rhyolitic melts: a quantitative FTIR study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rutherford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1311" to="1326" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydration rate of obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="347" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of pressure on electrolytic conduction in alkali silicate glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Austral J Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetics of zircon dissolution and zirconium diffusion in granitic melts of variable water content</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The behavior of apatite during crustal anatexis: equilibrium and kinetic considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1467" to="1477" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion compensation in natural silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Bishop Tuff: Evidence for the origin of compositional zonation in silicic magma chambers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hildreth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geol Soc Am Spec Paper</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Experimental studies on noble gas diffusion in basalt glass and partition between basalt melt and olivine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hiyagon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Tokyo</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Ca, Sr, Ba, and Co in a basalt melt: Implications for the geochemistry of the mantle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Geophys Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5432" to="5440" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of water in a granitic melt: An experimental study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carnegie Inst Wash Yearbook</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="352" to="355" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Données préliminaires sur la diffusion dans les magmas hydratés: le césium dans un liquide granitique à 3 kbar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Delbove</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Compt Rendu Paris D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">287</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Etude expérimentale de la diffusion des éléments alcalins K, Rb, Cs, dans une obsidienne granitique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Compt Rendu Paris D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3069" to="3072" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Helium diffusion and solubility in obsidians and basaltic glass in the range 200°-300°C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Shelby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sei Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="206" to="214" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental dehydration of natural obsidian and estimation of Dh 2 0 at low water contents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2931" to="2935" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in liquid slags</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ironmaking and Steelmaking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ion microprobe studies of water in silicate melts: Temperature-dependent water diffusion in obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Karsten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sei Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="420" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Brought to you by | provisional account Unauthenticated Download Date | 1/6/20 3:23 PM</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicomponent diffusion in Mg0-Al 2 0 3 -SiC&gt;2 and Ca0-Mg0-Al 2 0 3 -Si0 2 melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kress</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ghiorso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4453" to="4466" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicomponent diffusion in basaltic melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kress</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gbiorso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of H 2 0 and D 2 0 in obsidian at elevated temperatures and pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lapham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Way</forename><surname>Hollo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Non-Cryst Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a master equation in crystal growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lasaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">282</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1264" to="1288" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetics of Sr and Nd exchange in silicate liquids: Theory, experiments, and applications to uphill diffusion, isotopic equilibration, and irreversible mixing of magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Geophys Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9585" to="9604" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The behavior of noble gases in silicate liquids: Solution, diffusion, bubbles and surface effects, with applications to natural samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1549" to="1560" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Initial melting at grain boundaries of quartz and feldspar in gneisses and granulites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jr ; Jersey</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mehnert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Busch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Diffusion Kinetics for Atoms in Crystals. Van Nostrand Co</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton, New</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968. 1973</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="183" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theories and problems of liquid diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Onsager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann NY Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="1945">1945</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monazite solubility and dissolution kinetics: Implications for the thorium and light rare earth chemistry of felsic magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Rapp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="304" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rare gases in tektites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method for determining activity-composition relations using chemical diffusion in silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2019" to="2032" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">0bsidian-H 2 0 viscosities at 1000 and 2000 bars in the temperature range 700 to 900</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C. J Geophys Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6337" to="6343" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of H 2 0 in granitic liquids: Part I. Experimental data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Geochemical Transport and Kinetics</title>
		<title level="s">Carnegie Inst Wash Publ</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><surname>Aw Hofinann</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">634</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="154" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in Solids (2nd edn)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shewmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Minerals, Metals and Materials Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<pubPlace>Warrendale, Pennsylvania</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mathematical analysis of solute redistribution during solidification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tiller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Can J Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="744" />
			<date type="published" when="1955">1955</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dynamics of bubble formation and growth in magmas: A review and analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rsj</forename><surname>Sparks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Volcanol Geothenn Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isotopic effect on water diffusivity in silicic melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Stanton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hervig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans Am Geophys Union</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1131</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Speciation of water in silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2609" to="2620" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring the multicomponent diffusion matrix: Experimental design and data analysis for silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Trial</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium diffusion in a simple silicate melt to 30 kbar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of cesium ions in H 2 0-saturated granitic melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">205</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1259" to="1260" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in magmas at depth in the Earth: the effects of pressure and dissolved H2O</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sci Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basalt contamination by continental crust: some experiments and models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of dissolved C0 2 and CI in hydrous silicic to intermediate magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1897" to="1902" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">diffusion of cesium, samarium, strontium, and chlorine in molten silicate at high temperatures and pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bender</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geol Soc Am Abstr Progr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">545</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of dissolved carbonate in magmas: Experimental results and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sneeringer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ross</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sci Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Initial report on sulfur diffusion in magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Delano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EOS Trans Am Geophys Union</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">620</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extreme halogen abundances in tin-rich magma of the Taylor Creek rhyolite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Webster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Duffield</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econ Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<pubPlace>New Mexico</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A modified effective binary diffusion model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Geophys Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11901" to="11920" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Water diffusion in basaltic melL</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">351</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of water in rbyolitic glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wasserburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="456" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
