<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">High temperature strength of refractory complex concentrated alloys</title>
				<funder ref="#_wCHTzxV">
					<orgName type="full">United States Air Force</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">UES, Inc.</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2019-06-20">20 June 2019</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Materials and Manufacturing Directorate</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Air Force Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Wright-Patterson Air Force Base</addrLine>
									<postCode>45433</postCode>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gorsse</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 5026</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Univ. Bordeaux CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Bordeaux INP</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">ICMCB</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-33600</postCode>
									<settlement>Pessac</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Materials and Manufacturing Directorate</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Air Force Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Wright-Patterson Air Force Base</addrLine>
									<postCode>45433</postCode>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">High temperature strength of refractory complex concentrated alloys</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2019-06-20">20 June 2019</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">85FDECFE80A5271BB4B05BD9D4B79600</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.actamat.2019.06.032</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 8 May 2019 Received in revised form 17 June 2019 Accepted 18 June 2019</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Refractory alloys Mechanical properties High temperature strength CALPHAD High entropy alloys</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Thermodynamic and mechanical properties of 15 single-phase and 11 multi-phase refractory complex concentrated alloys (RCCAs) are reported. Using the CALPHAD approach, phase diagrams for these alloys are calculated to identify the solidus (melting, T m ) temperatures and volume fractions of secondary phases. Correlations were identified between the strength drops at 1000 C and 1200 C and the alloy compositions, room temperature properties, melting temperatures and volume fractions of secondary phases. The influence of alloy density on the temperature dependence of specific yield strength was also explored. The conducted analysis suggests that the loss of high-temperature strength of single-phase BCC RCCAs is related to the activation of diffusion-controlled deformation mechanisms, which occurs at T ! 0.6 T m , so that the alloys with higher T m retain their strength to higher temperatures. On the other hand, a rapid decrease in strength of multi-phase RCCAs with increasing temperature above 1000 C is probably due to dissolution of secondary phases.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Refractory complex concentrated alloys (RCCAs) have recently brought much attention as promising candidates for hightemperature structural applications, beyond Ni-based superalloys <ref type="bibr">[1e3]</ref>. An RCCA, which is also called refractory multi-principal element alloy (RMPEA), consists of three or more principal elements and it may also contain non-principal elements, which are generally added to further improve/optimize properties of the principal composition. Refractory high entropy alloys (RHEAs), which, by definition, contain five or more principal elements with concentrations of each principal element between 5 and 35 at%, are a sub-class of RCCAs. While RHEAs, because of their high configurational entropy, are sometimes considered to be single-phase, disordered solid solution alloys, RCCAs expand this vast range of new alloys by including multi-phase alloys. RHEAs were first introduced in 2010 <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and immediately attracted attention due to their ability to retain high strength at temperatures beyond 1000 C, and in some cases up to 1600 C <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. In the following years the number of newly reported RCCAs has increased steadily, exceeding 180 by the end of 2018. An extensive review of these alloys and their properties has recently been given <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>.</p><p>It is well known that metallic alloys generally show a considerable decrease in strength at temperatures above about 0.6T m , where T m is the absolute melting point. Increasing T m may therefore increase the maximum operating temperature. Thus refractory metals and alloys with extremely high melting points can be potential candidates for applications at temperatures significantly above Ni-based superalloys. High brittle-to-ductile transition temperature, inferior oxidation resistance and high density limit the applications of many conventional refractory alloys based on a single element. The RCCA concept provides much higher flexibility for the selection of alloy compositions for improved properties. In particular, RCCAs with reduced densities (down to 5.5 g/cm 3 ), considerably improved oxidation resistance and improved room temperature ductility and processability have been identified <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>More than half of the reported RCCAs are single-phase BCC structures. The matrix phase of multi-phase RCCAs has a BCC or B2 crystal structure and the secondary phases are primarily BCC, B2, Laves, silicides or their combination <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Due to the large variations in the compositions, phase content, microstructures and preparation/processing methods, reported RCCAs show quite a large range of mechanical properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>. For example, the yield strengths of reported RCCAs fall in the range of 400 MPae2612 MPa at 25 C, 40 MPae935 MPa at 1000 C and 24 MPae979 MPa at 1200 C <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Multi-phase RCCAs are generally stronger at room temperature (RT) but they lose their strength more rapidly with increasing temperature as compared to single-phase RCCAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. As a result, single-phase RCCAs become stronger than many multi-phase RCCAs at T ! 1000 C. For each of these two alloy categories, the temperature-dependent drops in strength are also composition/ microstructure dependent.</p><p>The reasons for such behaviors are currently not identified. The purpose of the present work is to evaluate the influence of alloy melting temperature and the volume fraction of second phases on the temperature dependence of RCCA yield strength. To explore these effects, we analyze the behavior of 15 single-phase and 11 multi-phase RCCAs for which the mechanical properties at room temperature (RT), 1000 C and 1200 C have been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>. Using the CALPHAD approach, we calculate phase diagrams for these same alloys to identify the melting (T m ) temperatures, volume fractions of secondary phases and the solvus temperatures (T s ) at which the secondary phases dissolve in the multi-phase RCCAs studied here. We then explore correlations between the strength drops at 1000 C and 1200 C, the alloy compositions, melting temperatures and volume fractions of secondary phases and analyze the results. We also explore the influence of alloy density on the temperature dependence of specific yield strength. Finally, based on this analysis we make several conclusions, which may be useful for the future development of high-temperature RCCAs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methods</head><p>15 single-phase RCCAs and 11 multi-phase RCCAs, for which compression properties at RT, 1000 C and 1200 C have been reported in the open literature or acquired by the authors, have been selected for this study. These alloys are drawn from a palette of 12 elements (Al, Cr, Hf, Mo, Nb, Re, Si, Ta, Ti, V, W, and Zr). They were prepared by mixing and arc-melting high-purity elements followed by solidification on a copper hearth. The compositions of these alloys and their yield strength values are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Nine alloys were in the as-solidified (AC) condition and seventeen alloys were in the annealed (A) condition. For fourteen alloys, hot isostatic pressing (HIP) preceded the annealing step. In spite of different processing conditions, all the studied alloys had coarse-grained structure, with the average grain size exceeding 100 mm. At such large grain sizes the grain boundary effects on the yield strength and its temperature dependence are considered to be negligible in comparison with solid-solution and precipitation strengthening [8e10]. Therefore, grain boundary (Hall-Petch) strengthening is not discussed in this work.</p><p>Phase diagrams for the studied alloys were calculated using the CALPHAD approach. We used ThermoCalc software and the TCHEA3-2018 thermodynamic database developed by ThermoCalc <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref> and Pandat software (version 2018) and the PanNb2018a database developed by CompuTherm, LLC <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref> for the calculations. The TCHEA3-2018 database contains 26 elements (Al, B, C, Co, Cr, Cu, Fe, Hf, Ir, Mn, Mo, N, Nb, Ni, Re, Rh, Ru, Si, Sn, Ta, Ti, V, W, Y, Zn, and Zr). All binary systems and 25 ternary systems from the 12elements included in this study are assessed to their full range of composition in this database. The PanNb2018a database contains 13 elements (Al, Cr, Fe, Hf, Mo, Nb, Re, Si, Ta, Ti, V, W, and Zr) and 135 phases. It has complete thermodynamic descriptions for all the binary systems and 34 ternary systems, among which 21 are related to the alloy systems explored in this work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Calculation of phase diagrams of the studied alloys</head><p>The level of correctness of the phase diagram calculations and the respective thermodynamic properties directly depend on the level of development of the used thermodynamic database. The calculation for a given alloy is considered to be the most reliable if the database has complete thermodynamic descriptions for all binary and ternary systems included in that alloy <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Both the PanNb2018a and TCHEA3-2018 have complete descriptions of the binary systems, but only few of the ternary systems related to the . The credibility of CALPHAD calculations increases with an increase in the fractions of the fully assessed ternary (FAT) systems. FAT is calculated as the ratio of the number of fully assessed ternaries for a given alloy system to the total number of ternaries in that alloy system <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. FAT values for each of the studied alloys in the PanNb2018a and TCHEA3-2018 databases are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>. The PanNb2018a database has higher FAT values for 21 of the 26 studied alloys, while TCHEA3-2018 has higher credibility for only two alloys, AlCrMoTi and AlCrMoNbTi. Both databases have the same credibility for 3 alloys, AlMoNbTi, CrMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and MoNbTaW. Nevertheless, for completeness, both databases were used to calculate phase diagrams for all the studied alloys and the results are compared with the available experimental data. The calculated phase diagrams are given in Supplementary Materials. The calculated solidus (T m ) and solvus (T s ) temperatures, as well as solid phases at T m and a T s -phase, are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>. T s is identified as the highest phase transition temperature before melting, and the T s -phase is a phase which dissolves at T s upon heating. Analysis of the calculations show that, for the same alloy, the two databases calculate almost the same T m values, with the exception of three Si-containing alloys, for which T m TC values were considerably lower than T m Pan (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">1a</ref>). The superscripts 'TC' and 'Pan' indicate that the quantities were calculated using ThermoCalc or Pandat software, respectively. It is likely that the TC calculations for the Si-containing alloys are incorrect, because they predict melting of these alloys around 1200 C, while the experimental results revealed that these alloys were solid and showed rather high strength at 1200 C. With five exceptions, the Pan and TC calculations predict almost the same phases at T m , for each of the studied alloys (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>). However, the T s values calculated with PanNb2018a and TCHEA3-2018 are quite different (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">1b</ref>). In spite of this, both databases calculate the same T s -phases for each of the studied alloys, with only three exceptions (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>).  <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and as-cast HfMoNbTaTiZr <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, indirectly indicating that T s is low enough to restrict the phase transformation kinetically. As a result, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref> Fractions of the assessed ternary systems (FAT) in PanNb2018a (Pan) and TCHEA3-2018 (TC) databases for the studied alloys. Also shown for both databases are the solidus (T m ) and solvus (T s ) temperatures; the phases present at T m ; the phase related to T s ; and T m calculated using the rule of mixtures (ROM). Preferred calculated values are shown in bold font (see Sec.  TCHEA3-2018 data will be used for these two alloys. Second, Pan-Nb2018a predicts two BCC phases in HfMoTaTiZr after solidification, which disagrees with the experiment. On the other hand, TCHEA3-2018 predicts one BCC phase at T m and the second BCC phase forms in equilibrium conditions below T s ¼ 1168 C. Therefore, the results from TCHEA3-2018 calculations will be used for HfMoTaTiZr. Finally, MoNbTaTiW has been found experimentally to be a single-phase BCC structure both in the as-cast condition and after annealing at 1200 C for 24 h <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, which agrees better with TCHEA3-2018 than with PanNb2018a calculations (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>).</p><p>3.1.1.2. Multi-phase RCCAs. Eight RCCAs that do not contain Si are reported to be multi-phase after annealing at 1200 C or 1400 C, and 3 Si-containing RCCAs are reported as multi-phase in the ascast condition (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). CALPHAD predictions of the type and number of phases in these alloys (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>) agree well with the experimental data. Both PanNb2018a and TCHEA3-2018 databases predict that 5 of these multi-phase RCCAs (AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr, CrMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr, HfMo 0.5 NbSi 0.3 TiV 0.5 , HfMo 0.5 NbSi 0.5 TiV 0.5 and HfMo 0.5 NbSi 0.7 TiV 0.5 ) are not single-phase above T s and retain a multi-phase structure up to T m . The other 6 RCCAs have a singlephase BCC region above T s ; e.g. Al 0.24 NbTiZr, MoNbTiVZr and NbTaTiVZr have T s below 1200 C, according to both databases, and thus they can be considered as single-phase structures when tested above T s .  </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">T ROM m ¼ X c i T mi<label>(1)</label></formula><p>Here c i is the atomic fraction and T mi is the melting temperature of element i. It is found that T m ROM is higher than T m CALPHAD for almost all the alloys. The difference is generally larger for alloys with lower T m , i.e. for alloys containing Al and Cr, as well as for multi-phase alloys (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>). Thus, the ROM overestimates T m for the studied RCCAs. Such behavior can be expected because ROM predicts a straight solidus line between any two melting points, while in the solid-solution based alloy systems, with no high-temperature compounds, the solidus line always deviates from a straight line towards lower temperatures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Effect of the melting temperature on the strength of RCCAs</head><p>It can be seen from the CALPHAD calculations (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>) that the multi-phase RCCAs have relatively low T m , often considerably lower than single-phase RCCAs. Indeed, T m of the reported multi-phase  RCCAs varies from 1397 C for CrMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr to 1780 C for AlCrMoNbTi, while T m of the reported single-phase RCCAs varies from 1632 C for Al 0.4 Hf 0.6 NbTaTiZr to 2804 C for MoNbTaW. Only two single-phase alloys have T m below 1700 C, while only two multi-phase alloys have T m above 1700 C. The lower melting temperatures can limit operating temperatures of the multi-phase RCCAs relative the single-phase RCCAs. The behavior of these two categories of RCCAs at different temperatures is described in detail in the following sections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1.">Room temperature (RT) behavior</head><p>There is no clear correlation between T m and the yield strength of RCCAs at 25 C (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3a</ref>). Single-phase alloys have RT yield strength , where c i and r i are the mole fraction and atomic radius of an alloying element i, respectively, and r ¼ P c i r i . It can be seen that the single-phase RCCAs have d r &lt; 7.5% and there is no clear correlation between s 0.2 25 C and d r for these alloys.</p><p>The multi-phase RCCAs have d r from 5.3 to 10.2% and there is a tendency for the alloys containing the Laves and silicide phases to increase s 0.2 25 C with increasing d r . Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3c</ref> shows the dependence of s 0.2 25 C on the experimentally reported volume fraction of all of the secondary phases, V, in multi-phase alloys. There is a clear tendency for s 0.2 25 C to increase with an increase in the volume fraction of the secondary phases; however, the alloy chemical composition (i.e. atom interaction forces) is also important. For example, Al 0.24 Nb-TiVZr and MoNbTiVZr have almost the same volume fraction (36% and 35%, respectively) of the secondary Laves phase; however s 0.2</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="25">C</head><p>of the first alloy is 1240 MPa and the second alloy is 1706 MPa. This analysis indicates that the higher RT strengths of the multi-phase alloys are likely a result of additional strengthening from the multi-phase microstructures and increasing volume fraction of the secondary phases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2.">Behavior of RCCAs at 1000 C</head><p>According to CALPHAD calculations and their comparison with the experimental data, the single-phase BCC RCCAs are metastable supersaturated solid solutions at room temperature. Therefore, during heating and holding at a testing temperature (1000 C) they may experience phase transformations and become multi-phase structures. The diffusion processes required to initiate the phase transformations generally become noticeable at temperatures T &gt; 0.4T m , where T m is the absolute melting temperature, while at T &lt; 0.4T m the phase transformations are kinetically restricted <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>.  <ref type="figure">4a</ref>, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). A former multi-phase Al 0.24 NbTiVZr, which contains a Laves phase at room temperature and has s 0.2 25 C ¼ 1240 MPa, becomes a single-phase BCC structure with the lowest strength (s 0.2 1000 C ¼ 82 MPa) at 1000 C among all the reported RCCAs, probably due to its relatively low T m ¼ 1545 C (Fig. <ref type="figure">4a</ref>). On the other hand, MoNbTiVZr also becomes single-phase at 1000 C but it has a T m of ~100 C higher than the former alloy and retains a relatively high strength of s 0.2 1000 C ¼ 467 MPa at 1000 C. The behaviors of these two alloys are in line with the behavior of singlephase RCCAs (Fig. <ref type="figure">4a</ref>). , strongly depends on the type of alloy. For the single-phase RCCAs, h 1 is the lowest (¼0.07) for the Al 0.24 NbTiVZr, which has the lowest T m ¼ 1545 C. The ratio tends to increase with increasing T m and approaches   <ref type="figure">5a</ref> and<ref type="figure">b</ref>).</p><p>These results clearly show that the drop in strength between 25 C and 1000 C is more dramatic for single-phase RCCAs with lower T m and for multi-phase RCCAs with a stronger temperature dependence of the volume fraction of secondary phases. Singlephase RCCAs with T m &gt; 2000 C, or multi-phase RCCAs with T s &gt; 1100 C and the secondary-phase volume fraction !20% at 1000 C, have better ability to retain high strength at 1000 C.  creases with increasing T m . The 'anomalous' behavior of the stress ratio h 2 for the first group of the single-phase RCCAs can be explained if the presence of non-equilibrium secondary phases (BCC2 in the three Hf-containing and A15 in two Al-containing RCCAs), which precipitate during heating and holding at 1200 C, is assumed. Although T s for these alloys is smaller than the testing temperature (1200 C), the secondary phases may remain at 1200 C due to insufficient diffusion kinetics and cause additional strengthening. In this case, a higher volume fraction of a residual secondary phase is expected for an alloy with smaller DT ¼ (1200 C -T s ). Indeed, s 0.2 1200 C /s 0.2 1000 C increases with decreasing DT for these 5 RCCAs (Fig. <ref type="figure">6c</ref>).</p><p>The multi-phase RCCAs do not show any dependence of s 0.2 1200 C / s 0.2 1000 C on T m (Fig. <ref type="figure">6b</ref>). However, their strength drop relates directly to the decrease in the volume fraction of the secondary phases (Fig. <ref type="figure">6d</ref>).  <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref> who used atomistic simulations and the Suzuki model to calculate the yield strengths of 3 ternary and 9 quaternary BCC RCCAs. They showed that the solid solution strengthening of these alloys at temperatures where diffusion processes are not active, including room temperature, is likely controlled by the stacking fault energy fluctuations along screw dislocations rather than by the atomic radius or shear modulus misfits. These stacking fault energy fluctuations cause significant barriers for kink migration and for dragging edge dislocation dipoles produced by kink collisions along the screw dislocations. The solute-dislocation interaction energies are composition dependent, which explains large variations in the RT yield strengths for the single-phase RCCAs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3a</ref>). In addition to solid-solution strengthening, multi-phase RCCAs are also strengthened by secondary phases. As a result, s 0.2 25 C of multi-phase RCCAs tends to increase with increasing V, and alloys with V ! 40% are generally stronger than single-phase RCCAs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>Other strengthening mechanisms, such as grain boundary (Hall-Petch) or dislocation forest strengthening provide second-order effects on yield strength. All the studied alloys have coarsegrained structures, with the average grain size exceeding 100 mm. Taking a typical value of 400 MPa mm À0.5 for the Hall-Petch constant k s <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, the contribution of the grain size d to the yield strength is ~40 MPa or 28 MPa when d ¼ 100 mm or 200 mm, which is negligible compared to the reported yield strength values. Recent analysis of the Hall-Petch effect on a classical refractory HEA HfNbTaTiZr resulted in k s ¼ 270 MPa mm À0.5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. This value of the Hall-Petch constant gives even smaller strengthening contribution from grain boundaries, only 27 MPa at d ¼ 100 mm. The contribution to the yield strength from forest dislocations is also low (&lt;50 MPa) as the dislocation density in HIP þ A, A or AC conditions is low ( 10 12 m À2 ). Strong texture is generally formed after extensive deformation and it is not typical in cast and annealed alloys <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. Microsegregation may affect local microhardnes, but the macroscopic strength is generally unaffected. Thus, the strengths of the reported RCCAs are largely controlled by dislocation/solute and dislocation/precipitate interactions.</p><p>The solid solution strengthening model by Rao et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref> does not take into account diffusion effects and it agrees well with the experimental data only at relatively low temperatures, where diffusion-controlling deformation mechanisms can be ignored. Earlier analysis of the deformation behavior of a HfNbTaTiZr RCCA showed at least two strengthening mechanisms: (i) thermallyactivated, diffusionless dislocation glide (similar to that described above) at low temperatures and (ii) diffusion-controlled dislocation climb/glide at high temperatures <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. The diffusion-controlled regime generally occurs above ~0.5e0.6T m and can be distinguished from the low-temperature regime by a more rapid drop in strength with increasing temperature, because dislocations are able to move more easily around obstacles <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28]</ref>. To identify the location of this transition in the studied RCCAs, their log(s 0.2 ) values are plotted versus T/T m in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7a</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7b</ref> for the singlephase and multi-phase RCCAs, respectively. The strength data for additional temperatures, taken from Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> or obtained by the authors, are also shown for several alloys to better identify the transition. For comparison, curves are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7a</ref> for commercial alloys based on Mo (TZM) and Nb (C-103), and for pure tungsten.</p><p>Two temperature regions, with very different temperature dependence of the yield strength, are clearly seen. The transition from the low-temperature regime to the high-temperature regime is manifested by a stronger decrease in the yield strength with increasing temperature. All the single-phase RCCAs show the transition at almost the same homologous temperature of ~0.6 T m (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7a</ref>). In seven single-phase RCCAs, which have T m &lt; 2121 K (1848 C), this transition occurs below 1000 C. In four single-phase RCCAs, with T m between 2143 and 2393 K (1870 and 2120 C), it occurs between 1000 C and 1200 C. Only four remaining singlephase RCCAs (MoNbTaW, MoNbTaTiW, MoNbTaVW and MoN-bTaTiVW) for which T m ! 2455 K (2182 C) show transition to the diffusion-controlling regime at temperatures !1200 C. Since s 0.2 drops more quickly with increasing T/T m in the diffusion-controlled regime than in the glide-controlling regime, this explains why the single-phase RCCAs with higher T m are generally stronger at 1000 C and 1200 C. For comparison, the transition to the hightemperature regime in pure tungsten occurs at ~0.45 T m (1371 C) and in TZM and C-103 at ~0.55 T m (1300 C and 1090 C, respectively) and these conventional materials have noticeably lower strength than many studied RCCAs at equivalent T/T m (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7a</ref>). A clear advantage of the RCCAs relative to the conventional refractory alloys can be seen: RCCAs are stronger and they have higher hightemperature capability.</p><p>The strength of multi-phase RCCAs is mainly controlled by solidsolution, precipitation and dispersoid strengthening, with contributions from other strengthening mechanisms assessed to be small. The transition to the high-temperature, diffusion-controlled regime occurs in these alloys in a rather wide temperature interval of ~0.56e0.7 T m (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7b</ref>). Because the reported multi-phase RCCAs have relatively low T m , not exceeding 1780 C, the effect from solid solution strengthening is lost at temperatures considerably lower than in many single-phase RCCAs with higher T m . For example, 0.6 T m represents temperatures below 1000 C for all the studied multi-phase RCCAs. However, precipitation and dispersoid strengthening can be noticeable at temperatures as high as ~0.7T m for alloys that have T s ! 0.75 T m or which are multi-phase at T m . The high-temperature strength of these RCCAs is generally lost when the volume fraction of the secondary phases becomes less than ~20%. This analysis suggests that multi-phase RCCAs with high T s and T m would be better candidates for high-temperature applications (at T &lt; T s ) than single-phase RCCAs with the same T m .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Future development of high temperature RCCAs</head><p>In the process of improving the properties of RCCAs at high temperatures, two main strategies can be proposed from the above analysis. One strategy is to develop single-phase solid solution RCCAs with high melting temperatures. This approach is based on the observed tendency for the single-phase RCCAs (i) to increase their high-temperature strength with increasing T m and (ii) to have higher T m than multi-phase RCCAs. To explore the high T m singlephase strategy, the variation in T m values for the vast number of alloying possibilities is estimated using the rule of mixtures (ROM) corrected by an empirical relationship found between T m ROM and T m CALPHAD , i.e. T m ¼ 4ðT ROM m À 807Þ=3 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>). Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">8</ref> shows T m as a function of density for equimolar mixtures of 455 ternaries, 1372  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">7</ref>(a) for W <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> and for commercial refractory alloys TZM (a Mo-based alloy) <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> and C-103 (a Nb-based alloy) <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>.</p><p>quaternaries, 3003 quinaries and 5005 senaries combinations pulled from a panel of 15 elements including Al, Co, Cr, Fe, Hf, Mo, Nb, Ni, Re, Si, Ta, Ti, V, W and Zr. There are two main trends. One is an averaging trend on the barycenter of the scatterplot (r ¼ 9.6 g/ cm 3 and T m ¼ 1666 C) as the number of principal elements increases. The second is the increase of T m with increasing density. From the 9835 possible equimolar mixtures of principal elements, 1804 can potentially have T m above 2000 C. These 1804 high melting temperature alloys have densities in the range from 8 to 19 g/cm 3 with a mean value of 12.3 g/cm 3 . Thus, single-phase RCCAs with higher T m will also have higher alloy density.</p><p>Alloy density is an important material constant for alloys used in flight applications and alloys with high specific strength (high strength to density ratio) are preferable for reducing weight and fuel consumption and decreasing environmental pollution. Conventional refractory alloys have high density, generally noticeably higher than other structural metals, contributing to limited use in aerospace structures. On the other hand, recently developed RCCAs have a wide range of densities, varying from 5.6 to 14 g/cm 3 . Higher density single-phase RCCAs generally have higher T m ; thus, in accord to this work, they should be stronger at high temperatures. It would therefore be interesting to compare the high temperature strengths of RCCAs having different densities and to identify how alloy density affects the specific yield strength of RCCAs at different temperatures. /r decreases from 85 to 40 MPa cm 3 /g. One can see that high specific strength at 25 C and 1000 C is expected from medium density (~6.5e9 g/cm 3 ) RCCAs.</p><p>The behavior at 1200 C is dramatically different (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">9c</ref>). Here a clear tendency is seen for s 0.2 1200 C to increase with increasing r until a peak strength of 735 MPa is achieved at r ¼ 12.3 g/cm 3 for MoNbTaVW. The s 0.2 1200 C /r values for RCCAs with r ! 10 g/cm 3 are noticeably higher than for the lower density RCCAs at this temperature. This trend is likely related to the observation that singlephase RCCAs with the highest density (e.g. those containing W) also have the highest T m values and that s 0.2 1200 C increases with T m faster than the density (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>, Fig. <ref type="figure">6b</ref>).</p><p>The second design strategy for high temperature RCCAs relies on developing multi-phase RCCAs with both high T s and T m . This approach is based on the observation that below T s multi-phase RCCAs generally have higher strength than many single-phase RCCAs, even if their melting temperature is lower and T s /T m &gt; 0.6. The basic idea is to distribute a high volume fraction of a hard ordered phase, which provides the high temperature strength, in a soft disordered solid solution matrix, which provides the room temperature ductility. Exploring this concept is much more difficult than the previous because it requires prediction of the extent of the solvus in composition and temperature space. There is no simple relationship or correlation that can be used to estimate T s as a function of composition. Accurate thermodynamic descriptions of the Gibbs free energies are needed that are not being met for high order concentrated mixtures of refractory elements mainly because important intermetallic phases, e.g ordered bcc structures (B2, L2 1 and D0 3 ), have no models in refractory alloys. While thermodynamic databases are slowly being improved, innovative approaches should be explored to more rapidly overcome the limitations of current CALPHAD databases. To this respect, the diffusion of artificial intelligence (data-mining and machine learning) in the field of thermodynamic, metallurgy and alloy design represents a great opportunity to anticipate the stability of phases of interests in high dimensionality composition and temperature space, and point out where to focus experimental effort.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Summary and conclusions</head><p>The objective of the present work is to explore origins of the temperature dependent decrease in the yield strength of refractory complex concentrated alloys (RCCAs) at elevated temperatures. By combining exploration of the experimental data with computational thermodynamics, correlations are analyzed between compressive yield strengths and microstructure (single-phase alloys are compared with multi-phase alloys), alloy melting temperature (taken as the solidus temperature, T m ), solvus temperature (T s ) and volume fraction of secondary phases (V), and an atom misfit parameter (d r ).</p><p>The reported single-phase RCCAs show a wide spread in T m ranging from 1632 C for Al 0.4 Hf 0.6 NbTaTiZr to 2807 C for MoN-bTaW. The T m range of multi-phase RCCAs is much narrower, from 1397 C for CrMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr to 1780 C for AlCrMoNbTi. Formation of secondary phases during solidification is associated with lower T m values.</p><p>The RT strengths of single-phase and multi-phase RCCAs with volume fractions V of secondary phases less than 40%, are similar and in the range from 880 MPa to 1790 MPa. No clear relationship was found between s 0.2 25 C and T m or d r for these alloys. The s 0.2 25 C of multi-phase RCCAs tends to increase with increasing V, and alloys with V ! 40% are generally stronger than single-phase RCCAs.</p><p>Single-phase and multi-phase RCCAs have a similar spread in  The analysis of the temperature dependence of the yield strength suggests that solid-solution strengthening in single-phase BCC RCCAs changes from thermally activated dislocation glide below 0.5e0.6T m to diffusion-controlled dislocation climb at higher temperatures, which causes a rapid drop in the strength above ~0.6T m . Thus RCCAs with higher T m experience this drop at higher temperatures.</p><p>The strength of the multi-phase RCCAs is controlled by solidsolution, precipitation and dispersoid strengthening. As the reported multi-phase RCCAs have relatively low T m , not exceeding 1780 C, the effect from solid solution strengthening is lost at temperatures considerably smaller than for many single-phase RCCAs with higher T m . However, precipitation and dispersoid strengthening can be noticeable at temperatures as high as 0.7T m . The high-temperature strength of these RCCAs is generally lost when the volume fraction of the secondary phases becomes less than ~20%. This analysis suggests that multi-phase RCCAs with high T s and T m would be better candidates for high-temperature applications (at T &lt; T s ) than single-phase RCCAs with the same T m .</p><p>Single-phase RCCAs with higher T m generally have higher density. Fortunately, their high-temperature strength (at T ¼ 1200 C) has the tendency to increase with increasing T m faster than their density. Therefore, the specific strength of the single-phase RCCAs at 1200 C increases with increasing density or T m . It is likely that, in order to achieve high specific strength in extreme hightemperature applications, future alloys will have high density, exceeding 10 g/cm 3 . The conducted analysis suggests that the loss of hightemperature strength of single-phase BCC RCCAs is likely related to the activation of diffusion-controlled deformation mechanisms, which occurs at T ! 0.6 of the absolute melting temperature T m , and that alloys with higher T m retain their strength to higher temperatures. On the other hand, a rapid decrease in strength of multiphase RCCAs with increasing temperature above 1000 C is probably due to dissolution of secondary phases, which is controlled by the solvus temperature T s of the phase responsible for precipitation strengthening. The rapid strength drop of these multi-phase alloys above T s , where they become single-phase solid solutions, is related to their T m , similar to single-phase alloys.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>3.1.1). Alloy FAT Pan FAT TC T m , C Pan T m , C TC T m , C ROM Phases at T m Pan Phases at T m TC T S , C Pan T S , C TC T S -phase Pan T S -phase TC</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>3. 1 . 1 . 3 .</head><label>113</label><figDesc>Selection of CALPHAD calculations for mechanical property analysis. In the analyses conducted in the following sections, CALPHAD calculations that best agree with the reported experimental data are used. When both PanNb2018a and TCHEA3-2018 calculations agree with the experimental results equally well, the calculations with higher FAT values are used. If FAT values are the same, TCHEA3-2018 calculations are used for the alloys which do not contain Nb. The T s and T m values and respective phases thus selected are highlighted by a bold font in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Comparison of (a) solidus (T m Pan , T m TC ) and (b) solvus (T s Pan , T s TC ) temperatures calculated with PanNb2018a (Pan) and TCHEA3-2018 (TC) thermodynamic databases.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,89.01,66.73,427.16,179.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Comparison of the CALPHAD-calculated solidus temperatures T m CALPHAD for the studied alloys with those calculated with the use of the rule of mixtures, T m ROM . The dashed line corresponds to the condition when T m ROM ¼ T m CALPHAD ; the solid line corresponds to the equation given in the figure.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,323.04,283.98,227.95,209.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>s 0. 2 25C</head><label>2</label><figDesc>in the range from 882 MPa for NbTa 0.3 TiZr (T m ¼ 1711 C) to 1841 MPa for Al 0.4 Hf 0.6 NbTaTiZr (T m ¼ 1632 C). The RT yield strength of MoNbTaW, which has the highest T m (¼ 2804 C), is 996 MPa. The multi-phase alloys have, on average, higher RT yield strength than the single-phase alloys (Fig. 3a). The s 0.2 25 C of these alloys is in the range from 1010 MPa for AlCrMoNbTi (T m ¼ 1780 C) to 2134 MPa for HfMo 0.5 NbSi 0.7 TiV 0.5 (T m ¼ 1642 C). Fig. 3b shows the dependence of s 0.2 25 C on the atomic radius misfit parameter, d r . By definition, d r ¼ 100% ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi P c i 1 À ri r 2 r</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Room temperature yield strength (s 0.2 25 C ) of single-phase (S) and multi-phase (M) RCCAs as a function of (a) the alloy melting temperature T m , (b) atomic radius misfit parameter d r , and (c) volume fraction (in percent) of the secondary phases. The type of the major secondary phase is shown in the legends.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,65.48,362.66,454.78,355.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 4b compares yield strength values at 1000 C and 25 C of the single-phase and multi-phase RCCAs with different melting temperatures. A strength drop occurs between these temperatures and the magnitude of the drop, h 1 ¼ s 0.2 1000 C /s 0.2 25 C</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 4 .Fig. 5 .</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. (a) Yield strength at 1000 C (s 0.2 1000 C ) and (b) yield strength ratio (s 0.2 1000 C /s 0.2 25 C) of single-phase (S) and multi-phase (M) RCCAs as a function of the melting temperature T m .</figDesc><graphic coords="6,74.95,311.13,455.23,197.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>h 1 ¼</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 5 shows dependence of s 0.2 1000 C of the multi-phase alloys on (a) the volume fraction of the secondary phases V at 1000 C and (b) the temperature difference between the solvus, T s , and testing temperatures (DT ¼ T s -1000 C). It can be clearly seen from Fig. 5a that the different strength values of multi-phase alloys at 1000 C are due to the different volume fractions of the secondary phases. With the same type of secondary phase, s 0.2 1000 C increases with an increase in V. Because V generally decreases with increasing temperature and approaches zero at T ¼ T S , s 0.2 1000 C tends to increase with increasing T s (DT), Fig. 5b. Because different alloys have different dependence of V on DT, the relationship between s 0.2 1000 C</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>3. 2 . 3 .Fig. 6 .</head><label>236</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. (a) Yield strength at 1200 C (s 0.2 1200 C ) and (bed) yield strength ratio (s 0.2 1200 C /s 0.2 1000 C ) of single-phase (S) and multi-phase (M) RCCAs as a function of (b) the melting temperature T m or (c) the difference between testing (1473 K) and equilibrium solvus (T s ) temperatures (for five single-phase alloys showing 'anomalous' dependence on T m ) normalized by T m or (d) the volume fraction ratio (V 1200 C /V 1000 C ) of the secondary phases in multi-phase RCCAs. The bubble in (a) represents the three off-trend alloys, i.e. HfNbTaTiZr, AlCrMoTi and HfMo 0.5 NbTiV 0.5 . The bubble in (b) shows the five reverse-trend alloys, i.e. AlMoNbTi and HfMoNbTiZr in addition to the three previous ones in (a).</figDesc><graphic coords="7,65.48,310.85,454.78,390.33" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>less than 100 MPa, which is typical for alloys with T m &lt; 1750 C. The overall trend of s 0.2 1200 C with T m can be described by a band:s 0.2 1200 C ¼ 0.625(T m e T B )<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.where T B is in the range from 1100 C to 1700 C (Fig.6a).The s 0.2 1200 C values of the multi-phase RCCAs are similar to those of the single-phase RCCAs with the same (low) T m values (Fig.6a). Therefore, multi-phase RCCAs have considerably lower strength than many single-phase RCCAs with higher T m . Softening behavior in the temperature range between 1000 C and 1200 C of the studied RCCAs with different T m values is shown in Fig.6b. There are two groups of single-phase RCCAs with different dependence of the strength drop h 2 ¼ s 0T m . In the first group, which includes AlMoNbTi, HfNbTaTiZr, HfMoNbTiZr, AlCrMoTi and HfMo 0.5 NbTiV 0.5 , h 2 decreases (from 0.372 to 0.163) with increasing T m (from 1711 C to 1987 C). In the second group, which includes all other single-phase RCCAs, h 2 in-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>4. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Influence of the T m on the temperature dependence of RCCA yield strength Both the CALPHAD calculations and ROM analysis show that the reported single-phase RCCAs have a wide spread in T m ranging, according to CALPHAD, from 1632 C for Al 0.4 Hf 0.6 NbTaTiZr to 2807 C for MoNbTaW. The T m range of the reported multi-phase RCCAs is much narrower, from 1397 C for CrMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr to 1780 C for AlCrMoNbTi. Formation of secondary phases during solidification is associated with considerably lower T m values. Single-phase RCCAs show RT yield strength values, s 0.2 25 C , in the range from 880 MPa to 1790 MPa. No clear relationship is found between s 0.2 25 C and T m or d r for the reported RCCAs. This agrees with recent work by Rao et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Plots of log (s 0.2 ) vs T/T m for (a) RCCAs reported to be single-phase BCC at 25 C and (b) RCCAs reported to be multi-phase at 25 C. For comparison, curves are shown in Fig.7(a) for W<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> and for commercial refractory alloys TZM (a Mo-based alloy)<ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> and C-103 (a Nb-based alloy)<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,108.00,66.73,369.83,457.17" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 9a shows</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 9a shows s 0.2 at 25 C of single-phase and multi-phase RCCAs as a function of alloy density. Only single-phase alloys have densities of 10 g/cm 3 or higher. The peak s 0.2 25 C values, exceeding 2000 MPa, are reported for multi-phase RCCAs having densities of ~7e8 g/cm 3 s 0.2 25 C decreases rapidly with decreasing r below 7 g/cm 3 or with increasing r above 8 g/cm 3 , approaching s 0.2 25 C e1000 MPa for both low-density (~6 g/cm 3 ) and high density (~14 g/cm 3 ) RCCAs. The specific yield strength, s 0.2 25 C /r, is in the range from ~150 to 280 MPa cm 3 /g for low-density (&lt;8 g/cm 3 ) RCCAs and it decreases almost linearly to s 0.2 25 C /r ¼ 70 MPa cm 3 /g</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Contour lines bounding the melting temperature as a function of density for all possible equimolar combinations of 3, 4, 5 and 6 elements from a palette of 15 elements including Al, Co, Cr, Fe, Hf, Mo, Nb, Ni, Re, Si, Ta, Ti, V, W and Zr. The averaging effect of increasing the number of principal elements shrinks the ranges in densities and melting temperatures toward r ¼ 9.6 g/cm 3 and T m ¼ 1666 C (black dot).</figDesc><graphic coords="10,54.09,66.73,227.95,185.73" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>s 0. 2 ,</head><label>2</label><figDesc>from 80 MPa to 855 MPa, at 1000 C. s 0.2 1000 C of single-phase RCCAs has a tendency to increase with increasing T m . s 0.2 1000 C of the multi-phase RCCAs shows no dependence on T m , but it depends on the type of secondary phase and increases with increasing total volume fraction of secondary phases. An increase in T s of the same type of the secondary phase beyond 1000 C increases s 0.2 1000 C . The drop in strength between 25 C and 1000 C is more dramatic for the single-phase RCCAs with lower T m and for multiphase RCCAs with low volume fraction (&lt;20%) of secondary phases. Single-phase RCCAs with T m &gt; 2000 C, or multi-phase RCCAs with T s &gt; 1100 C and V ! 20% at 1000 C, have better ability to retain high strength at 1000 C. There is a general trend for s 0are single-phase structures at 1200 C to increase with increasing T m. Multi-phase RCCAs have considerably lower s many single-phase RCCAs. Multi-phase RCCAs do not show any dependence of s 0.2 1200 C on T m . Their s 0.2 1200 C /s 0.2 1000 C ratio decreases with a decrease in the volume fraction of secondary phases.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. (a, b, c) Yield strength (s 0.2 ) of single-phase (S) and multi-phase (M) RCCAs at (a) 25 C, (b) 1000 C and (c) 1200 C as a function of alloy density. The dashed performance index lines give constant values of the yield strength to density ratio (specific yield strength). The arrow shows the increase in specific yield strength from the bottom-right to the top-left. The corresponding value of the specific yield strength is shown on the first performance line, and the increment of the specific yield strength between the nearest lines is shown on the second line. Materials with higher performance indeces have higher values of the specific yield strength.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,65.25,66.73,455.23,369.18" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Composition, processing condition, phase content, density and yield strength, determined at 23 C, 1000 C and 1200 C, of selected RCCAs. Data are taken from Ref.<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> and from the present work.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Alloy</cell><cell>Condition a</cell><cell>Phases</cell><cell>Density g/cm 3</cell><cell>YS at 23 C (MPa)</cell><cell>YS at 1000 C (MPa)</cell><cell>YS at 1200 C (MPa)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Reported single-phase alloys</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Al 0.4 Hf 0.6 NbTaTiZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>9.08</cell><cell>1841</cell><cell>298</cell><cell>89</cell></row><row><cell>AlCrMoTi</cell><cell>A</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>5.98</cell><cell>1100</cell><cell>375</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell>AlMoNbTi</cell><cell>A</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>6.46</cell><cell>1100</cell><cell>540</cell><cell>200</cell></row><row><cell>HfMo 0.5 NbTiV 0.5</cell><cell>AC</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>8.96</cell><cell>1260</cell><cell>368</cell><cell>60</cell></row><row><cell>HfMoNbTaTiZr</cell><cell>AC</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>9.93</cell><cell>1512</cell><cell>814</cell><cell>556</cell></row><row><cell>HfMoNbTiZr</cell><cell>AC</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>8.68</cell><cell>1575</cell><cell>635</cell><cell>187</cell></row><row><cell>HfMoTaTiZr</cell><cell>AC</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>10.18</cell><cell>1600</cell><cell>855</cell><cell>404</cell></row><row><cell>HfNbTaTiZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>9.89</cell><cell>929</cell><cell>295</cell><cell>92</cell></row><row><cell>MoNbTaTiVW</cell><cell>AC</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>10.91</cell><cell>1515</cell><cell>753</cell><cell>659</cell></row><row><cell>MoNbTaTiW</cell><cell>AC</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>11.72</cell><cell>1343</cell><cell>620</cell><cell>586</cell></row><row><cell>MoNbTaVW</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>12.29</cell><cell>1246</cell><cell>842</cell><cell>735</cell></row><row><cell>MoNbTaW</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>13.6</cell><cell>996</cell><cell>548</cell><cell>506</cell></row><row><cell>MoNbTi</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>7.67</cell><cell>1100</cell><cell>504</cell><cell>324</cell></row><row><cell>NbTa 0.3 TiZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>7.81</cell><cell>882</cell><cell>274</cell><cell>102</cell></row><row><cell>NbTiZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC</cell><cell>6.63</cell><cell>975</cell><cell>141</cell><cell>61</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Reported multi-phase alloys</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AlCrMoNbTi</cell><cell>A</cell><cell>BCC þ Laves</cell><cell>6.56</cell><cell>1010</cell><cell>550</cell><cell>105</cell></row><row><cell>Al 0.24 NbTiVZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC þ Laves</cell><cell>6.34</cell><cell>1240</cell><cell>82</cell><cell>24</cell></row><row><cell>AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>B 2 þBCC þ Al 4 Zr 5</cell><cell>7.14</cell><cell>2000</cell><cell>745</cell><cell>250</cell></row><row><cell>Cr 0.3 NbTiZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC þ Laves</cell><cell>6.56</cell><cell>1576</cell><cell>139</cell><cell>32</cell></row><row><cell>CrMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC þ BCC þ Laves</cell><cell>7.98</cell><cell>1595</cell><cell>546</cell><cell>170</cell></row><row><cell>HfMo 0.5 NbSi 0.3 TiV 0.5</cell><cell>AC</cell><cell>BCC þ M 5 Si 3</cell><cell>8.46</cell><cell>1617</cell><cell>398</cell><cell>166</cell></row><row><cell>HfMo 0.5 NbSi 0.5 TiV 0.5</cell><cell>AC</cell><cell>BCC þ M 5 Si 3</cell><cell>8.16</cell><cell>1787</cell><cell>614</cell><cell>188</cell></row><row><cell>HfMo 0.5 NbSi 0.7 TiV 0.5</cell><cell>AC</cell><cell>BCC þ M 5 Si 3</cell><cell>7.89</cell><cell>2134</cell><cell>673</cell><cell>235</cell></row><row><cell>MoNbTiVZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC þ Laves</cell><cell>7.27</cell><cell>1706</cell><cell>467</cell><cell>116</cell></row><row><cell>NbRe 0.3 TiZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC þ Laves</cell><cell>7.81</cell><cell>1244</cell><cell>323</cell><cell>89</cell></row><row><cell>NbTaTiVZr</cell><cell>HIP þ A</cell><cell>BCC þ BCC</cell><cell>8.43</cell><cell>1395</cell><cell>190</cell><cell>78</cell></row></table><note><p>a Hot isostatic pressing (HIP), Annealed (A), As-cast (AC).</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p><p><p><p><p>for each of the studied alloys. The superscript 'CALPHAD' or no superscript is used to indicate these preferred values in the remainder of this work.</p>3.1.2. Comparison of CALPHAD-calculated and rule-of-mixtures calculated T m</p>Fig.</p>2</p>compares T m CALPHAD values for the studied alloys with those calculated using rule of mixtures (ROM):</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>O.N. Senkov et al. / Acta Materialia 175 (2019) 394e405</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>Extensive discussions with <rs type="person">Drs. S.I. Rao</rs>, <rs type="person">C. Woodward</rs> and <rs type="person">J.-P. Couzinie</rs> are greatly appreciated. Work of <rs type="person">O.N. Senkov</rs> was supported through the <rs type="funder">United States Air Force</rs> on-site contract <rs type="grantNumber">FA8650-15-D-5230</rs> managed by <rs type="funder">UES, Inc.</rs>, Dayton, Ohio, <rs type="institution">USA</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_wCHTzxV">
					<idno type="grant-number">FA8650-15-D-5230</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A. Supplementary data</head><p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.actamat.2019.06.032.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chaput</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Couzinie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3092</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gorsse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">177</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gorsse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Couzini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B C R</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physique</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">721</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1758</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">698</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Couzini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dirras</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Data Brief</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1622</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gorsse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Data Brief</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2664</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cordero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Knight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schuh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. Mater. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">495</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ikeuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shibata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tsuji</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">201</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Tseng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloys Cmpds</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">795</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phase Equilibria Diffusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">353</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">279</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.computherm.com/index.php?route¼product/category&amp;path¼59_83" />
		<title level="m">CompuTherm for materials design. Database, Thermodynamics</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Kattner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phase Equilibria Diffusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Calphad Comput. Coupling Phase Diagrams Thermochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">32</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ber. Bunsenges. Phys. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">735</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3204</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gorsse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tancret</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2899</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gorsse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Entropy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">899</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2030</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Juan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-H</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-M</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-R</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-K</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">76</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">termetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">153</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Porter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Easterling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Phase Transformations in Metals and Alloys</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cheltenham, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Antillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Akdim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Parthasarathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N Scripta</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mater</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">165</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Akdim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Antillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Parthasarathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">222</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Meisenkothen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4062</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kuhlmann-Wilsdorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Caillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Thermally Activated Mechanisms in Crystal Plasticity</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lausanne, Switzeland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Engineering Properties of Tungsten and Tungsten Alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ogden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">DMIC Report</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
			<publisher>Battelle Memorial Institute</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Columbus, OH</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Molibdenum and Molibdenum Alloys</title>
		<ptr target="www.molybdenum.com" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chang</forename><surname>Ati Wah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.matweb.com/search/datasheet" />
		<title level="m">Nb Alloy C-103</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MatWeb. com</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7784150</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pilchak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Semiatin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metall. Mater. Trans. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2876</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
