<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and mechanical properties of in-situ MC-carbide particulates-reinforced refractory high-entropy Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi matrix alloy composite</title>
				<funder ref="#_cp2Y2FD #_jUFGMtk">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_ajfnWR2">
					<orgName type="full">Natural Science Foundation of China</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Key Laboratory for Precision Hot Processing of Metals</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150001</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Key Laboratory for Precision Hot Processing of Metals</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150001</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Key Laboratory for Precision Hot Processing of Metals</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150001</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Key Laboratory for Precision Hot Processing of Metals</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150001</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Key Laboratory for Precision Hot Processing of Metals</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150001</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Key Laboratory for Precision Hot Processing of Metals</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150001</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Key Laboratory for Precision Hot Processing of Metals</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150001</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">National Key Laboratory for Precision Hot Processing of Metals</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150001</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and mechanical properties of in-situ MC-carbide particulates-reinforced refractory high-entropy Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi matrix alloy composite</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">23DCBCADB94AC36307466D19C9DCF84A</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.intermet.2015.09.011</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 4 August 2015 Received in revised form 23 September 2015 Accepted 24 September 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>High entropy alloy In situ Casting (including segregation) Microstructure Mechanical testing</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Refractory high-entropy Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi alloy matrix composite with MC-carbide particulates-reinforced was prepared by arc melting. It is found that Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTiC 0.1 and Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTiC 0.3 alloys consist of one disordered body-centered cubic (BCC) solid solution phase as the matrix phase and MC carbide phase. MC carbide is enriched with Zr and Hf due to the higher binding strength and without any Mo. Noticeable strengthening from the carbide is not observed for C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys while the compressive plasticity is improved slightly due to the decrease of solution strengthening for the matrix BCC disordered solid solution phase.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Metal matrix composites containing carbide, nitride, boride as a rigid ceramic reinforcement are a unique class of engineering materials which combine the ductility and toughness of matrix alloys with the high strength and high modulus of the ceramic reinforcement <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. In all ceramic reinforcement, refractory carbide such as ZrC, HfC, NbC and TaC have recently drawn considerable attention in research since they show unique combination of properties such as high-melting temperature, high hardness, good high-temperature strength and good conductivity <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr">4]</ref>. Thus refractory carbides are usually as high-temperature structural materials in the form of hard constitutes in metal matrix composites.</p><p>In recent years, considerable research has been performed on high entropy alloys (HEAs) [5e7]. It was reported that HEAs have simple phase constitutes and exhibit excellent properties [8e10]. In all reported HEAs, refractory HEAs that are exclusively based on refractory metals have received great interest and been widely studied with the aim of increasing the mechanical properties at high temperature. They usually form a single disordered solid solution phase or the disordered solid solution phase is the dominant phase [10e17]. In this paper, the previous reported refractory HEAs of Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi is selected as the master alloy, which forms a single BCC phase and possesses a certain compressive plasticity (the compressive fracture strain is about 24.61%) <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. Carbon elements are added into this master alloy to prepare the refractory high-entropy alloy Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi matrix composites. The in situ MC-carbide ceramic particulates-reinforced refractory highentropy alloy Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi matrix composites are firstly prepared successfully.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental procedures</head><p>The samples of Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTiC x (x ¼ 0.1 and 0.3, denoted as C 0.1 and C 0.3 ) were prepared by arc melting the pure metals and carbon power under pure argon atmosphere in a water-cooled copper crucible. The carbon power was cladded using the aluminum foil to avoid being blown away. All samples were melted five times separately to ensure the chemical homogeneity. The crystal structure was investigated by X-ray diffraction (XRD) in a range of 2q ¼ 20e100 .The microstructure was studied using scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and transmission electron microscopy (TEM). The chemical compositions were analyzed by the SEM equipped with energy dispersive spectrometry (EDS). The mechanical properties were measured under compressive loading in an Instron 5569 testing machine at a constant strain rate of 1 Â 10 À3 s À1 at room temperature. The test specimens are in the shape of a cylinder (44 mm Â 6 mm).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head><p>The XRD patterns of the master alloy, C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. As reported in other paper, the master alloy Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi was composed of one disordered body-centered cubic (BCC) solid solution phases. C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys consist of predominant BCC phase (space group Im-3m ( <ref type="formula">229</ref>)) which match well with ZrTiNb (#65-7192) and some carbide which corresponds nicely to HfC (#65-8751, space group Fm-3m ( <ref type="formula">225</ref>)). The diffraction intensity of carbide increases with more addition of carbon which indicates more carbide forms. The lattice parameters of BCC phase in C 0.1 and C 0.3 are 337.05 pm and 335.92 pm, respectively and the lattice parameter of BCC phase in the master alloy Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi is 340.63 pm which indicates that the addition of carbon decreases the lattice parameter of BCC phase. This is attributed to carbon atoms occupy some metal atoms to form carbide and carbon atoms have different binding energy with five metals elements which causes the decrease of the configurational randomness of BCC phase (this will be verified by the following chemical compositions analysis) and thus decreases the degree of the lattice distortion.</p><p>Microstructure of C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The chemical compositions of Mo, Nb, Hf, Zr and Ti in different regions are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> since the measured value of carbon is not exact using EDS due to its light atomic weight. C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys exhibit dendritic structure and small amount of white precipitates distribute in the dendrites. However, only two phases of carbide and BCC are detected from the XRD patterns. The chemical The microstructure and crystallographic structure are also analyzed by TEM as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>. The precipitate (region B) distributes in the matrix (region A). The corresponding selected area electron diffraction patterns of A and B show that the matrix is a disordered BCC phase and the precipitate has a face-centered cubic (FCC) crystallographic structure. This result is consistent with the previous analysis. It can be concluded that C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys are composed of one disordered BCC phase and MC-typed carbide with FCC crystallographic structure enriched with Zr and Hf and containing small amount of Nb and Ti.   And the plasticity is also improved slightly The following possible reasons for the little change of the yield strength and the improvement of plasticity: the strengthening mechanism of the parent with single BCC phase is solution strengthening while the strengthening mechanism of C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys with BCC phase and carbide phase is solution strengthening and second-phase strengthening. The addition of carbon leads to the decrease of solution strengthening effect and produces second-phase strengthening. Carbon atoms occupy some metals atoms from the BCC phase to form carbide, which will decrease the degree of chemical compositions for the BCC solid solution phase. Thus the solution strengthening effect is reduced and the plasticity of the matrix BCC phase is improved. Work hardening arises from the interaction of dislocations with amongst themselves or with other defects such as second-phase particles. The higher work hardening rate of C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys is mainly attributed to the hardening from the carbide which will produce a turbulent and complex deformation pattern around them leading to the increase of the dislocation density.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p>In summary, carbon element with molar ratio of 0.1 and 0. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. XRD patterns of C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloy.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,49.83,66.73,236.60,169.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>shows the compressive stressestrain curves of master alloy, C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys. The yield strength, peak strength and fracture strain of C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloys are (1183 MPa, 2139 MPa,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. (a) TEM bright-field image of C 0.1 alloy, (b) and (c) are the corresponding selected area diffraction patterns of region A and B in (a).</figDesc><graphic coords="3,108.57,319.13,368.59,407.79" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>3 is added into refractory high entropy alloy Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi for preparing the in-situ MC-carbide ceramic particulates-reinforced Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi matrix composite by arc melting successfully. Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTiC 0.1 and Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTiC 0.3 alloys are composed of BCC solid solution phase and particulates-reinforced phase MC-carbide. MC carbide with FCC crystal structure is enriched with Zr and Hf and containing a small amount of Nb and Ti. Both the compressive strength and plasticity of Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTiC 0.1 and Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTiC 0.3 alloys are improved compared with the master alloy Mo 0.5 NbHf 0.5 ZrTi.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The chemical compositions (at.%) of C 0.1 and C 0.3 alloy.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Sample</cell><cell>Region</cell><cell>Mo</cell><cell>Nb</cell><cell>Hf</cell><cell>Zr</cell><cell>Ti</cell></row><row><cell>C 0.1</cell><cell>Average</cell><cell>11.26</cell><cell>24.77</cell><cell>14.82</cell><cell>24.20</cell><cell>24.94</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Dendrites</cell><cell>11.89</cell><cell>26.16</cell><cell>14.65</cell><cell>22.49</cell><cell>24.79</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Interdendrites</cell><cell>11.12</cell><cell>20.14</cell><cell>12.73</cell><cell>28.51</cell><cell>27.50</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>White precipitates</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5.68</cell><cell>39.26</cell><cell>46.93</cell><cell>8.16</cell></row><row><cell>C 0.3</cell><cell>Average</cell><cell>12.21</cell><cell>24.80</cell><cell>14.29</cell><cell>23.87</cell><cell>24.83</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Dendrites</cell><cell>14.09</cell><cell>32.10</cell><cell>10.80</cell><cell>17.48</cell><cell>25.47</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Interdendrites</cell><cell>8.44</cell><cell>15.32</cell><cell>17.47</cell><cell>39.02</cell><cell>19.78</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>White precipitates</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>8.68</cell><cell>33.23</cell><cell>48.07</cell><cell>10.02</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>We acknowledge financial support of 973 Project (<rs type="grantNumber">2011CB610406</rs>) and <rs type="funder">Natural Science Foundation of China</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">51425402</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">51371066</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_ajfnWR2">
					<idno type="grant-number">2011CB610406</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_cp2Y2FD">
					<idno type="grant-number">51425402</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_jUFGMtk">
					<idno type="grant-number">51371066</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure features of high-entropy equiatomic cast AlCrFeCoNiCu alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Ivchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Pushin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Uksusnikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wanderka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Met. Metallogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="514" to="e520" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and properties of high-entropy CoCr-CuFeNiSn x alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bashev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Kushnerov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Met. Metallogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="692" to="e696" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific segregation and compositional ordering in Ni-based ternary alloy nanoclusters computed by the free-energy concentration expansion method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rubinovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Polak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stabilization and transformation of asymmetric configurations in small-mismatch alloy nanoparticles: the role of coordination dependent energetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Polak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rubinovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1569" to="e1575" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Shun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tsau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Nanostructured high-entropy alloys with multiple principal elements: novel alloy design concepts and outcomes</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="e303" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructural development in equiatomic multicomponent alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cantor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">T H</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Knight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J B</forename><surname>Vincent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A Struct. Mater. Prop. Microstruct. Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">375</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="e218" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atomic-size effect and solid solubility of multicomponent alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scr. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progress in high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 1749e1750</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructures and properties of high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dahmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Mater. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="e93" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CALPHAD and the high entropy alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phase Equilib. Diff</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015) 1e2</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Refractory highentropy alloys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1758" to="e1765" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Intermetallics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low-density, refractory multi-principal element alloys of the CreNbeTieVeZr system: microstructure and phase analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1545" to="e1557" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental and theoretical study of Ti 20 Zr 20 Hf 20 Nb 20 X 20 (X ¼ V or Cr) refractory high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fazakas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Zadorozhnyy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Varga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Inoue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Louzguine-Luzgin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Vitos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Refract. Met. Hard Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="e138" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A refractory Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 high-entropy alloy with excellent structural stability and tensile properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Si</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="e280" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Search for high entropy alloys in the X-NbTaTiZr systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Poletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Szost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Battezzati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">; X ¼</forename><surname>Al</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Cr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Sn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloy Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">620</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="e288" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lilensten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Couzinie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Perriere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bourgon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Emery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Guillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">New structure in refractory high-entropy alloys</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="e125" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Corrosion and serration behaviors of TiZr 0.5 NbCr 0.5 V x Mo y high entropy alloys in aqueous environments</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="597" to="e608" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and properties of a refractory NbCrMo 0</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A Struct. Mater. Prop. Microstruct. Process</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="e320" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>5 Ta 0.5 TiZr alloy</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Compressive stressestrain curves of master alloy, C 0.1 and C 0</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>3 alloy</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
