<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneously increasing the strength and ductility of a refractory high-entropy alloy via grain refining</title>
				<funder ref="#_5YWqv6f">
					<orgName type="full">Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chien-Chang</forename><surname>Juan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30013</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ming-Hung</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Chung Hsing University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>40227</postCode>
									<settlement>Taichung</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Che-Wei</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30013</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wei-Lin</forename><surname>Hsu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30013</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chun-Ming</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Swe-Kai</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30013</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center for Nanotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Materials Science, and Microsystems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30013</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Su-Jien</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30013</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Jien-Wei</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
							<email>jwyeh@mx.nthu.edu.tw</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30013</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneously increasing the strength and ductility of a refractory high-entropy alloy via grain refining</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E0FD2077C1E7B21E2B32F5E1CCFA96BB</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.matlet.2016.08.060</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Refractory high-entropy alloys</term>
					<term>Metals and alloys</term>
					<term>Recrystallization</term>
					<term>solute-drag mechanism</term>
					<term>Hall-Petch equation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The HfNbTaTiZr refractory high-entropy alloy was investigated on the grain growth kinetics and tensile properties. Grain growth at 1200~1350 °C is rather slow.</p><p>The activation energy is 389 kJ/mol and the growth exponent is 3.5. The HfNbTaTiZr alloy has high strength, small work hardening and high ductility. Grain refining is found to enhance the tensile strength and ductility simultaneously.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>A new alloy design strategy called high-entropy alloys (HEAs) has attracted significant attention in the past decade <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. A subclass of HEAs, the refractory HEAs, is also of great interest <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>. These alloys can have exceptional high-temperature strength and reasonable compressive plasticity. However, their tensile ductility at room temperature is a major concern. In this regard, the HfNbTaTiZr alloy is special because it has a very high compressive plasticity (ε ＞ 50%) at room temperature. Grain refining is considered as a route to improve the mechanical properties of metals and alloys <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Some literatures on CoCrFeMnNi high-entropy alloy with single FCC phase had revealed the grain growth mechanism and the grain size effect on mechanical properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>, and the grain refining effectively strengthens this alloy. However, it is rare to see the literature reporting the grain growth kinetics and grain refining effect on the HfNbTaTiZr equiatomic alloy with single BCC phase yet. The understanding of these two aspects is important especially in controlling grain structure and tensile properties for structural applications. Therefore, the present study is focusing on the grain growth kinetics and the grain-size dependence of tensile properties of HfNbTaTiZr alloy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental procedures</head><p>The HfNbTaTiZr HEA was prepared by vacuum-arc-melting of high-purity elements (99.9 wt.%). Melting was repeated for at least five times to improve the chemical homogeneity of the alloy. The ingots were cold-rolled by a reduction of 70%, then sealed in a vacuum quartz tube and heat-treated in an air furnace at 1200, 1250, 1300 and 1350 °C for different time. The samples were examined by an optical microscope (OM). The grain size was measured from micrographs by using the linear-intercept method. At least 100 grain boundaries were intercepted for the calculation. Crystal structures of the alloys were examined with an X-ray diffractometer (Shimadzu XRD-6000). The tensile-test samples had the dog-bone shape with the gage-section dimensions of 2 × 3 × 20 mm. Tensile tests were performed at an initial strain rate of 10 -3 by Instron 4468 universal testing machine.</p><p>An Instron extensometer was used to record the strain of each specimen during tensile test. At least two specimens were tested for each heat-treatment condition to confirm the reliable data. where D is the grain size at annealing time t, D 0 is the initial grain size, n is the growth exponent, and C is a kinetic constant. Because grain sizes are at least tens of micrometers after annealing, D 0 at recrystallization can be treated as zero. The growth exponent n is approximately 3.5. The plot of D 3.5 versus time is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1(c)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head><p>Well linear relationship is found. Factors such as texture and pinning effect by solutes and second phase particles are known to increase n. Because second phase particles are not observed in the grain boundaries of our alloys, pinning by particles is excluded, and the solute-drag effect becomes the most probable reason <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. Liu et al.</p><p>proposed this solute-drag mechanism in addition to sluggish diffusion effect for the slow grain growth phenomenon found in single-FCC CoCrFeMnNi <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. In the present study, we propose that the solute-drag effect is significant in the whole-solute matrix of HEAs as compared with conventional solid solution alloy. This relates to the energy reason that the different sizes of abundant solutes along grain boundaries would in-situ adjust their relative positions to form the low-energy configuration of grain boundaries during boundary migration.</p><p>The kinetic constant C in Eq. ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) could be expressed as Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">2</ref>):</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">0 exp Q CC RT     (<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">)</formula><p>where Q is the apparent activation energy of grain growth, R is the gas constant, T is the absolute temperature, and C 0 is a constant. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>(d) shows the ln C versus 1/T plot in which a good linear relationship is seen. The activation energy of grain growth is 389 kJ/mol. This value is markedly higher than the self-diffusion activation energies of Hf (162 kJ/mol), Ti (198 kJ/mol) and Zr (126 kJ/mol), and close to that of Nb (397 kJ/mol) and Ta (413 kJ/mol) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Although the diffusion coefficients and activation energies of diffusion for composing elements in the present alloy have not been reported, it is expected from the study on the diffusion of CoCrFeMnNi <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> that the activation energies of Nb and Ta diffusion in the present alloy is very likely higher than that for their self diffusions. It is noted that the activation energies of grain growth in HfNbTaTiZr and that of self-diffusion in Nb and Ta have similar values.</p><p>This suggests that the grain growth in HfNbTaTiZr is directly related to the volume diffusion through the lattice, whose rate is controlled by the slowest species, i.e. Nb and Ta. Migration of grain boundaries cannot proceed except the average composition is maintained, i.e., the fast-moving species need to wait for the slow ones.</p><p>To investigate the grain size strengthening and tensile behavior of the present HEA, annealed samples with average grain sizes: 38, 81, and 128 μm (named as:</p><p>Sample A, Sample B, and Sample C, respectively) were selected for tensile testing. are 974 ± 0.7, 959 ± 1.5, and 953 ± 0.7 MPa, respectively. The corresponding elongations (or engineering fracture strain) are 20%, 18%, and 15%, respectively. In addition, the true fracture strains estimated from the reduction of area are 1.23, 1.13, and 0.97, respectively. All these demonstrate that grain refining could simultaneously enhance strength and ductility, which is not commonly found in metals <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>It is noted that slight work softening occurs before necking in the engineering stress-strain curves but small work hardening still exists in the true stress-strain curves.</p><p>Small work hardening is proposed to be related to the high yield strength of HfNbTaTiZr, which is due to large solution hardening from its whole-solute matrix with severe lattice distortion. This is entirely different from the high work hardening found in lower strength FCC HEAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref> and might be an unique feature of BCC HEAs. Similar low work hardening is found in BCC metals at low temperatures where the yield strength becomes markedly higher <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Both might have similar basic reasons. Physically, low work hardening means high dynamic recovery which eliminates most hardening of increased dislocations due to the multiplication from dislocation sources. It is expected that higher dislocation density (e.g. at higher strain) and higher applied stress for deforming high strength alloys would have higher strain energy and thus larger driving force to induce dynamic recovery. The very low work hardening in the present alloy suggests that its distorted whole-solute BCC matrix having high-strength and large lattice strain could potentially raise the driving force to reduce overall strain energy under the high applied stress level (&gt; σ y ~ 1000 MPa).</p><p>This lattice distortion effect is significant since their atomic size difference is quite large (atomic sizes of Hf, Nb, Ta, Ti and Zr are 1.58, 1.47, 1.47, 1.46, and 1.60 Å, respectively, and maximum difference between unlike atomic pairs is up to 9.6 %). As for the enhancement of ductility and ultimate tensile strength by smaller grain size, it relates with Considere's criterion <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> which suggests that a higher work hardening rate would give higher necking strain and necking strength (ultimate tensile strength).</p><p>Apparently, the work hardening is higher for smaller grain size from true stress-strain curves in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>, the enhancement is thus explained.</p><p>In order to evaluate the relation between strength and grain size, the yield stress as functions of grain size was plotted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>(b). The fitting line agrees well with the Hall-Petch equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">1 2 0 kD    <label>(4)</label></formula><p>where σ 0 is the intrinsic stress, D is the grain size and k σ is the Hall-Petch coefficient.</p><p>The Hall-Petch coefficient k σ of yield stress are 240 MPa•μm -1/2 . This suggests that size strengthening is significant in the present alloy. Suppose the grain size is reduced to 1μm, the yield strength would become 1159 MPa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p>The grain growth kinetics and tensile properties in the HfNbTaTiZr BCC    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Highlights</head><p> The HfNbTaTiZr solid solution refractory alloy exhibits low rate and high activation energy of grain growth at 1200~1350 °C.</p><p> The slow grain boundary migration is proposed to be a result of the solute-drag mechanism.</p><p> Five componential atoms drag grain boundary and the slowest two components, Nb and Ta, explain the high activation energy and low rate of grain growth.</p><p> Grain refinement simultaneously increases tensile strength and ductility.</p><p> The alloy with a grain size of 38 μm has an excellent combination of tensile yield strength, 958 MPa, and ductility, 20%.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 (</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1(a) shows the X-ray diffraction patterns of the HfNbTaTiZr alloy in the as-cast, as-rolled, and as-annealed (1250 °C, 6 h) states. All diffraction patterns exhibit single BCC structure with a lattice constant of 3.406 Å. Figure 2 shows the OM images of samples annealed at 1250 °C for different times. Based on the OM images, the grains sizes of the samples are plotted as functions of annealing time for each annealing temperature in Figure 1(b). As can be expected, the grain size increases with the annealing time and temperature. The equation for grain growth can</figDesc><graphic coords="3,95.00,53.26,406.22,713.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 (</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3(a) shows their engineering and true stress-strain curves. All the samples have the same Young's modulus of 81 GPa. The yield strengths of Samples A, B, and C are 958 ± 2.1, 944 ± 2.1, and 940 ± 0.7 MPa, respectively. The ultimate tensile strengths</figDesc><graphic coords="5,95.00,53.26,406.22,713.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>refractory high-entropy alloy was investigated. The activation energy of grain growth at 1200 ~ 1350 °C is 389 kJ/mol, and the growth exponent is 3.5. The grain growth rate is controlled by the slowest two components, i.e., Nb and Ta. The slow grain boundary migration is a result of the solute-drag mechanism. Grain refinement increases both strength and ductility. The tensile yield strength, elongation and true fracture strain of HfNbTaTiZr HEA with smallest grain size 38 μm are 958 MPa, 20%, and 1.23, respectively. The grain size strengthening is significant and obeys the Hall-Petch relationship.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1 (</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 (a) XRD patterns of the as-cast, 70%-rolled, and as-annealed (1250°C-6h) states of the HfNbTaTiZr alloy, (b) grain sizes of the HfNbTaTiZr alloy annealed at 1200, 1250, 1300, and 1350 °C for different times, (c) plot of grain size 3.5 vs. time at different temperatures, and (d) plot of ln C vs. 1/T.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,95.00,53.26,406.22,713.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 OM images of the HfNbTaTiZr alloys annealed at 1250 °C for different times.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,156.67,321.39,283.38,214.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 3 (</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3 (a) True and engineering tensile stress-strain curves of HfNbTaTiZr alloy with different grain size, in which dashed lines connecting necking point (marked with ×) with fracture point are treated to be linear, (b) The yield stress as a function of grain size in the HfNbTaTiZr alloy.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,95.00,53.26,406.22,713.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>The authors are pleased to acknowledge the financial support by <rs type="funder">Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan</rs>, under Grant No. <rs type="grantNumber">MOST102-2221-E-007-047-MY3</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_5YWqv6f">
					<idno type="grant-number">MOST102-2221-E-007-047-MY3</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Jom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1759" to="1771" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Res Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dahmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog Mater Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Murty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ranganathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>High-Entropy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Alloys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Butterworth-Heinemann</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Alloy Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">509</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6043" to="6048" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dieter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Metallurgy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="191" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scr Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="526" to="529" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Otto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dlouhy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Somsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Eggeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5743" to="5755" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Recrystallization and Related Annealing Phenomena. 2nd ed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Humphreys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hatherly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">338</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Grey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Higgins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Metall</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="321" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-diffusion and Impurity Diffusion in Pure Metals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tuijn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Experimental Data</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>First ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4887" to="4897" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83525</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Reed-Hill Re</forename><surname>Abbaschain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Physical Metallurgy Principles. 3</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>PWS-KENT</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="840" to="844" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>rd ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dieter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Metallurgy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="292" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
