<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Structure and mechanical properties of a light-weight AlNbTiV high entropy alloy</title>
				<funder ref="#_9FXPYrk">
					<orgName type="full">Russian Scientific Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-12-09">9 December 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Bulk Nanostructured Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Belgorod State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>308015</postCode>
									<settlement>Belgorod</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shaysultanov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Bulk Nanostructured Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Belgorod State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>308015</postCode>
									<settlement>Belgorod</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Bulk Nanostructured Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Belgorod State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>308015</postCode>
									<settlement>Belgorod</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">National Science Center &quot;Kharkov Institute of Physics and Technology&quot; NAS of Ukraine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>61108</postCode>
									<settlement>Kharkov</settlement>
									<country key="UA">Ukraine</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Structure and mechanical properties of a light-weight AlNbTiV high entropy alloy</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-12-09">9 December 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A277198AF41D81D733312EDE798B12A2</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.matlet.2014.11.162</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 29 October 2014 Accepted 30 November 2014</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>High entropy alloy Metals and alloys Crystal structure Mechanical properties</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The crystal structure, microstructure, density, microhardness and mechanical properties of new AlNbTiV high entropy alloy were examined. The alloy had coarse-grained single bcc phase structure with density of 5.59 g cm À 3 and hardness of 4315-4394 MPa. The compressive yield strength of the alloy gradually decreased from 1020 MPa at room temperature to 685 MPa at 800 1C, and then dropped to 158 MPa at 1000 1C. Specific yield strength of the alloy was found to be comparable with strength of multiphase refractory high entropy alloys. Effect of chemical composition on mechanical properties and potential ways to optimize composition are discussed.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The so-called high entropy alloys (HEAs) is a new emerging class of metallic alloys which are frequently considered as potential structural materials for high-temperature applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. In order to fully utilize potential of HEAs as high-temperature material, Senkov et al. has introduced refractory HEAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Several refractory HEAs compositions have demonstrated remarkable compressive strength at elevated temperatures <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref> but had large density of more than E10 g cm À 3 . The alloys of Cr-Nb-Ti-V-Zr system with lower density of E6.5 g cm À 3 and attractive mechanical properties were introduced in order to provide lighter materials <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>. Addition of Al as an alloying element has the potential to further decrease density of alloys <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>; however Al tends to form intermetallic compounds with constitutive elements of the Cr-Nb-Ti-V-Zr system. On the other hand, Al has similar atomic radii (143 pm) to those of Ti, Nb and V, which is expected to simulate formation of solid solutions in HEAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Formation of either solutions solutions or intermetallics will significantly affect mechanical properties of alloys. In current work we report microstructure, density, and mechanical properties of novel, presumably light-weight AlNbTiV alloy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental procedures</head><p>The alloy with nominal composition of AlNbTiV was produced by arc melting of the high-purity (Z99.9 (at)%) elements in a argon atmosphere inside a water-cooled copper cavity. Produced ingot with dimensions of E6 Â 15 Â 60 mm 3 was re-melted 5 times. The exact chemical composition of the alloy was 26.6 (at)%Al-23.8%Nb-25.1%Ti-24.5%V. After casting the alloy was homogenized at 1200 1C for 24 h in vacuumed (10 À 2 Torr) quartz tubes filled with titanium chips to prevent oxidation and cooled down on air.</p><p>Phase composition and microstructure of the alloy were studied using X-ray diffraction (XRD) and scanning electron microscopy (SEM). The XRD analysis was performed using RIGAKU diffractometer and Cu Kα radiation. Samples for SEM observations were prepared by mechanical polishing. SEM investigations were performed utilizing Quanta 200 3D microscope equipped with energydispersive (EDS) detector used for chemical composition measurements. Density of the alloy was measured via hydrostatic weighting. Vickers microhardness was measured using a 250 g load applied for 15 s. 20 measurements were made in each condition.</p><p>Compressive tests were performed on rectangular specimens with dimensions of 7 Â 5 Â 5 mm 3 using the Instron 5882 machine equipped with radial furnace. The initial strain rate was 10 À 3 s À 1 and the temperature was of 22 1C, 600 1C, 800 1C and 1000 1C. For high temperature testing, the samples were placed in preheated furnace and held for 10 min before testing. Obvious oxidation was observed only after testing at 1000 1C. The testing was performed until the fracture of the specimen or reaching height reduction of 50%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head><p>The XRD patterns of the AlNbTiV alloy in as-cast and homogenized conditions are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref> parameter of 31873 pm. SEM image of the as-cast AlNbTiV alloy (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>) demonstrates large grains with size of several hundred microns with dendritic structure inside. Dendrite areas (appear light on SEM image) are enriched with Nb (24.8%) and depleted of Al (26.3 (at)%) and Ti (24.3%), and interdendrite areas (dark) are enriched with Al (27.6%) and Ti (26%) and depleted of Nb (21.9%). Predominant segregation of refractory elements (i.e. Nb) in dendrite areas and lower melting temperature elements (mainly Al) in interdendrites is anticipated <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Complete elimination of dendritic segregations is observed after homogenization. Chemical composition of coarse grains with average size of about 300-400 mm corresponds to nominal composition of the alloy. No porosity is observed.</p><p>Formation of bcc solid solution phase instead of intermetallics in the Al-containing AlNbTiV alloy is correctly predicted by parameters Δδ¼3.14% and Ω¼ 1.38 (Δδo6.6% and Ω41.1 are required for solid solution formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>) and VEC¼4.25 (VECo6.87 is required for BCC structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>). It should be mentioned that Δδ and Ω parameters were successfully used to predict solid solutions formations in HEAs with somewhat similar compositions <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p><p>The measured density of the AlNbTiV alloy was found to be of 5.59 g cm À 3 and is slightly higher than the density predicted by the rule of mixtures, 5.39 g cm À 3 . Somewhat higher experimentally measured density values in refractory were already reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. It should be noted that the studied AlNbTiV alloy has the lowest density among reported refractory HEAs compositions <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. No noticeable effect of annealing on microhardness was revealed; hardness was found to be of 4315798 MPa and 43947118 MPa in as-solidified and annealed conditions respectively.</p><p>The compression stress-strain curves of the homogenized AlNbTiV alloy at different temperatures are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. The resulting mechanical properties, yield strength (σ 0.2 ), peak stress (σ u ) and fracture strain, ε, are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>. At room temperature the alloy has demonstrated high yield stress of 1020 MPa, but brittle fracture occurs shortly after yielding at strain of 5% at peak stress of 1318 MPa. Increase of testing temperature to 600 1C results in decrease of yield strength to 810 MPa. Pronounced work hardening stage is observed, and specimen fails when strain reaches 12% at stress of 1050 MPa. Further increase of testing temperature to 800 1C results in continuous decrease of yield strength to 685 MPa and increase of ductility of alloy-height reduction of 50% is reached without fracture. Pronounced steadystate flow stage is observed on the stress-strain curve. The AlNbTiV alloy behaves similarly during mechanical testing at 1000 1C, however, substantial decrease of yield strength to 158 MPa is observed.</p><p>The mechanical properties of the AlNbTiV alloy are rather unexpected for solid solution alloy-it has poor ductility at room temperature but maintain reasonably high compressive strength at temperatures below 1000 1C. The comparison of specific yield strengths of the AlNbTiV HEA and previously reported CrNbTiVZr, CrNbTiZr <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and Al 0.5 NbTa 0.8 Ti 1.5 V 0.2 Zr <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> alloys is even more surprising (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). The compared HEAs had multiphase structure beneficial for high temperature strength: the CrNbTiVZr and CrNbTiZr alloys contained bcc and Laves phases <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> whereas the AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and Al 0.5 NbTa 0.8 Ti 1.5 V 0.2 Zr alloys were composed from two bcc phases <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The AlNbTiV alloy has the lowest specific yield strength among the alloys at room temperature and at 600 1C. But at temperature of 800 1C the AlNbTiV alloy is outperformed only by the AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr alloy, whereas other alloys have considerably lower specific strength. Finally, at 1000 1C the specific strength of the AlNbTiV alloy is nearly the same as of CrNbTiVZr, CrNbTiZr and Al 0.5 Nb-Ta 0.8 Ti 1.5 V 0.2 Zr alloys but is about 3 times lower than strength of the AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr.</p><p>Unusual mechanical properties of AlNbTiV alloy can be attributed to large Al content. Effect of Al on mechanical properties of single bcc phase refractory HEAs was studied on Al 0.4 Hf 0.6 NbTaTiZr and   HfNbTaTiZr alloys with nearly identical microstructure <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. The room temperature strength of the Al-containing alloy was almost two times higher than of HfNbTaTiZr, however, at cost of decreased ductility. It was proposed that atoms of Al form the strong chemical bonds with atoms of other constitutive elements <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, which is mirrored in highly negative enthalpy of mixing between corresponding atomic pairs <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. But at temperature of 1000 1C the Al 0.4 Hf 0.6 NbTaTiZr and HfNbTaTiZr alloys had almost the same strength, most probably due to weakening of the chemical bonds, which is consistent with rapid decrease of strength of the AlNbTiV alloy at 1000 1C. Therefore, Al is likely to be responsible for high compressive strength of the AlNbTiV alloy. On the other hand, Al should be the reason of poor ductility of the AlNbTiV alloy at ambient temperature. Thus one can conclude that by tailoring the Al content in the Al-Nb-Ti-V system it is possible to control the mechanical properties of the alloys; increase of Al content will result in strengthening and loss of ductility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p>In this work, the structure, density and mechanical properties of novel AlNbTiV high entropy alloy were examined. The alloy had single bcc phase coarse-grained structure and low density of 5.59 g cm À 3 after homogenization. The compressive yield strength of the alloy gradually decreased from 1020 MPa at room temperature to 685 MPa at 800 1C, and then dropped to 158 MPa at 1000 1C. The comparison between specific strengths of the AlNbTiV alloy and previously reported multiphase refractory HEAs has demonstrated no significant difference. High compressive strength was attributed to effect of Al. Potential ways to optimize composition of the alloy are proposed. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Structure of the AlNbTiV alloy in as-cast and homogenized conditions: (a) XRD pattern; (b and с) SEM-BSE images: (b) as-cast condition; (с) homogenized condition.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,34.75,58.64,516.00,158.26" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Stress-strain compression curves of the AlNbTiV alloy at given temperatures.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,309.51,244.96,235.44,157.39" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Comparison between specific yield strength of the AlNbTiV alloy and CrNbTiVZr, CrNbTiZr [6], AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and Al 0.5 NbTa 0.8 Ti 1.5 V 0.2 Zr [7] alloys.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,54.15,58.64,228.00,163.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. The patterns show presence of only one phase with bcc lattice in both conditions with lattice Contents lists available at ScienceDirect journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/matlet</figDesc><table><row><cell>Materials Letters</cell></row></table><note><p><p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.matlet.2014.11.162 0167-577X/&amp; 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. n Corresponding author at: Laboratory of Bulk Nanostructured Materials, Belgorod State University, Pobeda 85, Belgorod 803015, Russia. Tel.: þ7 4722 585416.</p>E-mail addresses: stepanov@bsu.edu.ru, stepanov.nikita@icloud.com (N.D. Stepanov).</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Compression mechanical properties of the AlNbTiV alloy.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Т (1С)</cell><cell>σ 0.2 (MPa)</cell><cell>σ p (MPa)</cell><cell>ε (%)</cell></row><row><cell>20</cell><cell>1020</cell><cell>1318</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>600</cell><cell>810</cell><cell>1050</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>800</cell><cell>685</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>1000</cell><cell>158</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>N.D. Stepanov et al. / Materials Letters 142 (2015) 153-155</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the financial support from the <rs type="funder">Russian Scientific Foundation</rs> Grant no. <rs type="grantNumber">14-19-01104</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_9FXPYrk">
					<idno type="grant-number">14-19-01104</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructures and properties of high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dahmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog Mater Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Refractory highentropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1758" to="1765" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical properties of Nb 25 Mo 25 Ta 25 W 25 and V 20 Nb 20 Mo 20 Ta 20 W 20 refractory high entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="704" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and elevated temperature properties of a refractory TaNbHfZrTi alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Meisenkothen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mater Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1062" to="1074" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low-density, refractory multi-principal element alloys of the Cr-Nb-Ti-V-Zr system: microstructure and phase analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1545" to="1557" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical properties of low-density, refractory multi-principal element alloys of the Cr-Nb-Ti-V-Zr system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Sci Eng A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">565</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and properties of aluminum-containing refractory high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2030" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of aluminum on the microstructure and properties of two refractory high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of high-entropy stabilized solid-solution in multicomponent alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Chem Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure of a near-equimolar refractory high-entropy alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Couzinié</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dirras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Perrière</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chauveau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Leroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Champion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Guillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of valence electron concentration on stability of fcc or bcc phase in high entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and properties of a refractory NbCrMo 0.5 Ta 0.5 TiZr alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Sci Eng A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lilensten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Couzinié</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Perrière</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bourgon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Emery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Guillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">New structure in refractory high-entropy alloys</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="125" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A refractory Hf25Nb25Ti25Zr25 high-entropy alloy with excellent structural stability and tensile properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Si</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Search for high entropy alloys in the X-NbTaTiZr systems (X ¼Al,Cr,V,Sn)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Poletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Szost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Battezzati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Alloys Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">620</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="288" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mixing enthalpy of liquid phase calculated by Miedema&apos;s scheme and approximated with sub-regular solution model for assessing forming ability of amorphous and glassy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Takeuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Inoue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1779" to="1789" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
