<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Interdiffusion of hydrous dacitic and rhyolitic melts and the efficacy of rhyolite contamination of dacitic enclaves</title>
				<funder ref="#_6Cw5AGn">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Don</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geology and Center for Glass Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute Troy</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>12180-3590</postCode>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geological Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>McGill Uni-versity, 3450 University Street Montreal</addrLine>
									<postCode>H3A 2A7</postCode>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Interdiffusion of hydrous dacitic and rhyolitic melts and the efficacy of rhyolite contamination of dacitic enclaves</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BBC389BCF50FBA36408E00E022B4581D</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received February 8, 1990 / Accepted August 20, 1990</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Effective binary diffusion coefficients of Si during the interdiffusion of hydrous, 3 and 6% H20, dacitic and rhyolitic melts have been determined at 1.0 GPa, 1100 ~ 1400 ~ C. Water is shown to enhance diffusivities by one to two orders of magnitude above dry Si diffusivities in the same compositional system for SiO2 compositions 65-75 wt%. The effect of silica content on diffusion is small and typically within experimental error. With 3% H20 in the melts the Arrhenius equation for Si diffusion at 70% SiO2 is: D=2.583 x 10 -8 exp  </p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>where D is the diffusivity in m2/s, the activation energy (126.5) is in kJ/mol, R is in J/tool and T in Kelvin. Although less-well constrained, the Si diffusivity at 70% SiOz with 6% H20 in the melts can be described by: D=2.692 x I0 -7 exp(-131.4/RT).</p><p>The activation energies for diffusion are substantially below the activation energy of 236.4 kJ/mol measured during anhydrous interdiffusion in the same system <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baker 1990</ref>). The decrease in activation energy with the initial addition of 3 % water and the relative insensitivity of the activation energy to the additional water is related to the abundance of OH species in the melt, and the reduction of (Si,A1)-O bond strengths due to the interaction of hydroxyls with the (Si,A1)-O network. Changes in the pre-exponential factor of Arrhenius equations are attributed to the abundance of H20 species in the melts. No decoupling of non-alkalies from SiO2 during interdiffusion of the two melts was observed, although alkalies diffuse much more rapidly than non-alkalies (but were not measured quantitatively in this study) and can become decoupled. Interdiffusion of Si and all non-alkalies is demonstrated to be predictable, at least to within a factor of ten, by the Eyring equation. Using the diffusion data of this study for nonalkalies and of other studies for alkalies and Sr isotopes</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Although much research has been performed by geologists and materials scientists on the diffusion of water in silicate melts (reviews by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hofmann 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson and Baker in press)</ref>, comparatively little research into the effect of water on the diffusion of cations in silicate melts has been performed <ref type="bibr">(Harrison and</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson 1983, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Rapp and Watson 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Koyaguchi 1989)</ref>. Most previous studies of diffusion have concentrated on cation diffusion occurring in anhydrous silicate melts (reviews by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hofmann 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson and Baker in press)</ref>. A few studies, however, have investigated the role water might play in the chemical diffusion of cations in silicate melts. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Yoder (1973)</ref> published microprobe traverses of interdiffusion profiles between water-saturated rhyolitic and basaltic melts, from these profiles the diffusivity of non-alkalies can be estimated at 1-5x 10 -23 m2/s at 1200 ~ C, I kbar. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Fujii (1981)</ref> investigated the interdiffusion of Ca and Sr in albitic melts and discovered that the addition of 4% H20 increased diffusivities by a factor of six. <ref type="bibr">Harrison and</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson (1983, 1984)</ref> studied the effects of water on the chemical diffusion of Zr and P and <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Rapp and Watson (1986)</ref> looked at the effects of water on diffusion of rare-earth elements in rhyolitic melts. These studies on Zr, P and REE diffusion demonstrate that addition of small amounts of water enhances diffusivities of these cations in rhyolitic melts by two to three orders of magnitude relative to dry melts. Re-cently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Koyaguchi (1989)</ref> determined that when a dacitic melt initially containing 4% H20 interdiffused with a dry basaltic melt the measured diffusivities, at 10 kbar, 1300 ~ C, and 55% SiO2, were an order of magnitude greater than when both melts were initially anhydrous.</p><p>All of these studies point to a significant effect of water on the enhancement of cation diffusivities in silicate melts. Higher diffusivities will result in more effective modification of melt compositions by diffusion-controlled processes and therefore increase the significance of diffusion-controlled petrogenetic processes.</p><p>This study expands upon earlier diffusion studies to investigate the effects of 3 and 6 wt% water on the chemical diffusion of major elements during the interdiffusion of dacitic and rhyolitic melts at 1.0 GPa. These compositions were chosen because of the recent recognition that many "mafic" inclusions in granitoid and rhyolitic rocks are andesitic to dacitic in composition <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Fluk and Treiman 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Linneman and Myers 1988)</ref>. The chemical diffusion of major elements between these melts under anhydrous conditions has been previously documented <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baker 1990</ref>) and a forthcoming paper will discuss the effects of fluorine and chlorine on diffusion occurring between dacitic and rhyolitic melts (D.R. <ref type="bibr">Baker, in preparation)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental procedure</head><p>Starting compositions for these experiments were a synthetic dacitic glass, ATI50, and a natural rhyolitic glass, LCO (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). These compositions have been used in a previous study of anhydrous chemical diffusion during the interdiffusion of dacitic and rhyolitic melts <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baker 1990</ref>). Also, LCO has been used before frequently by Watson and co-workers in the diffusion studies mentioned above. Sample AT150 was prepared by grinding reagent-grade carbonates and oxides together in an agate mortar, firing to convert carbonates to oxides, then three fusions at 1500 ~ C with intermediate grinding in the agate mortar between fusions. Sample LCO was prepared by grinding the natural obsidian in the agate mortar. Both glasses were ground to have a grain size &lt; 70 pro.</p><p>Glass powders together with water added by microsyringe were placed into graphite capsules. The bottom layer of glass powder was always the more-dense AT150 to ensure gravitational stability of the experiment. The glass powders were tamped into graphite capsules with a plunger that fitted tightly against the inner capsule a FeO, total iron as FeO wall and had a finely polished surface. Graphite capsules were placed into 3 mm-ID platinum capsules which were welded closed without the loss of volatiles. The loaded capsules were stored in a drying oven for a minimum of a few h (most capsules were stored overnight) to homogenize the water inside each capsule.</p><p>Because of the small amounts of water added to the experiments (only a few tenths of microliters) the water contents of different experiments varied from the ideal 3 and 6 wt%. In almost all cases, however, the added water contents were within 0.5 wt% of the ideal water contents.</p><p>Other experimental and analytical procedures were similar to those used in the anhydrous diffusion measurements made on these compositions <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Baker 1989</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baker , 1990))</ref>. Experiments were performed in a piston-cylinder apparatus using 1.91 cm-diameter NaC1-Pyrex assemblies. Assemblies were pressurized to 10 kbar and heated to run temperatures while maintaining 10 kbar pressure. During experiments pressures were controlled to +0.5 kbar and temperatures to _+ 3 ~ C.</p><p>After the experiment samples were mounted in epoxy, sectioned longitudinally, and polished for microprobe analysis. Experiments were analyzed with an electron microprobe using a 15 kV accelating voltage and a 5 nA sample current. Standards were a variety of natural and synthetic glasses and minerals. The beam-spot size was 10-20 gm in diameter to reduce alkali loss during analysis.</p><p>The analytical traverses (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) were used to calculate silicon diffusivity by Boltzmann-Matano analysis. The silicon diffusivity calculated by this technique is an effective binary diffusion coefficient <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Cooper 1968</ref>). Boltzmann-Matano analysis was performed by fitting each diffusion profile with two third-order polynomials which intersected near the middle of the diffusion profile and then numerically calculating the appropriate integrals and derivatives necessary to determine the Matano interface and silicon diffusivity at four, or more, different silica contents along each diffusion profile. Based upon multiple microprobe traverses on the same experiment and upon multiple experiments at the same T and P conditions the estimated error for each diffusivity measurement is less The lengths of all non-alkali diffusion profiles are the same as the length of the SiO2 profile. Alkalies, K20 and Na20, have longer diffusion profiles. The K20 content of the system is almost completely homogenized; in fact, the KzO contents at each end of the experimental capsule have been substantially modified from their original concentrations of 1.77% in the dacite and 4.67% in the rhyolite. Unlike experiments on the interdiffusion between mafic and felsic melts no evidence of "uphill" diffusion is observed. (The one anomalously high alumina analysis is attributed to a speck of alumina polishing compound left on the surface of the experiment) than a factor of three. (See <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baker 1989</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker , 1990</ref> for a more-detailed description of the Boltzmann-Matano analysis technique and associated errors.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Independence of diffusivity from experimental duration</head><p>Experiments at 1100 ~ C, 3% H20 were performed for 2 and 8 h duration (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>) to investigate the possibility of advective transport in the experiments. Within error the diffusivities measured at 65, 70, and 75% SiO2 in each experiment are identical to each other (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, Table 2); these data support the assumption that diffusion was the only transport mechanism occurring in these experiments. 2.0x10 -lz 1.5• -12 3.7x10 -12 3.4 5.5x10 -13 7.9x10 -13 3.9x10 -13 3.4 4.8x10 -x3 3.6x10 -13 3.7xi0 -13 3.4 8.2x10 -13 3.8x10 -13 2.4x10 -13 2.6 3.8x10 -13 4.9x10 -13 3.2x10 -13 6.7 9.5x10 -lz 8.0x10 -J'2 9.5x10 -~z 6.6</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10">-</head><p>1.7x10 -11 1.2x10 -11 7.7x10 -12 6.3 4.4x10 -12 2.0x10 -12 1.7x10 -12 a Diffusivities measured by Boltzmann-Matano analysis at 65%, 70%, 75% SiOz along the diffusion profiles in each experiment (Expt). Note: two microprobe analyses and diffusion measurements were made for experiment D-129 and are labeled A and</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Water distribution during diffusion</head><p>Prior to experimentation all capsules were heated above 100 ~ C in an attempt to homogenize the water along all surfaces of the 70 gm diameter grains of glass in the capsules. Calculated water diffusivities at experimental temperatures of 1100~ ~ C (using Arrhenius equations derived from data in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Karsten et al. 1982)</ref> are high enough to diffuse water into 70-gm-diameter "domains" of melt (representing the original glass grains) at the temperatures of these experiments in only a few minutes. Because of this high diffusivity, the water in the melts is expected to be homogenized rapidly during the experiments.</p><p>One special experiment, D-125, was performed in a larger-diameter capsule (5 mm OD-Pt capsule with graphite liner) with 6.2% H20 at 1095~ for 6 h in order to measure the H20 distribution in the melt during diffusion. After the experiment the sample was ground to 718 gm thickness and a doubly polished section made for electron microprobe and infrared analysis. Water content in the glass was determined using Near-infrared (NIR) spectroscopy on a Perkin-Elmer model 180 UV-NIR spectrophotometer. A scan speed of 480 nm/min was used and the slit width was adjusted automatically by the spectrophotometer. Peak heights of the 1900 nm (5200 cm-1), H20, and 2200 nm (4500 cm-1), OH, peaks were measured and the extinction coefficients of <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Stolper (1982)</ref> used for the calculation of water content in the glass. More recent extinction coefficients <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Newman et al. 1986)</ref> were not used because their calibration did not extend to the high water contents used in this study. Densities of the glasses were calculated following the techniques of <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bottinga et al. (1982)</ref>. To account for the effect of water on the density the partial molar volume of water in albite melt <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Burnham and Davis 1971)</ref> was used to calculate hydrous melt densities. As a test of the density calculation technique the measured densities of rhyolitic melts <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Stolper 1982</ref>, with corrected water content from <ref type="bibr">Newman etal. 1986</ref>) were compared against densities calculated by the above techniques. In all cases the calculated densities were within 5% of the measured ones. Because the composition of the diffusion couple, and therefore its density, changes from top to bottom, the mean density (composition) of the sample, 2140 g/1 was used for the calculation of water contents from the NIR bands. Exact errors on measured water content cannot be given. Analyses of other experiments at Rensselaer Polytechnic Inst. indicate close correspondence between water added to experiments and water content measured by NIR, typically to within approximately 0.25% for melts with 3-6 wt% water. For comparison, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Stolper (1982)</ref> plots error bars of approximately +_0.15% in melts with similar total water contents. Because precision and accuracy are not well-constrained, measured water contents are arbitrarily given to the first decimal place. The smallest aperature successfully used was a regretfully large 1 mm diameter. Although such a large aperature gives poor resolution of the water distribution in the experiment, the water measurements (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>) demonstrate that water is not strongly fraction- along the diffusion profile. This experiment was not used for diffusivity calculations because the diffusion profile has reached the top of the capsule and therefore the rhyolite cannot be considered an infinite reservoir, which is necessary for Boltzmann-Matano analysis ated between the different melt compositions. Although the silica content of the experiment varies from 75 to 63 % the water content along the profile only varies from 6.1 to 5.7%. The depression of the measured water contents below the initial water content is possibly due to interaction between H20 and the graphite capsule to form very small amounts of a separate fluid phase with other species, H2, CO, CO2, and CH4, present. Even if a fluid phase is produced, Modified-Redlich-Kwong calculations of fluid speciation <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Holloway 1981)</ref> indicate that water will be the dominant species in a C-O-H fluid along the Carbon-CO-CO2 buffer at 10 kbar (cf., <ref type="bibr">Holloway and Jackobsson 1986)</ref>. No evidence, e.g., vapor bubbles trapped in glass, was seen for the existence of a separate vapor phase, however. Another reason for the discrepancy between initial and measured water contents may be due to the use of possibly incorrect extinction coefficients (due to their compositional dependence) or densities. Although these errors may be possible, the NIR spectra still demonstrate little partitioning of water along the diffusion profile.</p><p>The slight partitioning of water along the diffusion profile is consistent with the known higher water solubility in more-silicic as compared with less-silicic melts (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Burnham 1979)</ref>, just as other elements have been shown to achieve transient partitioning during the interdiffusion of basaltic and granitic melts <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Watson 1982)</ref>. However, because the analytical precision is not known it is unclear that water partitioning really does occur along the diffusion profile. It could be argued that the large aperture size results in an artifical averaging of the water content along the diffusion profile. As a result of this averaging the rhyolitic portion of the diffusion couple might contain substantially higher amounts of water than the dacitic end. This argument is discounted because the water content measured in the constant-composition dacitic base is near the initial water content of the experiment. If water were strongly fractioned into the rhyolitic portion of the melt then mass balance would require that the dacitic portion of the melt be more depleted in water relative to the initial water added. Based upon the NIR measurements it appears that in the experiments of this study water content along a diffusion profile does not vary by more than 0.4%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Coupling of non-alkali diffusivities</head><p>As observed in previous anhydrous, hydrous, and halogen-bearing interdiffusion-experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Yoder 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Oishi et al. 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Watson 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson and Jurweicz 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Baker and Watson 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Koyaguchi 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker 1990</ref>) all non-alkali cations display concentration profiles the same length as the SiOz and AlcOa profiles (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). Profiles for alkalies (Na20 and K20) are much longer reflecting the higher diffusivities of the alkalies. With the exception of alkalies there is no "decoupling" of minor elements from SiO2 and A1203 during interdiffusion of melts with differing composition. Coupling of non-alkalies has been observed also during the diffusive dissolution of silicates and alumina-containing minerals forsterite, olivine, diopside, spinel, and quartz into andesitic melts. In these experiments non-alkali diffusivities (SiO2, A12Oa, MgO, CaO) are frequently within estimated errors of each other and, at most, differ by a factor of 3.9 <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Zhang et al. 1989</ref>). However decoupling of nonalkali diffusivities, CaO and P2Os, has been observed during dissolution of apatite <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Harrison and Watson 1984)</ref>.</p><p>The coupling of non-alkali diffusivities during interdiffusion is because the local silica and alumina contents control the equilibrium amount of minor elements that can be accomodated in any microscopid volume of the silicate melt <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Watson 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker 1990)</ref>. Therefore such interdiffusion studies as this one are measuring in reality the "rates" of homogenization during the interdiffusion of a silica-rich, alumina-poor and a silica-poor, aluminarich melt. These "rates," with the exception of alkalies, are controlled by the interdiffusion of the networkformers silicon and aluminum <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Watson 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson and Jurewicz 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson and Baker in press)</ref>. Alkalies diffuse more rapidly because suitable charge-balanced sites, which are transitory with lifetimes on the order of only nanoseconds <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Liu et al. 1987</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Liu et al. , 1988))</ref>, can be created for these +J cations in melts of widely varying SiO2 and A1203 contents <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baker 1990</ref>). Although the lengths of the non-alkali elements' profiles are the same as the silicon profile during interdiffusion, any one individual cation may be diffusing at its tracer, or self-, diffusivity, usually orders of magnitude above the effective binary diffusion coefficients measured in  <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Koyaguchi 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker 1990</ref>). However, the effect of silica content on diffusivity over the range 65-75% SiO2 is not strong and typically within estimated experimental error. Although not plotted here, experiments with 6% H20 demonstrate similar trends (as can be seen in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>) this and other chemical interdiffusion studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Watson 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson and Jurewicz 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baker 1989</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker , 1990;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Lesher 1990</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effect of SiO2 on d~fusivity</head><p>The diffusivities measured (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>, Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>) demonstrate that SiO2 content has a small effect on silicon diffusivity over the range studied. In fact the variability is frequently within estimated error. Although the 1300 ~ C, 3% H20, experiment is anomalous (however, note that all measured diffusivities in this experiment are within estimated error of one another) for all other experiments, the effect of increasing SiO2 is to decrease diffusivity. This effect is small and is consistent with previous observations in anhydrous systems during interdiffusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Watson 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Koyaguchi 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson and Baker in press)</ref>. These hydrous experiments appear to demonstrate less of an SiO2 effect on measured diffusivities than anhydrous experiments on the same compositions <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baker 1990</ref>). This decrease in the effect of SiO2 on silicon diffusivity is also observed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Koyaguchi's (1989)</ref> hydrous experiments compared to his anhydrous ones on basalt-dacite interdiffusion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Enhancement of diffusivity with H20 addition</head><p>The experiments of this study demonstrate clearly the enhancement of silicon chemical diffusivity during interdiffusion with the addition of water. At 1200 ~ C the effect of water on silicon diffusivity in the rhyolitic ends</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">1 0 -12</formula><p>2"-10 -13  <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>) and the lines plotted on this diagram. Dashed line labeled "Dry" is based upon Si diffusivities measured at 70% SiO2 in anhydrous dacite-rhyolite interdiffusion experiments of <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker (1990)</ref>. H20 diffusion for 3% water in rhyolitic melts is calculated from the data of <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Karsten et al. (1982)</ref> and demonstrates the much greater diffusivitiy of water in silieic melts than diffusivities measured in this study of the diffusion profiles is compared against the effect of water on Zr and P chemical diffusion <ref type="bibr">(Harrison and</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson 1983, 1984)</ref> in melts of virtually identical composition (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">E &gt; I 0 -14 I 0 -15 I 1 0 =16~ 0 , , ,<label>, ,, , O ~</label></formula><p>For every 3 % water added to the melt the measured diffusivity increases by approximately an order of magnitude. Based on previous dry measurements the extrapolated 1200 ~ C diffusivity for silicon is 2 x 10-14 m2/s,  <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker (1990)</ref> at 3 wt% water the Si diffusivity has increased to 4 x 10 -13 mZ/s, and at 6wt% water the Si diffusivity is 7 x 10 -a2 m2/s. At all water contents the measured silicon diffusivity is one to two orders of magnitude greater than Zr and P diffusion (measured during the dissolution of zircon and apatite). But with the addition of 3 wt% H20 the diffusivities of Zr and P increase by 2 orders of magnitude over their measured dry diffusivities. The further addition of 3 wt% H20 only increases diffusivities of P and Zr by approximately a factor of five.</p><p>The experimental data of this study, the previous study on anhydrous interdiffusion in this system <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baker 1990)</ref>, and the study of the diffusivity of 3% water conducted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Karsten et al. (1982)</ref> have been plotted on an Arrhenius diagram (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>) and the diffusivity data at 70% SiO 2 fit to Arrhenius equations (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). Diffusivity data measured at other silica contents was not used because of the greater accuracy of Boltzmann-Matano analysis near the center of the diffusion profile (cf., <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baker 1989</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker , 1990) )</ref> which for these experiments is close to 70% SiO 2.</p><p>Addition to the first 3% water is shown (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>) to decrease the activation energy for diffusion, Ea, from 236.4 to 126.5 kJ/mol (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). Addition of 3 percent more water, to a total of 6 wt%, has little more effect on E,. Errors in the Ea for the 6 wt% water are very large (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>) and therefore the Ea for Si diffusion with 6 wt% water may be significantly less than the E, for Si diffusion with 3% water, however <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Rapp and Watson (1986)</ref> only found small effects of water content on activation energies for diffusion in melts with 3-6% water. Because the addition of water decreases activation energies of Si diffusion the relative effect of water addition on diffusion becomes greater at lower, more realistically magmatic, temperatures.</p><p>Despite the dramatic increases in Si diffusivity with the addition of water, the extrapolated diffusivity of 3% water <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Karsten et al. 1982</ref> only measured water diffusivity to 950 ~ C) is still approximately one order of magnitude above the measured diffusivity with 6% water in the melt.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Activation energies, pre-exponential factors, and bond strengths." the effect of water speciation</head><p>In solids the activation energy for diffusion, Ea, is correlated with the energy necessary for ionic motion between sites and for the formation of imperfections in the crystal structure that create the suitable sites for the diffusing ion; the pre-exponential factor, Do, is related to the jump distance an ion must move between such sites <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Hofmann 1980)</ref>. Because of the continuous creation and destruction of the interatomic bonds and the microscopic structures of silicate melts (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Liu et al. 1987</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Liu et al. , 1988) )</ref> the activation energy for interdiffusion measured in this study probably is not correlated with the energy of formation of imperfections, sensu stricto, but instead is suggested to reflect a fraction of the bond energy between silicon or aluminum and oxygen.</p><p>Clearly the effect of water, at least the first 3%, is to decrease the activation energy for diffusion to almost 1/2 of the Ea for dry diffusion (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref>, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). If the diffusion mechanism is the transitory coordination increase of Si or A1 from 4 to 5 or 6 (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Angell et al. 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker 1990</ref>) for both dry and wet melts, then it appears that the (Si,A1)-O bonds are being weakened, as reflected in the E,s, by the first 3% water added, and little affected by the next 3% water added (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref>).</p><p>The strong effect of the addition of a few percent water on both the Ea for diffusion (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref>) and the diffisivities (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>) is consistent with water speciation, H20 and OH-, in silicate melts determined by <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Stolper (1982)</ref> who correlated Cs tracer diffusivity with hydroxl con- with less than 2% total water). The strong effect of small amounts, less than 3%, of water on E, (filled circles) and the apparently inconsequential effect of additional water above 3% on E~ is attributed to the abundance of OH-species. The abundance of H20 species in the melts does not seem to correlate with changes in E~, but is suggested to be responsible for changes in Do centrations of granitic melts. Based upon spectroscopy, at low-water contents hydroxyl is the dominant species whose abundance increases rapidly as water is added to the system while the H20 species increases slowly; near 3% total water the abundance of OH-species becomes approximately constant, or increases slowly, whereas the abundance of H20 species continues to increase (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">7</ref>) and becomes the dominant species at higher total water contents <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Bartholomew et al. 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Stolper 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Acocella et al. 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Farnan et al. 1987)</ref>.</p><p>The microscopic interaction between water and silicate melts is complex and a detailed description is beyond the scope of this paper, but to a first approximation molecular HzO probably exists interstially in the silicate melt structure and interacts little with the (Si,A1)-O bonds, perhaps forming some hydrogen bonds with bridging oxygens <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Kohn et al. 1989</ref>). The hydroxyl species, however, interacts more extensively with the (Si,A1)-O bonds (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Mysen and Virgo 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr">Farnan etal. 1987</ref>). In general this interaction is described as the interaction of I-tzO with bridging oxygen to break the bridging oxygen between 2 silicons or between a silicon and aluminum atom and form a hydroxyl species and 2 nonbridging oxygens (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Burnham 1979)</ref>.</p><p>Formation of hydroxyl species at the expense of the bridging oxygen is expected to have an effect on the strength of another bridging oxygen connected to the same Si or A1 atom as the hydroxyl. Molecular orbital calculations of De <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Jong and Brown (1980)</ref> for the addition of OH-or H20 to the H6Si207 molecule demonstrate significant differences in the effects of these two species on the strength of a neighboring Si-O (bridging oxygen) bond. When hydroxyl is added the relative energy for the Si-O (bridging) bond decreases by 24% whereas for the addition of H20 to the same molecule the decrease in bond energy is less than 2% (De <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Jong and Brown 1980)</ref>. Although the calculations may not be quantitatively correct, qualitatively the hydroxyl species affects bond strengths in silicate melts much more than the molecular water species, and therefore hydroxyl interaction with the (Si-A1)-O bonds is most likely responsible for the decreases in activation energies for diffusion measured in this study and diffusion studies of other cations in hydrous versus anhydrous melts (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Watson 1981 ;</ref><ref type="bibr">Harrison and</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson 1983, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Rapp and Watson 1986)</ref>.</p><p>Despite similarities in Eas for the 3 and 6% water experiments, at any given temperature melts with 6% water display diffusivities an order of magnitude above the diffusivities of melts with 3% water because of the higher Do for melts with 6% water. Because the concentration of OH-species only increases slightly as the total-water content increases from 3-6 wt% <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Stolper 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Farnan et al. 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kohn et al. 1989</ref>) it is suggested that the increase in Do is due to the increase of HzO species in the melt. The effect of increasing molecular-water species in the melt may well be a simple-dilution effect; that is in any given volume of melt the silicate species are less abundant the higher the total-water content and result in an increase in the jump distance for a diffusing cation. This hypothesis implies that silicate-melt molar volumes, or densities, are primarily dependent upon the amount of molecular water in the melt, although some bond lengthening may occur as OH-species interact with bridging oxygens. Consistent with this hypothesis is the demonstration by <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Burnham and Davis (1971)</ref> of a linear relationship between the specific molar volume of melts of albite-water mixtures and total water in the melt (at least up to 10 wt% H20). <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker (1990)</ref> demonstrated the utility of using the Eyring equation: D kBT =~ (D=diffusivity; t/=viscosity; kB=Boltzmann's constant; T= temperature in Kelvin, and 2 =jump distance) for the calculation of non-alkali diffusivities during the anhydrous interdiffusion of dacitic and rhyolitic melts. Using <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Shaw's (1972)</ref> technique for calculation of melt viscosities and 3 x 10-a~ for the jump distance (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker 1990</ref>), the diffusivities measured in this study can also be reproduced by this equation to within less than an order of magnitude (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8</ref>). This relationship between viscosity and measured diffusivity suggests similar mechanisms for both viscous transport and the rate-limiting step for interdiffusion between melts of differing compositions (Si-A1 bond breaking). However, perhaps more significant to the petrologist is the fact that the combination of the Eyring equation with <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Shaw's (1972)</ref> ' 1 i ,,1111 Open circles and stars are 1 atm diffusivities at 65 and 70% SiO2 from <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker (1990)</ref>. Filledstar is A1 diffusivity between two rhyolitic melts <ref type="bibr">(Baker, unpublished)</ref> and open diamond is Si diffusivity during interdiffusion between mafic and felsic melts <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Watson 1982)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prediction of non-alkali diffusivities using the Eyring equation</head><formula xml:id="formula_2">I i i i[t11] i i )11]11 t [ i i ill,lj t i iiiJll~ , ,</formula><p>Diagonal line represents perfect correspondence between measured and calculated diffusivities: In the equation D is diffusivity, kB is Boltzmann's constant, T is temperature, A is the jump-d/stance during each diffusive step, and t/is viscosity viscosity calculations can be used to predict rates of chemical homogenization of non-alkalies in silicate melts during interdiffusion in the compositional range from basalt to rhyolite.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Enclave contamination of host magmas: the considerable effects of hydrous diffusion</head><p>The presence of enclaves of one magma composition enclosed in a host of another magma composition have been noted many times by igneous petrologists (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bacon 1986)</ref>. Using a simple model the diffusion data of this study can be used to estimate the amounts of diffusional contamination between enclaves and hosts when water is present in magmas of dacitic to rhyolitic composition.</p><p>The diffusion equation for a spherical body in a thoroughly mixed reservoir <ref type="bibr">(Crank 1975, pp. 90-95)</ref> is used for the calculation of diffusional contamination of the host by enclaves. Under these conditions diffusion is occuring across the boundary between the enclave and the host melts which are being physically mixed. The contamination calculations are performed for enclaves of 5 and of 50 cm radius at temperatures of 1000 ~ , 900 ~ and 800 ~ C and water contents of 3 and 6 wt%. The temperatures span much of the range determined for glassy ejecta from zoned eruptive units <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Hildreth 1981)</ref>; the water contents are near those expected in many continental dacitic to rhyolitic magmas (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Merzbacher and Eggler 1984)</ref>. (An example of diffusion between anhydrous dacitic enclaves and rhyolitic host melt at 1000 ~ C is given by Baker 1990.) Based upon observations on anhydrous diffusion in this system <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baker 1990</ref>) crustal pressures are expected to have little effect upon diffusivities. Thus the calculated homogenization rates are probably applicable at conditions from the middle to the lower crust. Contamination rates for alkalies, nonalkalies (i.e., Si-A1 interdiffusion which controls the homogenization rate of all other non-alkalies), and for Sr isotopes are all calculated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diffusivities used in modeling</head><p>The diffusivities necessary for the contamination calculations were taken from this and other studies of diffusion in intermediate to silicic melts. Non-alkali diffusivities at the conditions of interest are calculated from the Arrhenius equations fitted to the diffusion data of this study. Direct diffusivity measurements in the compositions studied could not be made because the liquidus of the dacite, even with 6% H20, is above 1000 ~ C. There are currently no data on chemical diffusion of Na in hydrous compositions in the dacitic to rhyolitic range. However, using Arrhenius equations for anhydrous chemical interdiffusion of Na and K <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Smith 1974)</ref> and for anhydrous tracer diffusion of Na <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Henderson et al. 1985)</ref> the different types of Na diffusivities are calculated to differ only by a factor of two in the temperature range 1000~ ~ C in silicic melts. However, Arr-henius equations for Na tracer diffusion given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Magaritz and Hofmann (1978)</ref> do yield larger discrepancies between their calculated Na tracer diffusivities and the chemical diffusivities of <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Smith (1974)</ref>. Because of the similarity of tracer and chemical diffusivities for Na in anhydrous systems, the diffusivities for alkalies were taken to be equal to Na tracer diffusion in LCO with 3.5% H20 measured by <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Watson (1981)</ref>. Alkali diffusion at higher water contents is not known, but is not expected to differ significantly from diffusion in melts with 3.5% H20 because <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Watson (1981)</ref> demonstrated the relative insensitivity of Na tracer diffusion to water content, unlike the strong effect of water of Ca tracer diffusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Watson 1981</ref>) and on the interdiffusion measured in this study. Using Na diffusivities with 3.5% H20 to model diffusion occurring at higher water contents only results in minimum diffusivities, or maximum times to reach any given degree of homogenization. The alkali diffusivities used for the calculations are: 1000~ -5.23 x 10-lo, 900 ~ C -3.02 x 10-10, 800 ~ C --1.57 X 10-10 m2/s. Minor elements were demonstrated in this study to homogenize at the same rate as Si during the interdiffusion of dacitic and rhyolitic melts, just as observed during anhydrous interdiffusion of AT150 and LCO. In the anhydrous system it was also demonstrated that nonalkali trace elements (abundance levels of just 100s of ppm) also homogenize as slowly as Si <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Baker 1990</ref>). However, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baker (1989)</ref> demonstrated that at 10 kbar, 1300 ~ C, Sr tracer diffusion during the interdiffusion of dacite and rhyolite is not controlled by Si-A1 diffusion and is approximately an order of magnitude above Sr chemical diffusivity which is the same as the measured Si diffusivity. Similar results for Sr and Nd also have been demosntrated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Lesher (1990)</ref> during the interdiffusion of basaltic and rhyolitic melts. Because the homogenization of Sr concentrations is controlled by chemical diffusivity and homogenization of Sr isotopes is controlled by Sr self-diffusivity (considered equal to Sr tracer diffusivity), <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Baker (1989)</ref> proposed the possible decoupling of Sr isotopic systematics from Sr composition by diffusional processes. To model rates of Sr isotopic homogenization ideally we need the tracer diffusivity of Sr in hydrous melts which unfortunately does not exist. However, Sr and Ca tracer diffusivities in anhydrous silicic melts differ only by a factor of two over the range of 1000 ~ C to 800 ~ C (cf., <ref type="bibr">Magaritz and Hofmann 1978 for Sr;</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson 1981 for Ca)</ref>. Therefore Catracer diffusion in hydrous LCO obsidian <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Watson 1981</ref>) is used to model Sr isotopic homogenization. For melts with 6% H20 the Arrhenius equation given by Watson for Ca tracer diffusion in melts with 6.2% H20 is used to calculate Sr tracer diffusivities: 1000~ 2.30x 10 -11, 900 ~ C -9.75 x 10 -12, 800 ~ C -3.51 x 10 -12 m2/ s. With 3.5% H20 in the melt, at 800 ~ C, the Ca tracer diffusion measured by <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Watson (1981)</ref> was 2.27• 10-13 m2/s. Assuming equal activation energies for Ca diffusion at 3.5% and 6.2% water the Ca diffusivities can be calculated to be 6.31 • 10 -13 m2/s at 900 ~ C and 1.49 • 10 -12 mZ/s at 1000 ~ C for melts with 3.5% water. These diffusivities were then used to calculate the rates  ~0.'0 0.1 0.2 0.5 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1.0 e Degree Homogenized Fig. <ref type="figure">9a-f</ref>. Diffusional contamination-rates of hydrous, 3 and 6% H20, melts containing enclaves of another melt-composition. Contamination is modeled for enclaves of 5 and 50 cm radius at temperatures of 1000 ~ 900 ~ and 800 ~ C using a spherical diffusion model (see text). Degree homogenized is defined to be the extent to which the host melt has achieved the final composition which is controlled by the ratio of host melt to enclave melt and the original compositions of the individual melts.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Watson (1981)</ref>. Results of calculations for alkali contamination with 5 cm-diameter enclaves are not plotted because alkali homogenization occurs for all cases considered in less than I year of isotopic homogenization for 87Sr and 868r between enclaves and their host magmas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diffusive contamination by enclaves</head><p>The results of the diffusion calculations are presented by plotting the time necessary to reach a given degree of homogenization, DH, (Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>). This plotting technique generalizes the results so the calculations can be applied to various intermediate to silicic melt compositions. When the degree of homogenization equals one the system is completely mixed and has a composition determined by the relative weight fractions and compositions of the dacitic and rhyolitic melts considered. For 87Sr/86Sr ratios the degree of homogenization is determined from the moles of STSr and Sesr in the dacitic and rhyolitic melts and weighted by relative proportions of the two melts in the final mixture.</p><p>As an example consider a rhyolite contaminated with 20 wt% dacitic enclaves. If the rhyolite has a composition of 75% SiO2 and the dacite a composition of 65% Si02 then the final homogenized composition is 73% SiO21 At DH=0.5 the host rhyolite would have 74% SiO 2. For a rhyolite with 3.0034 x 10 -s moles 86Sr and 2.1324x 10 -s moles of STSr per g the 87Sr/86Sr ratio is 0.7100. For a dacite with 1.5070 x 10 -7 moles of 868r per g and 1.0609x 10 -7 of 87Sr per g, the 87Sr/86Sr ratio is 0.7040. When the system is completely homogenized the final STSr/S6Sr ratio would be 017067. At a DH value of 0.5 the STSr/S6Sr value of the host rhyolite would be 0.7078.</p><p>At 1000 ~ C the rate of homogenization of the two melts is rapid (Fig. <ref type="figure">9a,</ref><ref type="figure">b</ref>). For 5 cm radius enclaves alkalies homogenize so rapidly, in under 1 year, that they are not plotted. With 3% water in the melt the Sr isotopes have undergone significant modification in I year, DH=0.4, and are completely homogenized in 13 years. Non-alkalies, major, minor, and trace elements controlled by Si-A1 interdiffusion, homogenize more slowly. However, in approximately 2 years the DH value is already 0.2 and in under 20 years, is 0.5. With 6% water in the melt homogenization occurs even more rapidly. Sr isotopes are homogenized in 2 years and nonalkalies reach a DH= 0.5 in less than 3 years.</p><p>By increasing the enclave radius to 50 cm the rate of homogenization decreases drastically at 1000~ (Fig. <ref type="figure">9b</ref>). Alkalies, however, still homogenize rapidly, DH=0.68 at 1 year and are homogenized in under 10 years. Strontium isotopes and non-alkalies are slightly affected after 1 year in melts with 3 % water and only reach a DH= 0.5 after approximately 200 and 2000 years respectively. Increasing the water content to 6% decreases the time necessary to reach DH= 0.5 to approximately 10 years for Sr isotopes and 300 years for nonalkalies.</p><p>At 900 ~ and 800 ~ C the same general trends are evident (Fig. <ref type="figure">9c-f</ref>). For 5 cm-radius enclaves, alkalies are homogenized most rapidly, followed by Sr isotopes and then non-alkalies at both temperatures. Even at 800 ~ C (Fig. <ref type="figure">9e,</ref><ref type="figure">f</ref>) the diffusion between the 5-cm enclaves and host melts can rapidly homogenize alkali compositions in less than 1 year and non-alkalies reach DH=0.5 in under 200 years for 3% water in the melts and under 30 years with 6% water. However, increasing the enclave radius to 50 cm drastically increases the time necessary to reach any given DH value. At 800~ alkalies still homogenize rapidly, under 2 years to reach DH= 0.5, but Sr isotopes require 10s to 100s of years to reach DH=0.5 and non-alkalies need 1000 to 20000 years to attain DH= 0.5.</p><p>The results of the diffusion calculations between enclaves of dacitic melt and a host of rhyolitic melt demonstrate rapid, under 100 years, and significant effects of diffusional contamination for small-radius, 5 cm, enclaves at typical magmatic temperatures and water contents. Large-radius enclaves, 50 cm, are much less effective at contaminating their host melts, although alkalies and, at least at higher temperatures, Sr isotopes can be modified rapidly and significantly in the host melt.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Geologic realism and the effect of crystals on diffusion</head><p>A question which must be asked and answered is whether natural rhyolitic and dacitic magmas contain few crystals under the conditions modeled, i.e., mid-crustal pressures, 1000-800 ~ C, and 3 and 6% water. The presence of crystals in the magmas results in tortuosity, which is important because tortuosity decreases the overall transport of cations by diffusion through the melt phase.</p><p>There is abundant natural evidence that rhyolitic magmas contain few crystals at temperatures as low as 800 ~ C. <ref type="bibr">Hildreth (1981, Table 2</ref>) lists 14 out of 20 zoned eruptive units that contain less than 35% phenocrysts. One example listed by Hildreth, the 1912 ejecta of Katmai that formed the Valley of Ten Thousand Smokes, spans almost the entire temperature range considered in the above models, but has a phenocryst content ranging from 1 to only 25%. The Bishop Tuff has temperatures estimated to vary from approximately 800~ to 725 ~ C and still contains only 5-30% phenocrysts <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Hildreth 1981)</ref>. Diffusion experiments on LCO + 3.5% H20 <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Watson 1981</ref>) demonstrate that at 2 kbar this composition stays liquid, or at least glassy, to femperatures as low as 700 ~ C. Some less-silicious, higher MgO and FeO rhyolitic compositions do, however, have liquidi near 1000 ~ C <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Naney 1983)</ref>.</p><p>Dacitic melts, however, are likely to contain crystals at the lower temperatures considered in the models. Phase equilibria on a Mt. St. Helens dacite <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Merzbacher and Eggler 1984)</ref> at 4 kbar demonstrate a liquidus of approximately 925 ~ C with 6% water and 1000 ~ C with 3% water. The modal percentage of crystals does not exceed 40% for melts of this bulk composition with 3% water until the temperature falls below 925 ~ C. With 6% water in the residual melts the crystal mode does not exceed 40% until temperatures are apparently, but not determined, well below 900~ <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Merzbacher and Eggler 1984</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Naney's (1983)</ref> experiments on a grandodioritic composition demonstrate similar liquidi temperatures for water contents of 3 and 6%, but no modal data are given.</p><p>Making the admittedly simplifying assumption that the melt does not interact with crystals during diffusion the effect of 40% modal crystals on the effective diffusivity can be calculated using equations derived for diffusion through gases in porous media <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cunningham and Williams 1980)</ref>. Equating the modal percentage of melt with the void fraction in a porous medium, V, the effective diffusivity, Deff, for a magma with 60% melt can be calculated using: The effective diffusivity with 40% modal crystals is 0.5 and 0.71 times the diffusivities in the absence of crystals, based upon the first and second equations respectively. The two equations have been proposed by different researchers to account for the effects of tortuosity on diffusion through gases in porous media <ref type="bibr">(Cunningham and Williams 1980, ,p. 134)</ref>. The decrease in the effective diffusity results in increasing the time necessary to reach any given degree of homogeneity, but only by a factor of 1.4 to 2. Therefore, at least using the simple models considered, the effect of up to 40% modal crystals in dacitic enclaves does not have a significant effect on the efficacy of diffusional contamination of a host rhyolitic magma by magmatic enclaves of dacitic composition,</p><p>Based upon these calculations is seems probable that unless magmas are erupted and quenched immediately following incorporation of enclaves, some contamination of the host magma will have occurred. The contamination will be greatest for the alkalies, less for the Sr isotope ratio, and least for the non-alkali elements,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>The effect of water addition on the interdiffusion between dacitic and rhyolitic magmas is shown to increase diffusivities dramatically by decreasing the activation energy for diffusion and affecting the Arrhenius equation pre-exponential factors. The decrease in activation energies is proposed to be due to weakening of (Si,A1)-O bonds when hydroxyl species interact with the (Si,A1)-O network. The change in the pre-exponential factor is attributed simply to the dilution effect of stuffing more H20 species into the silicate melt and increasing the mean distances between silicate tetrahedral networks in the melts.</p><p>As observed for anhydrous interdiffusion between dacitic and rhyolitic melts all non-alkalies appear to diffuse chemically at the same rate as the effective binary diffusion coefficient for Si. Individual cations, however, may be diffusing at their own tracer diffusivities, but their rates of homogenization are controlled by the slower Si-A1 diffusion. Thus, no "decoupling" of nonalkali elemental concentrations from SiO2 concentration is expected, even for trace elements. Alkalies, however, diffuse much more rapidly during both hydrous and anhydrous interdiffusion of silicate melts and can be decou-pled from SiO2. Isotopic ratios may also be decoupled because isotopic homogenization is occurring by the more-rapid self-, or tracer, diffusion whereas chemical homogenization is occurring by the slower chemical diffusion.</p><p>Modeling of the contamination of a rhyolitic host by enclaves of dacitic composition under hydrous magmatic conditions suggests rapid contamination of the host by small, 5-cm-radius enclaves and slower, but still possibly substantial, contamination by large, 50-era-radius enclaves. Even when the effects of phenocrysts in the enclaves are considered, contamination from small enclaves still appears to be geologically rapid and potentially significant in the chemical evolution of intermediate to silicic magmatic systems.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig.1. Typical profiles for interdiffusion of hydrous dacitic and rhyolitic melts. The lengths of all non-alkali diffusion profiles are the same as the length of the SiO2 profile. Alkalies, K20 and Na20, have longer diffusion profiles. The K20 content of the sys-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig.3. Silica-diffusion profile and water-contents measured by near-infrared spectroscopy in experiment D-t25. Filled circles are SiO2 contents along the diffusion profile. Measured water-contents are listed above bars which represent the area analyzed with the 1 mm-diameter aperature on the spectrometer. Note that the areas analyzed overlap because of the large aperature size. Despite the overlap, the water analyses do indicate little partitioning of water along the diffusion profile. This experiment was not used for diffusivity calculations because the diffusion profile has reached the top of the capsule and therefore the rhyolite cannot be considered an infinite reservoir, which is necessary for Boltzmann-Matano analysis</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>465</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Effect of HzO on diffusivity of Si, Zr, and P at 1200 ~ C in rhyolitic melts of 75-76% SiOz</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Effect of H20 on activation-energy, E,, for Si diffusion at 70% SiO2 during the interdiffusion of dacitic and rhyolitic melts and the speciation of water in melts of geologic interest (from Stolper 1982, with corrections of Newman et al. 1986 for melts</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. DiffusivitJes calculated by the Eyring equation plottedagainst measured diffusivities. Filled squares and circles are diffusivities at 70% SiO2 in this study with 3% and 6% water respectively. Open circles and stars are 1 atm diffusivities at 65 and 70% SiO2 from<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Baker (1990)</ref>. Filledstar is A1 diffusivity between two rhyolitic melts(Baker, unpublished)  and open diamond is Si diffusivity during interdiffusion between mafic and felsic melts<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Watson 1982)</ref>. Diagonal line represents perfect correspondence between measured and calculated diffusivities: In the equation D is diffusivity, kB is Boltzmann's constant, T is temperature, A is the jump-d/stance during each diffusive step, and t/is viscosity</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Electron microprobe analyses of</cell></row><row><cell>starting glasses</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>AT150</cell><cell>LCO</cell></row><row><cell>SiO2</cell><cell>63.51</cell><cell>76.37</cell></row><row><cell>TiO2</cell><cell>0.56</cell><cell>0.11</cell></row><row><cell>AlzO3</cell><cell>17.61</cell><cell>13.35</cell></row><row><cell>FeO"</cell><cell>4.91</cell><cell>0.76</cell></row><row><cell>MnO</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.06</cell></row><row><cell>MgO</cell><cell>1.68</cell><cell>0.07</cell></row><row><cell>CaO</cell><cell>5.24</cell><cell>0.51</cell></row><row><cell>NazO</cell><cell>4.67</cell><cell>4.31</cell></row><row><cell>KzO</cell><cell>1.77</cell><cell>4.67</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>99.55</cell><cell>100.24</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>12</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>i</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1 1 O0~</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">1.0 GPa</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">5% H20</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>03</cell><cell>s</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>O4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>b~ r'a</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 0 -13</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>8</cell><cell></cell><cell>L</cell><cell>I</cell><cell>i</cell><cell>[</cell><cell>=</cell><cell>~</cell><cell>i</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell>8</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Time, h</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="9">Fig. 2. Diffusivity at 1100 ~ C, 3% HzO, and 10 kbar plotted as</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">a function of time. Diffusivities are plotted at 65%, circles; 70%,</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">squares; 75% SiOz, triangles. Diffusivities plotted for the 8 h exper-</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">iment are the means of the diffusivities determined on two different</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">electron-microprobe traverses on the same experiment. Error bars</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">are based on reproducibility of diffusion measurements (see text)</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">Table 2. Measured Si effective binary diffusion coefficients during</cell></row><row><cell cols="9">the interdiffusion of dacitic and rhyolitic melts at 10 kbar</cell></row><row><cell>Expt</cell><cell>T</cell><cell cols="3">Dura-H20 D65 a</cell><cell></cell><cell>D7o</cell><cell></cell><cell>D75</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(~</cell><cell cols="2">tion (wt%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(mZ/s)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(s)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">D-134 1400 1800</cell><cell>3.0</cell><cell cols="5">2.4x10 -lz 3.1x10 -lz 2.9x10 -lz</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">D-136 1300 1800</cell><cell>2.7</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">D-113 1200 3600</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">D-129A 110028800</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">D-129B 110028800</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">D-132 1100 7200</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">D-137 1300 1800</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">D-139 1200 3600</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">D-133 1100 7200</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>!Effect of Si02 on Diffusivity! 1400~</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>1300~</cell></row><row><cell>~10 -1: c4</cell><cell>1200~</cell></row><row><cell>E</cell><cell>,11 oo~</cell></row><row><cell>rm</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 0 -~0 6'2 ' 64' 66 ' 68 '70 '72 '74 '7'6 '7'8 ' 80 SiO2</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Fig. 4. Effect of SiO2 on Si diffusivity with 3% water in the melt.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Diffusivities of Si measured by Boltzmann-Matano analysis are</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">fitted with lines for various temperature experiments. With one</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">exception the diffusivity decreases with increasing silica content,</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">as observed in other interdiffusion studies (e.g., Watson 1982;</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Arrhenius equations describing the effective binary diffusion-coefficient of Si at 70% SiO2 during the interdiffusion ofdacit-</figDesc><table><row><cell>ic and rhyolitic melts</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H20</cell><cell>D = Do exp(--EdR T)</cell></row><row><cell>(wt%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>D O (m2/s)</cell><cell>E a (kJ/mol)</cell></row><row><cell>0</cell><cell>+ 2.90 x 10 -s</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>6.73 x 10 -6</cell><cell>236.4_+23.9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>--5.46 x 10 -6</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>+2.62 x 10 -8</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2.58 x 10 -s</cell><cell>126.5_+8.5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>--1.30 x 10 -s</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>+2.35 x 10 -3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2.69 x 10 -~</cell><cell>131.3 _+ 110.5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>--2,69 x 10 -v</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Note: Do and Ea for anhydrous interdiffusion are from</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Calculations for non-alkalies, which contaminate only as rapidly as Si, are based upon diffusivity</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">10 81~0o, C</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">50 cm radius</cell><cell>/</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">10 enclaves</cell><cell>.5~ ~~</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>J.o</cell><cell>/.</cell></row><row><cell>lO</cell><cell>o,~.~~'</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">lo // .-</cell><cell cols="2">.,,d"%--"</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">00. 0.1 0.20.3 0.40.5 0.60.70.8 o.e 1.0</cell></row><row><cell>f</cell><cell cols="3">Degree Homogenized</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">meaurements of this study. All non-alkalies, major, minor, and</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">even trace elements, are expected to be controlled by the rate of</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">silica contamination (see text) 9 Calculations for Sr isotopic contam-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">ination and alkali contamination are based upon diffusivity mea-</cell></row><row><cell>surements of</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgements. This research was supported by <rs type="funder">National Science Foundation</rs> Grant No. <rs type="grantNumber">DMR 85-10617</rs>. <rs type="person">J. Ayers</rs>, <rs type="person">J. Brenan</rs>, <rs type="person">D. Laporte</rs>, <rs type="person">R. Rapp</rs>, <rs type="person">D. Wark</rs>, and <rs type="person">E.B. Watson</rs> are all thanked for many stimulating, and occasionally heated, discussions on diffusion and its significance in igneous petrogenesis. The two official reviewers are also thanked for their assistance.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_6Cw5AGn">
					<idno type="grant-number">DMR 85-10617</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The nature of dissolved water in silicate glasses and its effect on various properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Acocella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tomozawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Non-Cryst Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="372" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Water-like transport property anomalies in liquid silicates investigated at high T and P by computer simulation techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Angell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cheeseman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tamaddon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bull Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magmatic inclusions in silicic and intermediate volcanic rocks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bacon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Geophys Res B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6091" to="6112" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracer versus trace element diffusion: Diffusional decoupling of Sr concentration from Sr isotope composition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3015" to="3023" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical interdiffusion of dacite and rhyolite: anhydrous measurements at 1 atm and 10 kbar, application of transition state theory, and diffusion in zoned magma chambers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of major and trace elements in compositionally complex C1-and F-bearing silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Non-Cryst Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infrared spectra of water-containing glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bartholomew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hoover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C-K</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Ceram Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="481" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Density calculations for silicate liquids. I. Revised method for aluminosilicate compositions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bottinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Richet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="909" to="919" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The evolution of igneous rocks Fiftieth anniversary perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Burnham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Yoder HS Jr</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="482" />
			<pubPlace>New Jersey</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The importance of volatile constituents</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of H20 in silicate melts I. P-V-T relations in the system NaA1Si3Os-HzO to 10 kilobars and 1000 ~ C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Burnham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">270</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The mathematics of diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use and limitations of the concept of an effective binary diffusion coefficient for multi-component diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mass transport in oxides. Nat Bur Stand</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wachtman</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Franklin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>U.S.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Spec Publ</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">296</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="84" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rjj</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Diffusion in gases and porous media</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Plenum Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polymerization of silicate and aluminate tetrahedra in glasses, melts and aqueous solutions -II. The network modifying effects of Mg z+</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Jong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bhws</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1627" to="1642" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<pubPlace>K+, Na +, Li--, OH , F-, C1-, H20, CO2,</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>and H30 + on silicate polymers</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study of the structural role of water in hydrous silica glass using cross-polarization magic angle spinning NMR</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Farnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dupree</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2869" to="2873" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mafic-to-felsic enclaves in a syenite ring-dike</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fluk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Treiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Magma mixing and mingling</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>White Mountains, N.H.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1505</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ca-Sr chemical diffusion in melt of albite at high temperature and pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fujii</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EOS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">428</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetics of zircon dissolution and zirconium diffusion in granitic melts of variable water content</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6672</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The behaviour of apatite during crustal anatexis: equilibrium and kinetic considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sci Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1467" to="1477" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural controls and mechanisms of diffusion in natural silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lowry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gradients in silicic magma chambers: implications for lithospheric magmatism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hildreth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Geophys Res B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10153" to="94194" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in natural silicate melts: a critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics of magmatic processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hargraves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New Jersey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="417" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermodynamics of minerals and melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Phys Geochem</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Newton</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Navrotsky</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Volatile interactions in magmas</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volatile solubilities in magmas: Transport of volatiles from mantles to planet surfaces. Proceedings 16th Lunar Planet Sci Conf Part 2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jakobsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Geophys Res B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="D508" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ion microprobe studies of water in silicate melts : temperature-dependent water diffusion in obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Karsten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sci Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">428</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proton environments and hydrogen-boding in hydrous silicate glasses from proton NMR</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dupree</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">337</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="541" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical gradient in diffusive interfaces in magma chambers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Koyaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decoupling of chemical and isotopic exchange during magma mixing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mafic magmatic inclusions in the Holocene rhyolites at Newberry volcano, Oregon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Linneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EOS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1495</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relaxation mechanisms and effects of motion in albite (NaA1SiaO8) liquid and glass: a high temperature NMR study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brandis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys Chem Miner</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusive motion in alkali silicate melts: an NMR study at high temperature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pines</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">522538</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Sr, Ba and Na in obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim Cosmochim Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="605" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A magmatic geohygrometer: Application to Mount St. Helens and other dacitic magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Merzbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Eggler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volatiles in silicate melts at high pressure and temperature 1. Interaction between OH groups and Si 4+, A13+, Ca 2+, Na + and H +</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Virgo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">331</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase equilibria of rock-forming ferromagnesian silicates in granitic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Naney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">283</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="993" to="1033" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement of water in rhyolitic glasses: Calibration of an infrared spectoscopic technique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Epstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1527" to="1541" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of liquid-state interdiffusion in the system CaO-AI203-SiO2 using multiatomic ion models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Oishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nanba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pask</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Ceram Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="253" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monazite solubility and dissolution kinetics: implications for the thorium and light rare earth chemistry of felsic magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Rapp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Contrib Mineral Petroi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="304" to="316" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscosities of magmatic silicate liquids: An empirical method of prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">272</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="870" to="893" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An experimental study of the diffusion of Na, K, and Rb in magmatic silicate liquids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<publisher>University of Oregon</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Water in silicate glasses: An infrared spectroscopic study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in magmas at depth in the earth: The effects of pressure and dissolved H20</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet Sci Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basalt contamination by continental crust: some experiments and models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical diffusion in magmas: An overview of experimental results and geochemical implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in physical geochemistry</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Perchuk</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin Heidelberg New York Watson EB</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="131" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J Geol</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contemporaneous basaltic and rhyolitic magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yoder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusive crystal dissolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib Mineral Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="492" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Editorial responsibility: T. Grove</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
