<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Na, K. Rb and Cs in glasses of albite and ortboclase composition</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire de Mineralogie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitk d&apos;Orl&amp;ans</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>GCochimie Domaine Universitaire de la Source</addrLine>
									<postCode>45045</postCode>
									<settlement>Orlkans, Ckdex</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire de Geologic</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ecole normale supkrieure</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>46, rue d&apos;Ulm</addrLine>
									<postCode>75005</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Na, K. Rb and Cs in glasses of albite and ortboclase composition</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">AD868EE9309D104F7322B802F0C9165F</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 5 May 1975; accepted in revised form 19 December 1975</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The measurement of diffusion coefficients for Na, K, Rb and Cs has been realized by the technique of active salt deposits on glasses of albite and orthoclase composition, at normal pressure and in the temperature range 3O&amp;lOOO"C. The values of D are between 10e6 and lo-l2 cm' s-' and, for every type of run, they vary with temperature according to Arrhenius laws, with activation energies ranging from 13 to 68 kcal mole -I. These important variations are related to the size of the diffusing element (at 700°C in albite glass DN,/DK/DRJJCs N 107/105/103/1) and to the size of the major alkali element (for rubidium at 800°C Dor.g,/Dab.g, z 20). By comparison with available data on diffusion in feldspars, we emphasize the influence of the defect density on the diffusion process.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>RECENT studies of the diffusion of alkali elements in natural glasses <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(JAMBON and CARRON, 1973)</ref> led us to consider materials of simpler composition.</p><p>There is in fact a great deal of data concerning diffusion in industrial glasses containing a small number of components, but it is quite difficult to obtain thereby a clear view of the phenomena. The compositions are often very different from those of petrological interest, especially in that they do not contain Al, and the temperatures are often limited to below 500°C <ref type="bibr">(FRIS-CHAT, 1975)</ref>.</p><p>For the present study, we chose two glasses of albite and orthoclase composition, which differ thus only by the replacement of Na by K in the framework and which are located on the base of the q-a&amp;r triangle, where most natural obsidians may be plotted with a good approximation.</p><p>The glasses were prepared by dry melting of oxides, and we checked by electron microprobe investigation that the variations in the major elements never exceeded 1% of the measured average value. Because of alkali loss by evaporation, it was sometimes necessary to add alkali carbonates during the preparation; nevertheless, the albite glass no. AG 1 is somewhat poor in Na (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>); as will be seen later on, this is of little importance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURE</head><p>The samples were polished disks or cylinders, about 10 mm in diameter and 4 mm in thickness, the bases of which were used as a starting plane for the diffusion process. We used the radioactive tracers: lJ4Cs, 86Rb, 42K, 24Na with half life, respectively:</p><p>2.3 yr, 19 days, 12.5 h, 15.0 h. First, the alkali chloride solution was set and dried on both sides of the samples. A short annealing of about 2 min led some of the salt cations to exchange with the surface alkali cations of the glass. The annealing temperature was between 400 and 6OO"C, depending on the cations under examination.</p><p>We observed that during this procedure, the penetration of the radiotracers was less than 1 pm, and that in this slice the radiotracers never represented more than 1% of the total alkalis. We could thus consider that we dealt with conditions of a thin plane source and of dilute solid solutions. After that, the remaining salt was washed out, to prevent further evaporation and also redeposition on the edges of the cylinder. The diffusion run was then conducted by heating 15 min to 3 days in a furnace regulated between 300 and 1000°C. The thermal equilibrium of the sample was attained after about 1 min and the temperature was known with an accuracy of *5"C, by means of a Pt-Pt Rh thermocouple in close proximity to the glass. After the longer runs, the evaporation of IYs never exceeded 5% of the total amount; it was of lesser importance for the other alkalis. The absence of crystallization was checked by optical and X-ray analysis.</p><p>For measuring the penetration of the cations, the samples were dissolved in hydrofluoric acid by successive layers of l-20 pm, the thickness of which was calculated by weighing, with a precision corresponding to 0.2-0.4 pm according to the shape of the sample. As the penetration distance varied greatly with the value of the diffusion coefficient D, we calculated the heating time for a mean penetration of about 50 pm. For the high values of D (Na at high temperatures), this was not always possible. since the heating time could not be practically less than IS min: for dissolutions greater than 200 ,nm the acid etching may lead to irregular surfaces, and the limit for D is thus about IO-" cm' s-'. On the other hand, very low values of D (Cs at low temperatures) need to be measured on wide samples, leading to heavier etched layers. but possible evaporation of the radioactive tracers limited our measurements to about IO-l3 cm' s-'. which leads to an interval for D of 7 orders of magnitude.</p><p>The residual activity A(x) of the remaining matter was determined by /3 spectrometry (42K, s6Rb) with a geiger counter or by y spectrometry (14Na, 134Cs) with a channel analyser. It is related to the concentration C(y) by the formula:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">A(s) = 1 L' CWxplAx -Y) dy, (1) J,</formula><p>where 1, is the absorption coefficient of the glass for the radiation concerned, z a characteristic of the analyser, z the dissolved thickness and J' the integration variable for depth.*</p><p>After mtegration, we obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">A(x) = 4,) erfc (2)</formula><p>where A. is the cumulated activity before any diffusion. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OF THE EXPERIMENTS</head><p>The values of D are listed for both glasses in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>; by adding all the errors. we estimate that the overall error is about 207;;. The major source of error depends on the runs. It may be due to thickness for very high values of D (rough surface) or very low values of D (precision in weighing), or due to weak activity, or due to temperature and time when the heating time is brief (thermal equilibrium).</p><p>When plotting log D against I/r (T absolute temperature in "K, Figs. 223), we find that for each diffusing element, D varies according to an Arrhenius law for both albite and orthoclase glasses:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">D = Do exp ( -E/RI-).</formula><p>(3 R is the gas constant, Do is the pre-exponential factor or frequency factor. The slope of these straight lines gives the values of E which are listed in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>, together with the values of I)(,.</p><p>We may note here that CARRON (1968) had obtained for the electrical conductivity of an albite glass a value of E (16 kcal mole'. ') which is close enough to the value obtained here for self-diffusion of Na in the same sample (13.5 kcal mole-').</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>InJluence of the nature of the dzBsing species</head><p>In both glasses the diffusivity-at a given temperature-becomes lower as the atomic number of the diffusing element increases. For instance, in the albite glass at 700°C: D&amp;IzJ~bDcs N 107/105/103/1. Since the activation energy increases also with the ionic radius (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>) the discrepancies become still greater at lower temperatures; for instance, an extrapolation for the albite glass would give DNJDcp = 10" at 500°C and lo4 at 1ooo"C. It may be suggested that these great differences of mobility could well induce a kinetic disequilibrium for the fractionation of large alkali elements during the growth of crystals from glasses or melts, according to the conclusions of ALBAREDE and E~OTTINGA <ref type="bibr">(1972)</ref>.</p><p>We must, however, point out that these relations could not be extended to glasses containing Rb or Cs as major alkali elements, since TERAI <ref type="bibr">(1971)</ref> reported Table <ref type="table">3</ref> that in a series of Na-Cs glasses, DNa/DCs = 10' on </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Influence of the major alkali element</head><p>In the orthoclase glass, the diffusion of the large alkali cations is much faster than in the albite glass; for instance, at 7OO"C, the ratio is 50 for rubidium, and 1000 for cesium. This is obviously related to the size of the alkali sites in the matrix, which are better fitted with large ionic radii in the potassic glass (it AG I are not different from those of stoichiometric may be suggested from a density comparison and feldspar compositions. Therefore it seems that the melting relationships that in the orthoclase glass the dominant effect is the nature of the major alkali elealkali sites could be somewhat similar to the leucite ments, and not their absolute content. In another ones, which allow easy rep~a~emejlt by Rb and Cs).</p><p>way, we may hope that our data on feldspar glasses It is worth noting that in natural glasses, with inter-couid hc extended to ;I large part of the q-ah-or mediate Na/K ratios. we obtained intermediate values triangle. i.e. to granitic melts and not only trachytic both for D and E. although the total concentration ones. decrease for the albite glass, although it is not a linear relationship as claimed by WINCHELL (1969), we observe for the orthoclase glass a significant increase of E from K to Na. This indicates that the major alkali has in both cases the slowest activation energy, and such an observation agrees with the preceding one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparison with difision in feldspars</head><p>The main results on diffusion in feldspars are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">4</ref>. For convenience we plot only the values of SIPPEL (1963) (Na in albite) and FOLAND (1974) (K in orthoclase) beneath our results for Na and K in the related glasses (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>). We notice differences as great as lo5 at 700°C. The very slow diffusivities in crystals will be explained below in the light of diffusion rates in glasses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTERPRETATION AND MECHANISMS (1) DifSusion processes in glasses</head><p>In order to have a qualitative model for diffusion in glasses, we must look first into their structure. Silicarich glasses are considered as polymers of Si04 units with short-range order and bond angles varying around the mean value observed in crystals of the same composition.</p><p>This results in distorted sites where the network modifying cations (here alkalies) may be located: the problem is to known the size of such sites. An indication is given by the temperature at which the glass 'freezes': in albite glass, which freezes at 115O"C, the suitable sites for alkali elements must be smaller than in orthoclase glass, which freezes at 1550°C. Furthermore, we may think that in albite glass the number of suitable sites decreases from Na to K, Rb and Cs, whereas in orthoclase glass, it is maximum for K and decreases both for Na and for Rb and Cs. In the diffusion process, the motion of alkali ions is considered to proceed by a jump from the initial site to a nearby defect. If Em is the enthalpy of migration for such a jump, and  N the molar fraction of allowable defects. the phenomenological equation ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) may be written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">El?7 D = ND; exp -Er</formula><p>If the defects are interstitial positions (not charged), theoretical considerations</p><p>show that their number Ni is constant and unaffected by temperature.</p><p>In this case we have:</p><p>On the other hand, if the defects are vacancies (charged). the molar fraction of defects N,. varies with temperature according to: we may think that in a vacancy process the total activation energy for D is somewhat greater than in an interstitial process.</p><p>Although the results seem to be more regular for the albite glass (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref><ref type="figure">4</ref>), we shall first consider the orthoclase one. By a compilation of data, WINCHELL <ref type="bibr">( 1971)</ref> showed that in silica-sodic glasses there appeared to be a linear relation between E and log D,, for various diffusing elements: this 'compensation law' may suggest a unique diffusing process. We can see in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref> that, for the orthoclase glass. K, Rb and Cs are well situated on a straight line parallel to Winchelf's one. Since their activation energies are rather low, we may think that these three elements diffuse by the same process, which is probably of interstitial type if it was a vacancy mechanism, Na could not move faster than K. in so far as vacancy movement is controlled by the solvent ion-see</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MAN-</head><p>NING <ref type="bibr">(1968)</ref>. The sodium. which is off the compensation line. probably diffuses by another mechanism: vacancies or another type of interstitial position. Previous studies of Li diffusion in a natural glass (JAM- <ref type="bibr">BON, 1974)</ref> showed that this element has nearly the same parameters E and D, as Na. and this is better explained if we admit for both elements a vacancy model.</p><p>For the albite glass. consideration of the relation between E and D, leads to an ambiguous answer. We may draw a straight line passing near the representative points of K. Rb and Cs, with a slope somewhat lower than the previous one, and thus we can conclude that they diffuse by an interstitial mechanism, and Na by a different one. We might also draw a straight line for Rb and Cs. and argue for an interstitial mechanism for these two elements, a different one for Na and an intermediate one for K, as suggested by <ref type="bibr">LACHARME (1975)</ref>. We have no evidence, in both cases. to conclude whether Na diffuses by a vacancy process or by an interstitial one. It would be somewhat surprising that Na could diffuse in albite glass according to a process different from that of K in orthoclase glass (interstitial?) but we must keep in mind that the structure of albite glass is rather compact <ref type="bibr">(ARDNT and HAEBERLE. 1972)</ref> and not fitted to ions of such great size as K, Rb and Cs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>By comparison</head><p>between our results and those obtained for crystals of the same composition, we may estimate the effect of the structure. For that, we must only consider equation ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) which is independent of the diffusion mechanism. We may think that D'* and Em, which are related to the composition, have nearly the same values in vitreous and crystallized matter. The important difference will be for the values of N, which are certainly greater in glasses, according to their lower density. If we assume that the glass frame has a geometry not much different from that of a crystal (see DOREMUS, 1973), we may assume that the number of defects, which is negligible in crystals, is about 10" per cm3 in the corresponding glasses, since their density is about 15% lower. Using this value, we may calculate from equation ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) that the number of defects is about 10m6 per cm3 in a crystal, to fit with the mean measured ratio of D crystal/D glass. This agrees fairly well with the preceding hypotheses, and with the thermal expansion measurements of STEWART and LIMBACH <ref type="bibr">(1967)</ref> and of Kozu and UEDA <ref type="bibr">(1931)</ref>, which demonstrate that the number of defects remains very low in crystals up to about 1100"c.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. I. Penetration curves for the y emitter 14Na in an albite glass after a run of 900 s at 64O'C (a), and for the /I emitter 8hRb in an orthoclase glass after a run of 6.2 x IO4 s at 520 C (b).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>or WANG (1951). From this equation, easily deduce D by plotting against x the values of Y(Fig. I) given by: A(.y)/A, = erfc( Y). (3) *This formula is theoretically valid only if the salt is deposited on one face, but this approximation introduces an error much smaller than the uncertainties of in ;' spectrometry (Fig. la) and its value remains low for the /3 emitters (Fig. lb) we dealt with. Correction for radioactive decay was useful only for elements of short half-lives: 14Na and 42K.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, but D,,/D,, = lo2 on the caesic end. Before giving our conclusions to this problem we D o cn?s-' Ekcat mope-' Do cm2s-' will examine the influence of the major alkali cation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Variation of the diffusion coei3cient with ternper~ltur~ for Na. K. Rb and C's in albitc glasses.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Variation of the diffusion coefficient with temperature for Na. K, Rh and Cs in orthoclase glasses.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Comparison between self-diffusion of Na and K in feldspars and feldspathic glasses. The data for feldspars are taken from Sippel (albite) and Foland (orthoclase).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>EI, is the enthalpy of formation of vacancies and No,. and entropic factor. Thus in this case: Em,, + E, D = R:,l, Db,. exp -~~ RT As Elni and Ew,. seem to have very similar values.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Relationship between E and D,, in albite glasses (circles) and in orthoclase glasses (triangles). The dashed line was obtained by Winchell for silica-sodic glasses.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ALBAREDE F. et BOTTINGA Y. (1972) Kinetic disequilibrium in trace element partitioning between phenocrysts and host lava. Grochim. Cosmochim. Acta 36. 141-156. ARNDT J. et HAEBERLE F. (1972) Thermal expansion and glass transition temperatures of synthetic glasses of plagioclase-like compositions. Cunrrib. Mineral. Petrol. 30. 175-183.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 SiO2</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>AC1</cell><cell>AG2</cell><cell>OGl</cell><cell>OG2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>69.00</cell><cell>68.40</cell><cell>64.62</cell><cell>64.83</cell></row><row><cell>Al2 03</cell><cell>20.44</cell><cell>19.50</cell><cell>18.25</cell><cell>18.34</cell></row><row><cell>Na20</cell><cell>10.90</cell><cell>11.90</cell><cell>.15</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>KzO</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>16.50</cell><cell>16.83</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>99.80</cell><cell></cell><cell>100.00</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 Dcms</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>s-r</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 4 Na</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>(2) The size of the diffusing alkali element is the most important parameter for mobility: the differences reach seven orders of magnitude at 7oo"C, but they depend also on the temperature and on the elements concerned.</p><p>(3) Introduction of potassium as a major component in the feldspathic network makes diffusion easier for large cations such as Rb and Cs. It has little effect on the mobility of small cations, such as Na and K, which have lower activation energies.</p><p>(4) Theoretical considerations lead to the conclusion that there may exist several types of diffusion mechanisms according to the size of the element and to the nature of the silicate network.</p><p>(5) The comparison with crystals shows that the abundance of defects in glasses explain, in a semiquantitative way, the great differences between these disordered materials and the crystallized matter.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Recherches sur la viscositb et les ph&amp;nom&amp;nes de transport des ions alcalins dans les obsidiennes granitiques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
			<publisher>Thkse</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Mathematics of Diflususion</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Glass Science. John Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956. 1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alkali diffusion in orthoclase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Foland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Geechemical Transport and Kinetics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Carnegie Inst</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>t974</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ionic diffusion in oxide glasses. Diffusion monograph series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Frischat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Trans. Tech. Publ</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self diffusion of potassium in low albite using an ion microprobe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Giletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Semet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kasper R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geol. Sot. Amer. Ahstr. Program</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">754</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diffusion des alcalins dans quelques systemes naturels vitreux</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jamb~n</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ThBse 3tme cycle</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Etude exptrimentale de la diffusion des Cltments alcalins K. Rb. Cs dans une obsidienne granitique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Compr. Rend</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">60</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cation diffusion in a low albite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kasper R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geoi. S&apos;oc. Amer. Abstr. Programs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">815</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Kozu and UEDA (1933) Thermal expansion of plagioclase. ~ck~ow~e~ge~en~s-we are much indebted to A. W. HOF-MANN and R. B. KASPER for their helpful suggestions and criticisms, and their careful reading of the manuscript</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kasper R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Thbse</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Brown University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Unpublished Ph.D. Thesis</note>
	<note>Cation and oxygen diffusion in albite. ions Na&quot; et K+ dans des verres de silicates</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A. 11972) Potassium and sodium self diffusion in alkali feldipars</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Yund R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. .~~~~era~. Petrot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="184" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Di&amp;~usion Kinetics for Atoms in Crystals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
			<publisher>Van Nostrand</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">PETROVIE R. (19721 (al Diffusion of alkali ions in alkali feldspars. Pioc. NATO Feldspars Cot&amp; Manchester; (b) Alkali ion diffusion in alkali feldspars</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Mazurin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Yale University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Structure of Glasses. Unpublished Ph.D. Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sodium self diffusion in natural minerals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Sippel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermal expansion of low and high albite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Limbach D</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="413" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mixed alkali effect in the Na&amp; Cs,O-SiOZ glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Terai R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Non Crysfulfized Solids</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ionic diffusion and electrical conductivity in quartz</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Verhoogen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="655" />
			<date type="published" when="1952">1952</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Radioactivity applied to self-diffusion studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Radioactivity Applied to Chemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1951">1951</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="81" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compensation law for diffusion in silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Winchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">High Temperature Sci. l</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2W" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of 24Na, &apos;%b and &apos;%s in melts from the albite-sodium disilicate system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Winchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Ceram. Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">63</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
