<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Solution properties of silicate liquids from thermal diffusion experiments</title>
				<funder ref="#_dByKjtr">
					<orgName type="full">Committee on Experimental Geology and Geophysics of Harvard University</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_C3dRnhQ">
					<orgName type="full">Department of Energy</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_Jsxwyrq #_J9jwtGR">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_H4c2mRB">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesher</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory and Department of Geological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10964</postCode>
									<settlement>Palisades</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">U.S.A</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory and Department of Geological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10964</postCode>
									<settlement>Palisades</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">U.S.A</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Solution properties of silicate liquids from thermal diffusion experiments</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">58930E3AF4CA0F181D8ECDE0BA61E4A8</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received February 21, 1985; accepted in revisedform March 25, 1986</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Experimental thermal diRu.sion (Soret) fractionation of silicate liquids shows SiOl to be the principal ingredient of the component fractionating to the hot end of experimental charges. The chemical characteristics of disequilibrium Soret separations resemble those of equilibrium 2-liquid phase separation. This reflects the fact that liquid structural constitution does not depend upon the process leading to chemical separation. The activity-composition relations which lead to silicate liquid immiscibility strongly influence the Soret fractionation behavior of liquids near the solvus. This is especially well illustrated in the system Fa-Lc-Q. The temperature versus composition features of the steady state thermal diffusion profiles may be adequately described by an asymmetric regular solution model for silicate liquids, in contrast to any simpler solution</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>model. This model can be used to quantity Margules parameters and the heat of transport for Si02 in these silicate liquids. Observation of the rise time and steady state values of Soret fractionation allows calculation of ordinary and thermal diffusion coefficients for Si02</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCI'ION</head><p>A KNOWLEDGE OF the thermodynamic mixing prop et-ties of silicate liquids is a necessary ingredient for a detailed knowledge of magmas or any program of calculation of magmatic phase equilibria. Toward this end a number of investigators have used calorimetry (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">NAVROTSKY et al., 1980)</ref> or crystal-liquid equilibrium (e.g. GHIORSO et al., <ref type="bibr">1983)</ref> data. Both approaches are laborious and data-intensive but through persistent effort have yielded important results. Nevertheless both methods have shortcomings. Obtaining mixing prop erties and excess functions from calorimetric data requires that small differences between large numbers be known with a high degree of precision. This is especially a matter of concern when solution and drop calorimetric information are combined to cross the glass transition. The equilibration of crystals and liquid to obtain the mixing properties of the liquid is only as secure as our knowledge of the crystalline mixing properties. Although these difficulties do not preclude progress, there is clearly room for supplementary information from a technique which does not depend on finding the difference between similar large numbers or on a knowledge of crystalline solution characteristics.</p><p>Thermal diffusion (Soret effect) is the phenomenon of mass diffusion, and chemical differentiation, within a substance as a consequence of an externally imposed gradient of temperature. In a paper entitled "The heat of transport in binary regular solutions" DENBIGH <ref type="bibr">(1952)</ref> showed that the thermodynamic and kinetic treatments of thermal diffusion could complement each other in providing interpretive insight into the mixing properties of solutions. In concluding, Denbigh remarked: "Certainly in gases it is known that the measurement of thermal diffusion is one of the best methods of determining interaction potentials and it may be hoped that the same approach may prove fruitful for condensed phases." This paper and its concluding remarks have generated little petrologic interest. However recent developments, to be reported below, indicate that thermal diffusion experiments on silicate liquids are useful in the way Denbigh suggested. That silicate liquids exhibit spectacular Soret separations has been demonstrated experimentally only recently <ref type="bibr">(WALKER et al., 1981;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">LESHER, 1985)</ref>. It is the purpose of this paper to present some new thermal diffusion results for selected natural and synthetic silicate liquids. In the case of natural liquids the rates of Soret separation are characterized, providing a measure of the extent to which experimental separations reflect steady state. Further we show that quantitative estimates of component interaction energies and heats of transport for silicate liquids can be extracted from the steadystate temperature4zomposition Sot-et diffusion profiles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL METHODS</head><p>Thermal diffusion experiments were performed by holding short (3-5 mm) silicate liquid charges in the temperature gradient (SO-70"/mm) found along the axis away from the midpoint of cylindrical graphite electrical resistance heaters within a BOYD-ENGLAND ( 1960) piston-cylinder apparatus. Experiments were conducted at 10 kilobars pressure to suppress vesiculation due to alkali or oxygen loss. Samples were enclosed in graphite capsules within Pt sleeves. Salt/Pyrex composite pressure media were used. The temperatures were monitored with W/Re thermocouples at the hot end of the charge ( 1500-1650°C). Temperature gradients are known by calibration with multiple junction thermocouples in separate experiments at the same pressure rather than by direct measurement. During a run, temperature was regulated by controlling the power consumption of the heater. Design considerations have been discussed in detail by WALKER a al. <ref type="bibr">( 198 1)</ref> and LESHER(~~~~).</p><p>Compositions in the system FerSiO,-KAlSi206-SiO2 (FaLcQ) were prepared from mixtures of Johnson Mathey Puratronic reagents: SiOr , A&amp;O,, FerO,, and K$03. After weighing, components were ground together in an automatic mortar under ethanol for 5 hours and pressed into a 1 gram pellet with polyvinyl alcohol binder. Pellets were. baked at I atmosphere, 955°C in an Hz/CO2 gas stream with a pOr one half a log unit below the iron-wustite buffer. Baked pellets were crushed and reground to powder for one hour. Naturally occurring igneous rock compositions were prepared directly as powders from the rocks.</p><p>Runs of 46 to 264 hours duration were performed in order to test the achievement of steady-state Soret separation, as discussed below. Following quenching, charges are sectioned along their cylindrical axis, examined optically to insure the absence of crystals or phase separation, and analyzed by electron microprobe methods. Experimental parameters and analytical data are reported in Table <ref type="table">I</ref>. ). The parallel with silicate liquid immiscibility is explored below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Soret separation qf natural liquids</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rates ofseparation</head><p>In a temperature gradient an initially homogeneous liquid becomes heterogeneous with time, but not without limit, as there is a tendency for normal diffusion to restore systems to uniformity. At some point the heat-flow-induced thermal diffusion will be balanced by the homogenizing action of ordinary chemical diffusion. In this condition, where no further separation occurs and thermal and ordinary diffusion balance one another, a steady or time-invariant state is said to have been achieved. Two additional characteristics of the observed Soret separations merit note in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. To a very good approximation, the compositional separations project as linear trends in this ternary plot. Even though the liquids have the potential for very complex chemicai variation, the Soret process appears to be separating solutions which are effectively binary. This is not rigorously demonstrated by Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, but as shown by material balance calculations intermediate compositions of the MORB and MHA Soret arrays can be described in a very 'good approximation as linear combinations of the compositional end members (e.g. sum of residuals squared &lt; 1.2 when calculated on the basis of mole % of the oxides).</p><p>In order to compare the Soret profiles 01 diherent bulk compositions effectively it is important to establish the rates of Soret separation and the extent to which a given array is representative of the steady state. For instance, it is not obvious at this stage whether differences in the magnitude of Soret separations for the various bulk compositions (e.g. MORB VS. MHA: Table IA) are an intrinsic feature of the steady state or simply reflect differences in the unmixing rates of melts which have different viscosities and chemical diffusivities. We may inquire how closely our experiments correspond to the steady state condition by examining the development of chemical separation with time.</p><p>The other notable feature of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> is the deportment of the Soret arrays nearly radial to the silica apex with the hot end enriched in SiOz. The MORB and MHA arrays of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, however, are not precisely radial to SiOz as liquid compositions are projected from the components NaAlS&amp;Os (Ab) and KAISisOs (Or), both of which are aIso enriched at the hot end of the temperature gradient with SiOz. Nonetheless, multiple linear regression analysis demonstrates that 98-991 of the compositional variance displayed by the MORB and MHA arrays is explained by SiOz (see Table <ref type="table">1B</ref>).</p><p>In Figs. 2a and 2b the extent of Soret separation of MORB and MHA melts after 52 h and 264 h and after 46 h and 168 h, respectively, are compared in plots showing the variation of weight percent of the oxides with distance/temperature along the length of each charge constructed from data presented in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. Data points are omitted for clarity. One immediately obvious feature of "T-X" plots of this sort is that the linear character of the compositional separation seen in Fig. <ref type="figure">I</ref> is no longer readily apparent. (Tis temperature and X is compositional variation.) This is due in part to the non-linear dependence of Ton position along the charge but also in part on the non-linear dependence of X and T, an aspect given greater attention later. There is also some time variation. The linearity of thermal diffusion separations and</p><p>The direction of oxide separation, i. We may quantify the differences in the rate of Soret separation of MORB and MHA liquids. In this regard it is interesting to note that most major oxide components separate to either the hot or cold end on similar time scales. This can be appreciated from Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> by comparing the relative increases in separation of oxide components with time. For example, the hot/cold sep aration of Si02 in the MORB liquid increases by a factor of 1.30 during the 2 12 h that elapsed between the 52 h and 264 h runs. This compares with separation factors of 1.34 and 1.3 1 for CaO and Na20, respectively. Likewise, the SiOl gradient for MHA increases by a factor of 1.67 during the time that elapsed between the 46 h and 168 h runs. similar to the 1.79 and 1.55 fold increase seen for Fe0 and MgO. respectively. These observations may come as some surprise, since it is well known from experimental studies of tracer and self-diffusion that the diffusivities of mono-and divalent cations are one to two orders of magnitude larger than those for polyvalent cations. such as Si'J and Al+3, at equivalent temperatures (see fhFM~hx. 1980 for review). Tracer and self-diffusion experiments. however, are carried out under isothermal conditions in the absence of a melt structure gradient and. hence, the driving force for diffusion is dependent on14 on the concentration gradient of the tracer ion. Soret diffusion, on the other hand, involves the diffusion of chemical species in a thermally and compositionall&gt; zoned system. Under these conditions diffusion of each species depends on the chemical potential gradients for all the other species present in the melt.</p><p>We may use the observed rate of unmixmg of the SiOl component to calculate the chemical diffusivitt of SiOz in compositions such as those shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. This is done by regarding the unmixing process as binary, with Si02 as the component of interest. and by measuring the Soret coefficient, run duration, and capsule dimensions for at least two experiments quenched at different times less than steady state. A measure of the overall extent of separation in a binary system can be expressed by the Soret coefficient (Tb'-RRELL, 1961):</p><p>where Au is the compositional difference m mole fraction between points separated by AT. .\: is the mole fraction of component x in the bulk composition. Soret coefficients for oxide components for each experimental run are reported in Table <ref type="table">IA</ref>.</p><p>Drawing on the early work of DEGROO I I 1947). WI approximate solution for the time-dependent separation of a binary solution by Soret diffusion, consistent with a large body of experimental data on liquids</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(TYRRELL, 1961). is csorct(f) = Q&amp;SS)( 1 ~-exp(-f/O)). tTJ,</formula><p>where us&amp;t) is the Soret coefficient as detined by ( ! : In principle the diffusion coefficient Dsio&gt; is a function of temperature and composition (at constant pressure), both of which vary across the experiment. We have neglected this dependence in our analysis. Thus we regard these determinations of Dsio2 as mean values corresponding to the mean temperature and composition of the experiment. As a silica-rich melt develops at the hot end of the charge and a silica-poor melt at the cold end the composition and temperature dependence Of Dsio2 will have compensating effects thus reducing the potential variation of diffusivity across the thermal diffusion cell during the experiment.</p><p>The extent that each experiment represents steady state is shown as an alternate ordinate to the t/O function in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. The results of Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> show that at the conditions of our experiments, Soret separation of basaltic melt approaches to within 99% of its steady state value in less than a week (-125 h). Over the same period andesitic liquid has reached 97% of the steady state separation, while rhyolite melt achieves less than 50% of its potential steady state separation. For all intents then MORB and MHA profiles of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> can be taken as representative of the steady state. This demonstration will become important later in our thermodynamic analysis of "T-X" Soret profiles which is appropriate only for the steady state.</p><p>In addition to providing an evaluation of the approach to steady state the results of this analysis also supply an independent measure of Dsioz comple-  <ref type="bibr">(1980)</ref>, derived from a study of crystal/liquid boundary-layer diffusion in basaltic liquids. The compositional dependence reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">WATSON (1982)</ref> and that determined from the Soret rise time experiments are in remarkable conformity to one another. Our estimates of Db02 for mean temperatures of 14 15-1535'C, however, are roughly an order of magnitude higher than the 1300°C data of Watson. The value for MORB is approximateIy 2 orders of magnitude higher than reported by POWELL rt al. for basaltic melt at -1100°C. These relationships are consistent with the expected Arrhenius-type temperature dependence for DSia. The negative dependence on bulk silica is consistent with the anticipated decrease in species mobility with increasing ~lyme~~tion.</p><p>Future thermal diffusion experiments conducted at a variety of mean temperatures should enable determination of activation energies for the diffusion process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Soret separation near a silicate sohus: the system Fa-Lc-Q</head><p>The steady state condition results from the homogenizing influence of ordinary diffusion upon the heterogeneities introduced by thermal diffusion. Chemical potential imbalances drive ordinary diffusion. Thus the details of the steady state con~guration shoutd be sensitive to the chemical potential versus composition re-Iations of the diffusion medium. As such we might expect that experiments near a solvus will reflect the "abnormalities" in the activity-composition relations (e.g. deviations from Raoult's law) that are also responsible for 2-liquid phase separation. In the following section we explore the similarities between thermal diffusion and silicate liquid immi~ibility (SLI). which also produces chemical separation with an SiOz-rich component.</p><p>Specifically, if Soret diffusion and silicate liquid immiscibility (SLI) act on similar melt species, Soret fractionation should in detail be channelled along compositions vectors that parallel SLI conjugate liquid tie lines. A test of this conjecture is provided by experiments on hyper-soivus liquids in the system Fe2Si04-KAlSi206-SiO2 (FaLcQ) ( ROEDDER, 195 1). This system is particularly interesting as it possesses two fields of stable silicate liquid immiscibility. One is along the fayalite-silica join and the other in the central portion of the ternary shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">5a</ref>. The 2-liquid held occurring at low temperature, interior to the system, exhibits tie lines to conjugate liquids that are not radial to SiOz (in contrast to the SLI tie-lines in alumina-free silicate system), but rather are nearly radial to Fa.</p><p>Two bulk compositions lying at the Fa-rich (B) and Fa-poor (8') ends of the central SLI field were chosen for study for the following reasons: 1) the existence of stable SLI in this region indicates that at super-liquidus temperatures melts of these compositions should be highly non-ideal: 2) the relatively low temperatures of the solvus and adjoining liquidus surfaces makes the single liquid phase field ex~~men~IIy easily accessible; and 3) thermal diffusion experiments on these compositions should provide a test of our contention that Soret diffusion and SLI operate on similar silicate species.</p><p>Experimental reference. Mi~opro~ analyses pf these arrays are given in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. Large Soret separations are produced for both bulk compositions but the shapes of these arrays as ternary projections are distinctly different. These arrays are not truly ternary as there is some fractionation of K from Al by thermal diffusion, most evident in the case of ZM-99 (see Table <ref type="table">1A</ref>). There is also a slight shift of the bulk composition of ZM-99 shifted away from fayalite reflecting the reduction of minor amounts of ferrous iron during the experiment.</p><p>Using estimates of Dsioz taken from Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> corresponding to the silica content of B and B' and the relevant experimental parameters given in Table <ref type="table">I</ref> we can estimate vta Eqn. (2) how closely experiments ZM-96 and ZM-99 correspond to the steady state. For ZM-99 we conclude that separations after 207 h have achieved &gt;99% of steady state, while for ZM-96 the overall magnitude of separation after 2 10 h is -80% of steady state. For the purposes of this discussion we will assume that both ZM-96 and ZM-99 are representative of the steady state, although this is not fully justified in the case of ZM-96.</p><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure">5b</ref> it is seen that the more ferrous iron-rich composition B (ZM-99) forms a compositional array nearly radial to Fa and subparallel to the 2-liquid tielines. This behavior is consistent with our expectation based on the Soret-SLI analogy. Further note that ZM-99 is nearly linear in the ternary FaLcQ displaying a near binary separation behavior like that observed for MORB and MHA. Multiple linear regression analysis in terms of oxide components shows that 95% of the compositiona variance of this array can be accounted for by the component Si02 (see <ref type="table">Table 1 B</ref>). In contrast, the more siliceous B' array (ZM-96) displays a pronounced compositional curvature. This array is radial to Fa (and parallel to the 2-liquid tie lines) within the compositional region of the low-T 2-liquid field, while for more felsic compositions of the Soret array is deflected towards the silica apex. Soret diffusion in composition B' clearly is not binary and requires at least one additional component (i.e. alkali aluminate-rich component) to describe the chemical variations seen in Fig. <ref type="figure">5b</ref>. The ternary character of the separation is also reflected in a decrease of the com~sitional variance explained by the SiOz to only 79% (Table <ref type="table">1 B</ref>).</p><p>Equally intriguing are the "T-X" profiles of B and B' in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6a</ref> showing the variation of SiOz (expressed in mole fraction) with temperature between the hot end and cold end of the charge. For both ZM-99 and ZM-96 the mole fraction of SiOz is calculated in terms of the components Fa-Lc-Q. These if any, only slight curvature suggestive of more ideal solution behavior. To gain a better appreciation for the importance of liquid solution properties in thermal diffusion separations it is instructive to consider the constraints provided by non-equilibrium thermodynamics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>THEORETICAL CONSIDERATIONS</head><p>One of the basic conclusions of the study of irreversible processes is that the steady state is characterized by a minimum rate of entropy production. The development of this conclusion and the basis of much of the following treatment may be found in the textbooks of DEGROOT and MAZUR (I 962), <ref type="bibr">DENBIGH ( 195 I)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">KATCHALSKY and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">CURRAN (1975), and</ref><ref type="bibr">WISNIEWSK~ et al. (1976)</ref>. Entropy production results from irreversible flows of heat and mass (which may, in the general case, be coupled). The rate at which entropy is produced can be shown to be equal to the product of the flows times the potentials driving these flows. The entropy production which results from mass flow is driven by imbalances in chemical potential. This entropy production may be written in terms of the fluxes (Ji) of the components participating in the mass flows, times the appropriate of gradients in chemical potential, AWL, :</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">i JiVpi = "i' J/VP, + JnVp, (5) i-I i-1</formula><p>However in a closed, continuous system the fluxes Ji of all n substance components cannot be independent of one another. Interdiffusion of substances may be viewed from several reference frames. Adopting the center of mass reference frame following <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">WISNIEWSKI et al. ( 1976)</ref> the system closure condition becomes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">iJ,=O<label>(6)</label></formula><p>,=I</p><p>This expression may be used to make the terms in (5) independent of one another. Taking (6), multiplying by VP,,, solving for the J,,Vp, term and substituting the result into (5) gives:</p><p>The independent V(Mi -p,) is now identifiable as the potential driving the flux of component i leading to entropy production. We now allow mass flux to also be coupled to heat flow, through the independent potential V In T. <ref type="bibr">The</ref>  Where LM is the proportionality coefficient relating mass flow to imbalances of T and L,, is the coefficient relating mass flow to the various independent chemical potential imbalances. For a binary system this reduces to:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">J, = -L,,V In T -L,,V(p, --e2i (91</formula><p>At steady state minimum entropy producuon is realized when the flows unfixed by external potential differences vanish, or J, = -Jz = 0. so that: <ref type="figure">,</ref><ref type="figure">JL,</ref><ref type="figure">,</ref><ref type="figure">V</ref> In T = V(g, --~~1 <ref type="figure">,</ref><ref type="figure">/L,</ref><ref type="figure">,</ref><ref type="figure">V</ref> In T = Oh, -Vpl</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(IO)</head><p>For small parts of a continuous system which themselves may be thought of as being in internal equilibrium we can write the Gibbs-Duhem equation at constant T and P</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>x,dp, + xIdp2 = 0 dc(z = -x,lxzdp, (II)</head><p>The '? operators in (IO) can be simplified in one dimensional systems to dlnT, dp, , and dp2 where the differentials are taken with respect to T and composition, respectively, Substituting (11) into (10) gives: <ref type="figure">,</ref><ref type="figure">lL,</ref><ref type="figure">,</ref><ref type="figure">d</ref> In T = dw, + x,lx2dpI =dplfxz (12)</p><p>We may define the heat of transport as</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Q: = L,dL, (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">)</formula><p>which gives for ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">-xzQYdTlT = khIh)~..pdx, (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">)</formula><p>The nature of the Q: parameter is obscured by its definition in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">13</ref>). However, it may be thought of as the heat which must be added to the point ofdeparture of a mole of substance and must be removed from the place of arrival of that mole of substance in order to keep both places at the same constant temperature in the absence of any other diffusion flows. It resembles the energy barrier required to form the activated complex in transition state theory in that its value is dependent on the details of the mechanism involved in the transition. In the same way, it resembles the energy required to mobilize for a molecular jump in diffusion, although p is a macroscopic rather than a microscopic or kinetic property. From ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">14</ref>) we see that Q: must be negative if component I is to migrate towards the hot end of the system (positive dTlaZx,) since (&amp;,/ax,),, is positive-definite. In the ability to assume negative values. Q: does not resemble the energy associated with activated complex formation, even though this ability is related to the detailed nature of the diffusion process. as is activated complex formation. The positiveness of Q depends upon the energy of the transported material being greater than the enthalpy of the stationary material. If the average energy of the material in transit is less than fi then Q' is negative. The result of all this for thermal diffusion is that transport of mass provides a sink for some of the heat which has the potential to flow to cold regions as the result of temperature difference. If this heat is absorbed in driving mass flow then less entropy is produced.</p><p>Equation ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">14</ref>) can be rearranged to give an expression for the steady state Soret coefficient defined by Eqn. where R is the gas constant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(16)</head><p>Examples of theoretical thermal diffusion profiles for an ideal binary solution are shown in Figs. la and 7b as plots of chemical potential vs. composition and temperature vs. composition, respectively. In computing p-s profiles +Pldegree is taken as -13.0 calmole-'-degree-'. a value appropriate for cristobalite in the temperature range of 1600 K to I800 K <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(ROBIE et al.. 1979)</ref>. A value of Q: equal -10.0 kcal-mole-' is arbitrarily used in this model calculation. Values of Q: reported for liquid metals and organic binary solutions by TYRRELL ( 196 1) are generally a factor of 2-10 lower than this value. Our purpose in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. however, is simply to provide a graphical illustration of the relationships between T, p, and composition for thermal diffusion. Theoretical Soret profiles are computed by incrementally evaluating ( 16) through a specified T interval starting at T,,,, and an arbitrary xhol.</p><p>The l/T2 dependence of the ideal arrays is readily detected in a upward concavity of each model array. An important feature to note of the "ideal" thermal diffusion arrays shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref> is their steep slopes reflecting small chemical separation although in their calculation a large temperature contrast (AT = 300") and heat of transport was specified. One is lead to conclude that for ideal solutions Soret effects are likely to be small unless temperature gradients are extremely large or the heats of transport are correspondingly large.</p><p>A more interesting case to consider is thermal diffusion in non-ideal solutions. Consider a single phase solution in a compositional region of lower temperature immiscibility where chemical potential displays less dependence on composition than found away from the region of immiscibility. If the heat of transport remains relatively constant the magnitude of chemical separation by Soret separations (a!r/dT in Eqn. 15) will increase in direct proportion to the decreasing dependence of cc on composition (a&amp;3x -0). Although it is possible that Q: also approaches zero near the critical point the increase in chemical separation by thermal diffusion in the vicinity of a solvus shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6a</ref> for ZM-96 and ZM-99 would indicate that. certainly for the system FaLcQ. the heat of transport approaches zero more slowly than does +/ax.</p><p>Theoretical steady state Soret arrays for a non-ideal solution may be calculated using Eqn. (15) after choosing an appropriate expression describing deviations from ideal mixing. The simplest model which can account for non-ideal mixing behavior is that for a strictly regular symmetric solution involving a single interaction energy parameter, W,, independent of composition and temperature. Deviations from ideality are symmetrically disposed about the binary join. We may express the chemical potential of component I as which can be substituted into Eqn. f 15) to give an expression for the steady state Soret coefficient for a strictly regular binary solution</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">(19)</formula><p>Model Soret arrays for a strictly regufar symmetric solution calculated by Eqn. ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>) using values of U; = 6.5 kc&amp;mole-', implying a critical temperature of 1362°C and Q: = -2.0 kc&amp;mole-', are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">7c</ref> and<ref type="figure">7d</ref>. In Fig. <ref type="figure">7c</ref> the contours of@, clearly show flattening in the compositional region of iow-~immi~ibility. As expected from our discussion above the Soret arrays also flatten in this compositional region in response to the decreasing dependence of chemical potential on composition. Moreover, in contrast to the example for an ideal solution (Figs. <ref type="figure">7a,</ref><ref type="figure">b</ref>), we find that for a nonideal solution, a comparatively small value of the heat of transport leads to large chemical separation by thermal diffusion in the compositional region of a solvus.</p><p>The distinctive shapes of the Soret arrays for the ideal and non-ideal binary solutions shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref> should he noted. Important in this regard is the characteristic shape of Soret profiles of non-ideal solutions and their relationship to the position of the solvus at lower temperature. Arrays lying to the right of the consolute composition exhibit concave-upcurvature, those to the left are concave-down, and those traversing across the consolute composition display an inflection point. Clearly more complicated behavior could be envisaged had a more complex solution model been chosen to parameterize chemical potential (i.e. asymmetric regular or subregular model), however, the strong influence exerted by the a~i~ty-commotion relations of the medium on thermal diffusion separations is well illustrated by the examples, Moreover. large deviation from ideal mixing should be readily detected in a T-X deflection of an experimental thermal diffusion profile. With this in mind we call attention to the qualitative similarities between the theoretical Soret arrays for a non-ideal solution (Fig. <ref type="figure">?d</ref>) and the T-X projections of the experimental arrays ZM-99 and ZM-96 shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6a</ref>. This comparison suggests that the T-X details of experimental thermal diffusion Thermal diffusion in silicate melts t 407 profiles, such as those of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>, can provide quantitative information regarding the solution properties of silicate liquids and the heats of transport of silicate components. A method by which this info~ation is retrieved from experimental data is outlined in the final section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MIXING ENERGIES OF SOLUTIONS FROM THERMAL DIFFUSION ARRAYS</head><p>We retain the binary formulation of the energy balance equation as a first approximation in view of the near binary character of Soret fractionation shown earlier. A choice of appropriate binary components is more problematical. For example, we might use the thermal end member compositions or regroup components as network formers and network modifiers using a component scheme such as that proposed by <ref type="bibr">BOT-~INGA and WEILL (1972)</ref>. Another possible approach would be to identify a principal component common to each bulk composition examined, in order to promote comparison of results between bulk compositions of the same system. The component Si02 accounts for &gt;98% of the com~sition~ variance produced by thermal diffusion in MORB and MHA and between 79% and 95% of the variance observed for compositions B' and B. We adopt SiOz as our reference component, however, in the case of ZM-96 and ZM-99 its mole fraction is expressed in terms of the components Fa-Lc-Q (to permit compa~~n with Roedder's phase diagram), while simple oxide components are used in the description of natural silicate liquids (i.e. ZM-71; MHA and ZM-98; MORB).</p><p>The MORB system shows liquid immi~ibility <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(DIXON and RUTHERFORD, 1980)</ref> at extreme iron enrichment, therefore, it is inappropriate to treat natural melts as ideal solutions. This is also abundantly clear for the melts in the FaLcQ system. The simplest mixing model which can account for immiscibility will be that given by Eqn. ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>) for a regular symmetric solution. The thermal effusion energy balance Eqn. ( <ref type="formula">19</ref>) for a regular symmetric solution can be rewritten as RT/2x,x2 = WG -@dT/ZTdx,.</p><p>(20)</p><p>If the energy parameters IIi, and p are assumed independent of temperature and composition, Eqn. ( <ref type="formula">20</ref>) is an equation for a straight line and thus a plot of R T/ 2x1~2 against dT/tTdx, derived from any T-X Soret profile will give Q: as the slope and W, as the y-intercept. Because only two points on the experimental array at which x, T, and &amp;jdTare known are required to solve uniquely for fi and W, the degree of linearity of a muIti~int data plot provides a measure of the extent to which the regular symmetric solution model gives an adequate description of the experimental observations. It also provides a test of the compositional range over which @ can be reasonably assumed constant.</p><p>In the mole fraction of component 1 is xsie and that for component 2 given by ( 1 -Xsioz). The test plots of Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref> show crudely linear trends for each data array (regression coef. = .58-.88). Values of Q&amp;o2 derived from the slope and W, from the .pintercept are given in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. Critical temperatures implied by the model values of WC are also listed in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. The results of this exercise show that the regular symmetric solution model provides a reasonable description of the T-X relationships for ZM-96. That is, the heat of transport for SiOz is negative as required, since silica concentrates at the hot end of the temperature gradient. Furthermore, the critical temperature of 1253°C implied by ct;; is reasonable given the consolute temperatures reported by <ref type="bibr">ROEDDER (195 1. 1979</ref>) (see also Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6a</ref>). For the remaining experimental Soret arrays (ZM-99. MORB, MHA), however, the regular symmetric solution model is a poor description of the results, yielding not only positive values of Q&amp; but values of WG that imply critical temperatures in excess of the actual temperatures of the experiments (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</p><p>The failure of the regular symmetric binary solution model in the cases of ZM-99, MORB and MHA suggests that a more complex model is necessary to provide a description of our experimental thermal diffusion T-X profiles. For example, as has been suggested by <ref type="bibr">HALLER el al. ( 1974)</ref>. we might adapt our binary component scheme so that deviations from ideality are symmetrically disposed about the binary join. Alternatively, we might consider a solution model which can account for asymmetry in the chemical potentialcomposition relations. Certainly in the case of the system FaLcQ there is some justification for considering a more complex solution model as the solvus is not symmetrically disposed along the Fa-silica join. Further it might be argued that a more realistic treatment of thermal diffusion in the system FaLcQ, particularly in the case of ZM-96, requires at least a 3-component solution model: yet, even so an asymmetric model would be necessary to account for the asymmetry of the solvus in the interior of this system.</p><p>Asymmetric mixing behavior can be expressed for a regular binary solution by introducing two mixing energy parameters. U'G, and    <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">10a</ref> and lob). This ~o~es~nden~ is extremely encouraging considering the binary treatment of the data, particularly in the case of ZM-96 for which at least a small ternary component should be considered.</p><p>The critical temperatures calculated for MORB ( 1456°C) and MHA (I 323'C) appear high if compared with the experimental data of DIXON and RUTIIER-FORD ( 1980) fix. T, = IO 10°C). however, it should be noted that stable immiscibility was encountered by these authors only after liquids had evolved to extreme Fe enrichment rather unlike the bulk compositions of MORB and MHA. Presumably, the Soret arrays for MORB and MHA are reflecting the nature of the silicate liquid solvus in a different region of composition space where immiscibility may well occur at high temperatures but is metastable with respect to crystallization. Additional therma diffusion experiments on natural melts are clearly needed at this stage to characterize more fully the shape of the solvus in the natural silicate system. Work along these lines is currently underway.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUDING REMARKS</head><p>In summary the analysis given here shows that Soret diffusion arrays can be used to characterize solution properties of silicate melts as well as yield estimates of the heats of transport. Values of chemical diffusion and thermal diffusion coefficients can be obtained from observations of the rise time and steady state values of Soret fractionation. We show that for our choice of components an asymmetric regular solution model fits the experimental data very well, in contrast to the ideal or symmetric models. Negative heats of transport for SiO* of 2-7 kcal-mole-' and mixing energy parameters of comparable range are typical. Estimates of interaction energies are also similar in magnitude to those determined by calorimetric <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(NAVROTSKY et al., 1980)</ref> and phase equilibrium <ref type="bibr">(GHIORSO et af. 1983</ref>) data for silicate liquids.</p><p>We treat multicomponent silicate melts as binary solutions because of the striking binary character of Soret separations. However, it is clear that in some cases, such as for ZM-96 (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>), Soret arrays are not binary. A treatment more sophisticated than that presented here wih ultimately be required to account more exactly for thermal diffusion in non-binary solutions. Even so the appropriatenem of various solution models used for the description of these sohnion can be assess&amp; by an approach analogous to that outlined here for binary solutions and need not rely on the successful recovery of the data used to calibrate the solution model. The only requirement is that the experimental T-X data set have a number of observations equal to or in excess of the number of chara$erization parameters. Thermal diffusion studies of simple (binary) silicate systems are clearly needed at this stage to test further the approach outlined above and to develop a basis for extending the analysis to chemzally more complex systems.</p><p>Finally we wish to emphasize the utility of thermal diffusion studies as a complement to calorimetry and phase equilibrium studies. Thermal diffusion @es silicate liquids the opportunity to exhibit the peeuharities of the r-X topography of their free energy surface.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 shows the compositional separation which is produced by thermal diffusion in two naturally occurring volcanic liquids: a mid-ocean ridge basalt (MORB) from the Oceanographer Fracture Zone (OFZ-P22 Of WALKER et al., 1979: exp't ZM-98) and an andesite from Mt. Hood (MHA; exp't ZM-7 I). The separation is displayed on the ternary composition plot 01-(An + Di)-Q with the liquidus crystal cosaturation curves of WALKER et al. (1979) at lower temperatures than those of the experiments shown for reference. The differentiation shown by these compositions is quite spectacular in a petrologic context, exceeding the range of coeval liquids in the respective suites in which the starting composition occurs. However, although the separations may be spectacular in the laboratory, they appear in detail to be responsible for few of the variations seen in natural rock suites (WALKER and DE-LONG, 1982; LESHER, 1985).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. I. Projection of experimental Soret arrays ZM-98 (MORB) and ZM-71 (MHA) from nonnative albite and orthoclase on to the ternary plane represented by normative olivine (Ol)-[anorthite(An) + diopside(Di)]quartz(Q) (algorithm for projection taken from WALKER er al.. 1979).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 2. Temperature/distance versus composition plots comparing Soret fractionation of MORB [ZM-98 (264 h) and ZM-IO1 (52 h)] and MHA [ZM-71 (168 h) and ZM-70 (46 h)].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 4. Plot of -log,&amp;sio, versI(s butk silica content (wt.%) of MORB, MHA and 3T determined from Soret rise time analysis. The stipled band shows the compositional dependence of I&amp; at 13OOT measured by WATSON (1982) in granite-basalt interdiffision experiments. Estimates of Dsiol by POWELL ef al. (I 980) from crystal/liquid boundary layer diffusion studies in basaItic liquids at IO%-I 150°C are also indicated.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 5. Plots showing the composition of starting material for thermal diffusion experiments (5a) and experimental Soret arrays ZM-96 and ZM-99 (5b) in the system FeSiO&amp;AISi20~-SiOl (FaLcQ). (Phase topology after ROEDDER, 195 I)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>FIG. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>FIG. 6. Silica variation (in mole fraction) with temperature produced by thermal diffusion in compositions FaLcQ-B (ZM-99), FaLcQ-B' (ZM-96), MORB (ZM-98), and MHA (ZM-7 1). Projection of low-T immiscibility field along the trajectory of the ZM-96 and ZM-99 arrays shown in Fig. 6a. Xsie computed in terms of the components Fa-Lc-Q for ZM-99 and ZM-96. xsiol for MORE% and MI-IA exprewd in terms of simple oxides.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>total mass flux of component ; resulting from temperature and chemical potential imbalances becomes: n ! Ji = -&amp;V In T .-C L,,V(fi, --urn! (8) / I</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>( I) in terms of the heat of transport and chemical potential of component 1, ~som = dx,lx,xzdT = -QY/[Tx,(~~,l~,)~.,4 (15) For an ideal binary solution the steady state Soret coefficient can be written a~orr, = d.r,fx,xzdT = -@lRT2,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(e.g. GUGGENHEIM, 19671, p, = pp + RT In x, + U'&amp;. (17) Differentiating ( 17) with respect to component 1 gives @plih)T.Theoretical Soret arrays for ideal (Figs. 7a, b) and regular (Figs. 7c, d) binary solutions (see text for discussion). Calculated binodal (short dash) and spinodal (long dash) surfaces shown in Fig. 7d.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 8. Test plots for regular symmetric binary solution behavior governed by Eqn. (20). The slope gives -Q: and the pintercept yields W,, both in kc&amp;-mole-'. Components 1 is SiOz. xm computed in terms of the components Fa-Lc-Q for ZM-99 and ZM-96. xsio2 for MORB (ZM-98) and MHA (ZM-7 I ) expressed in terms of simple oxides.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Wti,. The chemical po-tential of component .l can be expressed (Guc;C;E%- HEIM, 1967)    Differentiating cc, with respect to x, and substituting for (&amp;,/ax,),.involves three unknown parameters, B;;,, U,,, and fl which, if assumed constant. can be determined by the method of least-squares from the experimental T-X Soret profiles. This has been done for MORB, MHA, ZM-96 and ZM-99 and the results presented in Table2. The quality of the fit of the experimental data to an asymmetric solution model is reported as the sum of residuals squared in Table2. The improvement in the fit of the asymmetric model to the experimental data can be shown graphically by taking the regression values of Q: . thus reducing by one the unknown parameters in Eqn. (32), and by rearranging (22) to give an expression for a straight line with I+',, as the slope and U,z as the J.-intercept. These plots are shown in Fig.9. Compared to the symmetric model test plots of Fig.8. those for the asymmetric model yields a much closer fit to a straight line (regression coef. &gt; .98). Furthermore. not only does the asymmetric model provide a better tit to our data (required by the introduction of an additional fitting parameter), but the heats of transfer for SiOz we calculated are negative (-2.3 to -7.5 kcal-mole-') as required by any proposed model. Interaction energies range between -.39 and 8.10 kcal-mole-' and are reasonable values based on the range reported from calorimetric(NAVROTSKY et ul., 1980)  and phase equilibrium<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(GHIORSO et al.. 1983</ref>) data for silicate liquids.In Fig.10theoretical Soret profiles (shown by +! calculated using interaction energies and heats of transport derived by least-squares are compared directly with the experimental profiles (squares) and provide another visual demonstration of the quality of</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>FIG. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>FIG. 9. Graphical test of the fit of the experimentaf data to a regular asymmetric solution model based on Eqn. (22). Component 1 is SOI. Vahres for the heat of transport of ISO2 taken from Table 2. The slope gives ES',, and y-intercept yields Wa in kcal-mole-'. xSo2 computed in terms of the com~nents Fa-Lc-Q for ZM-99 and ZM-96. xsie for MORB (ZM-98) and MHA (ZM-7 1) expressed in terms of simple oxides.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>FIG. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>FIG. 10. Comparison plots of experimental Soret arrays and theoretical arrays assuming ideat mixing and asymmetric mixing behavior. Calcuhtted 2-liquid fields predicted by the asymmetric solution model parameters given in TabIe 2. Critical temperatoms aLong the compositional trajectory of ZM-96 and ZM-99 as determined by ROEDDER (1979) are indicated by arrows in Figs. IOa, b. xsio2 computed in terms of the components Fa-I_c-Q for ZM-99 and ZM-96. xm for MORB (ZM-98) and NHA (ZM-71) expressed in terms of simple oxides.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>e. hot VS. cold, deportment of arrays radial to the component SiOz for experiments on MORB and MHA are analogous. (+Ab+Or) suggest that the Soret process operates on but as might Ix expected the magnitude of separation liquid structural species of the network-former/net-is reduced as run time is shortened. The difference in</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>TABLE 18</cell><cell cols="4">: EXFEFJMEWML</cell><cell cols="4">PAF.AXETERS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">SAMPLE</cell><cell>RUN TIBT</cell><cell>CAFWJLE LENnIl</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">l % ot</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EW.</cell><cell>#</cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell>(HRS.) --</cell><cell>(MBCH)</cell><cell>ATo -</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">="OT°C</cell><cell cols="3">QIJLD°C</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">%EAN</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">"_T3.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ZN-101</cell><cell>OR-PZZ</cell><cell></cell><cell>52</cell><cell>5. 0</cell><cell>300</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1650</cell><cell></cell><cell>1350</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1500</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">84.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ZN-98</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">OFZ-P2:</cell><cell>264</cell><cell>5.0</cell><cell>300</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1650</cell><cell></cell><cell>1350</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1500</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>&gt;99.e</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zn-70</cell><cell></cell><cell>MlLA-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>46</cell><cell>3. ?</cell><cell>2 7c</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1520</cell><cell></cell><cell>1250</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1385</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>bi.0</cell><cell></cell><cell>!</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zn-71</cell><cell></cell><cell>MHA-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>168</cell><cell>3.5</cell><cell>2711</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1550</cell><cell></cell><cell>1280</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1415</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>97."</cell><cell></cell><cell>'</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>m-96</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">FaLCU-B'</cell><cell>ili)</cell><cell>5.5</cell><cell>300</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1650</cell><cell></cell><cell>!350</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1500</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">80.r:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zn-99</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">FILCQ-B</cell><cell>207</cell><cell>5.0</cell><cell>300</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1650</cell><cell></cell><cell>11. 1350</cell><cell>IT'</cell><cell>"1'</cell><cell>IT'</cell><cell>"1 1500 6"'</cell><cell>"1'</cell><cell>TI'</cell><cell>11' .99.0 "1</cell><cell>0"'</cell><cell>6"'</cell><cell>8"</cell><cell>b-0</cell><cell>9"</cell><cell>9"</cell><cell>9"</cell><cell>9"</cell><cell>so</cell><cell>$0</cell><cell>9"'</cell><cell>1"</cell><cell>to</cell><cell>co</cell><cell>LO'</cell><cell>8"</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">'Parceot~e</cell><cell>of</cell><cell>steady</cell><cell>st.te</cell><cell cols="4">arparation calculated</cell><cell cols="2">by eq.</cell><cell cols="2">(2).</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">+Percenrqe</cell><cell cols="3">of capposicion~l</cell><cell>varimce</cell><cell cols="2">reduced</cell><cell cols="3">by SiO2;</cell><cell cols="2">multiple</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>linear</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">regression</cell><cell cols="2">perfamed</cell><cell cols="2">by Fortran</cell><cell>progrlrm</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">STRING,</cell><cell cols="2">courtesy</cell><cell cols="7">of B. McIntyre,</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">L-M!.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">overall separation of initially homogeneous MORB</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">0 96 liquid after 52 h and 264 h is modest, suggesting that "'(6 0.06 "'IS 0 vs "'LL "'EL "'(9 0.05 0 "C 0 o?. 0.1 only a few days are required to achieve near steady</cell><cell>0 ""1</cell><cell>"11"</cell><cell>ro,+o,</cell><cell></cell><cell>"'1</cell><cell></cell><cell>"'Z</cell><cell></cell><cell>0"</cell><cell>"'21</cell><cell></cell><cell>"'91</cell><cell>0 LZ</cell><cell></cell><cell>"'SC</cell><cell></cell><cell>0 "5</cell><cell></cell><cell>"'59</cell><cell></cell><cell>"'"8</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>0 ""1</cell><cell>.onv</cell><cell>r01rg</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">state Soret separation of this mafic liquid under the</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">present experimental conditions. In contrast, there are</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">marked differences in the magnitude of Soret separa-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">tion of MHA after 46 h and 168 h indicating that</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">greater time is necessary to reach steady state for an-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>desitic liquid.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgernenrs</head><p>-We thank <rs type="person">P. Candela</rs>, t. M. Stolper. and <rs type="person">J. B. Thompson</rs> for their comments at various early stages of this work and <rs type="person">Mark Ghiarso</rs> and <rs type="person">Allen Glazner</rs> for constructive reviews. <rs type="person">C. Lesher</rs> greatfully acknowledges support from the <rs type="funder">Committee on Experimental Geology and Geophysics of Harvard University</rs>. Compositions Band B' were synthesized by <rs type="person">D. Walker</rs> while a guest in Stolper's lab under the <rs type="grantName">Fairchild Scholar program</rs> at <rs type="affiliation">Cal Tech</rs>. This work was also supported by a grant from the <rs type="funder">Department of Energy</rs> to <rs type="person">L-DGO</rs> (Grant <rs type="grantNumber">DE-FGCQ-84ER 13287</rs>) and by grants from the <rs type="funder">National Science Foundation</rs> {Grants <rs type="grantNumber">OCEBS-11017</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">EARgS-13693</rs>). Thii is Lament-Doherty contribution #<rs type="grantNumber">3990</rs></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_dByKjtr">
					<orgName type="grant-name">Fairchild Scholar program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_C3dRnhQ">
					<idno type="grant-number">DE-FGCQ-84ER 13287</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Jsxwyrq">
					<idno type="grant-number">OCEBS-11017</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_J9jwtGR">
					<idno type="grant-number">EARgS-13693</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_H4c2mRB">
					<idno type="grant-number">3990</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscous flow in silica and binary liquid silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Edckris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>O'm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mackenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. Furuduv Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1734" to="1748" />
			<date type="published" when="1955">1955</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of liquid silicates: partial molar volumes and expansivities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bockris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>O'm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tomlinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. Faraday Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The viscosity of magmatic silicate liquids: a model for calculation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bo~inga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. J. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">273</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="438" to="475" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">(I 960) Apparatus for phase equilibrium measurements at pressures up to 50 kilobars and temperatures up to 1750 C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>England</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geoph:s. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="748" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The origin of immiscibility in silicate solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Charles R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Whys. Chem. Glasses</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Degroot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">L &apos;E&apos;cf Soref. North Holland. Amsterdam</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>I 947</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Non-equilibrium Thermodynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Degroot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mazur P</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
			<pubPlace>North Holland. Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">(195 1) The Thermodynamics of the Steudy-State</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Denbigh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Methuen, London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The heat of transfer in binary regular solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Denbigh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. Faraday Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="1952">1952</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plagiogranites as late-stage immiscible liquids in ophiolites and mid-ocean ridge suites: an experimental study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rutherford M</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Gibbs free energy of mixing of natural silicate liquids; an expanded regular solution ap proximation for the calculation of magmatic intensive variables</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ghiorso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S E</forename><surname>Carmichael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rivers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sack R. 0</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Min. Pet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Guggenheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thermo&amp;namics. North Holland</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">390</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>I 967</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Micibility gaps in alkali-silicate binaries-data and thermodynamic implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Blackburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Simmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Cerm. Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in natural silicate melts: A critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics of Mugmatic Processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hargraves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton U. Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="418" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>I 980</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonequilibrium Thermodvnamics in Biophvsics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Katchauky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Curran P</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Harvard U. Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">248</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge. MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Thermal diffusion in silicate liauids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">189</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>&apos;Harvard University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermochemistry of glasses and liquids in the system CaMgSizOn-CaAl$iZOs-NaAlSi108. Si02-CaAl&amp;011-NaAlSitOp and SiO*-AlgO</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Navrotsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hon R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim C&apos;osmochm .-lcla</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1409" to="1423" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cation diffusion in basaltic melts: measurements from c.ystal-liquid boundary layers in controlled cooling experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Powell M</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Walker D</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Grove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hays</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gecl. Sot. Amer. Abstr. Prog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">502</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermodynamic properties of minerals and related substances at 298. I5 K and I bar (IO pascals) pressure and at higher temperatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Robie R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hemingway B</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">U.S. Geol. Surver. &amp;r/l. 1452</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">(195 I) Low temperature liquid immiscibility in the svstem K-O-FeO-A1701-SiO</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Roedder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Min</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="282" to="286" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Silicate liquid immiscibility in magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Roed~er</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Evolution Q{ Igneous Rocks-F$ieth Anniversur~ Perspectives</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yoder</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton. New Jersey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton U. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1579">1579</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="58" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">) Diffusion and Heat Flow in Liquids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J V</forename><surname>Tyrrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Butterworths. London</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">329</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1961">196 1</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Soret separation of MORB magma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Delong S</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mm. Pet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abyssal tholeiites from the Oceanographic Fracture Zone II, phase equilibria and mixing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Walker</forename><forename type="middle">D .</forename><surname>Shibata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Delong S</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Min. Pet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">(198 I) Soret separation of lunar liquid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Walker</forename><forename type="middle">D . E</forename><surname>Lesher C</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hays</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Lunar Planet. Sci. Con/Y 12th</title>
		<meeting>Lunar Planet. Sci. Con/Y 12th</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="991" to="999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basalt contamination by continental crust: some experiments and models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contnb. Min. Pet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Wisniewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Staniszewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Szymanik R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Thermodynamic.7 c?fNonequilibn&apos;um Processes</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Reidel Pub., Mass</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">274</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
