<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts: II. Multicomponent diffusion in CaO-A1,03-SiO, at 1500°C and 1 GPa</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yan</forename><surname>Liang, ','</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of the Geophysical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>60637</postCode>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country>USA &apos;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>12180</postCode>
									<settlement>Troy</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Richter,'</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of the Geophysical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>60637</postCode>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country>USA &apos;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>12180</postCode>
									<settlement>Troy</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bruce Watson'</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of the Geophysical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>60637</postCode>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country>USA &apos;</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>12180</postCode>
									<settlement>Troy</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts: II. Multicomponent diffusion in CaO-A1,03-SiO, at 1500°C and 1 GPa</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6402EDBE92A11041EE6960B8E6766DDC</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received January 24, 1996; accepted in revised form October 3, 1996</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemical diffusion profiles in molten CaO-A1203-Si02</head><p>have been measured over a large range of compositions at 1500°C and 1 GPa. The diffusion profiles have been inverted for effective binary diffusion coefficients (EBDCs) and for the chemical diffusion matrix. The EBDCs are shown to depend strongly on both composition and direction of diffusion in composition space. The dependence of EBDCs on direction in composition space, which for the system studied here can be as large as a factor of seven, severely limits the applicability of EBDCs to interdiffusion in any direction other than the one used to derive the EBDCs.</p><p>The chemical diffusion matrix for molten CaO-A1203-Si02 was determined using diffusion profiles from two or three mutually orthogonal diffusion couples in the ternary composition space. All features of the diffusion profiles shown in this work can be reproduced by representing the chemical fluxes in the three-component system as a linear combination of concentration gradients via a 2 x 2 diffusion matrix. Chemical diffusion in molten CaO-A1203-Si02</p><p>shows clear evidence of strong diffusive coupling among the components. This can be seen in the uphill diffusion profiles of components that were initially uniform, in the fact that the apparent rate of diffusion of some components is a strong function of direction in composition space, and most quantitatively in the magnitude of off-diagonal elements of the diffusion matrix relative to the magnitude of the diagonal elements. SiO,, for example, is found to be strongly coupled with CaO in relatively silicic melts, whereas A1203 is strongly coupled with CaO in less silicic melts. Furthermore, the coupling of CaO with either A120, or Si02 reverses sign between more and less polymerized compositions.</p><p>Interdiffusion profiles in natural melts have numerous features that suggest similar coupling between A1203 and CaO and between Si02 and CaO. Yes no yes no no no 120 120 120 120 120 120 overturning fingering overturning no no no CD32 711 no 120 fingering CD32 t 6/l no 120 fingering Et 4 II2 IlO no 4 3/7 no z no CD41 4 4n no 60 "0 CD41 4 Ii5 no 60 no CD42 4 CD42 4 :: "0 120 no no 120 no CD42 4 4R no 120 no CD42 12/13* no no no *0 no IlO no 30 15 120 60 60 18 18 II0 no fingering no no no no CD9 3 10/B no 18 no CD10 2 17llO no ;0 0 no CD10 2 16/14 no no CD11 2 2/12 "0 42 "0 CD11 2 5115 no 42</p><p>"0 *Number of holes in a capsule; tnot used to invert a diffusion matrix due to a large offset at the interface of the diffusion couple; *not analyzed due to crystallization of gehlenite or anorthite in the lower half of the diffusion couple.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Chemical diffusion involves mass fluxes driven by chemical potential gradients and is an essential transport mechanism for many geological processes, such as crystal growth and dissolution, and magma contamination and mixing. In many cases, chemical diffusion plays a major role in determining the existence and style of other large-scale transport phenomena such as convection in magma chambers. Crystal growth or dissolution, for example, require material to diffuse into or out of the compositional boundary layers surrounding the crystal (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bowen, 1921;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Lasaga, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">Harrison and</ref><ref type="bibr">Watson, 1983, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kuo and Kirkpatrick, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr">Brearley and Scarf, 1986;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Zhang et al., 1989)</ref>. Although the diffusion of chemical species in a magma body is generally regarded as being too slow to cause significant compositional changes over large distances, it can in fact play an important role in magma mixing in that differences in the diffusion rate of heat and chemical components in a silicate melt are responsible for the vigor and style of double-diffusive convection in magma chambers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Huppert and Sparks, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Sparks et al., 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Turner, 1985)</ref>. A special case of isothermal double-diffusive convection driven by diffusive coupling among components in a silicate melt was recently demonstrated experimentally by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Liang et al. ( 1994)</ref> and illustrates how even subtle features of chemical diffusion can have large-scale implications. Understanding the diffusive properties of silicate melts has become an increasingly important part of quantitatively characterizing the origin, evolution, and differentiation of igneous rocks. In the Earth sciences, effective binary diffusion coefficients (EBDC, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cooper, 1968</ref>) have commonly been used to describe chemical diffusion in molten silicates (see reviews by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hofmann, 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">Watson and Baker, 1991)</ref>. The multicomponent melt is treated as a pseudobinary system in which all components other than the one of interest are taken together as the second component. The flux of the component of interest is then assumed to obey a relation of the form where J, , VCi , and Df: are the flux, concentration gradient, and effective binary diffusion coefficient for component i, respectively.</p><p>While this approach has the obvious appeal of simplicity, it is, in detail, seriously flawed in that the EBDCs depend not only on melt composition and thermodynamic state but also on the direction of diffusion in composition space. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Cooper ( 1968)</ref> showed that this directional dependence is a general property of EBDCs. In a later section we will report on experimental results for multicomponent diffusion in molten CaO-A1203-Si02 that show that the EBDC for Si02 differs by almost an order of magnitude depending on whether the principal counterdiffusing component is CaO or A1203. These experiments also show the pervasiveness of uphill diffusion (flux of a component in a direction opposite to its concentration gradient), an effect that cannot be described by the effective binary diffusion representation.</p><p>A more general representation of multicomponent diffusive fluxes in a mass-fixed frame of reference (barycentric) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">n-1 Ji = -C DzVCj (2) ,=I</formula><p>where n is the number of components in the system and the D$ values are multicomponent diffusion coefficients, independent of concentration gradients (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Onsager, 1945;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">de Groot and Mazur, 1962;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Haase, 1969)</ref>. The summation in Eqn. 2 is over only n -1 components because the concentration of the n th component can itself always be written in terms of a linear combination of the other n -1 components. The dependent variable, component n, is identified by the superscript in 0;. The matrix of diffusion coefficients D$ is called the diffusion matrix, designated as <ref type="bibr">[D]</ref> . The directional dependence of chemical fluxes and uphill diffusion that pose such a problem for an effective binary diffusion representation are now simply a reflection of diffusive coupling contained in <ref type="bibr">[D]</ref> . The chemical diffusion matrix <ref type="bibr">[D]</ref> can be written as the product of a kinetic matrix <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref> (often referred to as the phenomenological matrix) and a thermodynamic matrix [G] (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">de Groot and Mazur, 1962;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Haase, 1969;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gupta and Cooper, 197 1)</ref> PI = <ref type="bibr">[Ll*[Gl (3)</ref> where the elements of <ref type="bibr">[G]</ref> are functions of the derivatives of activity with respect to concentration, and the elements of <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref>, according to empirical models (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Darken, 1948;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cooper, 1965;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Manning, 1970;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Lasaga, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">Richter, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Liang, 1994)</ref>, are functions of concentration, partial molar volume, and self diffusion coefficients of the components in the system. For nonideal solution properties, which are a characteristic of silicate melts, <ref type="bibr">[G]</ref> takes into account the fact that the driving force for chemical diffusion is gradients in chemical potential, not concentration. <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref> or <ref type="bibr">[G]</ref> or a combination of them can contribute significantly to the offdiagonal terms of <ref type="bibr">[D]</ref> (see <ref type="bibr">Liang, 1994, for details)</ref>.</p><p>There are only a limited number of experimental determinations of the diffusion matrix for silicate melts and glasses (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Varshneya and Cooper, 1972;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al., 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kubicki et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kress and Ghiorso, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr">Chakraborty et al., 1995a)</ref>. Diffusion matrices were determined by Varshneya and <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Cooper (1972)</ref> for the system K20-SrO-Si02, and by <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. (1977)</ref> for the system CaO-Al&amp;-SiOz at 40 wt% CaO, 20% A1203, and 40% SiOz. Recent studies of the diffusion matrix in more geologically relevant systems (melts along the join CaMgSi206-CaA12Si208 by <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kubicki et al., 1990</ref>; melts in MgO-Al@-Si02</p><p>and CaO-MgO-A1203-Si02 by <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kress and Ghiorso, 1993</ref>; and melts in K20-A1203-Si02 by <ref type="bibr">Chakraborty et al., 1995a)</ref> have met with only limited success. As pointed out by <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Zhang ( 1993)</ref>, the diffusion matrices obtained by <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kubicki et al. (1990)</ref> have complex eigenvalues and thus do not satisfy the constraint from nonequilibrium thermodynamics that all eigenvalues must be real (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">de Groot and Mazur, 1962;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Haase, 1969)</ref>. The diffusion matrices obtained by <ref type="bibr">Kress and Ghi-orso ( 1993 )</ref> are problematic because many of their published diffusion profiles have features that cannot be explained by any linear diffusion matrix of the form given by Eqn. 2, and they suggest that perhaps this representation is not applicable to the melts used in their study. The diffusion matrices reported by <ref type="bibr">Chakraborty et al. (1995a)</ref> were obtained from diffusion experiments run in only one direction in composition space, even though two of the three diffusion couples used in their study did intersect at a common composition. It is our experience with both laboratory experiments and numerical simulations that the off-diagonal elements of the diffusion matrix are poorly resolved unless one simultaneously inverts diffusion profiles in different directions in composition space <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Liang, 1994)</ref>.</p><p>In order to establish a systematic way to study multicomponent diffusion in silicate melts and to better understand the nature and cause of diffusive coupling, chemical diffusion experiments were conducted in different compositions and compositional directions in molten CaO-A1203-Si02 at 1500°C and 1 GPa. The concentration profiles were inverted for diffusion matrices as defined by Eqn. 2. The diffusion profiles presented in subsequent sections illustrate the inherent complexity of chemical diffusion in a silicate melt. Diffusive coupling among components is most obvious in experiments where components with no initial gradient are seen to have uphill flux that with time results in a characteristic spatially nonuniform distribution. Diffusive coupling is also responsible for the effective binary diffusivity of a component being dependent on the direction of diffusion in composition space. Diffusive coupling is made quantitative by inverting the diffusion profiles to calculate the diffusion matrix [D] and noting the relative size of off-diagonal to diagonal elements. In the case of SiOz, for example, its flux is often found to be more dependent on gradients in CaO than on gradients of SiO: itself. Because the diffusion matrix <ref type="bibr">[D]</ref> for molten CaO-A1203-Si02 has been determined at a number of compositions, the dependence of [D] on composition can be explored.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">EXPERIMENTAL METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">General Strategy</head><p>The experimental study of chemical diffusion in molten silicates involves juxtaposing two melts of different compositions in a container placed in a high temperature (and sometimes high pressure) furnace. Such chemical diffusion experiments are usually designed to follow a particular direction in composition space, for example, along the diopside-anorthite join, rhyolite-dacite join, or rhyolitebasalt join (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bowen, 1921;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Medford, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Yoder, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Smith, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Watson, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baker, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baker, , 1991;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Koyaguchi, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lesher, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">van der Laan et al., 1994</ref>). An experiment run in a single direction in composition space can be used to determine an EBDC, but as we show below, the resulting EBDC is strictly speaking only relevant to the particular experiment from which it was determined.</p><p>A single-direction chemical diffusion experiment can in principle also be used to invert for the full set of chemical diffusion coefficients (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Schut and Cooper, 1982)</ref>, but the derived diffusion matrix is extremely sensitive to both the quality of the measured concentration profiles and the specific inversion method used <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Liang, 1994)</ref>. Monte Carlo simulations using numerically generated diffusion profiles, to which Gaussian noise representing analytical errors has been added, show that the relative errors of the inverted elements of the diffusion matrix from single-direction runs are typically 2 to 6 times greater than when data of equal quality from two or three different directions are used <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Liang, 1994)</ref>. In general, an accurate estimate of the diffusion matrix in an n component system requires at least n -1 different diffusion couples because there are (n -1)' unknowns in the diffusion matrix and each diffusion couple has only n -1 independent concentration profiles <ref type="bibr">(Gupta and Cooper,</ref><ref type="bibr">197 1)</ref>. Ideally, one should select a set of diffusion experiments such that the n -1 diffusion couples not only cross at the composition point of interest but also are orthogonal to each other in the eigenspace of the diffusion matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Liang, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Trial and Spera, 1994)</ref>. But, since the diffusion matrix, and thus the eigenspace, is not known a priori, the n -1 (or n) directions are often chosen so that one of the components is constant along each of the directions (e.g., <ref type="bibr">Kirkaldy and Young, 1987, page 179)</ref>. Several other factors are important in determining the best compositions to juxtapose in a given diffusion experiment. From the point of view of accurately measuring concentration changes along a diffusion profile, one would want to choose diffusion couples that have large concentration differences, and thus large signal to analytical noise ratios. This, however, is limited by the compositional dependence of the diffusion matrix, which poses real difficulties in terms of determining the diffusion matrix corresponding to a single composition. Hence, the compositions used to make diffusion couples are usually a compromise between concentration differences large enough to allow for accurate measurement but small enough to minimize the compositional dependence of the diffusion matrix. Stability with respect to convection is another crucial factor, given the possibility of isothermal double-diffusion convection that can occur even when the lower density melt is placed above the more dense one <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(McDougall, 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">Turner, 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Liang et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Liang, 1995)</ref>. The difficulty here is that predicting convectively stable directions requires knowledge of the diffusion matrix, which is unknown at the outset. As a result, some of the initial experiments designed for the purpose of determining the diffusion matrix will prove unsuitable because of convection. 2-D X-ray concentration maps of the diffusion couples (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Liang et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Liang, 1995)</ref> allowed easy identification of the effects of convection. It is often possible to obtain stable chemical diffusion runs in convectively unstable directions by using short run durations. The use of smaller diameter cylindrical capsules was also helpful in retarding the onset of convection (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Liang, 1994</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Liang, , 1995, ,</ref> for details).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Materials and Methods</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the compositions in the ternary system CaO-Al@-Si02 which were used to form the chemical diffusion couples. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> lists the nominal composition and calculated density of each melt. A rather large compositional range was chosen in this study, with CaO varying from 20 to 40 wt%, A1203 from 10 to 25 wt%, and Si02 from 40 to 65 wt%, so that these melts could serve as simple analogs to terrestrial melts of basaltic (low SiOz) to andesitic (high SiOz) composition.</p><p>Chemical diffusion couples were formed by juxtaposing compositions 317, 7/l, 715, (412, 315, 6/l), (l/2, 6/5), (3/l, 4/7), (2/12, 5/15), (16/14, 17/10), and 1018 (diffusion couples enclosed in parentheses intersect at a common point in composition space). Thus, in most cases the diffusion matrix at a particular composition is derived from the simultaneous inversion of chemical diffusion profiles in two or three directions. The 5 to 10% difference in concentration between the two halves of a diffusion couple is a compromise between reducing the effect of the compositional dependence of the diffusion matrix and maintaining reasonably good analytical resolution of the concentration changes along the diffusion profile.</p><p>The chemical diffusion experiments were carried out in a '/," piston cylinder apparatus at 1500°C and I GPa in much the same way as the self diffusion experiments described in the preceding paper (see Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> and discussion in <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Liang et al., 1996)</ref>. For runs using the four-hole capsule, uniform glass rods were synthesized from starting glass powders in platinum-lined four-hole molybdenum capsules held at 1500°C and 1 GPa for 1 h. The capsules were then cut in half perpendicular to their axis, the exposed surface polished, and chemical diffusion couples assembled by either rotating the half capsules (referred to as "cut and rotate" ) or by joining half capsules from two different synthesis runs (referred to as "switching"). For runs using l-3 hole capsules, a diffusion couple was formed by firmly packing starting glass powders of one composition against another in a predrilled hole (2-3 mm I.D.) in a molybdenum capsule.</p><p>No platinum liner was used in this setup because the exchange between molybdenum sidewall and melts used in this study is negligibly small ( &lt;50 ppm). To start a diffusion experiment, a diffusion  <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996)</ref>. Compositions A to D were not synthesized. Melt densities (in g%m-3) at 1500°C and 1 GPa were calculated using the partial molar volume and compressibility data of <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Lange and Carmichael (1987)</ref>.</p><p>capsule was first pressurized cold to 1 GPa in the piston cylinder apparatus. The temperature was then raised to 1500°C at a rate of -100°C min-' up to 1000 to 1200°C and -150°C min-' to 1500°C. At the end of the run, the capsule was warm quenched (to minimize dilation cracks) following the same procedure used for the self diffusion experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996)</ref>. The quenched capsules were then sectioned longitudinally, polished, and mounted for electron microprobe analysis. Chemical diffusion profiles were measured using a Cameca SX-50 electron microprobe at the University of Chicago. Operating conditions common to all analyses were an accelerating voltage of 15 kV, a beam current of 25 nA, and a beam spot of 5 pm. Long counting time (30 s) were used to achieve high analytical accuracy, because numerical simulations showed that the accuracy of the inverted diffusion matrix is very dependent on the accuracy with which the diffusion profiles are measured. All microprobe analyses were corrected following the PAP procedure <ref type="bibr">(Pouchou and</ref><ref type="bibr">Pichoir, 1988, 1991)</ref> The analytical uncertainties ( ? la) estimated from repeated analysis of hombgeneous starting materials are 0.08-o. 12 wt% for CaO, 0.05-0.08 wt% for A1203, and 0.1 l-0.30 wt% for SiOz. Representative chemical diffusion profiles are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref><ref type="figure">4</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>Diffusion couples in runs CD12 and CD5 were formed by the "cut and rotate" technique (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>). Thus, only two of the four diffusion couples in each capsule were initially gravitationally stable. The rest of the diffusion couples in the four hole capsules were formed by the "switching" technique and there was no initial density inversion in any of these couples. In those couples with initial density inver-sions, convective overturning was always observed. Axisymmetric double-diffusive convection was found in couples juxtaposing compositions 6 and 1, or 7 and 1 when the run durations were greater than 30 min. These convective instabilities are expected based on linear stability theory and have been reported in detail elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Liang et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Liang, 1995)</ref>. Normal chemical diffusion was observed in couples juxtaposing compositions <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">412, 315, 712, 317, 3/l,  4/7,7/5,6/5,2/12,5/15,  16/14, 17110,</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_0">10/8</ref>. In addition, normal chemical diffusion was observed in experiments juxtaposing compositions 6 and 1 for 15 and 30 min. Composition 7 in the couple 3 I7 from run M 105 (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>) was also spiked with 42Ca and 3oSi isotopes. A preliminary account of the effect of chemical concentration gradients on the redistribution of isotopes in this diffusion couple was given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Liang ( 1994)</ref> and a detailed analysis in terms of multicomponent diffusion will be reported elsewhere.</p><p>When diffusion is one-dimensional in an effectively infinite domain starting from an initial step change in composition at the interface, it is customary to plot concentrations against xl&amp;, since the concentration profiles are then invariant in time. Plotting the diffusion profiles in this way allows for a direct comparison among couples with the same endmember compositions but run for different times. It is also the best way to compare the profiles from couples with different endmember compositions.</p><p>Figures <ref type="figure">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref><ref type="figure">4</ref>display diffusion profiles from selected runs listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>. Some interesting features in these diffusion profiles are summarized here: ( 1) uphill diffusion in CaO or A1203 or SiOZ was observed in all but two diffusion couples (3/l and 615, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>); (2) the direction of uphill diffusion in CaO in relatively siliceous melts is opposite that in the less siliceous ones (Figs. 2a, 3a, and 4a); (3) the widths of the diffusive layers, indicated by the two vertical dotted lines in Figs. <ref type="figure">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref><ref type="figure">4</ref>, are different along different compositional directions, with couples showing no uphill diffusion (3/ 1 and 615) having the widest diffusive layer and couples along the initially constant CaO direction having the narrowest diffusive layers (Figs. <ref type="figure">2</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>); (4) diffusion profiles along the initially constant CaO direction are slightly asymmetric, with concentration gradients steeper in the higher SiO, end (Figs. <ref type="figure">2a</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3a</ref>). These features will be discussed first in terms of effective binary diffusion coefficients and later in terms of the relative magnitude and sign of the elements of the diffusion matrix.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Effective Binary Diffusion Coefficients</head><p>One cannot determine the EBDC for a component which shows uphill diffusion (e.g., CaO in Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2a, 3a,</ref> and<ref type="figure">4a</ref>) because in such cases the flux is clearly not proportional to the concentration gradient of the component.</p><p>For those components that do not exhibit uphill diffusion, the EBDCs can be determined according to Eqn 1. The measured EBDCs of SiOZ <ref type="bibr">(D$o,)</ref> are plotted in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> as a function of the inverse of melt viscosity calculated using the parameterized relations given in the preceding paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996)</ref>. The effect of composition can be seen by comparing the EBDCs derived from experiments in the same direction in the composition space but at different average composi-  <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>. Dotted vertical lines marked the approximate zone of diffusion for each element. tions. For example, Dfio2 differs by a factor of 2.5 due to changes in composition as small as 5 wt% (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>). The directional dependence of the EBDCs is quite evident in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>. D~io, in runs with initially uniform (and subsequent uphill diffusion of) CaO are consistently lower than those from couples having initially uniform A&amp;O3 which, in turn, are lower than those from couples exhibiting no uphill diffusion. 050, is about a factor of seven larger in the direction with no uphill diffusion compared to the constant CaO direction. The directional dependence of the EBDC can also be seen in the diffusion profiles shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref><ref type="figure">4</ref>by the obvious differences in the widths of the diffusive layers of a given component depending on the species it counterdiffuses with. Any specific choice for Dfioz in the vicinity of composition A, for example, will be imprecise to the same degree as the SiOl profile in Fig. <ref type="figure">2a</ref> differs from the SiO, profile in Fig. <ref type="figure">2b</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Chemical Diffusion Coefficients</head><p>The one-dimensional chemical diffusion equations with constant diffusion coefficients for a ternary system can be written as (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Onsager, 1945;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">de Groot and Mazur, 1962;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Haase, 1969)</ref> dC1 _ D" d2CI + D3 a2c2 at " ax2 '.</p><p>'.</p><p>-  Since the exact solutions to the ternary chemical diffusion Eqns. 4a-d are known <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Fujita and Gosting, 1956;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kirkaldy, 1958)</ref>, a nonlinear inversion procedure (Levenberg-Marquardt method, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Press et al., 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Liang, 1994)</ref> can be used to invert for the diffusion matrix. The assumptions made for inverting the data to obtain the diffusion matrices are ( 1) diffusion is one-dimensional, (2) elements of the diffusion matrix are locally independent of composition, (3) density variations across a diffusion couple are small so that the one-dimensional diffusion equation can be used with Ci in units of mass fraction and thus Eqn. 4e holds, and (4) errors associated with the measurement of CaO, A1203, and Si02 concentrations are uncorrelated. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> summarizes the diffusion matrix at eight compositions (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) when SiO, is taken as the dependent component. Eight out of eleven new diffusion matrices listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> were obtained from simultaneous inversion of concentration profiles along at least two directions in the composition space, and these are considered the most reliable. The diffusion matrix reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. ( 1977)</ref> and a matrix derived from our inversion of the diffusion profiles of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. (1982)</ref> are also included in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>. The solid curves in Figs. <ref type="figure">2</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref><ref type="figure">4</ref>are diffusion profiles calculated using the new diffusion matrices listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>, and the advantage of a diffusion matrix representation for multicomponent diffusion, instead of an effective binary diffusion representation, is clearly demonstrated by the fit to the data in all directions in composition space.</p><p>The elements of the measured chemical diffusion matrices are plotted as a function of the inverse of the calculated melt viscosity <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996)</ref> in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>, which further illustrates the greater precision of inverting a ternary diffusion matrix using diffusion profiles from at least two directions. The elements of the diffusion matrix obtained from multiple-direction runs (open circles) vary systematically with the inverse of the calculated melt viscosity, whereas those inverted from single-direction experiments (large crossed circles) are more scattered, though they still follow the general trend defined by the former (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>). This is in agreement with our Monte Carlo simulations <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Liang, 1994)</ref> that show that relative errors of the inverted elements of the diffusion matrix using a single-direction run are much larger than those using two-or three-direction experiments. The sources of error for the chemical diffusion coefficients given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> are expected to be similar to those for the self diffusion experiments discussed in the preceding paper (e.g., uncertainties in temperature and pressure measurements, small offset at the interface of diffusion couple, capsule deformation; <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Liang et al., 1996)</ref>. The errors listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> for the averaged diffusion matrices were estimated either from the nonlinear inversion or from the difference in the inverted D, from two duplicate runs as 1 AD, / /2, whichever is larger. The relative 10 errors for the elements of the diffusion matrix around composition 7 are approximately 3% for D sloZ_ cao caO, 18% for Dsiod_ Ca A1ZOi and Df$,,_c,o, and 15% for Df$++03. Estimated relative errors for the diffusion matrices obtained using single direction experiments are 3-53% for the diagonal terms and 20-132% for the off-diagonal ones (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> ) .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Diffusive Coupling and Choice of the Independent Compositions</head><p>The diffusion matrix provides a realistic representation of chemical fluxes, including the effect of diffusive coupling among the components, but it does not lend itself to any simple interpretation of how the flux of a given component depends on gradients of that component and of the other components present. The reason is that for the three-compo-nent system studied here, such an interpretation would require a 3 X 3 matrix specifying how each of the three fluxes depends on each of the three compositional can be stated as 5. Semilogarithm plot of the effective binary diffusion coefficients of SiO, along three directions in composition space vs. the inverse of melt viscosity ( 1500°C and 1 atm) calculated using the parameterized relations given in the preceding paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996)</ref>. The EBDCs for SiOZ were obtained using a nonlinear inversion procedure (Levenberg-Marquardt method, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Press et al., 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Liang, 1994)</ref>, assuming constant diffusivity across the diffusion couple.   <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>). In the discussion that follows we address ii . 6. Semilogarithm plots of the elements of diffusion matrix with SiO, as the dependent variable in CaO-Al@-Si02 at 1500°C and 1 GPa vs. the inverse of the parameterized melt viscosity at 1500°C and 1 atm <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr">1 = CaO, 2 = Al*O?. and 3 = SiOZ)</ref>. Small open symbols represent diffusion coefficients obtained from simultaneous inversion of concentration profiles from two or three compositional directions, whereas large crossed circles are diffusion coefficients obtained using concentration profiles along only one direction in composition space. The large solid circle represents data for composition 14 obtained from the concentrations profiles of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. ( 1982)</ref> at 1500°C and 1 atm. certain features of the diffusion profiles in terms of diffusive coupling among particular components, but it should be understood that this coupling is based on a particular choice of the [D] matrix, and therefore subject to the limitations implicit in relation 5. It is also understood in the following discussion that the term "strong diffusive coupling" refers to the situation when the off-diagonal term ( D$AC, 1 is comparable to or larger than the diagonal term 1 D$AC, ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Liang, 1994)</ref>, where AC, and AC, are the maximum concentration differences for components i and j, respectively, in a diffusion couple. Hence, it is sufficient to compare the diffusion coefficients directly to assess the effect of coupling when the concentration differences are comparable for the components in question.</p><p>The usefulness of choosing a particular component as the dependent variable was discussed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Miller et al. ( 1986)</ref> and is further demonstrated below. The magnitude, and even the sign, of diffusive coupling depends strongly on melt composition. For example, Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows that the magnitude of coupling of A1203 with CaO (D~$'&amp;i.cao) increases by almost a factor of ten from more-siliceous (viscous) melts to less-siliceous ones. A&amp;O3 can be characterized as strongly coupled with CaO in all compositions studied given that the magnitude of the off-diagonal term for A1203 is comparable to, and in the less viscous melts considerably larger than, the diagonal term. Since the off-diagonal term is negative, the effect of CaO gradients is to increase the rate of A&amp;O3 diffusion. The coupling of CaO with A1203 is relatively weak, but the direction of coupling is significant. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>, CaO is negatively coupled with A1203 in melts of more viscous compositions (D~$&amp;,~ &lt; 0), whereas CaO is positively coupled with A&amp;O3 in melts of less viscous compositions ( D~&amp;,O, &gt; 0). This change in the sign of the diffusive coupling between CaO and A1203 is responsible for reversing the directions of uphill diffusion of CaO between more and less viscous melts (see Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3a</ref> and<ref type="figure">4a</ref>).</p><p>As noted earlier, the widths of the diffusive layers of CaO and Si02 are approximately the same in Figs. <ref type="figure">2b,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3b</ref>, and 4b when the gradients of both CaO and Si02 are large. The fact that CaO and SiOz diffuse at more or less the same rate is particularly interesting because the self diffusion of Ca was shown to be more than an order of magnitude faster than that of Si <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996)</ref>. Clearly the flux of SiOz must be strongly coupled to CaO gradients in the sense of increasing the SiOz flux and/or reducing that of CaO. This coupling can be seen most clearly when A1203 is taken as the dependent variable. The diffusion matrix with A&amp;O3 as the dependent composition is calculated using the following relations (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Kirkaldy et al., 1963;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Ziebold and Ogilvie, 1967)</ref>:  Ds~@-cao is almost three times that of the diagonal term D~~~~~io, in more viscous melts, and in being negative will 7c along with its initial and boundary conditions is a standard have the effect of speeding up SiOZ diffusion. This strong uncoupled diffusion equation and has well known analytical coupling of SiOz with CaO is the principal cause for the solutions (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Carslaw and Jaeger, 1959;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Crank, 1975)</ref>. The large variations in the EBDCs of SiO* with direction in eigenvalue hi becomes the diffusion coefficient for the eigencomposition space. SiOZ diffuses much faster, and thus has composition T, . Another advantage of working in the eigensa larger EBDC, when its gradient is opposed by a large pace is that the double-diffusive convection stability problem gradient in CaO. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Liang et al. (1994)</ref> found that it is quite for chemical diffusion involves two uncoupled components helpful to choose A1203 as the dependent variable when with different diffusivity and thus is identical to the classical discussing the fingering instabilities in couple 6/l. theory for thermohaline convection (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Liang, 1995)</ref>. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref> also lists the diffusion matrices taking CaO as the dependent variable. The asymmetry in the Si02 profile along the initially constant CaO directions (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2a, 3a,</ref> and<ref type="figure">4a</ref>) can now be understood in terms of the increase of D&amp;io, with decreasing SiOZ content in the melt. In spite of the apparently large diagonal term D$$_sio,, the width of the diffusive layer of SiOZ was actually smaller along the initially constant CaO direction than along the constant A&amp;O3 or Si02 directions (Fig. <ref type="figure">2a</ref>). This is due to the large positive off-diagonal term D$$.A1203 which when a large A1203 gradient is present, reduces the net flux of SiOZ. To a first approximation one expects that DFio, = D,!&amp;io, _ Dc?O_ s,02 A1203 when SiOZ interdiffuses with only A1203 (along the direction of constant CaO), whereas Dtio, = D~@io, -D &amp;'~&amp;C,O when SiOl interdiffuses with only CaO. This expectation is in reasonably good agreement with the results given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Dcao-cao = D%cao -D%,,o, A1203<label>(</label></formula><p>The eigenvalues and eigendirections in composition space (CaO-A1203 and CaO-SiO*) are listed in Table <ref type="table">5</ref>. Although both the major and minor eigenvalues (A, and XZ, respectively) increase with the decrease of melt viscosity and SiOZ content, their ratios remain approximately the same with hl/Xz -4. Table <ref type="table">5 reveals</ref>  remain approximately the same, whereas the directions of the minor eigenvector reverse their sign between more and less polymerized (i.e., less viscous) melts. The abrupt change in the directions of the minor eigenvector corresponds to the change in the directions of diffusive coupling of CaO with A&amp;O3 and CaO with SiOZ (see Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>) and is likely related to the abrupt change in the mobilities of the network-forming cations Al and Si reported in the preceding paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996)</ref>. Table <ref type="table">5</ref> also reveals that the diffusion couples 3/ 1 and 6/5 are nearly parallel to their major eigenvector directions [tan (a) = -0.5 vs. -0.4 and -0.51, whereas diffusion couples along the constant CaO direction ((Y = 90") are quite close to the minor eigenvector directions (76-104"), explaining the large differences in the EBDC of SiO? observed between these two directions (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Eigenvalues and Eigenvectors</head><p>The diffusion matrices with elements Dt (k = CaO, SiOZ, A1203) listed in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref> are but three of an infinite number of similar 2 x 2 matrices that could be used to characterize chemical diffusion in molten CaO-A1203-SiO*. By similar we mean that all these matrices are related by a simple linear transformation and therefore have the same eigenvalues. Among these matrices there is one of particular interest in that it is a diagonal matrix and thus uncouples the diffusion of the corresponding independent compositions. The diagonal diffusion matrix, designated as [A], can be derived from any of the other 2 X 2 matrices by the linear transformations (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Toor, 1964;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Cullinan, 1965;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Gupta and Cooper, 1971</ref>)</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">T = [B]C, (<label>7a</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">) [Al = [BI[DI[Bl-' (<label>7b</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">)</formula><p>where T is a column vector in the new composition space, C is the vector of independent compositions associated with In several cases, the boundary conditions for the diffusion equation can also be diagonalized via Eqn. 7a. Hence, Eqn.</p><p>The eigendirections listed in Table <ref type="table">5</ref> can be regrouped to form two directional vectors in the ternary composition space (CaO-A1203-SiO*):</p><p>[I, tan (a,), tan (PI)] for the major eigenvector and [ 1, tan ( CQ), tan (&amp;)I for the minor eigenvector. The indices for the major and minor eigendirections were interpreted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chakraborty et al. ( 1995b)</ref> to represent coefficients for the linear homogeneous exchange reactions among the diffusion species. For example, the exchange reactions along the major and minor eigendirections, according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chakraborty et al. ( 1995b)</ref>, can be written as respectively. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chakraborty et al. (1995b)</ref> suggested that any multicomponent diffusion in the ternary melt can be described as a sum of the two uncoupled homogeneous exchange reactions given in Eqns. 9a and b. Strictly speaking, this interpretation is valid only for diffusion along an eigendirection, for only then is the diffusion path a straight line in composition space (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Gupta and Cooper, 1971)</ref>. In all other cases, the diffusion path is "S" shaped and thus not from diffusion matrices with SiO3 as dependent variable, while eigendirections tan@t) and tar@) are calculated from diffusion matrices with Al203 as dependent variable. ZEstimated using the diffusion matrix in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> for <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. (1982)</ref>. @tlculated using data of <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. (1977)</ref>.</p><p>representable by a linear combination of homogeneous reactions. As a final comment, it is worth noting that the composition is restricted to the plane C, + C, + C, = 1; therefore, two-dimensional vectors are sufficient to characterize the eigendirections. For example, either [ 1, tan ( CK, )] or [ 1, tan (PI)] fully specify the major eigendirection, and are related by the fact that tan ( o1 ) + tan (PI) + 1 = 0 (similarly, tan (c+) + tan (&amp;) + 1 = 0, see Table <ref type="table">5</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Comparison with Previous Studies</head><p>Chemical diffusion in the system CaO-A1203-Si02 has been studied previously at 40% CaO, 20% A1203, and 40% SiOr (our composition 14) by <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. (1977)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. ( 1982)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. (1977)</ref> conducted interdiffusion experiments along three compositional directions around composition 14 at 1450-1550°C and 1 atm. They used data from two (intersecting) compositional directions and estimated multicomponent diffusion coefficients via the Boltzmann-Matano method (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Fujita and Gosting, 1956;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kirkaldy, 1957)</ref>. The chemical diffusion coefficients of <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. (1977)</ref>, listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>, have stimulated considerable discussions in the recent geological literature (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Spera and Trial, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kress and Ghiorso, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chakraborty et al., 1995b)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. ( 1982)</ref> conducted similar interdiffusion experiments along four compositional directions, three of which are identical to those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. (1977)</ref>, at 1370-1550°C and 1 atm. Although the primary purpose of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. ( 1982)</ref> was to test empirical models relating chemical diffusion coefficients to self diffusion coefficients and thermodynamic properties of the melt (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Cooper, 1965)</ref>, multicomponent diffusion coefficients can be readily extracted from their published data. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> lists the chemical diffusion coefficients, at 1500°C and 1 atm, obtained by a simultaneous inversion of digitized concentration profiles from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3a</ref>, b, and c of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. (1982)</ref>. Surprisingly, the chemical diffusion coefficients derived from the data of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. ( 1982)</ref> differ substantially from those reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. ( 1977)</ref>   <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). A comparison of the results reported in these two earlier studies reveals a major difference in the concentration profiles along the direction of initially constant CaO-the directions of uphill diffusion in CaO being reversed in the two reports (see Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> of <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al., 1977, and</ref><ref type="bibr">Fig. 3a of Oishi et al. 1982)</ref>. The fact that the diffusion matrices derived from the data of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. (1982)</ref> and the matrix reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. ( 1977)</ref> are very different from each other, together with the fact that our own results are in much better agreement with the matrix derived from the data of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. ( 1982)</ref>, suggests that conclusions regarding the validity of the Onsager reciprocal relations <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Spera and Trial, 1993)</ref> and diffusive coupling <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Chakraborty et al., 1995b)</ref> based on the diffusion matrix of <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Sugawara et al. (1977)</ref> should be viewed with a certain amount of caution.</p><p>Comparing the diffusion matrix of <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. (1982)</ref> at 1 atm and our own at 1 GPa (composition 14) shows that although the diagonal terms of the diffusion matrix between the two sets of data are quite similar (Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>), the extent of diffusive coupling of A1203 with CaO is considerably less at 1 atm than at 1 GPa. Consequently, the major eigenvalue (A,) is slightly larger, and the minor eigenvalue (A,) smaller, at 1 GPa than at 1 atm (Table <ref type="table">5</ref>). In spite of this, the eigenvectors for the diffusion matrix at composition 14 at 1500°C and 1 atm are nearly identical to those at 1500°C and 1 GPa (Table <ref type="table">5</ref>)) suggesting that the eigendirections for diffusion in molten CaO-AlZ03-Si02 are much less sensitive to pressure changes than are the eigenvalues. This is similar to the small temperature dependence of the eigenvectors for the diffusion matrices in I&amp;O-CaO-Si02, K20-SrO-SiO*, and KzO-A1203-Si02 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Engelke, 1972;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Varshneya and Cooper, 1972;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Chakraborty et al., 1995b)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.">Geological Applications</head><p>Many previous chemical diffusion studies have the advantage of having treated more geologically relevant compositions than those used in the present study; but they do have the drawback of having been designed to follow only one  <ref type="figure">7</ref>. Interdiffusion between ' 'felsic" and "mafic" magmas. The initial conditions in panel (a) with AIZO, higher in "mafic" magma than in "felsic" magma resemble the diffusion setup of <ref type="bibr">Koyagushi ( 1989)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baker ( 1990 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">1991)</ref>. The initial conditions in panel (b) are similar to the experimental setup of <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Watson (1982)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lesher ( 1994)</ref>.</p><p>direction in composition space (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bowen, 1921;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Medford, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">Yoder, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Smith, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Watson, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baker, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baker, , 1991;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Koyaguchi, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kubicki et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lesher, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">van der Laan et al., 1994)</ref> and thus an accurate determination of the diffusion matrices for these systems is not possible. Some insight into diffusive coupling in geologically relevant melts can be obtained by using the coupling seen in CaO-A1203-Si02 as a guide. As an example, we consider the coupling behaviors of A&amp;O3 and SiOZ in melts on the CaMgSi206-CaAlZSi208 (Di-An) join, using the chemical diffusion profiles of <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kubicki et al. ( 1990)</ref>. The width of the diffusive layer of SiOl is much less than those of CaO and MgO in the diffusion couple Dis&amp;nZ0-Di&amp;n60 (Figs. 5 and 7 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kubicki et al., 1990)</ref>, whereas the width of diffusive layer of A&amp;O3 is only slightly smaller than those of CaO and MgO in Di80AnZ0-Di40An60 and Di-DimAnbO diffusion couples (Figs. 7 and 8 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Kubicki et al., 1990)</ref>. This suggests that A1203 is moderately to strongly coupled with CaO and/or MgO (DA1,03_ca0 &lt; 0 and/or DA1203.M~0 &lt; 0) while SiOZ is only weakly coupled with CaO and/ or MgO, which is consistent with the observed coupling behaviors of A1203 and SiOl with CaO in the less siliceous compositions in CaO-A&amp;O,-SiO,. One of the major reasons that the ternary CaO-A120,-SiO* was chosen in the present study is because it represents a simple system with some of the key components of natural magmas. The coupling behaviors learned from chemical diffusion in molten CaO-AlZ03-Si02 can thus be used as a guide for understanding interdiffusion between natural magmas (e.g., basalt-rhyolite, dacite-rhyolite) . Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref> presents calculated interdiffusion profiles, using the composition-dependent chemical diffusion coefficients parameterized from the measured diffusion coefficients listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>, to represent two ternary "felsic-mafic" interdiffusion couples-one with A&amp;O3 initially enriched in the "mafic" melt (Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref>, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Koyaguchi, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr">Baker, 1990,199l)</ref> and the other with A&amp;O3 initially enriched in the "felsic" melt (Fig. <ref type="figure">7b</ref>; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Watson, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lesher, 1994)</ref>. The concentration profiles of CaO in Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref> and b resemble those of CaO, MgO, and Fe0 in basalt-rhyolite and dacite-rhyolite interdiffusion experiments (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Watson, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Koyaguchi, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baker, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baker, , 1991;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lesher, 1994)</ref>. The compositional dependence of DcaO_caO as well as the transition from negative coupling (Si02 &lt; 53%) to positive coupling (SiO, =-53%) of CaO with SiOp can be seen in the asymmetry of the concentration profiles of CaO shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref> and<ref type="figure">b</ref>. The large SiO? gradient enhances the diffusion of CaO in the negative coupling regime, whereas the gradient of Si02 reduces the actual flux of CaO in the positive coupling regime. The overall effect of coupling between CaO and SiO? is to make their respective diffusion distances very comparable. The characteristic minimum concentration of A1203 in melts of more siliceous compositions shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref> and b has also been observed in interdiffusion studies of basalt-rhyolite and dacite-rhyolite (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Koyaguchi, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baker, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baker, , 1991;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lesher, 1994)</ref>. The minima in A1203 results from the negative coupling of A1203 with CaO (and perhaps with MgO, FeO, K20, and Na20 as well). However, the broad "uphill" diffusion of A&amp;O3 in the silica-poor side of Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref> and<ref type="figure">b</ref> has rarely been observed in interdiffusion experiments using natural magmas, suggesting the coupling of A1203 with CaO (and with MgO, FeO, K20, and NazO) in natural magmas of less siliceous compositions is not as strong as that in the ternary synthetic system. Although the diffusion matrices obtained in the present study cannot be used to address the coupling behaviors of alkalis in natural magmas, comparisons of the widths of diffusive layers of K20 and Na,O with those of Si02 and A1203 in basalt-rhyolite, andesite-rhyolite, and dacite-rhyolite interdiffusion experiments (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Watson, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Watson and Jurewicz, 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Koyaguchi, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baker, 1990</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Baker, , 1991;;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Lesher, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">van der Laan et al., 1994)</ref> suggest that KzO and Na20 are likely to be strongly coupled with Si02 and A1203.</p><p>and comments of this paper. We also thank Sumit Chakraborty, Victor Kress, and Bill Minarik for their official reviews and comments. This work is supported by NSF grant EAR-9316390 and DOE grant DEFG02-94ER14478 to Frank Richter and NSF grant EAR-940691 to Bruce Watson.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">SUMMARY</head><p>Editorial handling: F. .I. Ryerson Chemical diffusion profiles in molten CaO-AIZOj-Si02 have been measured over a large range of compositions (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>) at 1500°C and 1 GPa. The diffusion profiles have been inverted for effective binary diffusion coefficients (EBDCs, Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>) and for the chemical diffusion matrix (Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> and<ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>). The EBDCs are shown to depend strongly on both composition and direction of diffusion in the composition space (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>). The dependence of EBDCs on direction in composition space, which for the system studied here can be as large as a factor of seven, severely limits the applicability of EBDCs to interdiffusion in any other system or compositional direction other than the experiment that was used to derive the EBDC.</p><p>The chemical diffusion matrix for molten CaO-A1203-SiOZ was determined using diffusion profiles from two or three mutually orthogonal diffusion couples in ternary composition space. A representation of chemical fluxes in the three component system studied here by a 2 X 2 diffusion matrix reproduces all features of the diffusion profiles including the uphill flux of components initially uniformly distributed and the large differences in the apparent diffusivity of a given component depending on direction in composition space. This is in contrast to the problems encountered by <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kress and Ghiorso ( 1993)</ref> who were unable to find a 2 x 2 diffusion matrix to fully account for diffusion profiles measured in molten MgO-A1203-Si02 or 3 X 3 matrices for profiles in MgO-CaO-AlZ03-Si02, and then argued that more complex models might be required for these melts. We suspect that their diffusion profiles may have been distorted by double-diffusive convection similar to what has been observed in molten CaO-Al~0~-Si02 <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Liang et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Liang, 1995)</ref>; but in any event, we found no evidence in our experiments that a 2 X 2 matrix is in any way inadequate to describe chemical diffusion in a three-component silicate melt.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemical diffusion in molten CaO-A1203-Si02</head><p>shows clear evidence of strong diffusive coupling among the components. This can be seen in the uphill diffusion profiles of components that were initially uniform, in the fact that the apparent rate of diffusion of some components is a strong function of direction in composition space, and most quantitatively in the magnitude of off-diagonal elements of the diffusion matrix relative to the magnitude of the diagonal elements. SiO,, for example, is found to be strongly coupled with CaO in melts of more siliceous compositions, whereas Al*O, is strongly coupled with CaO in melts of less siliceous compositions.</p><p>Furthermore, the coupling of CaO with either AllO or Si02 reverses its sign between more and less polymerized compositions. Interdiffusion profiles in natural melts have numerous features that suggest similar coupling between A1203 and CaO and between SiOZ and CaO.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG.1. Composition space relevant to the study of chemical diffusion in the system CaO-A1203-SiOz. Closed circles represent starting compositions (in wt%) Open circles represent compositions for which chemical diffusion coefficients are reported.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 2. Electron microprobe traverses (weight fractions, plus symbol) of chemical diffusion runs around compositionA along two compositional directions: 417 (a) and 3/l (b) at 1500°C and 1 GPa. The distance (X) is measured in meters and time (t) in seconds. Solid lines are the calculated diffusion profiles using the inverted diffusion matrix at composition A listed in Table3. Dotted vertical lines marked the approximate zone of diffusion for each element.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where Ci (i = 1, 2) is the concentration (mass fraction) of component i and 0: (i, j = 1, 2) are elements of the diffusion matrix taking component 3 as the dependent variable. Initial and boundary conditions appropriate to the chemical diffusion experiment conducted in the present study correspond to an effectively one-dimensional unbounded domain with an initial change in concentration at the interface of the diffusion couple (x = 0) : C,(x, 0) = c': C,(x, 0) = cy xc0 (4c) C,(x, 0) = cl C,(x, 0) = c: xz-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIG. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>FIG. 3. Electron microprobe traverses of chemical diffusion runs around composition 7 along three compositional directions: (a) constant CaO, (b) constant Al,O1, and (c) constant SiOz. Solid lines are the calculated diffusion profiles using the average diffusion matrix at composition 7 listed in Table3. Dotted vertical lines marked the approximate zone of diffusion for each element.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG.  5. Semilogarithm plot of the effective binary diffusion coefficients of SiO, along three directions in composition space vs. the inverse of melt viscosity ( 1500°C and 1 atm) calculated using the parameterized relations given in the preceding paper<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996)</ref>. The EBDCs for SiOZ were obtained using a nonlinear inversion procedure (Levenberg-Marquardt method,<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Press et al., 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Liang, 1994)</ref>, assuming constant diffusivity across the diffusion couple.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>coupling of Si02 to gradients in A1203, the dependent component used to reduce the matrix to 2 X 2. This property of [D] accounts for the fact that D$~_&amp;,, f the value of matrix elements depending on which component is taken as the dependent component (Tables</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 6. Semilogarithm plots of the elements of diffusion matrix with SiO, as the dependent variable in CaO-Al@-Si02 at 1500°C and 1 GPa vs. the inverse of the parameterized melt viscosity at 1500°C and 1 atm<ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Liang et al., 1996</ref>; 1 = CaO, 2 = Al*O?. and 3 = SiOZ). Small open symbols represent diffusion coefficients obtained from simultaneous inversion of concentration profiles from two or three compositional directions, whereas large crossed circles are diffusion coefficients obtained using concentration profiles along only one direction in composition space. The large solid circle represents data for composition 14 obtained from the concentrations profiles of<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al. ( 1982)</ref> at 1500°C and 1 atm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the contrasting features between the major and minor eigenvectors-the directions of the major eigenvector, defined by tan ((Y,) = D~~&amp;,12031(XI -D&amp;,0) = AC,lAC, (8a) tan (PI) = D$&amp;io,/(X, -De2&amp;a-fao) = AC,/ACl (8b)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>[D] , and the eigenvectors of [D] form the columns of the modal matrix [B]-'. The eigenvalues Xi of [D] are the elements of the diagonal matrix [A]. The diagonalized diffusion matrix has a number of virtues (see Gupta and Cooper, 197 1) , among them that the diffusion equation for the compositional components of T is of the form !% = h.V2T at ' '</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(compare, for example, D~&amp;r203 and D~,(&amp;_A1,O, in Table</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Nominal starting compositions of the ternary</figDesc><table><row><cell>Composition</cell><cell>CaO</cell><cell>Al203</cell><cell>SiQj</cell><cell>Density</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>60</cell><cell>2.654</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>55</cell><cell>2.659</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>65</cell><cell>2.597</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>65</cell><cell>2.614</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>55</cell><cell>2.681</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>60</cell><cell>2.618</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>60</cell><cell>2.639</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>2.810</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>2.841</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>2.764</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>2.143</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>2.788</cell></row><row><cell>15</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>2.724</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>2.700</cell></row><row><cell>17</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>2.719</cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>12.5</cell><cell>62.5</cell><cell>2.624</cell></row><row><cell>B</cell><cell>27.5</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>57.5</cell><cell>2.656</cell></row><row><cell>C</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>17.5</cell><cell>57.5</cell><cell>2.647</cell></row><row><cell>D</cell><cell>22.5</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>62.5</cell><cell>2.588</cell></row></table><note><p>* Compositions (in wt%) 1 to 17 were synthesized by fusing mixtures of ultrapure CaCO3, Al2O3. and SiO2 in a Deltech furnace at 1450°C and 1 atm</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Summary of chemical diffusion experiments.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Run #</cell><cell>Capsule</cell><cell>Couple</cell><cell>Dawty</cell><cell>Durahon</cell><cell>Convectmn</cell></row><row><cell>CD12</cell><cell>type 4'</cell><cell>top/bottom</cell><cell>inversion "0</cell><cell>(minutes) 120</cell><cell>no</cell></row><row><cell>CD12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CD12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CD12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SD22</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CD32</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CD32</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>LL</figDesc><table><row><cell>Composition</cell><cell>caocso Ds'%</cell><cell>SiO, DC0 AIS,</cell><cell>SiO, D AI$+30</cell><cell>DsiO? Al&amp;-A120,</cell><cell>Couples Used</cell></row><row><cell>D</cell><cell>3.02kO.20t</cell><cell>-1.15kO.50</cell><cell>-0.99kO.20</cell><cell>1.7oiO.50</cell><cell>3t7( 1 &amp; 2 hours)*</cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>3.15kO.07</cell><cell>-0.54&amp;0.05</cell><cell>-1.03&amp;0.03</cell><cell>0.92M.02</cell><cell>3/1(l) +4I7(1)</cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>3.14kO.07</cell><cell>-0.59ZkO.05</cell><cell>-0.87kO.03</cell><cell>1.2OkO.02</cell><cell>3/1( 1) + 4/7(2)</cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>3.15kO.07~</cell><cell>-0.56M.05</cell><cell>-0.95fo.08</cell><cell>1.06fo.06</cell><cell>Average of the two</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>4.08M.04</cell><cell>-0.52kO.04</cell><cell>-0.44M.01</cell><cell>1.22f0.01</cell><cell>4/2(2) + 3/5(2) + 6/1(0.25)</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>4.35M.10</cell><cell>-0.36M.07</cell><cell>-0.64f0.04</cell><cell cols="2">1.66kO.02 4/2(1.5) + 3/5(1.5) + 6/1(0.25)</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>4.22% 140</cell><cell>-0.44d10.08</cell><cell>-0.54&amp;0.10</cell><cell>1.44iO.22</cell><cell>Average of the two</cell></row><row><cell>C</cell><cell>5.25kO.09</cell><cell>-0.72M.07</cell><cell>-2.13fo.04</cell><cell>1.31?0.03</cell><cell>6/5( 1) + 7/2( 1)</cell></row><row><cell>C</cell><cell>5.33f0.09</cell><cell>-0.56kO.07</cell><cell>-2.04kO.04</cell><cell>1.50.03</cell><cell>6/5( 1) + 7/2(2)</cell></row><row><cell>C</cell><cell>5.29M.O9 §</cell><cell>-0.64kO.07</cell><cell>-2.08kO.04</cell><cell>1.40&amp;O. 10</cell><cell>Average of the two</cell></row><row><cell>B</cell><cell>4.6OkO.18</cell><cell>-0.16kO.09</cell><cell>-1.22M.31</cell><cell>2.42*1.29</cell><cell>7/5(1 &amp; 2)</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>10.60kO.15</cell><cell>1.23M.08</cell><cell>-4.76kO.06</cell><cell>1.62kO.03</cell><cell>2/12(0.7) + 5/15(0.7)</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>14.6Od~O.38</cell><cell>2.26M.23</cell><cell>-7.35k0.28</cell><cell>2.02M.15</cell><cell>16/14(0.5) + 17/10(0.5)</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>14.82kO.90</cell><cell>3.30k0.69</cell><cell>-6.49kO.62</cell><cell>0.75kO.44</cell><cell>10/8(0.3)</cell></row><row><cell>14 (15WC, 1 atm)</cell><cell>10.0</cell><cell>-2.8</cell><cell>-4.2</cell><cell>7.3</cell><cell>Sugawara et al. (1977)</cell></row><row><cell>14 (1500°C, 1 atm)</cell><cell>12.49</cell><cell>2.8</cell><cell>-3.8</cell><cell>3.0</cell><cell>Oishi et al. (1982)</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p>*Diffusion coefficients in x10-1' m2 s-1. t&amp;la errors are. calculated directly from each inversion. *Experimental run duration (in hours) is listed in parentheses, %kla errors for the average are calculated either from the nonlinear inversion or from the difference in the inverted Dtj from two duplicated runs as IADrjll2, whichever is larger. %verted from digitized concentration profiles in Figs.</p>3a, 3b</p>, and 3c of</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Oishi et al., 1982.</ref> </p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Summary of the chemical diffusion coefficients taking Al203 or CaO as the 2</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Composition D&amp;</cell><cell>DAt&amp; CaO-SQ</cell><cell>AN3 DsiO&amp;tO</cell><cell>D? LO*-SQ</cell><cell>Couples Used</cell></row><row><cell>D</cell><cell>4.17</cell><cell>1.15</cell><cell>-1.48</cell><cell>0.55</cell><cell>3n</cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>3.71</cell><cell>0.56</cell><cell>-1.70</cell><cell>0.50</cell><cell>311 + 4n</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>4.66</cell><cell>0.44</cell><cell>-2.68</cell><cell>1 .oo</cell><cell>412 + 315 + 6/l</cell></row><row><cell>C</cell><cell>5.93</cell><cell>0.64</cell><cell>-2.45</cell><cell>0.76</cell><cell>6l5 + 712</cell></row><row><cell>B</cell><cell>4.76</cell><cell>0.16</cell><cell>-1.12</cell><cell>2.25</cell><cell>715</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>9.37</cell><cell>-1.23</cell><cell>-2.99</cell><cell>2.85</cell><cell>2ll2 + 5115</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>12.34</cell><cell>-2.26</cell><cell>-2.97</cell><cell>4.28</cell><cell>16/14 + 1700</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>11.52</cell><cell>-3.30</cell><cell>-4.28</cell><cell>4.05</cell><cell>10/8</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Couples Used</cell></row><row><cell>D</cell><cell>2.69</cell><cell>0.99</cell><cell>1.48</cell><cell>2.03</cell><cell>3i7</cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>2.01</cell><cell>0.95</cell><cell>1.70</cell><cell>2.20</cell><cell>311 + 4n</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>1.98</cell><cell>0.54</cell><cell>2.68</cell><cell>3.68</cell><cell>4/2+3/5+6/l</cell></row><row><cell>C</cell><cell>3.48</cell><cell>2.08</cell><cell>2.45</cell><cell>3.21</cell><cell>6/S + 712</cell></row><row><cell>B</cell><cell>3.64</cell><cell>1.22</cell><cell>1.12</cell><cell>3.38</cell><cell>715</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>6.38</cell><cell>4.76</cell><cell>2.99</cell><cell>5.84</cell><cell>2l12+5/15</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>9.37</cell><cell>7.35</cell><cell>2.97</cell><cell>7.25</cell><cell>16/14 + 1700</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>7.24</cell><cell>6.49</cell><cell>4.28</cell><cell>8.33</cell><cell>1018</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">14 (lSOOT, 1 atm) 6.8</cell><cell>3.8</cell><cell>2.8</cell><cell>8.6</cell><cell>Oishi et al. (1982)</cell></row></table><note><p>*Diffusion coefficients in x10-11 m* s-1.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note><p>lists the new diffusion matrices with AlzOs as the depndent variable. The magnitude of the off-diagonal term</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Eigenvalues (I.1 and X2) in XIO-tt m2 s-1. ?E' tgenvectors directions tan(at) and tan(a3) are obtained</figDesc><table><row><cell>B</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>d directionst.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Composition</cell><cell>ht</cell><cell>h2</cell><cell>mr@t)</cell><cell>Wa2)</cell><cell></cell><cell>WPI)</cell><cell>W$2)</cell></row><row><cell>D</cell><cell>3.615</cell><cell>1.105</cell><cell>-0.5171</cell><cell>1.6649</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.4829</cell><cell>-2.6648</cell></row><row><cell>A</cell><cell>3.379</cell><cell>0.831</cell><cell>-0.4096</cell><cell>4.1417</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.5904</cell><cell>-5.1417</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>4.303</cell><cell>1.357</cell><cell>-0.1886</cell><cell>6.5068</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.8114</cell><cell>-7.5068</cell></row><row><cell>C</cell><cell>5.606</cell><cell>1.084</cell><cell>-0.4945</cell><cell>6.5726</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.5055</cell><cell>-1.5726</cell></row><row><cell>B</cell><cell>4.686</cell><cell>2.334</cell><cell>-0.5384</cell><cell>14.1634</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.4616</cell><cell>-15.1634</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>9.892</cell><cell>2.328</cell><cell>-0.5754</cell><cell>-0.6754</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.4246</cell><cell>5.7254</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>13.101</cell><cell>3.519</cell><cell>-0.6633</cell><cell>-4.903 1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.3367</cell><cell>3.903 1</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>13.084</cell><cell>2.486</cell><cell>-0.5262</cell><cell>-3.7374</cell><cell></cell><cell>-0.4738</cell><cell>2.7374</cell></row><row><cell>14s</cell><cell>11.079</cell><cell>4.321 1</cell><cell>-0.4753</cell><cell>-2.9060</cell><cell>t</cell><cell>-0.5247</cell><cell>1.9060</cell></row></table><note><p>*</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical interdiffusion of dacite and rhyolite: anhydrous measurements at 1 atm and 10 kbar, application of transition state theory, and diffusion in zoned magma chambers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interdiffusion of hydrous dacitic and rhyolitic melts and the efficacy of rhyolite contamination of dacitic enclaves</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="473" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="1921">1921</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dissolution rates of upper mantle minerals in an alkali basalt melt at high pressure: An experimental study and implication for ultramafic xenolith survival</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brearley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scarfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1182" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Conduction of Heat in Solids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Carslaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jaeger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicomponent diffusion in ternary silicate melts in the system K20-A1203-Si02: I. Experimental measurements. Geochim. Cosmochim</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dingwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rubie</forename><forename type="middle">D C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="264" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicomponent diffusion in ternary silicate melts in the system K,O-A1203-SiO?: II. Mechanisms, systematics, and geological applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dingwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rubie</forename><forename type="middle">D C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model for m&amp;i-component diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Chem. Glasses</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use and limitations of the concept of an effective binary diffusion coefficient for multicomponent diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mass Transport in Oxides</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wachtman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Franklin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>NBS Special Publ</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">296</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="84" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Mathematics of Diffusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of the flux equations of multicomponent diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Cullinan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ind. Eng. Chem. Fundamen</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion, mobility and their interrelation through free energy in binary metallic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Darken</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. Metall. Sot. AlME</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">175</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="1948">1948</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>De Groot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mazur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
			<publisher>Dover</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Non-Equilibrium Thermodynamics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemische diffusion und brechungsindexverlauf in zuasmmengeschmolzenen g&amp;em</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Engelke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Univ. Erlangen-Ntimberg</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An exact solution of the equations for free diffusion in three-component systems with interacting flows, and its use in evaluation of the diffusion coefficients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fujita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gosting</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Chem. Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1099" to="1106" />
			<date type="published" when="1956">1956</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The [D] matrix for multicomponent diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Haase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Thermodynamics of Irreversible Processes</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Dover</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetics of zircon dissolution and zirconium diffusion in granitic melts of variable water content</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The behavior of apatite during crustal anatexis: Equilibrium and kinetic considerations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1467" to="1477" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in natural silicate melts: A critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics of Magmatic Processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hargraves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="417" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Double-diffusive convection due to crystallization in magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Huppert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S J</forename><surname>Sparks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Rev. Earth Planet. sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in multicomponent metallic systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kirkaldy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canadian J. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="440" />
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in multicomponent metallic systems: I. Phenomenological theory for substitutional solid solution alloys</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canadian J. Phys</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kirkaldy</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="899" to="906" />
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Acknowledgments-We thank Andrew M. Davis for careful reviews</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diffusion in the Condensed State</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kirkaldy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
			<publisher>The Institute of Metals</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in multicomponent metallic systems: VII. Solutions of the multicomponent diffusion equations with variable coefficients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kirkaldy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mason</forename><forename type="middle">G R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canadian J. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2174" to="2186" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical gradient at diffusive interfaces in magma chambers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Koyaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetics of crystal dissolution in the system diopside-forsterite-silica</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L-C</forename><surname>Kuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. J. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicomponent diffusion in MgO-Al@-Si02 and CaO-MgO-A120,-SiOz melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kress</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ghiorso</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4453" to="4466" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical diffusion in melts on the CaMgSi20,-CaAlzSi208 join under high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kubicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Muncill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lasaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2709" to="2715" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Densities of Na,O-K,O-Ca0-Mg0-Fe0-Fe,03_A1203-TiO~-SiO~ liquids: New measurements and derived partial molar properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S E</forename><surname>Carmichael</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Actu</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="2946" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicomponent exchange and diffusion in silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lasaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="469" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a master equation in crystal growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lasaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. J. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">282</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1264" to="1288" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetics of Sr and Nd exchange in silicate liquids: Theory, experiments, and applications to uphill diffusion, isotopic equilibration, and irreversible mixing of magmas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9585" to="9604" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Models and experiments for multicomponent chemical diffusion in molten silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Univ. Chicago</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Axisymmetric double-diffusive convection in a cylindrical container: Linear stability analysis with applications to molten CaO-Si02-A120~</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Double-Diffusive Convection</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brandt</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fernando</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophys. Monogr. Ser</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="124" />
			<publisher>AGU</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convection in multicomponent silicate melts driven by coupled diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">369</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="392" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts: I. Self diffusion in CaO-Si02-A&amp;O-, at 1500°C and 1 GPa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4353" to="4367" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross terms in the thermodynamic diffusion equations for multicomponent alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metall. Trans</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="1970">1970</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Double-diffusive convection caused by coupled molecular diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcdougall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Fluid Mech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="397" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium diffusion in a mugearite melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Medford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canadian J. Eurth Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some comments on multicomponent diffusion: Negative main term diffusion coefficients, second law constrains, solvent choices, and reference frame</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vitagliano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sartorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1509" to="1519" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of liquid-state interdiffusion in the system CaO-Alz09 SiOz using multiatomic ion models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Oishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nanba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pask</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Ceram. Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="253" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theories and problems of liquid diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Onsager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. New York Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="1945">1945</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simplified version of the PAP model for matrix corrections in EPMA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pouchou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pichoir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Microbeam Analysis</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Newbury</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>San Francisco Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="318" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative analysis of homogenous or stratified microvolumes applying the model PAP</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pouchou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Pichoir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Electron Probe Quantitution</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F J</forename><surname>Heinrich</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="75" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Plenum</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Press</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Flannery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Teukolsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Vetterling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Numerical Recipes: The Art of Scientijic Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method for determining activity-composition relations using chemical diffusion in silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2019" to="2032" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A method for determination of [D] in ternary systems from a single experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Metull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1957" to="1959" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An experimental study of the diffusion of Na, K, and Rb in magmatic silicate liquids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Univ. Oregon</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The fluid dynamics of evolving magma chambers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S J</forename><surname>Sparks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Huppert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phil. Trans. Roy. Sot. London A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Verification of the Onsager reciprocal relations in a molten silicate solution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Trial</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">259</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Interdiffusivities matrix of CaO-Al@-Si02 melt at 1723 K to 1823 K</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sugawara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nagata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Goto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
			<publisher>Metall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. 8B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="605" to="612" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solution of the linearized equations of multicomponent mass transfer: I. A.1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Toor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ch.E. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="448" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="1964">1964</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring the multicomponent diffusion matrix: Experimental design and data analysis for silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Trial</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3769" to="3783" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multicomponent convection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Rev. Fluid Mech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of element and isotope diffusion of K and Ca in multicomponent silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Der Laan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wyllie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in the system KzO-SrO-SiOz: III, Interdiffusion coefficients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Varshneya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Ceram. Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="312" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basalt contamination by continental crust: Some experiments and models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical diffusion in magmas: An overview of experimental results and geochemicai applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physical Chemistry of Mugmas</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="135" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavior of alkalies durina diffusive interaction of granitic&apos;xenohths with basaltic magma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jurewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yoder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Contemporaneous basaltic and rhyolitic magmas</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="171" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A modified effective binary diffusion model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11901" to="11920" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusive crystal dissolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="492" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ternary diffusion in copersilver-gold alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">0</forename><surname>Ziebold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ogilvie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. Metall. Sot. AIME</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">239</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="942" to="953" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
