<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Self-diffusion of magnesium in spine1 and in equilibrium melts: Constraints on flash heating of silicates</title>
				<funder ref="#_MTBwKkp">
					<orgName type="full">DOE</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_mS5Ayf6">
					<orgName type="full">NASA</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wasserburg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hutcheon</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Geological and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Lunatic Asylum of the Charles Arms Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Pasadena</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<postCode>1125</postCode>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Self-diffusion of magnesium in spine1 and in equilibrium melts: Constraints on flash heating of silicates</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8F6B4B3BDCD59B41EB9253845A020655</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received September 6, 1991; accepted in revisedform March 25, 1992</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ah&amp;act-We</head><p>have measured Mg self&amp;fusion in spine1 and coexisting melt at bulk chemical equilibrium using an isotopic tracer. The diffusion coefficients were calculated from the measured isotope profiles using a model that includes the complementary diffusion of 24Mg, "Mg, and 26Mg in both phases with the constraint that the Mg content of each phase is constant. This model also permits the calculation of the diffusion coefficient in one phase from the measured data in a coexisting phase. The activation energy and pre-exponential factor for Mg self-diffusion in spine1 are, respectively, 384 f 7 kJ and 74.6 + 1.1 cm'/s. These data indicate Mg diffusion in spine1 is much slower than previous estimates, probably because earlier measurements included grain boundary transport. The activation energy for Mg selfdiffusion in coexisting melt is 343 + 25 kJ and the pre-exponential factor is 7791.9 + 1.3 cm*/s. The results from this study were applied to evaluate cooling rates of Plagioclase-Olivine Inclusions (POI) in the Allende meteorite. Given a maximum melting temperature for POIs of -1 SOO"C, these results show that a 10 pm radius spine1 would equilibrate isotopically with a melt within about 60 min. To preserve Mg isotopic heterogeneity, the POIs must have initially cooled faster than 15 to 250°C/h depending on the initial temperature of flash heating. The cooling rate must also be slow enough to generate the observed basaltic textures. The inferred cooling rate appears to be comparable or up to ten times greater than those inferred from experimental and textural studies of synthetic CA1 systems. The nature of the heating process is thus required to be short with relatively rapid cooling, such as flash heating. However, the relatively rapid cooling cannot be due to radiation into a cold, -400°K nebula but would require radiation into a &amp;her stable hot environment.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCI'ION IN A STUDY OF THE MINERALOGICAL, chemical, and isotopic</head><p>properties of Plagioclase-Olivine Inclusions ( POIs) in the Allende meteorite, SHENG et al. ( 199 1 a) noted that a surprisingly large fraction of the POIs studied were not isotopically homogeneous. Despite textural evidence of a molten or partially molten origin, approximately half of the POIs studied exhibited variations in Mg isotope composition of up to 1 1 '%/ amu between spine1 and coexisting silicates. Based on these observations <ref type="bibr">SHENG et al. ( 199 la)</ref> proposed that POIs formed by partial melting of an isotopically heterogeneous aggregate, including some spinels with isotopically fractionated Mg, and silicates with a normal bulk Mg isotope composition. The presence of isotopically heterogeneous spine1 in the POIs requires that the maximum temperature experienced by these objects was low enough and the subsequent cooling rate fast enough to prevent homogenization of Mg isotopes by diffisive transport.</p><p>The determination of the thermal history that allows preservation of relict isotopic heterogeneity requires knowledge of the self-diffusion rate of Mg in spinel. Therefore, we designed experiments to determine the self-diffusion coefficients of Mg in single crystal spine1 at temperatures reflecting possible melting conditions of Plagioclase-Olivine Inclusions ( SHENG et al., 199 la). The only available Mg diffusion data in MgAlzO4 are those cited by <ref type="bibr">LINDNER and ARERSTROM ( 1958)</ref>. They used a radiotracer (**Mg) precipitated on a polycrystalline aggregate of spinels.</p><p>A common technique for the preparation of a diffusion couple in simple solids is to coat the diffusing species onto the surface of the sample by electroplating or chemical precipitation (see, e.g., COLES and LONG, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">REED and WUENSCH, 1979</ref>; CYGAN and <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">LASAGA, 1985)</ref>. The sample is then annealed to allow species in the thin film to diffuse into the sample. Some of the potential drawbacks to this technique are that the thin film and the crystal are in very different chemical and physical states, and the boundary between them may not be well defined. Imperfections along this contact could serve as a major obstruction to the diffusing species and thus limit the reliability of the data. The thin film method usually does not permit a check on the mass balance of the species transported between the two phases. Another potential problem is that if the thin film has one or more components that are volatile in the enclosing gas, differential volatilization may occur at the surface.</p><p>In order to avoid these problems, we designed an experimental approach in which volume diffusion in both phases is maintained. The experiment was defined so that diffusion occurs only in response to an isotopic concentration gradient in media that are each homogeneous with respect to chemical composition. We report on the diffusion coefficients of Mg as a function of temperature in spine1 (MgAl2O4) and coexisting silicate liquids under the condition of bulk chemical equilibrium but bulk isotopic disequilibrium. Our technique permits precise determination of the activation energy and is applicable to many other systems (cf. <ref type="bibr">JUREWICZ and WAT-SON, 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr">WATSON et al., 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">FREER et al., 1982)</ref> in which elements with multiple isotopes (e.g., Mg, Ti, Fe, K, Ca, Si, 0) can be used as tracers. The measured Mg diffusion rates for spine1 are used to establish the temperatures and time scales which control isotopic homogenization of Mg in refractory inclusions found in some meteorites. A preliminary report of this approach has been given by <ref type="bibr">SHENG et al. (199lc)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL METHOD</head><p>We investigated Mg self-diffusion in MgA1204 (spinel) using isotopic tracers and a diffusion couple. The diffusion couple consists of a single crystal, gem-quality natural spine1 with a normal Mg isotopic composition and spine1 saturated, 25Mgdoped, CaO-MgO-A1,Or-SiO1 melts representative of PO1 compositions. The spine1 crystal was sawed into thin slabs -300 pm thick and one side polished to a smooth, flat surface with I pm diamond paste. The polished spine1 slabs were annealed in air for 24 h at 1500°C. No study of residual defect structures, the effectiveness of the annealing process, or their effect on diffusion was carried out here. "Mgdoped glasses were produced by first mixing *'MgO powder (*'MgO &gt; 98.7%; Oak Ridge National Laboratory) with appropriate amounts of CaCO, , MgO, A120,, and Si02 and then grinding under ethanol in an agate mortar. The mixtures were decarbonated at 800°C for 12 h, followed by melting in Pt crucibles in a Del-Tech VT-3 1 furnace at 1550°C for 24 h in air and quenching in deionized water. Each bulk composition was chosen based on phase equilibria studies ( SHENG <ref type="bibr">et al., 199 I b;</ref><ref type="bibr">SHENG, 1991)</ref> to be in equilibrium with spine1 at the desired temperature for the diffusion experiment. Glass chips were analyzed atier melting and verified to be both chemically and isotopically homogeneous by electron probe and ion probe measurements. Magnesium isotope ratios measured in the glasses are consistent with the amount of isotope tracer added into each mixture.</p><p>Preparation of the diffusion couple is shown schematically in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Chips of the *'Mg-doped glass were placed in a cylindrical Pt CNcible of 3 mm diameter. The glass chips were remelted inside the crucible to produce a nearly bubble-free glass. Chemical and isotopic compositions of the glass were not changed by the remelting. The The glass was polished after the open end was sawed off. A polished spine1 slab which had been annealed at 1500°C for 24 h was placed against the polished glass. The glass and spine1 slab were fastened together with Pt wire and placed into a furnace at a selected temperature at which the melt-crystal couple was then held for a known time.</p><p>remelted glass was then heated to a temperature slightly ( -5°C) below the spine1 saturation temperature of the melt composition to ensure chemical equilibrium with spine]. The melt was then quenched in air to prevent fracturing of the glass. Observation of this re-equilibrated glass under the optical microscope showed that some spine1 grains crystallized from the melt but had settled to the bottom of the crucible. The amount of spine1 crystallized was much less than 5% of the total mass and no significant change in the chemical composition of the melt occurred in the experiments. Measurements of glasses before and after the experiment showed no measured difference in composition. The open end of the crucible was sawed off and the glass polished to a flat surface. The pre-annealed and polished spine1 slab was then placed against the polished surface of the glass and tied together with Pt wire. This couple was then placed into the hot spot of a preheated Del-Tech furnace adjacent to a thermocouple and held at the selected temperature for periods of 0.5 to 20 h. Samples were removed through the top of the furnace and allowed to cool slowly in air, to avoid fracturing spine1 or glass. All experiments were conducted in air at one atmosphere. This procedure produced a welldefined, wetted contact between spine1 and a bubble-free, spine1 saturated melt. Assuming there was no convection in the melt, diffusion coefficients in both melt and crystal can be determined by measurements on the glass (quenched melt) and crystal.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">2a</ref> is a backscattered electron image (BSE) ofone run product showing the spine1 slab welded onto the "Mgdoped glass contained within a Pt crucible. As shown in the enlarged BSE image in Fig. <ref type="figure">2b</ref>, wetting of the melt on the spine1 surface yielded a boundary of spine1 to glass that was a sharp, welded contact. This figure is an illustration of a contact in which the two phases are in chemical equilibrium. In contrast, the spine1 to glass boundary in one experiment, where the melt was over-saturated with respect to spine], shows a serrated contact due to a spine1 growth (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>), The irregular contact between the two phases indicates that bulk chemical disequilibrium existed at some point during the experiment. The diffusion coefficient of Mg determined from the measured isotope abundance profile in spine1 from this experiment is not consistent with the data from our other experiments and is not included in our discussion.</p><p>In some preliminary experiments with a rather limited amount of melt relative to the crystal (T = 1302, 1354, and 1497"C), we found that the 2rrMg/24Mg isotope ratio of the glass measured at the point furthest away from the spinel-glass boundary was significantly lower than the initial ratio oftheglass prior to the experiments. This indicates that the amount of Mg in the melt, and hence the mass of the melt in these experiments, was inadequate to be treated as an infinite medium, complicating any attempt to extract diffusion coefficients for the melt. However, the data for the spine1 in these three experiments could be very well fitted with a diffusion profile (see Results section). In subsequent experiments, we ensured that sufficient glass was present so that the liquid could be treated as an infinite reservoir and verified that the *~M~/*%lp, ratio measured in the glass far from the spine1 following the d&amp;us&amp;r anneal correspondedto that of the initial glass.</p><p>At the conclusion of each experiment the diffusion couple was mounted in epoxy and sliced perpendicular to the spinel-glass interface. The resulting surface was polished and carbon coated for chemical and isotopic analysis. The chemical and isotopic compositions of the glasses and spine1 are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. The 25Mg/24Mg ratios for each experiment were arbitrary and dependent on the mix of tracer and normal Mg used. If spine1 and melt were in chemical equilibrium for each run, then Mg diffused only in response to the isotopic disequilibrium. That this condition was fulfilled during our experiments was tested by measuring the chemical and isotopic compositions along diffision profiles perpendicular to the interface.</p><p>A major concern was the possibility of convection in the melt. To test this possibility chemical and isotopic gradients were measured in the glass across three profiles perpendicular to the spinel-glass interface for experiments at 1495, 14 15, and 1354°C. These three profiles were located at the center of the spinel-glass interface and 1 mm from each side of the center. Points on each profile were measured from close to the interface to 2 mm away from the interface. The melt was found to be chemically uniform. From the absence of differences in isotopic compositions along different profiles at equal distance away from the interface, and the excellent fit to a simple of the profiles enabled us to measure the variations in Mg isotopic composition along a traverse normal to the diffusion interface in both spine1 and glass. Depth profiling techniques required in many isotopic tracer experiments (cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">COLES and LONG, 1973;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">REED and WUENSCH, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">CYGAN and LASAGA, 1985)</ref> were not required.</p><p>The Mg isotopic compositions in spine1 and glass were determined with the PANURGE ion microprobe following procedures described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">HUNEKE et al. ( 1983) and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">HUTCHEON et al. ( 1987)</ref>. A massanalyzed, 0.2-0.5 nA i60-primary beam was focussed to a diameter of -5 pm. Secondary Mg+ ions were extracted and accelerated nominally to 4.5 keV. Small (45 V) offsets were applied to the accelerating voltage to compensate for sample charging. An aperture inserted in the sample image plane allowed only positive secondary ions emitted from an 8 pm diameter region concentric with the beam center to enter the mass spectrometer. A mass resolving power of -3000, sufficient to resolve ah molecular interferences in the mass region of interest, and an energy bandpass of -60 V were used in all analyses. Measured isotope ratios were corrected for counting system deadtime (-20 nsec) following the procedure described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">HUTCHEON et al. ( 1987)</ref>. Isotopic profiles were measured by moving the sample under computer control in predetermined increments, while holding the position of the primary beam fixed. In addition to the Mg isotopes, the 28Si+/24Mg+ ratio was recorded to provide a sensitive indicator of the presence of glass. The 2a errors for measured ratios are +3%0 for 2sMg/24Mg and &amp;2% for 26Mg/24Mg.</p><p>The data analysis required two types of corrections for instrumental mass-dependent fractionation. Since the 26Mg/24Mg ratio in the "Mgdoped glass was approximately (within *3%) normal, measured 25Mg/24Mg ratios in spine1 and glass were corrected for fractionation using a power law after normalizing to 26Mg/24Mg = 0.13955 <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(BRIGHAM, 1990)</ref>. Close to the interface the Mg isotopic compositions in spine1 and glass must approach a common value. The measured isotope ratios in spine1 and glass will, however, differ due to composition-dependent "intrinsic" fractionation. To correct for this fmctionation, an 8k offset was applied to 25Mg/24Mg ratios in glass. The correction was determined from Mg isotope measurements in spine1 and isotopically normal glass. The distances between the sputtered holes from the ion microprobe analyses were determined on a high-precision (resolution -0.5 pm) measuring stage attached to an optical microscope. In calculating the diffusion parameters, we assumed that the measured values, which sample an excitation region with a maximum diameter of 8 pm, represent the value at the center point of the beam. For the profile lengths in this experiment (-50 pm), this assumption introduces negligible errors ( GANGULY et al., diffusion model in both melt and crystal, we inferred that convection was not a factor in our experiments. We also note that bubbles were often present in the original melt that were attached to the capsule. The interior of the melt was always bubble-free. The same bubbles were present during heating for the diffusion period and did not move from their initial position. In addition, no spinels were ever found to be trapped in the melt during this diffusion period.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ANALYTICAL TECHNIQUE</head><p>The determination of diffusion coefficients usually requires isotopic or chemical analysis with very high spatial resolution, as produced by depth profiling using secondary ion mass spectrometry. In our experiments we found that at the temperatures of interest, diffusion of Mg in spine1 (and melt) was sufficiently fast that isotopic profiles -40 pm long were developed in spine1 in less than 24 h. The length FIG. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. BSE image of a serrated boundary between spine1 and glass which is the result of chemical disequilibrium between the two phases. The melt composition was oversaturated with respect to spine1 at the run temperature ( 1393°C) of this experiment so that spine1 crystallized onto the surface of the spine1 slab. This behavior was absent in all the diffusion experiments reported here. The scale bar is 10 pm. 1977). The isotope ratios at the boundary were determined by extrapolating the measured data in both spine1 and glass on different sides of the border to the boundary. Chemical compositions of spine1 and glass were measured with a wavelength dispersive spectrometer ( WDS) on a JEOL 733 electron microprobe using a ZAF correction <ref type="bibr">(LOVE and Scorr, 1978)</ref> as modified by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">ARMSTRONG ( 1984)</ref>. The concentrations of each Mg isotope species in spinei and melt were calculated from measured isotope ratios and total Mg concentrations in each phase and expressed in terms of moles per cubic centimeter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATHEMATICAL TREATMENT</head><p>The data collected in the experiments described above were treated as diffusion in an infinite composite medium, taking into account the complementary diffusion of 24Mg, "Mg and 26Mg in both spine1 and melt with the total concentration of Mg in each phase maintained constant. The two phases were in bulk chemical equilibrium but with isotopic disequilibrium. The conditions are schematically illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>, showing the distribution of total Mg and of the different isotopes in the two phases before and after the diffusion experiment. For the three species 24Mg, 25Mg, 26Mg we assign the indices i = 1, 2, 3, respectively. The atomic concentrations of these species, C'i , in the two media, spine1 (R) and melt where DL and DR are, respectively, the diffusion coefficients for the chemical species in phases L and R, and t is the time.</p><p>The assumption of constant, concentration-independent diffusion coethcients is most reasonable given that the bulk chemical composition of each phase is constant. For simplicity, we ignore isotopic fractionation effects in this transport model. From Eqns. ( 1) and ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) and (3a) (3b)</p><p>The continuity of flux for each species through the spinelliquid interface requires that  Errors in ion probe measurements of 25Mg/24Mg ratios were incorporated into the diffusion coefficient from each experiment by an error propagation technique. A linear regression of the diffusion data for all experiments was performed to determine the activation energy and pre-exponential factor. The associated error in each diffusion coefficient was included in this regression.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>Diffusion experiments were performed at seven different temperatures. The results are listed in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. The experiments at 1553, 1495, 1415, and 1261°C were conducted under conditions in which both spine1 and melt can be treated as infinite sources. The isotopic composition at the boundary can be quite accurately determined from the set of isotopic profiles in the two phases. In three previous experiments ( 1497, 1354, and 1302"C), data for the melt were not used because the amount of melt was not sufficient to treat the melt as an infinite source. A major concern is whether using the diffusion coefficients for these three experiments, extracted from the measured data in spinel, can be justified. The experiment at 1495'C was conducted to check whether there are any significant differences between the values of the diffusion coefficients for spinel, calculated through Eqn. ( 13), for experiments with and without adequate melt. The results (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>) show no significant differences in DR for the 1495°C and 1497°C experiments, and we therefore feel justified in using the data from the 1354 and 1302°C experiments in our analysis. We wish to emphasize that our results for the diffusion coefficient parameters are unchanged if these data are omitted.</p><p>The results for the experimental run at T = 1495°C are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">5</ref> and<ref type="figure">6</ref> as examples of the technique for extracting the diffusion coefficient. In Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>, the chemical profiles in the glass from an electron probe WDS analysis, measured to within 5 pm of the boundary, show no significant variations in abundances of the chemical species, partially justifying the assumption that spine1 and melt were in chemical equilibrium. Isotopic abundance profiles measured in both spine1 and glass, where only a portion of the diffusion profile in the glass is presented, appear in Fig. <ref type="figure">6a</ref>. The **Si+/ 24Mg+ ratio monitored during these analyses shows the sharp drop off of Si across the glass-spine] boundary. Figure <ref type="figure">6b</ref> shows a somewhat enlarged view of isotopic compositions in the glass and the spine1 and illustrates how isotopic composition at the boundary was determined by extrapolating from both sides. This value of the composition and the initial parameters of the system then determine (Y from Eqn. ( <ref type="formula">12</ref>). Figure <ref type="figure">6c</ref> is the variation of "Mg/ ZMg across a traverse in the spine1 showing a penetration distance of about 50 pm. The corresponding ion probe traverse for the melt in this same experiment is shown in Figure <ref type="figure">6d</ref>. Variations in Mg isotopic composition in the glass are smaller in magnitude but extend to much greater distances ( -2 mm). The diffusion coefficient (DR) for spine1 is extracted by using a least square fit to the measured data from the values at the boundary and the initial conditions. Using these values and Eqn. ( 1 la), the diffusion coefficient in the melt ( DL) is determined through the relations ( 10 ) , ( 11 b ) , and ( 12 ) . The calculated diffusion profiles in both regions are shown by the curves in Fig. <ref type="figure">6a,  c,</ref> and<ref type="figure">d</ref>. The agreement between the calculated profiles and the measured data for both spine1 and melt is very good and serves as a fundamental check on the applicability of our diffusion model to the experimental data. Results from experiments at other temperatures show equally good fits to the measured data.</p><p>The set of equations ( 1 la and b) are related by common parameters; thus, the solution of any one equation also fixes the solution of the other equation. From the nature of the equations, it is possible that the diffusion coefficient of a species in one phase, whose measurement is limited by the slow  diffision rate of that species, can be determined from the diffusion coefficient of the same species in a coexisting phase (e.g. melt), in which the diffusion rate may be several orders of magnitude faster. As a test, we used the diffusion coefficient of Mg ( DL) extracted from a best fit to the measured data in the melt for the above experiment and calculated the di8bsion coefficient of Mg in spine1 (DR) through the parameter (Y. The diffusion coefficients of Mg in spine1 derived from a best fit of the measured data in spine1 and derived from the data in the coexisting melt are 3.21 f 0.27 X lo-" and 3.01 + 0.40 X lo-" cm*/s, respectively. This result shows these two approaches to be in reasonable agreement given the uncertainties in the analysis.</p><p>We also point out that the 25Mg/24Mg ratio (or Cz5 / ZMg) at the boundary is defined more precisely by extrapolating the diffusion profile in the glass to the boundary than by extrapolating the profile in spinel. The long diffusion profile and the small isotopic abundance gradient in the glass are very sensitive to the isotopic composition at the boundary. A variation of +O.O 1 in the value of C2J ZMg at the boundary would greatly affect the fit to the measured data in glass. In contrast, due to the short profile and steep gradient in the spinel, the diffusion coefficient derived from a best lit of the measured data is affected only slightly by this variation in the boundary value. For example, the diffision coefficient in spine1 at 1354"C, calculated from a best fit of the measured data using a boundary value, &amp;/ZMg -0.535, is 3.21 X lo-" cm*/s, while using C2JxMg -0.470 the diffusion coefficient is 3.04 X lo-". However, this variation in the boundary value, when translated into the diffision coefficient of the corresponding glass, gives a much greater uncertainty. From the boundary values given above, the calculated diffusion coefficients for melt are, respectively, 7.78 X lo-* and 4.55 X lo-' cm*/s. Because of these uncertainties resulting from the functional dependence shown in Eqn. ( <ref type="formula">11</ref>)) we did not attempt to extract the dit%.ion coefficient for coexisting melt using the data in spine1 for the three experiments ( 1497, 1354, and 1302°C) where the isotope compositions in the melt were not directly measured and the melt volume was too small for treatment as a half space.</p><p>The temperature dependence of the diffusion coefficient for Mg self-diffusion in spine1 is obtained from the Arrhenius relation,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D = Do exp(-EIRT). (14)</head><p>As can be seen (Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref>), the data exhibit a very good linear relationship on a In D vs. 1 /T plot, suggesting that a single diffusion mechanism governs the transport of Mg in spine1 crystals over the temperature range studied. The activation energy (E) and pm-exponential factor (Do) derived by a linear regression of the experimental diffusion data are, respectively, 384 ? 7 kJ and 74.6 + 1.1 cm*/s. The activation energy for Mg in the melts is deduced from the four experiments in which diffusion data for the melts are available. The activation energy derived from this analysis is 343 + 25 kJ and the preexponential factor is 779 1.9 + 1.3 cm*/s. Although the melts are of different bulk compositions (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> ), the linear relation of the diffusion coefficients derived from an Arrhenius plot (Fig. <ref type="figure">7b</ref>) suggests that the diffusion coefficient is not a strong function of composition; thus, a constant Dt can be assumed for all PO1 compositions of interest. We also note that the activation energies for Mg diffusion in spine1 and melt are quite similar for the temperature range of our experiments. The pre-exponential factors are, however, very different, thus reflecting the much higher intrinsic jump frequency orjump amplitude in the melt structure as compared with the crystal. The near agreement of the activation energies suggests that the potential barriers for diffusion are the same in both crystal and melt. This is a rather surprising result considering the different phases and the lattice sites that are anticipated for Mg in the melt (octahedral) versus spine1 (tetrahedral ) .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUS!3ION</head><p>From the characteristics of POIs summarized in the Introduction and discussed in detail by <ref type="bibr">SHENG et al. ( 199 la)</ref>, it is apparent that the existence of isotopic heterogeneity is the critical clue that provides information on the high-temperature thermal history of these inclusions. Our experiments provide accurate data on the activation energy for Mg diffusion in spine1 and allow us to evaluate the nature of the thermal event(s). The activation energy and pre-exponential factor for Mg diffusion in spine1 extracted from our experi-mental data are somewhat different from those reported by LINDNER and AKERSTR~M ( 1958 ) . Our results give an energy of 384 kJ and a Do of 74.6 cm'/s, compared to their results of 360 kJ and 200 cm'/s, respectively. At the temperature pertinent to melting of POIs, our data yield a Mg diffusion coefficient approximately an order of magnitude smaller than that calculated from the results of LINDNER and AKERSTROM ( 1958). Since their experiments were conducted on a polycrystalline spine1 aggregate, the faster diffusion rate indicated by their data may reflect some combination of grain boundary and volume diffusion, if grain boundary dilfusion is rapid.</p><p>The temperature-dependent diffusion coefficient of Mg in spine1 is used to evaluate the duration, thermal limits, and the nature of the heating process that partially melted the POIs. We also discuss the possible initial cooling rates of these partially melted droplets following a heating event.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mg diffusion in spine1</head><p>-18 f04/ T ("K-l) If we take spine1 of a certain grain size and plot the estimated homogenization time (x2 = D&amp;) vs. temperature (Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>), the maximum time that a spine1 and melt can coexist at any specified temperature before diffusive transport of Mg produces isotopic equilibrium can be approximated. A more precise relaxation time will depend on the details of geometry, etc. (cf. CHAKRABORTY and GANGULY, 199 1). For example, for a spine1 with radius of 10 grn (maximum grain size of spine1 in POIs), the relaxation time at 1500°C is less than one hour. The temperature of 1500°C was inferred by <ref type="bibr">SHENG et al. ( 199 I b</ref> ) to be the maximum temperature of the melting event for spinel-bearing POIs. Even if the maximum temperature were only 1400°C, the isotopic heterogeneities in PO1 spinels would not be expected to survive more than a few hours. Clearly, a short thermal event is implied.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mg diffusion in melt</head><p>A more realistic sense for the thermal history reflected in  Let us regard the penetration distance x as the minimum grain size (radius) of the spine1 that will preserve the isotopic heterogeneity.</p><p>By plotting r. vs. TO, for a given grain size, the initial cooling rate can be determined if the initial or maximum melting temperature (To) is known.</p><p>The dependence of initial cooling rate (rob) on To for a given characteristic diffusion distance, x, calculated using this relation is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref> where the temperature is given in degrees Celsius. The initial rates at 1500°C for x of 5, 10, and 15 pm are, respectively, 356,89, and 40"C/h within the framework of the assumed cooling model. For a 10 pm grain size, isotopic homogenization would occur if the initial cooling rate was slower than 89"C/h, or, for an initial cooling rate of 89"C/h, grain sizes of less than 10 pm would be homogenized. At a low&amp; temperature, e.g. 135O"C, a grain size of 5 pm requires an initial cooling rate &gt;25'C/h to avoid ho- 15 pm. At a specified temperature, Mg isotope heterogeneity can be preserved in spine1 of a given grain size if the initial cooling rate is greater than that defined by the calculated curve for that grain size. Spinels in POls are generally smaller than 5 pm. Thus, in order to escape Mg isotope homogenization, we would expect initial cooling rates greater than lOO'C/h at suggested melting temperatures of POIs, or at temperatures where POIs are 80% molten, greater than 15"C/h. mogenization. Since most spine1 grains in POIs are less than 10 pm across and maximum temperatures were on the order of 15OO"C, we would expect an initial cooling rate &gt; 100°C/ h for POIs based on Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>. At 1500°C (the maximum temperature of PO1 melting inferred by SHENG et al., 199 lb), the initial cooling rate for spine1 of 5 pm radius is 356'C/h. At this temperature, the POIs are &gt;95% melted, and the only phases present are spine1 and melt. In some POIs, silicates do not appear until below 1325'C. These POIs are still &gt;80% melted. At this temperature, isotopic homogenization of 5 pm spine1 grains could be avoided if the initial cooling rate was &gt; 15 "C. The nature of the heating process is thus required to be short with relatively rapid cooling, such as flash heating or impact melting. These lower limits on the cooling rates (which depend on grain size) are comparable to or up to ten times greater than those inferred from experimental and textural studies of synthetic CA1 systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(WARK and LOVERING, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">MAC-PHERSON et al., 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">STOLPER and PAQUE, 1986)</ref>. It thus appears that the igneous textures of POIs are generally compatible with the cooling rates estimated to produce CA1 textures; but much faster rates, which would still preserve isotopic heterogeneity, may be. inconsistent with petrographic observations. Experimental studies of textures of PO1 composition melts as a function of cooling rate will be required to address this case. Faster cooling rates, however, would be compatible with the glassy and skeletal textures of CA chondrules ( BKHOFF and KEIL, 1984 ) . Thus, if isotopically heterogeneous aggregates were also their precursor, and if the melting temperature of some phases did not exceed the liquidus of the bulk aggregate, then Mg isotopic heterogeneity may also be preserved in CA chondrules. The lower limits on cooling rates for POIs are much lower than radiative loss cooling rates of millimeter-size droplets in a cold nebula. This would therefore require formation of POIs in a relatively hot region of the nebula or on a modestly insulated planetary surface after an impact event, possibly in a thin ejecta blanket.</p><p>The Mg diffusion data can also be applied to constrain the thermal history of CAIs. For an initial temperature of 142O'C and r. s 2O"C/ h, as suggested for some Type B CAIs ( STOL PER and PAQUE, 1986), our calculations show a characteristic diffusion distance  <ref type="bibr">, 199la)</ref> this isotopic homogeneity requires either maximum temperatures significantly greater than 1500°C and/or cooling rates much slower than 20°C/ h (the T,,,., / r. ratio must be increased by a factor of at least 5 to 10 over the value given above). Alternatively, Type B CAIs may have formed from isotopically homogeneous precursor material. The presence of Mg isotope heterogeneity in POIs and the results of our diffusion experiments provide one of the most direct means of establishing a constraint on the thermal his-tory of these inclusions. The presence or absence of Mg isotopic heterogeneity is a quantitative measure of the initial flash heating temperature and cooling rate not only of POIs but also of other types of refractory inclusions and chondrules, if we assume that these objects sampled similar material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Our Mg diffusion experiments used an isotope exchange technique for phases in chemical equilibrium. This allows precise and simultaneous determination of diffusion coefficients in both phases. For spinel, we obtain an activation energy of 384 + 7 kJ for Mg and pre-exponential coefficient of 74.6 ? 1.1 cm2/s. These values for coexisting melt are calculated to be 343 + 25 kJ and 7791.9 f 1.3 cm2/s, respectively. Since the diffusion coefficients in the coexisting phases are related by common parameters, it is possible to determine the diffusion coefficient of a species in the second phase from the measured data in the first phase and the initial and boundary values. The results suggest that this type of experiment may have broader application and can be applied to other elements (including Si and 0) and other mineral systems. Indeed, simultaneous determination of the diffusion coefficients in a single experiment can readily be done. Such experiments only require the use of labelled isotopes for all of the chemical elements of interest in a single mixture to produce the melt. Using the technique described here, diffusion data in phases where measurement is limited by the slow diffusion rate of a species can be obtained by means of indirect measurement of its transport in a coexisting phase where dilfusion is rapid. We believe that dilli.tsion coefficients on the order of lo-l4 cm'/s can be readily measured by the procedure outlined here. The results from our Mg selfdiffusion experiments in spine1 provide information on the thermal history of POIs. For a maximum melting temperature of POIs of -1500°C the duration of heating at this T is &lt; 1 h and the initial cooling rate at 1500°C is &gt; lOO"C/h. This appears to be faster than the cooling rate of a few tenths to -5O'C/h for CAIs inferred from petrographic studies. For a more reasonable temperature where most of the PO1 is liquid (-135O"C), the cooling rate must be faster than 25'C/ h. We believe this latter value to be the appropriate estimated cooling rate. The melting of POIs probably occurred by flash heating in a hot parcel or region of the nebula. As shown by our previous study ( SHENG et al., 199 la), the absence of 26A1 in most POIs suggests flash heating occurred several million years after CA1 formation. Thus, repetitive heating events may have frequently generated or reprocessed refractory residues which were not themselves primary assemblages but rather material reflecting similar heating processes over a prolonged timescale over very early solar system history. More broadly, we believe that the approach presented here may have widespread application to precise studies of multicomponent diffusion transport and provide insight into transport mechanisms in melts and crystals.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. I. Schematic illustrations showing preparation of the diffusion couple. Crucible dimensions (3) were 3 mm ID and -5 mm height to spine1 slab. Chips of homogenized *'Mg-doped glass were remelted inside a Pt crucible to produce bubble-free glass. The glass was then re-equilibrated at a temperature slightly below the spine]-saturation temperature of the melt composition to ensure chemical equilibrium.The glass was polished after the open end was sawed off. A polished spine1 slab which had been annealed at 1500°C for 24 h was placed against the polished glass. The glass and spine1 slab were fastened together with Pt wire and placed into a furnace at a selected temperature at which the melt-crystal couple was then held for a known time.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 2. (a) SEM backscattered electron (BSE) image of one run product ( 1553°C) showing a cross section of the spine1 slab welded to the glass contained inside a Pt crucible. (b) An enlarged secondary electron image showing that the wetting of melt on the spine1 surface yielded a sharp welded contact between the two phases. The scale bar is 10 rm.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,42.78,70.12,237.60,440.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where CL0 and CR0 denote the initial concentrations (atoms per unit volume) of species Ci in phase L and R, mspectively, and Z L and ZR are the total concentrations of all the isotope species of the element in phase L or R . Note that the isotopic compositions determine Cp" / ZhR . For example, Equations for the other species and phases are similar. Provided that there is no convection, and no growth or dissolution of spine1 (i.e., no moving boundaries), the relevant transport equations for constant diffusion coefficients are</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIG. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>FIG. 4. Schematic drawing illustrating the diffusion couple prior to heating (a and b) and after heating with some diffusion of Mg. (a) The abundance profiles of MgO in melt and spinet which are in chemical equilibrium. The concentration of MgO in spine1 (MgA120d) is always 28.2% by weight, while the con~ntmtion of MgO in the melt is adjusted to achieve chemical ~u~b~urn for each experiment. (b) The initial concentrations of Mg isotopes, Cp and Cfo, in melt and spine1 respectively. (c) The concentrations of Mg isotopes after heating; some diffusion of Mg has occurred. Note that while the Ci are discontinuous at the boundary (x = 0), the ratios are not, Cf I;&amp; = Cjs ZR at x = 0. The parameters used are listed in the figure and were chosen for convenience in graphing. They are not related to the experimental data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>special relation from Eqns. ( 11 a) and ( 11 b ) , when two isotopes (i, j) have the same initial ratio in both L and R. That is, when C? jC]% = Cp j Cb = Ki,j (a constant), then CfjCf = CfjCf = Ki,j for all x and t. This means that if the 26Mgj2%g ratio is initially the same in L and R, then the ratio C&amp;/C&amp; = C$,jC&amp; = constant, even though dCfR /at # 0 for i = 24 or 26. This condition allows one to correct for instrumental mass fractionation and obtain precise and reliable results for the tracer isotope. Given a solution in one region (L or R), Eqn. ( 11) can be used immediately to construct a solution in the other phase. At the boundary x = 0, we have CT(O) C?(O) ~ *i = cp + UC? is a constant. The value of [i at the boundary thus depends only on the initial chemical and isotopic composition of the system and on the diffusion coefficient in each phase, via LY. Note that if cr = 1 and Z R = Z L, then we obtain the usual resultEqn. 11 b) and the value of Ai and Bi as determined above, we can plot the inverse error function vs. x/G;. The slope of the best fit line determines the diffusion coefficient DR.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>profiles from electron probe WDS analysis of the experiment at 1495'C showing concentrations of MgO, A&amp;q, SiOr, and CaO in the melt as a function of distance from the spinelmelt interface. (b) The percent deviation of each analysis from the mean concentration of respective oxides in the glass. The scale rep resents the data in (a) (one data point per bin) but are compressed to include all results. The relatively constant concentrations of these oxides indicate that there are no detectable changes in the chemical composition of each phase. Errors in the elemental concentrations are in general less than 2%.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 6. (a) Variation of the isotopic composition, CZs / ZMg (filled squares), in spine1 and melt following a diffusion experiment held at 1495°C for 2 h. Mg isotope ratios are analyzed with an ion microprobe using a primary beam focussed to a diameter of about 5 pm. The 2sSi+/24Mgf ratio (open squares) was monitored to verify the position of the spinel-melt boundary. (b) Enlarged view of area near boundary shown in (a). The value of &amp; at the boundary is determined by extrapolating the measured data in spine1 and melt to the spinel-glass interface. It can be seen that the profile in the glass places a much more stringent constraint on the boundary value. (c) Isotopic composition profile in spine1 showing a diffusion distance of about 50 pm. The fitted curve is the calculated diffusion profile using Eqn.( 1 I b). The analytical errors in Cz=,/ZMg are smaller than the spot size. The diffusion coefficient was extracted from a best fit of the data plotted using Eqn. ( 13). (d) Isotopic composition profile in glass showing a diffusion distance of about 2000 Frn. The diffusion coefficient of Mg in the melt calculated from DR and LY is DL = 6.19 X lo-' cm*/s. The fitted curve is calculated from Eqn. ( I la).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 7. (a) Temperature dependence of the diffusion coefficient for Mg self-diffusion in spine1 obtained from the Arrhenius relation D = D,,exp( -E/RT). The activation energy E = 384 f 7 kJ and pre-exponential factor DO= 74.6 f 1.1 cmZ/s are derived by a linear regression of the diffusion coefficients obtained from experimental data at different temperatures. (b) The diffusion coefficients in the melt, cakulated with the constraints imposed by the solutions from Mg diffusion in coexisting spinel, are used to determine the activation energy of Mg in the silicate melt. From the available data in four experiments, the activation energy and pre-exponential factor are 343 + 25 kJ and 779 1.9 k 1.3 cm2 , respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG.8. Calculated curve showing the time to homogenize Mg isotopes between a spine1 crystal (radius = 10 pm) and a PO1 melt as a function of temperature. The diffusion data from our experiments constrain time that the spine1 grain can be maintained at a certain temperature and still allow preservation of Mg isotope heterogeneity in spine]. This does not account for the time elapsed during heating or cooling of the inclusion and thus represents an upper limit on the duration of the heating event at r,,, In order to preserve Mg isotopic heterogeneity in POIs at a heating temperature of 15OO"C, the maximum amount of time allowed is less than one hour.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>F</head><label></label><figDesc>'OIs can be obtained by considering the case of instantaneous heating to a maximum temperature followed by cooling. We define the time integral of the diffusion coefficient (15) If we integrate Eqn. ( 15 ) over a sufficiently long time so that diffusion effectively ceases, the total time integral T(W) of the diffusion coefficient from an initial temperature To to freeze out (D + 0temperature T is some function of time t. As shown by KAISER and WASSERBURG ( 1983), The parameter r. is the initial cooling rate ( dT/dt),=o, and r0 ,I-o = T, ' The approximation given in Eqns. ( 16b) and ( 16~) assumes that E/RTo $ I and that T(t) is a smooth monotonically decreasing function of time. The exact integral of Eqn. ( 16a) depends on the cooling model but is adequately represented by Eqn. ( 16~) for the purposes required here. The initial cooling rate r. is related to the fractional cooling rate p (GOLDSTEIN and OGILVIE, 1965) by the relation r. = pTo. Using Eqn. ( 16c), the characteristic diffision distance is given approximately by x2 =7(m)= RT;D( To) roE '</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 9. Calculated curves showing the dependence of initial cooling rate (rO) upon temperature (To) for grains with radii of 5, 10, and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>smaller than -11 pm would isotopically reequilibrate with the melt. Spine1 in Type B CAIs frequently exceeds 50 pm in size, yet few Type B CAIs exhibit heterogeneity in 2sMg/24Mg ratios either among spinels or between spine1 and silicates. In the context of the model developed for PO1 ( SHENG et al.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 Comwsition d hrthm hfatdd 155361 149761 149561 1415Gl 135461 1302Gl 126161 Spillel</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Mro</cell><cell>MA</cell><cell>w</cell><cell cols="4">cao sum %fgmg "c,</cell><cell>r&amp;rr</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">11.69 32.29</cell><cell>43.71</cell><cell>12.76</cell><cell cols="2">100.55 0.90530</cell><cell>0.00299</cell><cell>0.00679</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">13.23 33.06</cell><cell>43.35</cell><cell>10.82</cell><cell>100.56</cell><cell>1.47665</cell><cell>0.00433</cell><cell>0.00767</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">13.81 30.84</cell><cell>44.39</cell><cell>10.92</cell><cell>99.96</cell><cell>0.81343</cell><cell>0.00334</cell><cell>o.OOgO3</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">14.08 28.60</cell><cell>47.34</cell><cell>10.06</cell><cell cols="2">100.08 1.18216</cell><cell>0.00416</cell><cell>0.00817</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">13.12 25.81</cell><cell>49.32</cell><cell>11.10</cell><cell cols="2">100.35 1.47809</cell><cell>0.00431</cell><cell>0.00761</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">13.17 25.16</cell><cell>51.78</cell><cell>10.47</cell><cell cols="2">100.58 1.47841</cell><cell>0.00431</cell><cell>0.00764</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">14.58 22.76</cell><cell>54.45</cell><cell>7.97</cell><cell>99.76</cell><cell>0.85726</cell><cell>0.00423</cell><cell>0.00848</cell></row><row><cell>28.20</cell><cell>72.63</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell cols="2">100.88 0.12633</cell><cell>0.00254</cell><cell>0.02541</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Oxides are in wt. I, initial UMg m and total Mg (C Mg) concentrations are in moles/cc.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgmenfs-We express our appreciation to <rs type="person">D. S. Burnett</rs> who generously allowed us use of his laboratory. We are thankful to <rs type="person">M. L. Johnson</rs> and <rs type="person">T. LaTourette</rs> for their good-spirited aid and support in use of the furnace. G. <rs type="person">R. Rossman</rs> kindly provided the spinels used in our experiments. We appreciate the helpful comments of <rs type="person">J. R. Beckett</rs> and <rs type="person">Y. Zhang</rs> and the assistance of L. Hedges in sample preparation. Thorough reviews by <rs type="person">R. T. Cygan</rs>, <rs type="person">F. Richter</rs>, and <rs type="person">J. Ganguly</rs> were of great aid and are gratefully acknowledged. This work was supported by <rs type="funder">DOE</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">DEFGO388ER13851</rs> and <rs type="funder">NASA</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">NAG 9-43</rs>.</p><p>Editorial handling: <rs type="person">M. S. Ghiorio</rs></p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_MTBwKkp">
					<idno type="grant-number">DEFGO388ER13851</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_mS5Ayf6">
					<idno type="grant-number">NAG 9-43</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative analysis of silicate and oxide minerals: A reevaluation of ZAF corrections and proposal for new Bence-Albee coefficients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Microbeam Analysis-1984</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Romig</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>San Francisco Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="212" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Al-rich objects in ordinary chon-d&amp;es: Related origin of carbonaceous and ordinary chondrites and their constituents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bischoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Keil</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="709" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Isotopic heterogeneity in calcium-aluminum rich meteoritic inclusions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brigham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>California Institute of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">) Compositional zoning and cation diffusion in garnets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ganguly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Phy. Geochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">199 1</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An ion-microprobe study of the self-diffusion of Li+ of lithium fluoride</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Coles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V P</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phiios. Mag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Mathematics ofDi$usion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Claredon Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-diffusion of magnesium in garnet at 750 to 900°C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T C</forename><surname>Cygan R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. J. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Null result&quot; diffusion experiments with diopside: Implications for pyroxene equilibria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Freer R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V P</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Reed</forename><forename type="middle">S J B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="292" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mg-Fe Order-Disorder in ferromagnesian silicates. II. Thermodynamics, kinetics and geological applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ganguly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Phy. Geochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convolution effect in the determination of compositional profiles and diffusion coefficients by microprobe step scans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ganguly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chakraborty</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bha-~tacharya R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="909" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The growth of the Widmanstatten pattern in metallic meteorites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">1</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ogilvie R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="893" to="920" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FUN with PANURGE: High mass resolution ion microprobe measurements of Mg in Allende inclusions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Huneke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1635" to="1650" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isotopic studies of Mg, Fe, MO, Ru and W in Fremdlinge from Allende refractory inclusions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hutcheon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3175" to="3192" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diffusion in Solids, Liquids, Gases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Jost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1952">1952</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cations in olivine, part 1: Calcium partitioning and calcium-magnesium distribution between olivines and coexisting melts, with petrologic applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J G</forename><surname>Jurewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson E</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="176" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The isotopic composition and concentration of Ag in iron meteorites and the origin of exotic silver</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kaiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diffusion von Ni-63 in Nickelspinellen. 2. Phys. Chem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lindner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="307" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of a new correction procedure for quantitative electron probe microanalysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Love</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Scott V</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1369" to="1376" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The origin and significance of reverse zoning in melilite from Allende Type B inclusions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Macpherson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Paque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Grossman L</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ion-probe measurement of oxygen self-diffusion in single-crystal Al203</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Cer. Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Origin of plagioclase-olivine inclusions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">199 1</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>California Institute of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">a) Origin of plagioclase-olivine inclusions in carbonaceous chondrites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hutcheon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="599" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">1 b) Experimental constraints on the origin of plagioclaseolivine inclusions and CA chondrules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Beckett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hutcheon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lunar Planet. Sci. Conf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1231" to="1232" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">~) Mg self-diffusion in spine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hutcheon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Constraints on the thermal history of plaaioclase-olivine inclusions</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">XXII</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1233" to="1234" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystallization sequences of Ca-Al-rich inclusions from Allende: An experimental study. Geochim</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Stolper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cosmochim. Acta SO</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1785" to="1806" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The nature and origin of Type Bl and B2 &amp;Al-rich inclusions in the Allende meteorite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="2594" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Sm, Sr, and Pb in fluorapatite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wa'ison E</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1813" to="1823" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
