<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">~~usiv~~ of oxygen in jadeite and diepside melts at high pressures</title>
				<funder ref="#_mFTqHBN">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSF</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shimizu'</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro~</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">&apos;Center for Geoalchemy</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dept. of Earth and Planetary Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">%eophysical Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02 139</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Inst. W~in~on</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20008</postCode>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>D.C</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">~~usiv~~ of oxygen in jadeite and diepside melts at high pressures</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BC5BA05670514B1659FD2F45F18719D3</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received September 2, 1983; accepted in revised form March 19, 1984</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Abatmct-The dif%sivity of oxy-gen was determined in melts of jade&amp;e (PkAlSiz06) and dioppide (CaMgSi~O~) compositions using diffusion couples with '8ct as a tracer. In the jadeite melt, the diffisivity of oxygen +0.28 increases from 6.g7_0.25 X lO-1o cms/sec at 5 Kb to 1.32 It 0.08 X 10e9 cm'/sec at 20 Kb at constant +0.29 temperature (14OO"C), whereas in the diopside melt at 165O"C, the diffisivity decreases from 7.30+ 18 +0.60 X lo-' cm2/sec at 10 Kb to 5.28_o,55 X lo-' cm2/sec at 17 Kb. These results demonstrate that the diffisivity is inversely comlated with the viscosity of the melt. For the jadeite melt, in particular, the inverse correlation is very well approximated by the Eyring equation using the diameter of oxygen ions as a unit distana of translation, Suggesting that the viscous 5ow is rate-jimited by the diffusion of i~i~du~ oxygen ions. In the diopside melithe activation volume is slightly greater than the molar volume of oxygen ion, indicating that the individual oxygen ion is the diffusion unit. The negative activation volume obtained for the iadeite melt is interpreted as the volume decrease associated with a diffusive jump of an oxygen ion due to local collapse of-the network structum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCIION</head></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>OXYGEN IS THE most abundant element in silicate melts of geologic interest and its di&amp;sivity is important for understanding their structure and its relationship with physical properties such as viscosity and elastic wave velocities. The diffusivity of oxygen in silicate melts of geologic interest has been measured by severat investigators at 1 atm (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">KOROS and KING, 1962;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">OISHI et al., 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">MUEHLENBACHS and KUSHIRO, 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr">MUEHLENBACHS and !&amp;HAEFFER, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">DUNN, 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">among others)</ref>. No measurements had been made, however, on the diffirsivity of oxygen in silicate melts at high pressures until those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">DUNN (1983)</ref>, who studied "chemical difision" of oxygen associated with redox reaction of basaltic melts at high pressures. <ref type="bibr">Recently, ANGELL et al. f 1982)</ref> demonstrated with an ion dynamics computer simulation that the diffusivity of oxygen as well as that of Si and Al ions in jadeite melt increases with increasing pressure to 200 kbar and then decmases at higher pressures at constant temperature (6000 K). <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">KUSHIRO (1983)</ref> demonstrated by experiments that the rates of Si-Ge and Al-Ga interdiffusion in jadeitic melts (NaAl(Si, GehOs and Na(A1, Ga)S&amp;Ob) increase with increasing pressure at constant temperature, thus supporting the results of the ion dynamics computer simulations. He noted that the increase of the diffusivities of these ions with pressure may be related to the decrease of viscosity of the same melt observed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">KUSHIRO (1976)</ref>. However, the diffusivity of oxygen (or more precisely the rate of selfdiffusion of oxygen) must be known before the relation between diffisivity and viscosity of a melt can be discussed conclusively.</p><p>In view of the increasing use of oxygen isotope ratios (or 6"O) as a tracer in igneous petrogenesis (e.g., IT0 and STERN, 1981; JAMES, 1982; among others), diffusivity of oxygen in natural magmas could provide an important constraint on kinetic aspects of geochemical models particularly with respect to the isotopic systematics.</p><p>As a step toward these goals, the self diffusion of oxygen was experimentally investigated in two contrasting simple silicate melts: one of jade&amp; composition and the other of diopside composition. With respect to the degree of polymerization, the jadeite melt rep resents one of the most polymerized silicate melts of geologic interest both at 1 atm and at high pressures (SHARMA et al., <ref type="bibr">1978)</ref>, whereas the diopside melt is significantly depolymerized. Reflecting, perhaps, the contrast in polymerization, these melts represent two extremes in a spectrum of viscosities in silicate melts: the jadeite melt at the high viscosity end and the diop side melt at the low viscosity end (for instance, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">SCARFE et al., 1979)</ref>. Another aspect of the contrasting behavior of these melts is their pressure-induced variations in viscosities. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">KUSHIRO ( 1976)</ref> showed that in the jadeite melt viscosity decreases with increasing pressure at a constant temperature (135O"C), whereas S~ARFE d al. <ref type="bibr">( 1979)</ref> reported that in the diopside melt viscosity increases with increasing pressure. Given the background information just mentioned, the main effort of the present study was to determine the diffisivity of oxygen in these melts at high pressures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Slarting material</head><p>The self ditfusion of oxygen was measured with a diffusion couple consisting of a melt (of either jadeite or diopside composition) enriched in '80 and one with normal '"0 abundance.</p><p>The W-enriched glass was prepared by the following pro-I296 Y. Shimizu and 1. Kushiro cedures. First, '*O-enriched Si02 was made by reacting metallic Si and H20 enriched in '*O ('*O abundance of 50%). These were sealed in a Pt tube 3 mm in outside diameter and 22 mm in length and were heated at 800°C at 6 kbar for 2 hours in a gas-media, high-pressure apparatus. The run products were mostly Si02 (quartz) with a small amount of unreacted Si near the ends of the capsule. Apparently the reaction: Si +-2H20 = SiO, + 2H2 took place, and hydrogen produced by the reaction diffused through the Pt capsule. Next, the '80-enriched Si02 was mixed thoroughly with spectroscopically pure Na2COj, and A&amp;O3 for the jadeite melt and with CaCO, and MgO for the diopside melt (of normal 6180) in an agate mortar. The well-mixed. very line-grained powder was melted in a Pt crucible in air. The melting for the jadeite composition was done at 128O'C for about 20 minutes, and at 1450°C for 15 minutes for the diopside composition The melting durations were intended to be short to prevent extensive loss of '*O from the starting materials. The glass thus made was again ground to a fine powder (less than 5 pm in diameter). Some '*O was lost during this melting procedure as described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Run procedure</head><p>The powder of '*O-enriched glass was compressed in a Pt tube 3 mm in diameter and 12 mm in length with a metal rod with a polished end surface just fitted to the inside wall of the Pt tube. The fine-grained "normal" glass ("0 is 0.2% of total oxygen) was packed on top of the compressed powder which had a flat smooth surface. It is important to note that the present experimental configuration provides a system without a bulk flow, suitable for determining self diffusion. A similar technique was used in a study of Si-Ge and AI-Ga interdiffusion in jadeite melts <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(KUSHIRO, 1983)</ref>. It was demonstrated in the previous experiments that the interface was not disturbed during the runs with this procedure. The charges were dried in an oven and heated to -500°C immediately before welding the Pt tube.</p><p>The runs were made with a solid-media, high-pressure ap paratus. The run conditions and durations are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Furnace assemblies with a tapered graphite heater, described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(KUSHIRO, 1976)</ref>, were used for all runs. The advantage of this is to reduce the temperature gradient inside the charge to within 10°C. The charges were surrounded by hematite powder. except near the top of the charge. 13 trap hydrogen possibly diffusing into the charges. Hematite in contact with the charge was recrystallized to coarse-grained crystals but was not reduced during the runs. A hot pistonout method with 4% correction for friction was applied. The error of pressure measurements is probably less than 5% above 10 kbar and less than 20% near 5 kbar. After the runs the charges were sliced longitudinally and polished for ion probe analysis.</p><p>The MIT.-Harvard-Brown Cameca IMS 3F ion microprobe was used to measure 'RO/'60 ratios along the longitudinal traverse through the sectioned experimental charges. A primary O-ion beam with 0.2 nA current was focused to a spot of approximately 15-20 pm in diameter. The principal difference from the previous oxygen isotope analysis with the ion microprobe (e.g., GILETTI and YUND, 1983) was in measuring negative (O-) secondary ions with an electron multiplier/pulse counter, which provided an intensity of '60 up to 5 X 10' cps as opposed to less than 3 X lo' cps for positive secondary ions with approximately the same primary beam conditions. The measurements were made without energy filtering because molecular ion interference was virtually nonexistent on masses 16 and 18.</p><p>'sO/'6O ratios were obtained using a computer program which measures intensities at mass positions 15.5 (background), I6 and I8 by switching the magnetic field stepwise in the ascending mass direction in a cycle; seven cycles of measurements were taken, and six sets of doubly-time-interpolated ratios were calculated for every block. Four blocks of data were taken for each spot, and the in-run precision based on 24 ratios was typically less than 0.2% at the 95% confidence level, and in the most adverse case (the "normal" end of the charge) it was around I .5W.</p><p>Since an O-primary ion beam with normal isotopic composition was used, the measured 'sO/'6O ratios were significantly modified from the expected values due mainly to the following mechanisms: (I) backscattered primary O-ions may be directly mixed with the secondary O-ions and detected. thereby increasing the abundance of I60 in the measured oxygen ion population; (2) implanted primary-ion oxygen may be sputtered and ionized later together with the oxygen atoms in the sample, increasing the abundance of '60 in the measured ion population; (3) oxygen atoms with normal isotopic composition absorbed on the surface and/or attached to the surface during gold coating process may be knockedon to a certain depth of the sample by the primary ions and sputtered later with the sample oxygen atoms, which also increases the abundance of "0 in the measured ion population. Furthermore, isotopic fractionation during sputteting/ionization may increase the abundance of I60 in the secondary ion population if Fractionation during negative ion production is similar to that observed for positive ions (SHIMIZU and HART, 1982). Although it is difficult to evaluate the significance of these individual mechanisms separately, it should be noted that all these effects increase the '60 abundance (decreasing I80 abundance) in the measured ion population and can thus be treated together as an overall "dilution" effect. In the present study, the 'dilution" effect was evaluated in the following manner. A oolvcrvstalline SiO? with 50% IsO synthesized as part of the &amp;r&amp; material was analyzed repeatedly in order to determine the magnitude and reproducibiIity of the dilution effect. At the beginning of sputtering, 'sO/'6O ratios increased from 0.307 to 0.325, and after approximately 6 minutes of sputtering the measured values remained constant within the analytical error at a value of0.325. Based on this observation, data aquisition for each spot was initiated after 6 minutes of sputtering. The measured 'sO/"O ratio just mentioned corresponds to mixing proportions of 49% sample oxygen and 51% "normal" oxygen from various sources. The replicate analyses of the '%-enriched SiOl in a 6-month period, showed that these mixing proportions are reproducible to within 2% (relative) at 95% confidence level, demonstrating a long-term reproducibility of the dilution effect. In addition, during the course of the analysis, the i*O-emiched end of the experimental charge was analyzed repeatedly to verify that the dilution effect was not variable over a period of several hours. The fact that the '8O/'6O ratios were reproducible within 2% (20) during a Chour traveme suggests that although the dilution effect indeed varied outside the counting statistics (which were 0.2-1.52 typically) and could in fact be a major source of analytical uncertainties, it does not change the results significantly.</p><p>The abundance of '80 in the 'Soenriched end of the jadeite melt corrected for the dilution effect was approximately 20%, compared with the nominal value of 28.6% estimated from the stoichiometric proportions of NarCOr (normal), A1203 (normal) and SiOr (50% IsO). This shows that a portion of '*O was exchanged with normal air oxygen during melting of the starting mix in the air. A greater ia0 exchange was found in the diopside melt, as the corrected "0 abundance in the '*O-enriched end was about 13% compared with the nominal value of 25%. This was due to the higher temperature of fusion for the diopside mix.</p><p>The reproducibility of the dilution effect on both short-(within a day) and long-term (day-today) basis and the reproducibility of the '*O abundance in the L80-enriched end among different charges suggest that each starting material was homogeneous with respect to the abundance of "0 and that the results are internally consistent.</p><p>The abundance of I*0 in the "normal" end of the charge was typically 0.22 + 0.02% identical, within the analytical uncertainty, to the nominal abundance of 0.2%. This suggests that there was no significant molecular ion interference at mass 18 (for instance, 'H2'60).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Absence of convection</head><p>In order for the calculated ditfusion coefficients to be rep resentative of volume diffusion, the absence of other modes of transport must be established. Convection may be the easiest mechanism of transport in the silicate melt. In his Si-Ge and</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AlGa interdiffision experiments, KUSHIRO (1983) placed</head><p>the Ge-bearing and Ga-bring (i.e., heavy) starting materials at the bottom ofthe charge to maintain gravitational stability. He obtained a sharp and planar interface which was optically visible due to the difference in refractive indices, suggesting that convection was virtually non-existent.</p><p>In the present experiments, the same precaution was made in placing the '*O-enriched (i.e., heavy) starting material at the bottom of the charge. Three parallel longitudinal traverses made on both the jadeite and diopside melt samples revealed no difference in the shape and location of the diffusion gradients, suggesting that convection was not significant. Furthermore, no gradient larger than the spatial resolution (-20 pm) was observed in a charge run at 5 kbar and 1280°C for the jadeite composition and this also attests to the virtual absence of convection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Time study</head><p>In order to show that the run duration of the present study was sufficiently long, a duplicate run was conducted at a selected P and T (I 5 Kb, 1400°C for jadeite and 17 Kb, 1650°C for diopside) with a greater duration (6 hours as opposed to 2 hours for jadeite; 60 minutes as opposed to 15 minutes for diopside). As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, the diffusion coefficients obtained were indistinguishable from those of the short runs, suggesting that the run duration was sufficient for the diopside runs and at least for the 14OO'C runs for jadeite. The results can be interpreted by a diffusion model with a composite semi-infinite media <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(CRANK, 1975)</ref>. The solution to the diffusion equation is:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Calculation of d@iiion coejkient</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">(_. _ c, + cz + Cl - c2 erf 1x1 -- 2 2 ( 2\/Tsi;j 1 (1)</formula><p>where C denotes the concentration of the diffusing species (igO in the present case) at position x (measured born the initial interface), C, and Cr are the initial concentrations in the right (x &gt; 0) and the left (x c 0) halves, respectively, D is the diffusion coefficient and t the time in seconds. Equation</p><p>(1) can be linearized as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">y = erf-' [ 2c -(C, + C,) c, -c2 1 =$ (2)</formula><p>where erf' denotes the inverse of the error function. based on the initial observed concentrations (C, and Cr), the data points in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> can be replotted in an x vs. y diagram to give a straight line. The ditfusion coefficient can thus be obtained from the slope of the line.</p><p>In the present case, no effort was made to correct the observed iSO abundances for the "dilution" effect in view of its constancy as noted previously and in view of the fact that the dilution correction simply changes C and Ci but not the slope of the line; C, and C2 were thus directly taken from the values obtained for the flat ends of the profile. Since the initial interface was optically invisible on the surface of the sample, it was estimated as the position corresponding to C = (C, + C2)/2 and x of each data point was measured directly from the profile. The diffusion coefficient was calculated from the slope of the best-fit line through the data using the leastsquares method of YORK (1969) with a blanket error of 2% on both x and y. Judging from the reproducibility mentioned earlier, the error used in the cakatlation results in a conservative estimate of uncertainty in the diBusion co&amp;icients. The values in Table <ref type="table">I</ref> show that the diffusion coelEcients are determined with a standard error ranging from 3.6% to 10% for the jadeite melt and 2.5% to 11% for the diopside melt.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>The present results, summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1,</ref><ref type="table"></ref>  This conclusion is in contrast to that of MAGARITZ and HOFMANN <ref type="bibr">(1978)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">WAT~UN (1979)</ref> who showed that the Stokes-Einstein relation is qualitatively and quantitatively incompatible with the behavior of cations in silicate melts. As noted by ANGELL et al. <ref type="bibr">( 1982)</ref>, however, a bulk physical property such as viscosity may be determined essentially by the mobility of network ions rather than non-network cations which occupy network-channel positions.</p><p>For the diopside melt, the fact that the 0 kb and 10 kb data are not well approximated by the Eyring relationship suggests that viscous flow in a depoly-me&amp;d, low viscosity melt is not rate-limited by the diffusion of oxygen. Also plotted in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>   <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">YINNON and COOPER, 1980)</ref>. In plotting, the dilfusivity was calculated at 1400°C using the Arrhenius equations given, and the viscosity at the same temperature was calculated from the chemical composition using the method of BOT-TlNGA and WEILL (1972). <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">DUNN's (1982)</ref> data on diopside and l&amp;Arr,r melts are also shown for comparison.</p><p>From the difhtsivity data obtained in the jadeite melt at three different temperatures at 15 kbar (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>), the activation energy is calculated as 61 + 2 kcal/mole. If an individual oxygen ion is indeed the diffusion and viscous flow unit as suggested by the Eyring relationship, it may be expected that the activation energy of oxygen diffusion is identical to the activation energy of viscous flow. In fact. the activation energy of oxygen diffusion obtained above is close to the activation energy of viscous flow at I5 kb (67.3 -+ 2.4 kcal/mole), calculated with the two new viscosity measurements reported here and KUSHIRO'S (I 976) data. thus supporting the present interpretation. <ref type="bibr">OISHI t'l al. (1975)</ref> stated that in some of the melts in the NazO-SiOZ. Na*O-CaO-Si02 and C'aO-A1203-SiO-, systems, the activation energies are practically identical for oxygen diffusion and viscous flow and suggested that viscous flow in these melts is rate-limited by the diffusion of oxygen. It can be concluded that the same holds true for the jadeite melt at I5 kbar.</p><p>Based on the isothermal data (1400°C for the jadeite melt and 1650°C for the diopside melt, see Table <ref type="table">I</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>). the activation volume can be calculated using the relationship:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">D = Dp exp</formula><p>where Dp is the zero pressure diffusion coefficient at T, P is the pressure, V, the activation volume and R the gas constant. The values obtained here are: for the jadeite melt, V. = -6.3 + 1.2 cm3/mole and for the diopside melt, V. = 8.48 + 0.13 cm'/mole (using the present results and DUNN'S ( 1982) 0 kb data). For comparison, the molar volume of oxygen ions is calculated as 6.9 cm3, using an ionic radius of 1.4 X 10m8 cm and the formula V = (4/3)v3N,</p><p>where N is Avogadro's number.</p><p>The physical significance of the activation volume is not yet clearly understood (see, for instance, <ref type="bibr">WAT-SON, 1979)</ref>. Assuming that transport phenomena in liquids occur by migration of ions or molecules via "holes" (or free volume), the activation volume may be understood as the volume change associated with a diffusive jump, for which the size of the hole relative to the volume of migrating species determines the magnitude of the volume change. For instance, if the  size of the hole is smaller than the migrating species, the latter must shoulder away atoms or molecules surrounding the hole, thereby producing a positive volume changeandthusapositiveactivationvolume. HAMANN (1965) observed a positive activation volume in the electrolytic conduction of alkali silicate glasses with a magnitude slightly greater than the molar volume of the conducting ions, and concluded that the migration of an ion requires an amount of dilation slightly greater than the volume of the ion itself. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">WATSON (1979)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">WATSON et al. (1982)</ref> adopted Hamann's interpretation and the latter authors in particular used the activation volume in identifying the diffusing species. Using the same argument for the diopside melt, the fact that the activation volume (8.48 cm3/mole) is 12% greater than the molar volume of oxygen ion (6.9 cm3) may suggest that individual oxygen ions are the migrating species (i.e., the difTusion unit) in diopside melt.</p><p>On the contrary, the negative activation volume observed in the jadeite melt suggests that a volume decrease occurs with a diffusive jump due to a local collapse of the network structure of the melt. BRUM-MER and HILTS ( 196 1) observed a negative activation energy in the electrolytic conduction in a dilute KC1 aqueous solution at lo-60°C and l-900 bars and suggested that the solvent in the immediate vicinity of the migrating ions is caused to collapse from its open network structure. Since similarities are recognized between aqueous and polymerized silicate melt solutions, particularly with respect to their anomalous physical characteristics (decrease in viscosity with increasing pressure, reduction of bond angle; see, for instance, ANGELL et al., 1982), the physical significance of the negative activation volume in the jadeite melt may be construed by analogy to Brummer and Hills' interpretation. Although it is unclear how much volume decrease should occur upon a diffusive jump of an oxygen ion in the jadeite melt, the closeness of the volume decrease (6.3 cm-'/mole) to the molar volume of oxygen ion (6.9 cm3) appears more than a coincidence.</p><p>It seems important to note that the data compiled by SCARFE et al. ( <ref type="formula">1979</ref>) demonstrate that many silicate melts of geologic interest, including natural bar&amp;s fraction of free volume may decrease with increasing and andesites, show a decrease in viscosity with in-degree of polymerization. creasing pressure. Therefore, if the inverse correlation</p><p>The notion that a liquid consists of molecules and between viscosity and oxygen ditfusivity is maintained, holes WCS first theorized by EYRING ( 1936) and more these melts would show an increase in oxygen dilfu-recently by COHEN and TURNBULL <ref type="bibr">(1959)</ref> and, as sivity with increasing pressure, thereby providing a pointed out by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">CHARLES ( 1962)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">WATSON ( 1979)</ref>, negative activation volume. It thus seems that negative knowledge of the free volume is very important in activation volumes for oxygen diffusion are a rule understanding the relationship between structure and rather than an exception for natural silicate melts.</p><p>transport properties of silicate melts. It is our belief <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">DUNN'S (1983)</ref> recent data show that the rate of that combined effort in studies of molecular contigchemical diffusion of oxygen in the natural basaltic urations (e.g., the Raman Spectra studies) and those melts changes discontinuously as a function of pressure of diffusion in the light of the free volume concept at constant temperature when the liquidus phase will provide an integrated view of silicate melt structure. changes from olivine to pyroxene. Data are not avail-</p><p>The conclusion drawn here that an individual oxable to verify that the sudden change in oxygen chem-ygen ion is the diffision unit for both polymerized ical diffusion is associated with viscosity change.</p><p>(iadeite) and depolymerized (diopside) melts does not Dependence of the activation volume on temper-imply that the diffusion of individual oxygen ion is ature was not experimentally determined but by a the only mechanism of oxygen transport in these melts, comparison with the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">ANGELL et al. (1982)</ref>, but that the diffusion of oxygen ions is the fastest it is suggested that the magnitude of the activation mechanism observable under the experimental convolume for oxygen diffusion in the jadeite melt de-ditions encountered in the present work. Thus the creases with increasing temperature (6.3 cm'/mole at present results do not directly contribute to the un-1673 K and 3.17 cm'/mole at 6000 K). <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">WATSON ( 1979)</ref> derstanding of the molecular configuration of silicate also observed a decrease in the activation volume of melts. Ca diffusion with increasing temperature in a silicate melt (11.9 cm3/mole at 1373 K and 2.24 cm3/mole GEOCHEMICAL IMPLICATIONS at 1673 K). The rate of decrease of activation volume for oxygen diffusion is more than two orders of mag-</p><p>The geochemical applications of diffusivity data have nitude smaller than that for Ca diffusion, suggesting been discussed by many authors (e.g., HOF&amp;~ANN and that the size of holes related to oxygen diffusion does <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">MAGARITZ, 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr">MAGARITZ and HOPMANN, 1978</ref>; not change much with temperature whereas the size <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">HOFMANN and HART, 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">HOFMANN, 1980</ref>; SHAW, of the holes related to non-network cation diffusion 1974; <ref type="bibr">KARSTEN et al., 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">WATSON, 1979;</ref><ref type="bibr">1982;</ref><ref type="bibr"></ref> may vary significantly with temperature. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">WATSON et al., 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr">among others)</ref>. BOTIINGA and Based on the contrasting geophysical and transport <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">JAVOY (1975)</ref> discussed the importance of oxygen difproperties between the jade&amp;e and diopside melts, their fusion in igneous and metamorphic rocks with respect relative structural differences can be visualized as folto oxygen isotope thennometry. Most of the studies lows: the diopside melt consists of smaller structural are concerned with cation diffusion and thus the main units (depolymerized), with a smaller average inter-interest is in estimating the time required to homogunit distance (higher density). This results in a smaller enize a material with initial inhomogeneity with respect size of the individual holes. In contrast, the jadeite to the concentration of an element of interest. Although melt consists of large structural units (polymerized) the basic principles are the same between cation difwith more open network structure so that the density fusion and self-diffusion of oxygen as studied here, is considerably smaller, and the size of the individual problems to which the oxygen diffusivity data are ag holes is greater. Overall, the structure of a silicate melt plicable are limited, because there is very little differis characterized not only by the size of the structural ence in the concentration of oxygen among geologic units (or degree of polymerization), but also by the materials; they are applicable to cases where homogsize, number and distribution of free volume (or holes). enization of isotopic composition is examined. For In particular, the bansport properties such as dithtsivity instance, consider the interaction of basaltic magma and viscosity could be controlled mainly by the prop and a wall rock. Exchange of oxygen isotopes occurs erties of the free volume. For instance, the size of the between the magma and the wall rock and subsequent free volume relative to the size of the migrating species self-diffusion of oxygen gradually alters the 6isO value determines the activation volume, and perhaps the of the "contaminated" magma. Diffusive alteration of number of holes in a unit volume could play a role PO of a magma by partially melted xenoliths is anin determining what fraction of atoms, molecule or other example where oxygen diffusivity data is appliions can be, statistically, in the activated state, thereby cable. determining the pre-exponential term (or the 'fre-However, usefulness of the present results in the quency factor': De) of the Arrhenius-type expression for the diffusion coefficient. In this context, it is in-geochemical problems just mentioned depends on whether they can be extrapolated to silicate melts of teresting to note that Do decreases from 16.4 cm2/sec natural magmatic compositions and whether selfdifin diopside melt (DUNN, 1982) to 0.0129 cm2/sec in a D&amp;Ah melt <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(DUNN, 1982)</ref>, suggesting that the fusion of oxygen is an effective mechanism of oxygen transport in natural magmas. As to the former, the 0 diffusion in jadeite, diopside 1301 "u. Shlmizu and I. Kushlro fact that an excellent inverse correlation exists between viscosity and oxygen diffusivity in two "end member" silicate melts of geologic interest strongly suggests that the oxygen difisivity in various dry natural magmas may be estimated by using the regression line through the data points in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, when the viscosities of the magmas are known. The regression line obtained has a slope of 1.06 + 0.04 ( 1 (T), suggesting that the Eyringtype relationship, which predicts a slope of unity in a diagram such as Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, is indeed a good approximation for silicate melts with a wide range of viscosities. Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> illustrates the regression line (solid line) from which the oxygen diffusivity in various natural magmas is estimated. Also plotted are the Sr and REE diffusivity data in granitic and basaltic melts from <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">MAGARITZ and HOFMANN ( 1978)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">HOFMANN and MAGARITZ (1977)</ref>. Insofar as the relationship in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> is representative, the oxygen diffusivity varies by more than four orders of magnitude from lO-'o cm'/sec in granitic magma to 5 X 10V6 cm'/sec in basaltic magma. Compared with the Sr diffisivity, it may be concluded that the oxygen diffuses significantly more slowly than cations in granitic magma but faster in basaltic magma.</p><p>It is suggested that in a granitic magma Sr isotopes may be homogenized during petrogenetic processes for a given period of time but oxygen isotopes may not. In a basaltic magma. however, oxygen isotopes are more readily homogenized than Sr isotopes. The question as to whether self-diffusion of oxygen is an effective mechanism of oxygen transport in natural magmas requires a comparison between selfdiffusion of oxygen and that of other oxygen-bearing species. Of particular interest is the difI&amp;ivities of water and CO2 The data of <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">SHAW ( 1974) and</ref><ref type="bibr">KARSTEN et al. ( 1982)</ref> suggest that the dilT&amp;ivity of water in granitic magmas ranges from IO-'* cm2/sec to 5 X 1 O-' cm'/ set at 756950°C for water content between I and 3 wt%. Insofar as the selfdiITirsion of oxygen is estimated from Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>, it seems clear that diffusion of water is a significantly more effective mechanism of oxygen transport in granitic magmas. However, adding Hz0 to a granitic melt lowers viscosity and presumably increases self-diffusion of oxygen in the melt, and it is not clear if the rate of diffusion of water (as HZ0 or as OH) is faster than self-diffusion of oxygen in hydrous granitic melts. The data of WATSON et ai. <ref type="bibr">( 1982)</ref> suggest that the diffusivity of CO2 in a sodium alumino-silicate melt is more than an order of magnitude slower than that of water in the granitic melt obtained by <ref type="bibr">KARSTEN et al. ( 1982)</ref> at comparable temperatures. The diffusivity of oxygen in the same sodium alumina-silicate melt is more than an order of magviscosity value calculated by the Bottinga-Weill model and by the regression line in Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>, is approximately 10e6 cm2/sec, about a factor of 5 greater than the measured diffusivity of CO2. This suggests, therefore, that the diffusion of CO* does not seem to be an effective mechanism of oxygen transport. Although the mechanism of water diffusion in granitic melt is not well understood (see, for instance, KARSTEN ef ul., 19821, it may be concluded that the rate of oxygen isotopic homogenization via water diffusion appears comparable to that of Sr isotopes by self-diffusion.</p><p>Data for diffusivity of water in basaltic melts 1s unknown. The CO* diffision data Of <ref type="bibr">WATSON ef al. ( 1982)</ref> in a synthetic basalt melt and the oxygen diffusivity estimated from Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> suggest that the self-diffusion of oxygen is the most effective mechanism of oxygen transport in basaltic magmas.</p><p>Depending on the transport mechanism (and thus the diffusion coefficient), effectiveness of a certain geochemical process for a given time varies significantly. For instance. consider diffusion-controlled oxygen isotope exchange-contamination process with a molten xenolith (radius 1 m) of granitic composition trapped in a large body of basaltic magma. Assuming that the granitic melt retains its integrity <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(WATSON, 1982)</ref> and using the Ehrenburg equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(LOVERING, 1936)</ref> modified for diffision, it is shown that the center of the xenolith would reach 95% isotopic equilibrium with basalt in 16,000 years if transport of oxygen iS governed by diffusion of water (3%) in the granitic melt. whereas it would reach only 40% equilibrium in 60 m.y. if self-diffusion of oxygen in a dry granitic melt is operative</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Typical diffusion profiles obtained in this study are shown in Fig. I. Each data point is represented by a rectangle for the jadeite melt (Fig. IA), representing the spatial resolution limited by the primary beam spot sire. Although data points covering the entire length ( 12 mm) of the experimental charge exist in all samples, they are not shown in the figure. The total length of the profiles in the jadeite melt ranges from approximately 200 pm for the 5 kbar run to 250 pm for the 20 kbar run, whereas in the diopside melt it exceeds I mm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIG. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIG. 1. The observed diffusion pro&amp;s of "0. The abundance of '*O was calculated from the measured "O/% ratios, uncorrected for the "dih&amp;on effects" (see text). Only the important part of the traverse is shown; both '%B-enriched and %-poor (normal) ends remain constant and extend to the edges of the charge. A: % prof11e in the jadeite melt at 20 Kb, 1400°C. The spatial resoiution limited by the primary beam spot size (-15 pm) is shown as rectangle. The dotted curve is the theoretiatl diffusion profile with D = 1.30 x 10W9 cn&amp;ec. B: % profile in the diopside melt at 10 Kb, 165OT. The dotted curve is the theoretical diffusion profile with D = 7.30 X IO-' cm'lsec.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>are some of the recent data on self difhsion of oxygen in melts in the Na$D-CaO-Si02 and CaO-A1203-Si02 systems at 1 atm (OISHI et al., 1975;</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 3. Effect of pressure on the diffusivity of oxygen in the jadeite melt at 1400°C. Each rectangle represents the experimental uncertainty of the diffusion coefficient ( 10).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIG. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>FIG. 4. Effect of temperature on the diffusivity of oxygen in the jadeite melt at 15 Kb. Each rectangle represents the experimental uncertainty of the diffusion coefficient ( 1 g).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIG. 5. The inverse correlation between viscosity (x) and oxygen diffusivity (0) in natural silicate melts. The solid line is the regression line through all the data points shown in Fig. 2. The measured viscosity can he used to estimate the diffisivity of oxygen in the various melts. The data for the rhyolites are from SHAW (1963, 850°C, 2 kbar, 6.2% water) and MURASE and MCBIRNEY (1973, 13OO"C, 0.5% water); Mt. Hood And&amp;e from MURASE and MCBIRNEY (1973); Basalt Mak. is a basalt from Makaopnhi, Hawaii, from SHAW (1969. I235'Ck Basalt. Gal. is an alkali hasalt from Galanaaos from kuRGE'&amp;d M~BIRNEY (1973, 1200°C, 0.48% water); Basalt, Kil. is an olivine tholeiite from Kilauea, Hawaii from FUJII and KUSHIRO (1977, I atm, 1400°C and 20 Kb, 1400°C); Data for the andesite from Crater Lake, Oregon (Anhydrous at 20 Kb, 1350°C) are from KUSHIRO ef al., (1976). Arrows represent Sr and REE diffusivities in granitic (MAGARITZ and HOFMANN, 1978,900"C) and basaltic (HOF-MANN and MAGAR~, 1977, 1300°C) melts.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 Experimental</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Jadeite</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>1400</cell><cell>7200</cell><cell>6.872:;; x lo-lo</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1400</cell><cell>7200</cell><cell>+0.54 7.94 -0.45 x IO-lo</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>15</cell><cell>1400</cell><cell>7200</cell><cell>1.12+&amp;$ x 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>21600</cell><cell>1 03+o.18 . -0.14 x lO-9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1535</cell><cell>3600</cell><cell>4.722';; x 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1610</cell><cell>3600</cell><cell>8.72;';; x 1O-9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>20</cell><cell>1400</cell><cell>7200</cell><cell>1.322';; x 10 -9</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Diopside 10</cell><cell>1650</cell><cell>900</cell><cell>7.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>conditions and the measured diffusion coefficients Camp. P(kb) T('C) t(sec) D + o(cm2/sec) 30+0.29 -0.18 x 1D-i 1650 900 5.28$;; x 10 -7 3600 5.742';; x lo-'</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements-Ken</head><p>Burrhus is instrumental in maintaining the ion-microprobe at the State-of-the-Art performance level. We thank <rs type="person">Stan Hart</rs> for comments on the early version of the manuscript. <rs type="person">Tom Hoering</rs> and <rs type="person">Bjom Mysen</rs> provided useful advice in preparing the starting materials. Skilled technical assistance of <rs type="person">D. S. Hall</rs> (drafting) and <rs type="person">S. D. Luria</rs> (word processing) is appreciated. The work is supported in part by <rs type="funder">NSF</rs> grant <rs type="grantNumber">EAR-7922049</rs>. This paper has benefited from constructive reviews by <rs type="person">C. J. Allegre</rs>, <rs type="person">C. A. Angell</rs>, <rs type="person">J. Brady</rs>, <rs type="person">T. Dunn</rs> and <rs type="person">C. Scarfe</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_mFTqHBN">
					<idno type="grant-number">EAR-7922049</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pressure enhancement of ion mobilities in liquid silicates from computer simulation studies to 800 kilobars</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Angell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cheeseman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tamadd~n S</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">218</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="885" to="887" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The viscosity of magmatic silicate liquids: a model for calculation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>B~itinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. J. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">272</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="438" to="475" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen isotope partitioning among the minerals in igneous and metamorphic rocks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bottinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Geophys. Space Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="418" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetics and ionic conductance part 2: temperature and pressure coefficients of conductance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Brummer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hills G</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. Faradav Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1823" to="1837" />
			<date type="published" when="1961">1961</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural s&amp;e and diffusion in a silicate glass</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Charles R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Ceram. Sot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular transport in liquids and gasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Turnbull D</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1164" to="1169" />
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Mathematics ofD$iiion</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">414</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>nd edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen diffusion in three silicate melts along the join diopside-anorthite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2293" to="2299" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen chemical diffusion in three basaltic liquids at elevated temperatures and pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1923" to="1930" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscosity, plasticity, and diffusion as examples of absolute reaction rates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Eyring</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="1936">1936</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Density, viscosity and compressibility of basaltic liquid at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fujii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kushiro I</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carnegie Inst. Wash. Yearb</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="424" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen diffusion in quartz</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Giletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yund R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of pressure on electrolytic conduction in alkali silicate glasses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Glasstone</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">600 PP. HAMANN S. D.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Laidler</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">600 PP. HAMANN S. D.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Eyring H</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">600 PP. HAMANN S. D.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aust. J. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="1941">1941. 1965</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Theory ofRate Processes</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in natural silicate melts: a critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">10 Physics ojMagmatic Processes (ed. R. B. HARGRAVES)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton Univ. Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="417" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An assessment of local and regional isotopic equilibrium in the mantle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hart S</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. L&amp;t</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of Ca, Sr, Ba and Co in a basalt melt: implications for the geochemistry of the mantle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Magaritz M</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5432" to="5440" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A combined 0, Sr, Nd and Pb isotopic and trace element study ofcrustal contamination in central Aodean lavas: I. Local geochemical variations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stern R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carnegie Inst. Wash. Yearb</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">198. 1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Earth Planet. Sci. Lett.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ion microprobe studies of water in silicate melts: temperature-dependent water diffusion in obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kar~ten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="420" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The self-diffusion of oxygen in a lime-silica-alumina slag</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Koros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>King T</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. AIME</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">224</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in viscosity and structure of melt of NaAlSi*Q composition at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kushiro 1</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6347" to="6350" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">I1 980) Viscosity. density, and structure of silicate melts at high pressures, and their-petrological applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics ofMagmatic Processes (ed. R. B. HARGRAVES)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton Univ. Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="120" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of pressure on the diffusivity of network-forming cations in melts of jadeitic compositions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1415" to="1422" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscosities of basalt and andesite melts at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yoder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geophys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">0</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="6356" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heat conduction in dissimilar rocks and the use of thermal models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lovering</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geol. Sot. Amer. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="1936">1936</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Duffusion of Sr, Ba and Na in obsidian</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magaritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hofmann A</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="605" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen isotope exchange and equilibration of silicates with CO* and OZ</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Muehlenbachs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kushiro I</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carnegie Inst. Wash. Yearb</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="236" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen diffusion in vitreous silica-utilization of natural isotopic abundances</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Muehlenbachs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">!</forename><surname>~chaeffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Can. Mineral</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Properties of some common igneous rocks and their melts at high temperatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Murase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geol. Sot. Amer. Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3563" to="3592" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen diffusion in liquid silicates and relation to their viscosity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Oishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Terai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ueda H</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mass Transport Phenomena in Ceramics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Heuer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>N.Y.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Plenum Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="310" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of sodium aluminosilicate melts containing at least 50 mole W Si02 at 1500°C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Riebling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2857" to="2865" />
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in viscosity and density of melts of sodium disilicate, sodium metasilicate, and diopside composition with pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scarfe</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">VIRGO D.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mysen B</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">VIRGO D.</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carnegie Inst. Wash. Yearb</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="547" to="555" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ramao study of structure and coordination of Al in NaAISitOe glasses synthesized at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Virgo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mysen B. 0</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Carnegie Inst. Wash. Yearb</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="658" to="662" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Obsidian-H20 viscosities at 1000 and 2000 bars in the temperature range 700&quot; to 900°C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Geephys. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6337" to="6343" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rheology of basalt in the melting range</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="510" to="535" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diffusion of HZ0 in granitic liquids, I. Experimental data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>A. W. HOFMANN, B. J. GILEITI, H. S. YODER, JR. and R. A. YUND</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
			<publisher>Carnegie Inst. Wash. Publ</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">634</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="154" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isotope fractionation in secondary ion mass spectrometty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shimizu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hart S</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1303" to="1311" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium diffusion in a simple silicate melt to 30 kbar</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basalt contamination by continental crust: some experiments and models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Mineral. Petrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of dissolved carbonate in magmas: experimental results and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sneeringer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Left</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen diffusion in multicomponent glass forming silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper A</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Chem. Glasses</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Least-squares fitting of a straight hoe with correlated errors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>York</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Planet. Sci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="320" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
