<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Self diffusion of Si and O in dacitic liquid at high pressures</title>
				<funder ref="#_QCN46ey">
					<orgName type="full">National Science Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">NSF</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Charles</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesher</surname></persName>
							<email>tinker@geology.ucdavis.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Geology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>One Shields Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>95616</postCode>
									<settlement>Davis</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">U.S.A</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">New York University Bobst Library Technical Services</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">New York University Bobst Library Technical Services</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Self diffusion of Si and O in dacitic liquid at high pressures</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3410BCBF28A0C663AFA887915511111A</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-02-05T18:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Laboratory experiments have been conducted to determine simultaneously the self diffusivities of Si and O in synthetic dacite melt (NBO/T = 0.1) from 1 to 5.7 GPa and from 1355 to 1662 °C. Glasses enriched in 18 O and 28 Si were synthesized and mated to their isotopically normal counterparts to form diffusion couples used in the piston cylinder device (1 and 2 GPa) and multi-anvil apparatus (4 to 5.7 GPa). Profiles of isotope abundances were measured by secondary ion mass spectrometry. Self-diffusion coefficients for Si (D* Si ) are significantly lower than self-diffusion coefficients for O (D* 0 ) at all run conditions; for example, D* 0 = 6.45 ± 0.65 × 10 -14 m 2 /s and D* Si = 1.45 ± 0.45 × 10 -14 m 2 /s at 1 GPa and 1355 °C. The temperature dependence is similar, but not identical, for Si and O self diffusion at all pressures, yielding activation energies of 293-380 kJ/mol at 1 GPa, 264-305 kJ/mol at 2 GPa, and 155-163 kJ/mol at 4 GPa. The pressure dependence is similar for Si and O at all temperatures, giving activation volumes for Si and O that are -14.5 to -17.1 cm 3 /mol at 1460 °C, -9.8 to -8.7 cm 3 /mol at 1561 °C, and -8.8 to -9.3 cm 3 /mol at 1662 °C. Self-diffusion coefficients for Si and O reach maximum values at roughly 5 GPa. The mode of Si and O self diffusion in dacitic liquids is constrained by the large activation volumes, D* 0 ≈ 2 D* Si , and predictions using the Eyring equation, which suggest that Si and O diffuse as molecular species at 1460 °C. At 1561 and 1662 °C, less negative activation volumes and predictions of the Eyring equation are consistent with diffusion of Si and O by a combination of mechanisms, including the formation of a high-coordinated intermediate species.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Silicon (Si) and oxygen (O) are the major structural constituents of silicate melts. Bonding of the Si 4+ and O 2-ions controls diffusion and viscous flow in silicate melts, so an understanding of the compositional and compressional effects on local melt environments is essential for modeling igneous processes, including the equilibration and extraction of silicate melts from a partially molten source region, the time scales for magma mixing, and rates of crystal growth and dissolution. The network former Si is variably coordinated by O in silicate melts, and Si-O molecular configurations influence the transport of Si and O. For this reason, measured diffusion coefficients for Si and O are powerful probes of dynamic melt structure that complement interpretations of nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) studies (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Liu et al. 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stebbins and McMillan 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Xue et al. 1991)</ref> and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Rustad et al. 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Wasserman et al. 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kubicki and Lasaga 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bryce et al. 1999)</ref>.</p><p>Local melt structure can be deduced from experimental diffusion studies by determining the nature of the species activated for diffusion. The size of the diffusing species has been estimated using the Eyring equation, which relates the self-diffusion coefficient to melt viscosity. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Oishi et al. (1975)</ref> in a study of calcium aluminosilicate, <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Yinnon and Cooper (1980)</ref> in a study of K-Sr silicate, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and Kushiro (1984)</ref> in a study of jadeite and diopside melts, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Rubie et al. (1993)</ref> in a study of Na 2 Si 4 O 9 melt, accurately predicted melt viscosities using the Eyring equation with self-diffusion coefficients for O and jump distances for diffusion equal to the diameter of the O 2-anion (λ = 2.8 Å). The agreement between independently determined melt viscosities and those calculated using the Eyring equation with λ = 2.8 Å suggests that ionic diffusion of O is the rate-limiting step permitting viscous flow. Jump distances for diffusion that are greater than the diameter of the O 2-anion imply that O diffuses as part of a molecular complex. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dunn (1982)</ref> suggested the diffusion of a large, molecular species [i.e., (SiO 4 ) 4-] based on good agreement between translation distances greater than the diameter of the O 2-anion in the Eyring equation and self-diffusion coefficients for O in diopside, Di 58 An 42 , and Di 40 An 60 melt compositions.</p><p>Stebbins and coworkers (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Farnan and Stebbins 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Xue et al. 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">and Liu et al. 1988</ref>) in interpretations of nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) results, have proposed an alternative to ionic and molecular models for self diffusion of network formers involving a high-coordinated (five-or sixfold) Si transition state complex. The formation and subsequent disassociation of high-coordinated species passes network-forming Si and O ions through the silicate melt by incremental exchange of ions between nearest neighbors. High-coordinated Si complexes have been detected in NMR spectra for glasses quenched from pressures as low as 1.9 GPa <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Stebbins and McMillan 1989)</ref>. MD simulations predict that a predominance of these species coincides with a diffusivity maximum for network formers in jadeite <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Angell et al. 1982</ref>) and anorthite liquids <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Nevins and Spera 1998)</ref>. Furthermore, recent experimental work by <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Poe et al. (1997)</ref> suggests that Al plays a key role in the formation of high-coordinated species in polymerized melt compositions. An important corollary of a model involving high-coordinated Si or Al is that the relatively small disruptions of the melt required to permit diffusional exchange should be associated with activation volumes for diffusion with small absolute values. Likewise, the activation energies should be small considering the small number of Si-O bonds that need to be broken to allow ionic exchange.</p><p>Here, we report the results of systematic laboratory measurements of the simultaneous self diffusion of Si and O in synthetic liquids of dacitic composition from 1 to 5.7 GPa and temperatures from 1355 to 1662 °C. This work extends to more polymerized silicate melts work by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lesher et al. (1996)</ref> to monitor simultaneous diffusion of Si and O in basaltic liquids at 1 and 2 GPa. The self diffusion of Si and O in dacitic liquids at the conditions of this experimental study occurs by a combination of cooperative mechanisms, possibly involving the formation and disassociation of high-coordinated species.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURE</head><p>Starting materials for this study were synthesized from laboratory reagents (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Isotopically normal glasses were synthesized from chemical reagents, and isotopically enriched glasses were doped with inexpensive 28 SiO 2 and 18 O-enriched CaCO 3 . Enriched CaCO 3 was precipitated from a Ca(OH) 2 solution, first flushed with N 2 gas then aerated with 18 O-enriched CO 2 . (Isotopically enriched reagents were obtained from Cambridge Isotope Labs.) Both of the powder mixtures were fused at 1350 °C in a one atmosphere, gas-mixing furnace, under flowing N 2 gas. The material was held at the fusion temperature for 25 minutes, quenched in air, and the resulting glass was ground in a mortar and pestle. The process was repeated a minimum of four times. Starting glasses were stored in a dessicator. Experimental assemblies were stored in a vacuum oven at 110 °C until immediately before each run.</p><p>Simple diffusion couples used in all experiments were formed by packing the starting materials in graphite capsules (1 mm I.D. and 2-3 mm long), which were weld-sealed in platinum capsules. To ensure gravitational stability in the charges, the heavier, enriched composition was loaded in the bottom of each capsule and overlain by the lighter, isotopically normal powder. Multiple ion microprobe analyses perpendicular to the diffusion interface yielded statistically identical self-diffusion coefficients (D*), demonstrating that convective mixing was not a factor with the experimental assembly used in this study.</p><p>Self-diffusion experiments were conducted at 1, 2, 4, 5.2, and 5.7 GPa, between 1355 and 1662 °C (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). The 0.5 inch <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Boyd and England (1960)</ref> piston cylinder apparatus was used in experiments run at 1 and 2 GPa. Piston cylinder sample assemblies were constructed of graphite tube furnaces (7.93 mm O.D., 6.33 mm I.D.) and semi-sintered MgO filler rods surrounded by a CaF 2 or BaCO 3 pressure cell. Experiments at 4 and 5 GPa were performed using a Walker-design MA6/MA8 multianvil device, using Ceramacast 584 octahedral pressure media cast to fit carbide anvils with truncation edge length (TEL) of 10 mm <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Walker 1991)</ref>. Experimental assemblies for the multianvil device contained 4.55 mm O.D., 3.27 and 3.54 mm I.D. sectioned graphite furnaces, with semi-sintered MgO spacer rods.</p><p>The multianvil apparatus was calibrated for the 10 mm TEL experimental assembly at room temperature using Bi metal transitions at 2.55 GPa (I-II) and 7.7 GPa (III-V), and the Ba I-II transition at 5.5 GPa <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bean et al. 1986</ref>). High-temperature calibrations included Au melting at 3 GPa (1235 °C) and 4 GPa (1290 °C) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Akella and Kennedy 1971)</ref>, the transformation of fayalite to spinel at 5.25 GPa (1000 °C) <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Yagi et al. 1987)</ref>, and the transformation of coesite to stishovite at 9.2 GPa (1200 °C) <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Zhang et al. 1996)</ref>. Room-temperature data give slightly more efficient pressurization curves than the high-temperature calibration data for the 10 mm TEL assembly (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>). Assemblies were pressurized cold, and temperature was raised at 150 or 200 °C per minute to the run temperature using a programmable controller. Run pressure was maintained only by advancing the piston or anvils during the experiments to reduce hysteresis. Each charge was held isothermally for a prescribed time, then quenched to glass by shutting off the primary voltage. In general, the quenching was accompanied by a significant drop in sample pressure, but in some cases, sample pressure was maintained by manually advancing the ram. There was no noticeable difference between the experimental charges pro-  duced by the two quenching methods. Complete assemblies were removed from the piston cylinder or the multianvil, impregnated with epoxy, sectioned longitudinally, and mounted and polished for ion microprobe analysis. Silicon and O isotope gradients were measured using a Cameca IMS 3f ion microprobe at the Center for Solid State Science, Arizona State University. We used a primary ion beam of 16 O -accelerated to 12.5 KeV. The beam current was approximately 1 nA, and the beam was focused to yield a spot size of ≤20 µm. The sample potential was -4.5 kV. The energy bandpass was set to allow ions with 50 ± 20 eV excess kinetic energy to pass into the mass spectrometer. Typical counts per second for 28 Si, 30 Si, 16 O, and 18 O in the isotopically "normal" end-member dacite composition were 9000, 300, 512 000, and 500, respectively. In the isotopically enriched end-member composition, counts per second for 28 Si, 30 Si, 16 O, and 18 O were 8000, 170, 450 000, and 3000, respectively. Counting times were 10 s for 28 Si, 30 s for 30 Si, 10 s for 16 O, and 30 s for 18 O. Measured isotope abundances for the end-member compositions were used to find the limits of the diffusion zone, and step sizes for scans across the diffusion interface varied from 10 to 20 µm, depending on the overall length of the traverse.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>Examples of isotopic abundance profiles are shown in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>, where measured profiles for 28 Si and 18 O are compared to profiles calculated using Fick's second law with calculated selfdiffusion coefficients reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. The self-diffusion profiles are monotonic and asymptotically approach the starting compositions for the normal and enriched end-members. Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> also shows that the width of the diffusion zone is vis-ibly wider for 18 O than it is for 28 Si, requiring that D* 0 &gt; D* Si . In fact, D* 0 ≈ 2 D* Si in this study.</p><p>Self-diffusion coefficients (D*) were calculated using the solution for diffusion in a semi-infinite medium <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Crank 1975)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">C C C C C z D t = + + - 1 2 2 1 2 2 2 ( * ) erf (1)</formula><p>where C1 and C2 are the isotope abundances for 28 Si or 18 O in the enriched and normal starting materials respectively and C is the measured isotope abundance at a distance z from the normal-enriched interface at time t. The inflection of the isotopic profile is taken as the diffusion interface, and is treated here as z = 0. The values for D* were derived from the slopes of bestfit lines to plots of y vs. z, where</p><p>is the inverted solution to the diffusion equation, as described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and Kushiro (1984)</ref>. The linearized solution to the diffusion Equation 2 gives an isotopic gradient across the normal-enriched interface whose slope is used to calculate the diffusion coefficient <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Shimizu and Kushiro 1984)</ref>. Diffusion coefficients for O are reported with an error of 10%, and those for Si are reported with an error of 30%. These estimates of analytical error were made by calculating maximum and minimum diffusion coefficients to fit the shallowest and steepest profiles of isotope abundances across the diffusion interface allowed by variations in measured isotopic ratios in the unreacted portions of the diffusion couples. These Calibration curve for the 10 mm TEL assembly (inset) in the Walker-design multianvil apparatus. Calibrations using room temperature Bi metal transitions at 2.55 and 7.7 GPa and Ba I-II transition at 5.5 GPa <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bean et al. 1986</ref>) are represented by the bold curve. The dashed curve is fit to data from bracketing experiments for the high-temperature coesite-stishovite transformation at 9.2 GPa and 1200 °C (squares) <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Zhang et al. 1996)</ref>, the fayalite-spinel transformation at 5.25 GPa and 1000 °C (triangles) <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Yagi et al. 1987)</ref>, and the melting of gold at 3 GPa, 1235 °C, and 4 GPa, 1290 °C (circles) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Akella and Kennedy 1971)</ref> University. The distance (z) along the horizontal axis is in µm relative to the isotopically normal reservoir-enriched reservoir interface (the inflection point of the profile is taken to be z = 0). Curves through data are model isotope profiles generated using calculated diffusion coefficients (2.43 × 10 -13 m 2 /s for O and 1.02 × 10 -13 m 2 /s for Si) in Fick's second law.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">y C C C C C z D t ≡ - + - = - erf 1 2 1 2 1 2 2 ( ( ) ) *</formula><p>Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM errors are similar to the errors due to ion microprobe counting statistics calculated by 1/√counts. For example, errors are ±55 for typical 18 O abundances of 3000 and ±77 for typical counts per second on 28 Si of 6000. Counting statistics for O are influenced by 16 O of the primary 16 O beam. Using normal isotopic ratios for O, an 18 O abundance should be accompanied by a 16 O abundance of roughly 14 700. However, with the addition of 16 O from the primary beam, typical counts per second for 16 O are 450 000 ± 671. Previous authors have been concerned with this "oxygen dilution" <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Liang et al. 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and Kushiro 1984)</ref>, but the systematic shift in measured O abundances does not affect the shape of the isotope profiles used to calculate D*. Errors based on scatter of isotope abundance measurements in unreacted portions of the diffusion couple account for the reproducibility observed in multiple experiments at the same conditions. Similar values derived from experiments with different run times suggest that there is no time dependence for D*.</p><p>In addition to analytical errors, uncertainties in reported diffusion coefficients may be introduced by deformation of the experimental charge. All high-pressure studies need to demonstrate that analyses made at room temperature and atmospheric pressure accurately reflect behavior at experimental conditions. The most important consideration in our analyses is the combined effect of thermal expansion and isothermal compressibility on the lengths of diffusion profiles during the quenching and decompression of an experimental charge. If significant deformation of a diffusion couple occurs following an experiment, a bias is introduced into the calculated diffusion coefficient. Using partial molar volume data for oxide melt components from <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Lange and Carmichael (1990)</ref>, we can calculate the volume of the cylindrical diffusion couple at different temperatures and pressures. Comparing the volume calculated for the diffusion couple at run conditions and the volume calculated for the diffusion couple at room temperature and one atmosphere pressure provides an estimate of the volume change of the experimental charge due to contraction on cooling and to expansion on decompression. The greatest change in volume will occur on quenching from relatively low temperature and decompression from relatively high pressure. The worst case scenario for conditions used in this study is an experiment at 4 GPa and 1460 °C. Quenching and decompression from these conditions would result in a net expansion of the diffusion couple by roughly 30%, which can be achieved with an increase in the length of the diffusion couple by 9%. Increasing the length of the diffusion profile by 9% leads to an overestimate of the calculated diffusion coefficient by 16%. For comparison, a diffusion couple run at 1 GPa and 1355 °C, and quenched and decompressed to room temperature and atmospheric pressure, would expand by less than 1%, resulting in an increase in the length of the diffusion profile by only 0.2%. This extension of the diffusion profile corresponds to a calculated diffusion coefficient that is overestimated by just 0.4%. These uncertainties introduced by the net expansion of the diffusion couples on quenching and decompression from run conditions are at worst similar in magnitude to the errors we assigned to our analyses and have no effect on the relative magnitudes of self-diffusion coefficients for Si and O determined for a given run.</p><p>Multiple linear regressions on D*, P/T, and 1/T for selfdiffusion data from 1 to 4 GPa were used to determine the coefficients in the relationship ln D* = ln D 0 -(E a + P∆V a )/RT, where D* is the self-diffusion coefficient, D 0 is the pre-exponential factor, E a is the activation energy, ∆V a is the activation volume, R is the gas constant, and T is temperature in Kelvin. The relationship determined for O is ln D* = -10.58 ± 0.83 -[280 ± 12 kJ/mol + P(-11.05 ± 0.69 cm 3 /mol)]/RT, and the relationship determined for Si is ln D* = -7.38 ± 1.30 -[341 ± 19 kJ/mol + P(-12.03 ± 1.01 cm 3 /mol)]/RT. These results are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>. Errors reported in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref> were determined by a Monte Carlo approach, recalculating regression coefficients for 500 iterations that included uncertainty in P/T (±10%), 1/T (±0.00004), and D* (±10% for O and ±30% for Si). Regression coefficients are constant for calculations with 500 or more iterations. Activation energies and activation volumes calculated by multiple linear regression describe the general trend in the data for this experimental study, but do not provide the best fits to isothermal and isobaric subsets of the entire data set. Therefore, we also recovered E a , ∆V a , and lnD 0 by simple linear regressions to determine D* variations with increases in P and D* variations with increases in T. Only experiments from 1 to 4 GPa were used to determine the regres- -12.5 ± 0.9 -7.9 ± 3.2 174 ± 24 -12.9 ± 1.6 Notes: Top shows results of simple linear regression analysis on Si and O self diffusion data for the dacite composition in this study. Bottom shows results of multiple linear regression for Si and O self diffusion data for the dacite composition in this study and for the basalt composition of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lesher et al. (1996)</ref>.</p><p>Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM sion coefficients. We draw on these simple linear regression results for much of the discussion below.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the variation of Si and O self-diffusion coefficients with reciprocal temperature. In Figure <ref type="figure">3a</ref>, the natural log of the self-diffusion coefficients for O (ln D* 0 ) increase from -30.37 to -27.06 between 1355 and 1662 °C in 1 GPa experiments, from -29.05 to -26.69 between 1410 and 1662 °C in 2 GPa experiments, and from -26.58 to -25.46 between 1460 and 1662 °C in 4 GPa experiments. Similarly, in Figure <ref type="figure">3b</ref>, the natural log of the self-diffusion coefficients for Si (ln D* Si )increase from -31.86 to -27.68 between 1355 and 1662 °C at 1 GPa, from -29.91 to -27.30 between 1410 and 1662 °C at 2 GPa, and from -27.18 to -26.00 between 1460 and 1662 °C at 4 GPa. A comparison of Figures <ref type="figure">3a</ref> and<ref type="figure">3b</ref> shows that the O self-diffusion coefficient is significantly greater than the Si selfdiffusion coefficient for all experiments represented. This relationship is also found in the experiments performed at 5.2 and 5.7 GPa. In Figures <ref type="figure">3a</ref> and<ref type="figure">3b</ref>, it is apparent that the positive temperature dependence for the O and Si self-diffusion coefficients is greatest at 1 GPa, intermediate at 2 GPa, and lowest at 4 GPa.</p><p>The data plotted in Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> obey the Arrhenius relationship lnD* = lnD 0 -E a /RT. Activation energies for Si and O self diffusion calculated by simple linear regression on D* and 1/T are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>. The activation energies for Si are greatest at 1 GPa ( 380 ± 21 kJ/mol) and decrease with increasing pressure, i.e., 305 ± 28 kJ/mol at 2 GPa and 163 ± 35 kJ/ mol at 4 GPa. Similarly, activation energies for O are 293 ± 10 kJ/mol at 1 GPa, 264 ± 13 kJ/mol at 2 GPa, and 155 ± 14 kJ/ mol at 4 GPa. Errors listed here for the activation energies are determined using the same Monte Carlo approach described for multiple linear regressions.</p><p>The values we calculated for the activation energies of Si and O self-diffusion are similar to previous results for polymerized and partially polymerized compositions. The degree of polymerization of the melt is commonly estimated using the ratio of non-bridging O atoms (NBO) to tetrahedrally coordinated cations (T). Melts are fully polymerized when NBO/T = 0 and completely depolymerized when NBO/T = 4 (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Mysen 1990)</ref>. Using this index, dacitic liquid has NBO/T = 0.1. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kushiro (1980)</ref> reported that the activation energy for O self diffusion for fully polymerized jadeite liquid (NBO/T = 0) decreases with increasing pressure from 334.7 kJ/mol at 0.8 GPa to 188.3 kJ/ mol at 2.1 GPa. In contrast, <ref type="bibr">Shimizu and Kushiro (1991)</ref> reported an increase in activation energy from 209 kJ/mol at 1 GPa to 259 kJ/mol at 2 GPa for Si self diffusion in Di 60 Jd 40 (NBO/T = 1) liquid, and from 280 kJ/mol at 1 GPa to 310 kJ/ mol at 2 GPa in the activation energy for Si self diffusion in Di 20 Jd 80 (NBO/T = 0.3) liquid.</p><p>Activation energies for Si and O self-diffusion have also been calculated in MD simulations. <ref type="bibr">Kubicki and Lasaga (1991)</ref> reported activation energies for the self diffusion of Si of 102.3 kJ/mol at 4 GPa in SiO 2 (NBO/T = 0), 100.5 kJ/mol at 2.5 GPa in MgSiO 3 (NBO/T = 2), and 103.3 kJ/mol at 2.5 GPa in Mg 2 SiO 4 (NBO/T = 4). They reported slightly lower activation energies for O that are 91.1 kJ/mol at 4 GPa in SiO 2 , 90.1 kJ/ mol at 2.5 GPa in MgSiO 3 , and 75.0 kJ/mol at 2.5 GPa in Mg 2 SiO 4 . More recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bryce et al. (1999)</ref> reported activa- The lines through these data were generated using the Arrhenius relationship lnD* = lnD 0 -E a /RT, with simple regression coefficients for lnD 0 and E a . For 1 GPa data E a = 293 ± 10 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -8.9 ± 0.7, for 2 GPa E a = 264 ± 13 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -10.2 ± 0.9, and for 4 GPa E a = 155 ± 14 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -15.9 ± 0.9. (b) D* Si variation with reciprocal temperature. Open triangles are 1 GPa data, open squares are 2 GPa data, and open circles are 4 GPa data, plotted with 30% error bars on D* 0 . The lines through these data are generated using the Arrhenius relationship used for a. For 1 GPa data E a = 380 ± 21 kJ/mol and ln D 0 = -3.8 ± 1.4, for 2 GPa E a = 305 ± 28 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -8.3 ± 1.9, and for 4 GPa E a = 163 ± 35 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -15.9 ± 2.3.</p><p>Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM tion energies for Si, O, and Al self diffusion in fully polymerized sodium aluminosilicate liquids that were the same within error, roughly 300 kJ/mol.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> shows the variation in Si and O self-diffusion coefficients with increasing pressure. In Figure <ref type="figure">4a</ref>, ln D* 0 values increase from -29.58 to -26.58 between 1 and 4 GPa at 1460 °C, from -27.98 to -26.06 between 1 and 4 GPa at 1561 °C, and from -27.06 to -25.46 between 1 and 4 GPa at 1662 °C. Figure <ref type="figure">4b</ref> shows that ln D* Si values also increase between 1 and 4 GPa. These values increase from -30.66 to -27.18 at 1460 °C, from -28.18 to -26.58 at 1561 °C, and from -27.68 to -26.00 at 1662 °C. An important feature of Figures <ref type="figure">4a</ref> and<ref type="figure">4b</ref> is that the self-diffusion coefficients for experiments at 1662 °C have maximum values between 4 and 5.7 GPa. Experiments at 1612 and 1637 °C suggest that the self-diffusion coefficients reach a maximum at pressures less than 5.2 GPa. For the purpose of discussion in this paper, we consider the occurrence of maximum self-diffusion coefficients at 5.0 ± 0.5 GPa.</p><p>The self-diffusion coefficients for Si and O from 1 to 4 GPa in Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> follow the Arrhenius-type relationship ln D* = ln D 0 -P∆V a /T. Activation volumes for Si and O self diffusion calculated using a simple linear regression on D* and P-T are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>. Positive pressure dependence displayed by the Si and O self-diffusion coefficients corresponds to a negative activation volume. The activation volumes for Si are -17.1 ± 1.9 cm 3 /mol at 1460 °C, -8.7 ± 1.4 cm 3 /mol at 1561 °C, and -9.3 ± 1.5 cm 3 /mol at 1662 °C, and the activation volumes for O are -14.5 ± 1.3 cm 3 /mol at 1460 °C, -9.8 ± 1.0 cm 3 /mol at 1561 °C, and -8.8 ± 0.9 cm 3 /mol at 1662 °C. Errors for activation volumes are determined following the method described above.</p><p>For comparison, data from <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lesher et al. (1996)</ref> yield activation volumes for Si and O in basaltic melt that are close to -8 cm 3 /mol (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and Kushiro (1984)</ref> reported an activation volume of -6.3 cm 3 /mol for O self diffusion in jadeite melt and an activation volume of 8.48 cm 3 /mol for O self diffusion in diopside melt. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Rubie et al. (1993)</ref> calculated an activation volume for O in Na 2 Si 4 O 9 liquid at 1825 °C that was -3.3 cm 3 /mol. There is a large range in activation volumes calculated in MD simulation studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bryce et al. (1999)</ref> reported activation volumes of -6.1 cm 3 /mol for Si and -5.9 cm 3 /mol Between 1 and 4 GPa, these data obey the Arrhenius-type relationship listed in part a. Lines through the data are determined using this equation with lnD 0 and ∆V a determined from simple linear regression. For 1460 °C, ∆V a = -17.1 ± 1.9 and lnD 0 = -32.0 ± 0.3, for 1561 °C, ∆V a = -8.7 ± 1.4 and lnD 0 = -28.9 ± 0.2, and for 1662 °C, ∆V a = -9.3 ± 1.5 and lnD 0 = -28.3 ± 0.2. The selfdiffusion coefficient for Si also reaches a maximum between 4 and 5.7 GPa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>M</head><p>Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM for O in jadeite melt. The same authors calculated an activation volume of -7.7 cm 3 /mol for O self diffusion in albite melt <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bryce et al. 1999)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Nevins and Spera (1998)</ref> reported zero pressure activation volumes of -38.6 cm 3 /mol for O and -15.2 cm 3 / mol for Si. The results of their MD simulations suggest that the increase in self-diffusion coefficients with pressure decreases dramatically (to roughly -3 cm 3 /mol) at 2 GPa, and that the self-diffusion coefficients have maximum values at about 5 GPa.</p><p>The main results of the present study include the fact that at all run conditions between 1 and 5.7 GPa, the self-diffusion coefficient for O is roughly twice that of Si. The self-diffusion coefficients for Si and O increase with increases in temperature. This positive temperature dependence is less dramatic at elevated pressure. The self-diffusion coefficients for Si and O also increase with increases in pressure to 4 GPa, but appear to reach maximum values at roughly 5 GPa. This positive pressure dependence relates to negative activation volumes that are less negative at higher temperatures. In all cases, the absolute magnitude of the activation volume for self diffusion is greater than the molar volume of O.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>Previous workers have used temperature (activation energy) and pressure (activation volume) dependence to propose a range of models that describe the self diffusion of Si and O in silicate liquids (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dunn 1982;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and Kushiro 1984;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Liu et al. 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lesher et al. 1996)</ref>. These models for self-diffusion mechanisms can be distinguished by determining if these atoms are transported ionically or cooperatively. Ionic self-diffusion of Si and O involves the independent launching of individual Si 4+ and O 2-ions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and Kushiro (1984)</ref> suggested that the self diffusion of O 2-anions occurs in fully polymerized jadeite melt and depolymerized diopside melt. Cooperative self diffusion occurs when both Si and O participate in a transport mechanism. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dunn (1982)</ref> proposed a model for O self diffusion in diopside, Di 58 An 42 , and Di 40 An 60 melts that involves the activation of the SiO 4 4-monomer as well as the diffusion of individual O 2-anions. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Towers and Chipman (1957)</ref> proposed the activation of neutral SiO 2 species for diffusion in calcium aluminosilicate slags. Alternatively, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lesher et al. (1996)</ref> adopted a cooperative model for Si and O self diffusion in partially polymerized basaltic liquid that was originally proposed in NMR studies of melt relaxation (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Liu et al. 1988</ref>). In this model, Si and O are exchanged between nearest neighbors in the melt via the formation and disassociation of a high-coordinated Si species. The existence of five-coordinated Si was deduced from NMR spectra in K 2 Si 4 O 9 glass cooled at variable rates from 1300 °C at atmospheric pressure <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Stebbins 1991)</ref>. Also, five-and sixfold coordinated Si are present in K 2 Si 4 O 9 liquid quenched from experiments at pressures as low as 1.9 GPa <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Stebbins and McMillan 1989)</ref>. Complementary spectroscopic studies (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Farnan and Stebbins 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Xue et al. 1991)</ref> and MD simulations (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bryce et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Kubicki and</ref><ref type="bibr">Lasaga 1988, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Nevins and Spera 1998)</ref> suggest that the formation of high-coordinated Si plays an important role in silicate melt dynamics and that high-coordinated species are increasingly abundant at high pressure. In the fol-lowing discussion, we review our new results for Si and O self diffusion in dacitic liquids and evaluate the results in terms of proposed diffusion models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ionic diffusion</head><p>The simplest model for network-former self-diffusion involves the launching of Si 4+ and O 2-in discrete jumps. The diffusion of individual ions requires the breaking of multiple network bonds and distortion of the melt structure to form a landing site for the transported ion, so ionic diffusion should be associated with a large activation energy. In fully polymerized liquids, the activation of O 2-would require the breaking of two network bonds while the activation of Si 4+ would require the breaking of four network bonds. Therefore, ionic self diffusion of Si and O should result in activation energies for Si that are as much as twice those for O. If diffusion is ionic, one might expect a simple relationship between ionic radius and activation volume. Although this relationship is unlikely in complex, polymerized melts, it is a useful starting point for discussion. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and Kushiro (1984)</ref> studied O self diffusion in jadeite and diopside melts. They showed that the activation volume for O is -6.3 cm 3 /mol in jadeite melt and 8.48 cm 3 /mol in diopside melt. The absolute magnitudes of both of these activation volumes are similar to the molar volume of O (6.9 cm 3 /mol), although there is an important distinction associated with the sign of the activation volume. Shimizu and Kushiro interpreted the negative activation volume for O self diffusion in fully polymerized jadeite melt as reflecting the collapse of the network structure when launching an individual O 2-anion for a diffusive jump. In contrast, the positive activation volume in depolymerized diopside melt was interpreted to reflect the expansion of a melt volume, characterized by small, densely packed structural units, due to the diffusion of the O 2-anion.</p><p>Additional insight into the configuration of the diffusing species comes from the Eyring equation, which relates the characteristic translation distance for diffusion to the self-diffusion coefficient and to melt viscosity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and Kushiro (1984)</ref> found that a translation distance equal to the diameter of the O 2-anion (2.8 Å) agreed with measured self-diffusion coefficients for O and independently determined viscosities for jadeite melt. Furthermore, they reported an activation energy of 255 kJ/mol for O self diffusion in jadeite melt. This activation energy could be explained by a model involving the breaking of two Si-O bonds to launch O 2-in a fully polymerized melt, followed by disruption of the melt structure to create a landing site for the diffused anion.</p><p>Dacitic liquids have activation energies for Si that are 380 ± 21 kJ/mol at 1 GPa and 305 ± 28 kJ/mol at 2 GPa. Activation energies for O self diffusion are 293 ± 10 kJ/mol at 1 GPa and 264 ± 13 kJ/mol at 2 GPa. These large activation energies suggest extensive disruption of the melt structure during the self diffusion of both Si and O, which could be associated with ionic diffusion. However, the simultaneous measurement of Si and O self-diffusion coefficients in the present study allows direct comparison of activation energies and activation volumes for Si and O. The observation that in dacitic liquid the Si and O activation energies are similar at 1 GPa and statistically indistinguishable at 2 GPa, coupled with the fact that activation vol-Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM umes at all temperatures are virtually identical, is not consistent with the expectations for ionic self diffusion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Molecular diffusion</head><p>It is possible that Si and O are transported cooperatively, as parts of a molecular complex activated for self diffusion. One possible activated complex is a neutral SiO 2 species, as proposed more than four decades ago by <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Towers and Chipman (1957)</ref> for Si diffusion in Ca aluminosilicate slag compositions. More recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dunn (1982)</ref> proposed diffusion of the (SiO 4 ) 4- monomer in diopside-anorthite melts.</p><p>The activation of molecular species should be apparent in the activation energy, the activation volume, and if available, the relative magnitudes of the self-diffusion coefficients for Si and O. For example, in a fully polymerized melt, four network bonds must be severed to release the (SiO 4 ) 4-species, and the activation energy should be correspondingly large. Because only two network bonds are broken to activate the SiO 2 species, diffusion of this species might be associated with a relatively small activation energy. The activation volume associated with the diffusion of (SiO 4 ) 4-should have a large absolute value, comparable to four times the molar volume of O. In contrast, the diffusion of the SiO 2 species is expected to be associated with an activation volume close to two times the molar volume of O. The transport of (SiO 4 ) 4-is expected to yield self-diffusion coefficients for O that are four times those for Si, whereas SiO 2 diffusion would result in self-diffusion coefficients for O that are two times those for Si. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dunn (1982)</ref> studied O self diffusion in 1 atm isotope exchange experiments using diopside, Di 58 An 42 , and Di 40 An 60 melts. He calculated activation energies for O self diffusion that were 264 kJ/mol for diopside, 197 kJ/mol for Di 58 An 42 , and 184 kJ/mol for Di 40 An 60 . Because self-diffusion coefficients that are similar between compositions may be associated with very different activation energies, Dunn stated that the activation energy for self diffusion may not provide the best comparison between diffusion data. He postulated that the self diffusion of individual O 2-anions should occur at a rate similar to the self diffusion of divalent cations. A comparison of O self-diffusion coefficients in diopside, Di 58 An 42 , and Di 40 An 60 melts, and self-diffusion coefficients for divalent cations reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Hofmann (1980)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Watson (1981)</ref>, showed that the O self-diffusion coefficients were up to an order of magnitude lower than self-diffusion coefficients for divalent cations. Dunn concluded that this could be the result of self diffusion of both O 2-anions and molecular species. To constrain the configuration of the dominant diffusing species, Dunn used a version of the Eyring equation applicable to nonspherical species and determined that a translation distance consistent with diffusion of the SiO 4 4-monomer provided the best agreement with his diffusion data.</p><p>Dacitic liquids have activation energies for Si and O that are 263-305 kJ/mol at 2 GPa, and 155-163 kJ/mol at 4 GPa. An important characteristic of these values is that Si and O activation energies are the same within error (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). This result is consistent with a cooperative diffusion mechanism, which could involve the diffusion of a molecular species. The large activation energy at 2 GPa could then reflect the breaking of numerous network bonds to launch a large molecular species while the small activation energy at 4 GPa could reflect the breaking of few network bonds to launch a small molecular species or an individual ion. Evaluated in light of MD simulations, the decrease in the size of the activated species corresponds to the emerging predominance of TO 5 and TO 6 species with increasing pressure in anorthite melt structure, and the concomitant changes in T-O bond angles that can reduce individual bond strengths <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Nevins and Spera 1998)</ref>. Studies of silicate melt viscosity offer additional explanations for the temperature effect on self diffusion. For example, recent workers (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bryce et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bottinga and Richet 1995)</ref> have discussed melt dynamics using the relationship between configurational entropy and viscosity proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Adam and Gibbs (1965)</ref>. One result of the Adam-Gibbs theory is that flow units consist of smaller clusters of atoms at higher temperatures. However, recent work by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Toplis (2000)</ref> indicates that changes in the sizes of rearranging clusters in Na 2 O-SiO 2 compositions are small from T g to 2000 K.</p><p>The most conclusive evidence for the Si and O self-diffusion mechanism is the activation volume. At 1460 °C, Si and O activation volumes are -17.0 ± 1.8 and -14.4 ± 1.3 cm 3 /mol. Similar to the activation energies at 2 and 4 GPa, the activation volumes are the same within error, suggesting that Si and O are transported by a cooperative mechanism. The collapse of the network structure on Si and O self diffusion is comparable to the activation volume predicted for the diffusion of the SiO 2 species, twice the molar volume of O (2 × 6.9 cm 3 /mol). This comparison is substantiated by the observation that D* 0 ≈ 2 D* Si . At 1561 and 1662 °C, Si and O activation volumes are -9 cm 3 / mol. This smaller collapse of the network structure is difficult to reconcile with the activation of molecular species.</p><p>Our observation that D* 0 ≈ 2 D* Si in dacitic liquids from 1 to 5.7 GPa can be compared to previous studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and</ref><ref type="bibr">Kushiro (1984, 1991)</ref> reported D* 0 ≈ 1.5 D* Si in fully polymerized jadeite melt at 2 GPa and 1400 °C. They reported D* 0 ≈ 0.9 D* Si in depolymerized diopside melt at 1.0 GPa and 1650 °C and D* 0 ≈ 0.8 D* Si at 1.7 GPa and 1650 °C. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lesher et al. (1996)</ref> found diffusivities for Si and O that were the same, within error, in partially polymerized basaltic liquids at 1 and 2 GPa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>High-coordinated species</head><p>Formation of high-coordinated species is strongly supported by recent NMR studies of silicate liquids <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Farnan and Stebbins 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Liu et al. 1988)</ref>. A schematic diagram of this mechanism is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>. This mode of Si and O self-diffusion is initiated when the non-bridging O corner of one (SiO 4 ) 4-tetrahedron (presumably with three bridging O atoms) (A in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>) impinges on a second (SiO 4 ) 4-tetrahedron (B) where all four O atoms are bridging two Si atoms. This association is shown as reversible step 1 in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>. The two tetrahedra may join temporarily, giving species A four and species B five bridging O atoms; B is the [5] Si intermediate species. Diffusion occurs when the [5] Si dissociates from one of its original neighbors (C), and A and B remain as part of a local, fully polymerized melt configuration (step 2 in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>). This model also can apply to the formation of high-coordinated Al, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Poe et al. (1997)</ref> suggested that this mechanism accounts for the O self-diffusion behavior Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM observed with increasing pressure in Na 3 AlSi 7 O 17 liquid.</p><p>Because Si and O are exchanged in this model, D* 0 ≈ D* Si . Also, diffusion by this mechanism involves minimal disruption of the melt structure and should be associated with small activation energies. The activation volumes would be expected to have magnitudes similar to the molar volume of O. Because Si and O are transported cooperatively, their activation energies and activation volumes should be identical. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lesher et al. (1996)</ref> favored this model for Si and O self diffusion in basaltic melt at 1 and 2 GPa. This mechanism of self diffusion explains the similarity in D* 0 and D* Si in basaltic liquids, as well as the similarity in activation volume and activation energy for Si and O. From multiple linear regression, the activation volume for both Si and O is -8 cm 3 /mol, and the activation energy is 175 kJ/mol (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>). Because the formation of high-coordinated Si requires non-bridging O atoms, Lesher et al. conjectured that diffusion in polymerized compositions may be dominated by the transport of individual ions. Alternatively, the formation of triclusters may occur in compositions with few non-bridging O atoms and in which high-coordinated species have not been observed. Originally proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Lacy (1963)</ref>, the formation of three-coordinated O has been invoked in recent studies of melt viscosity <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Toplis et al. 1997)</ref>.</p><p>As discussed earlier, the activation energy for Si and O in dacitic liquids is 263-305 kJ/mol at 2 GPa and 155-163 kJ/ mol at 4 GPa. These activation energies could be associated with the formation of a high-coordinated species in a polymerized melt where a large energy barrier exists at low pressure and is gradually relaxed as the melt is compressed. The activation volume for O is -14.4 ± 1.3 cm 3 /mol at 1460 °C, -9.7 ± 0.9 cm 3 /mol at 1561 °C, and -8.8 ± 0.8 cm 3 /mol at 1662 °C. The activation volume for Si is -17.0 ± 1.8 cm 3 /mol at 1460 °C, -8.6 ± 1.4 cm 3 /mol at 1561, and -9.2 ± 1.5 at 1662 °C. Again, the activation volumes for Si and O at a given temperature are the same within error. The activation volumes at 1460 °C are much greater than the molar volume of O, which is not consistent with a diffusion mechanism involving the formation of highcoordinated Si. The absolute values of the activation volumes at 1561 and 1662 °C are also greater than the molar volume of O, but they are significantly smaller than the absolute value of the activation volumes at 1460 °C. These data, along with the observation that D* 0 ≈ 2 D* Si , are difficult to reconcile with a single mechanism for diffusion involving the formation of high-coordinated Si. This result is similar to the fact that activation of a neutral SiO 2 species does not adequately describe Si and O self diffusion in dacitic liquids at 1561 and 1662 °C. Rather, similar to the conclusion of <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dunn (1982)</ref>, the intermediate activation volumes suggest that diffusion in dacitic liquids occurs through a combination of diffusion mechanisms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Melt viscosity</head><p>Additional information on the configuration of the diffusing species in dacitic liquids can be gained by investigating the link between self diffusion and viscosity. When it is assumed that both diffusion and viscous flow occur through thermally activated jumps, the D* can be related to melt viscosity (η) using the Eyring equation, η = k B T/D*λ (where k B is the Boltzmann constant and λ is the jump distance for diffusion). For melts where network formers Si and O diffuse at significantly different rates, the best agreement between D* and η in the Eyring equation is found using a jump distance consistent with the size of the O anion <ref type="bibr">(Chakraborty 1995, and references therein)</ref>.</p><p>One goal of high-pressure, self-diffusion studies has been to estimate the viscosities of melts where traditional methods of viscometry are difficult or impossible. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Rubie et al. (1993)</ref> used the Eyring equation with D* 0 from self-diffusion experiments and λ = 2.8 Å to estimate viscosities of Na 2 Si 4 O 9 melt from 2.5 to 10 GPa. These authors confirmed their predictions of Na 2 Si 4 O 9 melt viscosity from the Eyring equation with 1 bar measurements of Na 2 Si 4 O 9 melt viscosities.</p><p>Successful application of the Eyring equation with D* 0 derived from experiments and λ = 2.8 Å suggests that the O 2- anion is the dominant diffusing species. If the O 2-anion is the activated species in these experiments, activation volumes for self diffusion should have absolute magnitudes similar to the molar volume of O (6.9 cm 3 /mol). However, the relationship between the activation volume and the translation distance for diffusion in the Eyring equation is not predictable. In one case, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Shimizu and Kushiro (1984)</ref> produced a consistent set of results for O self diffusion in jadeite melt, accurately calculating Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM viscosity using the Eyring equation with D* 0 and λ = 2.8 Å, and independently calculating an activation volume of -6.3 cm 3 / mol. In the same study, Shimizu and Kushiro could not recover diopside melt viscosity using the Eyring equation, despite the fact that the activation volume (8.48 cm 3 /mol) for O self diffusion was within 12 percent of the molar volume of oxygen. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Rubie et al. (1993)</ref> calculated accurate viscosities of Na 2 Si 4 O 9 melt at high pressure using the Eyring equation with λ = 2.8 Å. However, they also showed that the absolute magnitude of the activation volume for O was significantly smaller than the molar volume of O (-3.3 cm 3 /mol).</p><p>With no measured viscosities for our dacitic liquids, we take an alternative approach to interpreting our self-diffusion data using the Eyring equation. Following <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Lesher et al. (1996)</ref>, we compare viscosities calculated using the Eyring equation with D* 0 derived from our experiments and λ = 2.8 Å, with viscosities estimated for all of our experiments using the method of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bottinga and Weill (1972)</ref>. This comparison allows independent evaluation of the translation distance λ in the Eyring equation. The first set of viscosities is represented by the diagonal lines in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>. These lines are all possible lnη-lnD* relationships calculated at 1460, 1561, and 1662 °C using the Eyring equation for λ equal to multiples (0.5, 1, 2, and 4) of the diameter of the O 2-anion. The second set of viscosities is represented by individual points in these plots. The measured O self-diffusion coefficient is plotted along the abscissa and the viscosity estimated using the method of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bottinga and Weill (1972)</ref> is plotted along the ordinate. Estimates of melt viscosity at high pressure are made with pressure corrections represented by vertical lines extending down from individual data points in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>. These pressure corrections are equal to the pressure effect on the self-diffusion coefficients at a given temperature. Estimates of high-pressure melt viscosities and the translation distance for self diffusion at high pressure depend on accurate estimates of low-pressure melt viscosities plotted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref>. The <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bottinga and Weill (1972)</ref> model gives melt viscosities (in Poise) for the dacite composition in this study that are 0.5 to 1 log units greater than melt viscosities estimated using an alternative model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Shaw (1972)</ref>.</p><p>The data plotted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6</ref> provide information on the nature of the diffusing species in dacitic liquids. To constrain the translation distance for diffusion that is associated with the experiments in this study, we need to consider the pressure-  <ref type="bibr">Bottinga and Weill (1982)</ref> for dacitic liquid at 1460, 1561, and 1662 °C and with measured selfdiffusion coefficients D* for O. Vertical extensions from predicted λ values give maximum ranges of the pressure effect (taken to be equal to the pressure effect on the self-diffusion coefficient) on viscosity at these temperatures. For example, a pressure effect of one log unit per GPa increase in pressure from atmospheric pressure on D* equals a maximum pressure correction of one log unit on η per GPa increase in pressure. The predicted values for λ are compared with lines generated using the Eyring equation with measured D* and λ equal to multiples (n = 0.5, 1, 2, and 4) of the diameter of the O 2-anion. The general trend is for λ to decrease with increasing pressure and temperature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>M</head><p>Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM corrected viscosities indicated by the lower end of the vertical lines extending down from individual data points. The data plotted for experiments run at 1460 °C (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6a</ref>) suggest that the translation distance for the self diffusion of O in dacitic liquids is close to 2× the diameter of the O 2-anion. This result is consistent with the activation of a large, molecular species at 1460 °C. The apparent translation distance decreases with increasing temperature, and data plotted in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6b</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">6c</ref> for experiments at 1561 and 1662 °C suggest that the translation distance for self diffusion slightly less than the diameter of the O 2-anion. The Eyring equation analysis suggests that Si and O self diffusion occurs as the result of the activation of large molecular species, possibly the neutral SiO 2 species, at 1460 °C. At 1561 and 1662 °C, the Eyring equation indicates a lessdisruptive mechanism for self diffusion, consistent with the formation of a high-coordinated species.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Maximum self-diffusion coefficients</head><p>An important feature of the pressure effect on self diffusion in dacitic liquids is an apparent maximum in the self-diffusion coefficients for both Si and O at 5 ± 0.5 GPa (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). Our results for O self diffusion in dacitic liquids are compared in Figure <ref type="figure">7a</ref> with maximum self-diffusion coefficients predicted for O by MD simulations in jadeite liquid <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Angell et al. 1982)</ref> and anorthite liquid <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Nevins and Spera 1998)</ref>, and maximum self-diffusion coefficients for O measured in NaAlSi 3 O 8 (albite) and Na 3 AlSi 7 O 17 by <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Poe et al. (1997)</ref>. Experimentally determined self-diffusion coefficients for O in basalt <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Lesher et al. 1996)</ref> and Na 2 Si 4 O 9 <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Rubie et al. 1993</ref>) are also included, although maximum self-diffusion coefficients have not been identified in these compositions.</p><p>The rapid increase in the self-diffusion coefficient for O can be explained by the compression of the relatively polymerized melt structure, weakening bonds and facilitating the formation of high-coordinated species. Predictions from MD simulations (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Nevins and Spera 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Angell et al. 1982)</ref> and NMR spectra of experimental run products quenched from high pressure suggest that the abundances of high-coordinated Al (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Yarger et al. 1995)</ref> and Si (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Stebbins and McMillan 1991)</ref> increase with increasing pressure in silicate melts. Because the increase in the abundance of high-coordinated Si </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>M</head><p>Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM occurs at the expense of non-bridging O atoms, the rate of increase in self-diffusion coefficients that results from the formation of high-coordinated intermediate species should diminish. As mentioned earlier, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Poe et al. (1997)</ref> suggest that high-coordinated Al determines the limit of increasing self-diffusion coefficients. Poe et al. cite NMR evidence from <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Yarger et al. (1995)</ref> that shows that high-coordinated Si is not formed at 10 GPa in Na 3 AlSi 7 O 17 liquid, while five-coordinated Al reaches a maximum abundance near 8 GPa, and the population of six-coordinated Al continually increases between 6 and 12 GPa. The Al-O bond is weaker than the Si-O bond, so it is possible energetically for some bridging O atoms (e.g., Al-O-Si) to contribute to the formation of high-coordinated species. The bridging O that contributes to the formation of the highcoordinated species becomes threefold-coordinated. This process allows the formation of high-coordinated species, and therefore increases self-diffusion coefficients with increasing pressure, even in fully polymerized melts with no non-bridging O atoms. The formation of high-coordinated species will end when all fourfold-coordinated Al in the melt is transformed to high-coordinated species.</p><p>Self-diffusion coefficients reach maximum values when abundances of high-coordinated species peak and no new high-coordinated Al or Si species can form. The end of the formation of high-coordinated species essentially eliminates a pathway for rapid diffusion of network formers that exists at lower pressures. Early MD simulations of jadeite (NaAlSi 2 O 6 ) melt predicted that high-coordinated species may eventually dominate the network structure at pressures near 30 GPa, the same pressure where O self-diffusion coefficients were predicted to reach maximum values <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Angell et al. 1982</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Angell et al. , 1988))</ref>. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Nevins and Spera (1998)</ref> predicted maximum self-diffusion coefficients for Si and O near 5 GPa in an MD simulation study of anorthite (CaAlSi 2 O 8 ) liquid, when fivefold-coordinated Si and Al (generally, TO 5 in the Nevins and Spera terminology) are most abundant. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bryce et al. (1999)</ref> predict maximum self-diffusion coefficients for Si, Al, and O at pressures very near the pressures (20 to 25 GPa) at which TO 5 populations peak in nepheline (NaAlSiO 4 ), jadeite (NaAlSi 2 O 6 ), and albite (NaAlSi 3 O 8 ) liquids at 5000 K. For comparison, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Poe et al. (1997)</ref> observe a maximum in the O self-diffusion coefficient in albitic (NaAlSi 3 O 8 ) liquid near 5.5 ±0.5 GPa, as well as a maximum in the O self-diffusion coefficient in Na 3 AlSi 7 O 17 liquid at roughly 8.5 ±1 GPa. <ref type="bibr">Poe et al.</ref> suggested that the maximum self-diffusion coefficient for O coincides with the end of formation of high-coordinated Al. The large disparity between the MD simulations and the experimental results for albitic liquid is most likely due to the choice of constants A ij and B ij in the interaction potential U ij (from <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Dempsey and</ref><ref type="bibr">Kawamura 1984, discussed by Stein and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Spera 1995)</ref>, and to ignoring polarization and covalency of particles in the simulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Bryce et al. 1999)</ref>.</p><p>Experimental results showing maximum O self-diffusion coefficients are limited. However, existing data can be used to estimate pressures required to reach maximum self-diffusion coefficients in other compositions. For example, characteristics of dacitic liquids discussed in this study, and albitic and Na 3 AlSi 7 O 17 liquids from <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Poe et al. (1997)</ref> in which maximum self-diffusion coefficients have been observed, can be used to predict the pressures of maximum self-diffusion coefficients in basaltic and Na 2 Si 4 O 9 compositions. If pressure-induced increases in self-diffusion coefficients of network formers are limited by the abundance of Si and Al in the melt, we can relate maximum self-diffusion coefficients for O to molecular abundances of Si and Al. Silicon and Al constitute 73 cation percent of Na 3 AlSi 7 O 17 , and we place the maximum self-diffusion coefficient for O at 8.5 ± 1 GPa. In NaAlSi 3 O 8 , Si and Al are 80 cation percent and we place the maximum self-diffusion coefficient for O at 5.5 ± 0.5 GPa. In dacitic liquid, Si and Al are 84 cation percent and the maximum self-diffusion coefficient for O occurs at 5 ± 0.5 GPa. These data are plotted in Figure <ref type="figure">7b</ref>, with total Si and Al cation percent (Si + Al) on the abscissa and the pressure of maximum diffusion coefficient on the ordinate. Filled circles, which represent observations from experiments on Na 3 AlSi 7 O 17 , NaAlSi 3 O 8 , and dacitic liquids, show good correlation between the pressure of maximum self-diffusion coefficients and total Si and Al cation percent. A least squares, best fit to these data is shown as a solid line in Figure <ref type="figure">7b</ref>. The dashed line in Figure <ref type="figure">7b</ref> represents an extrapolation of this fit to lower total Si and Al cation contents. The maximum selfdiffusion coefficient for O is estimated at 15.9 GPa in Na 2 Si 4 O 9 and at 14.3 GPa in basaltic liquid. These estimates need to be confirmed experimentally. If the O self-diffusion coefficient in basaltic liquid does reach a maximum at 14.3 GPa, O self diffusion will have a positive dependence on pressure for the entire depth of the upper mantle, and this will affect the transport properties of basaltic liquids likely to be produced by partial melting of the mantle. For example, reactions controlling magma mixing or element partitioning in basaltic liquids may be accelerated at high pressures. Likewise, silica-rich liquids have been reported in mantle xenoliths <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Draper 1992)</ref>, suggesting that the results of the present study have direct relevance to the behavior of silicate liquids at high pressures in the Earth. Even if silica-rich liquids are not important components of the mantle, experimental study of these polymerized compositions can provide important insight into the mechanisms of Si and O transport at high pressures.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIGURE 1. Calibration curve for the 10 mm TEL assembly (inset) in the Walker-design multianvil apparatus. Calibrations using room temperature Bi metal transitions at 2.55 and 7.7 GPa and Ba I-II transition at 5.5 GPa<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bean et al. 1986</ref>) are represented by the bold curve. The dashed curve is fit to data from bracketing experiments for the high-temperature coesite-stishovite transformation at 9.2 GPa and 1200 °C (squares)<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Zhang et al. 1996)</ref>, the fayalite-spinel transformation at 5.25 GPa and 1000 °C (triangles)<ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Yagi et al. 1987)</ref>, and the melting of gold at 3 GPa, 1235 °C, and 4 GPa, 1290 °C (circles)<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Akella and Kennedy 1971)</ref>.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIGURE 3. (a) D* 0 variation with reciprocal temperature. Filled triangles are 1 GPa data, filled squares are 2 GPa data, and filled circles are 4 GPa data, plotted with 10% error bars on D* 0 . The lines through these data were generated using the Arrhenius relationship lnD* = lnD 0 -E a /RT, with simple regression coefficients for lnD 0 and E a . For 1 GPa data E a = 293 ± 10 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -8.9 ± 0.7, for 2 GPa E a = 264 ± 13 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -10.2 ± 0.9, and for 4 GPa E a = 155 ± 14 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -15.9 ± 0.9. (b) D* Si variation with reciprocal temperature. Open triangles are 1 GPa data, open squares are 2 GPa data, and open circles are 4 GPa data, plotted with 30% error bars on D* 0 . The lines through these data are generated using the Arrhenius relationship used for a. For 1 GPa data E a = 380 ± 21 kJ/mol and ln D 0 = -3.8 ± 1.4, for 2 GPa E a = 305 ± 28 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -8.3 ± 1.9, and for 4 GPa E a = 163 ± 35 kJ/mol and lnD 0 = -15.9 ± 2.3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIGURE 4. (a) Pressure dependence of D* 0 . Filled triangles are 1460 °C data, filled squares are 1561 °C data, and filled circles are 1662°C data, plotted with 10% error bars on D* 0 . Between 1 and 4 GPa, these data obey the Arrhenius-type relationship lnD* = lnD 0 -P∆V a /T. Lines through the data are determined using this equation with lnD 0 and ∆V a determined from simple linear regression. For 1460 °C, ∆V a = -14.5 ± 1.3 and lnD 0 = -30.6 ± 0.2, for 1561 °C, ∆V a = -9.8 ± 1.0 and lnD 0 = -28.6 ± 0.1, and for 1662 °C, ∆V a = -8.8 ± 0.9 and lnD 0 = -27.7 ± 0.1. It is important to note the maximum self-diffusion coefficient that occurs between 4 and 5.7 GPa. (b) Pressure dependence of D* Si . Open triangles are 1460 °C data, open squares are 1561 °C data, and open circles are 1662 °C data, plotted with 30% error bars on D* Si . Between 1 and 4 GPa, these data obey the Arrhenius-type relationship listed in part a. Lines through the data are determined using this equation with lnD 0 and ∆V a determined from simple linear regression. For 1460 °C, ∆V a = -17.1 ± 1.9 and lnD 0 = -32.0 ± 0.3, for 1561 °C, ∆V a = -8.7 ± 1.4 and lnD 0 = -28.9 ± 0.2, and for 1662 °C, ∆V a = -9.3 ± 1.5 and lnD 0 = -28.3 ± 0.2. The selfdiffusion coefficient for Si also reaches a maximum between 4 and 5.7 GPa.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIGURE 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>FIGURE 5. Schematic diagram of the cooperative diffusion mechanism involving the formation of a high-coordinated Si intermediate species. Here, four-coordinated B joins with fourcoordinated A and becomes a five-coordinated intermediate species (step 1). Diffusion occurs when B dissociates from its original bridging oxygen (step 2). Figure redrawn after Farnan and Stebbins (1994).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIGURE 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>FIGURE 6. Predicted λ calculated using the Eyring equation (D* = k B T/ηλ) with η estimated using the method ofBottinga and Weill (1982)   for dacitic liquid at 1460, 1561, and 1662 °C and with measured selfdiffusion coefficients D* for O. Vertical extensions from predicted λ values give maximum ranges of the pressure effect (taken to be equal to the pressure effect on the self-diffusion coefficient) on viscosity at these temperatures. For example, a pressure effect of one log unit per GPa increase in pressure from atmospheric pressure on D* equals a maximum pressure correction of one log unit on η per GPa increase in pressure. The predicted values for λ are compared with lines generated using the Eyring equation with measured D* and λ equal to multiples (n = 0.5, 1, 2, and 4) of the diameter of the O 2-anion. The general trend is for λ to decrease with increasing pressure and temperature.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIGURE 7. (a) Comparison of apparent maxima in O self-diffusion coefficients reported in this study for dacitic liquid (NBO/T = 0.1) at 1662 °C (filled circles) with maxima observed in experimental work on NaAlSi 3 O 8 (NBO/T = 0) at 1827 °C (filled triangles) and Na 3 AlSi 7 O 17 (NBO/T = 0.25) at 1827 °C (open triangles) (Poe et al. 1997). Also shown are experimental data for basalt at 1400 °C (open circles, Lesher et al. 1996) and Na 2 Si 4 O 9 (closed squares, 1827 °C from Rubie et al. 1993; open squares, 2227 °C from Poe et al. 1997) compositions, in which maximum self-diffusion coefficients have not been observed. The inset shows maximum D* 0 values predicted on the basis of MD studies at roughly 30 GPa for NaAlSi 2 O 6 (NBO/T = 0) at 5727 °C (dashed curve, Angell et al. 1982) and at roughly 5 GPa for CaAl 2 Si 2 O 8 at 4273 °C (solid curve, Nevins and Spera, 1998). (b) Estimates (open circles) of pressures for maximum O self-diffusion coefficients in Na 2 Si 4 O 9 [at 50 cation % (Si + Al), 15.9 GPa] and basaltic [at 55 cation % (Si + Al), 14.3 GPa] liquids. These estimates are based on extrapolation of the linear relationship defined by observed maximum self-diffusion coefficients in NaAlSi 3 O 8 , Na 3 AlSi 7 O 17 , and dacitic liquids (closed circles).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Starting compositions of the isotopically enriched and normal dacite compositions Chemical reagents from Fisher Scientific, Inc. 18 O-enriched CO2 and 28 Si-enriched SiO 2 from Cambridge Isotope Lab measured using the Cameca SX-50 electron microprobe at UC Davis.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>"Enriched"</cell><cell>"Normal"</cell></row><row><cell>SiO 2</cell><cell>68.39</cell><cell>69.38</cell></row><row><cell>TiO 2</cell><cell>0.52</cell><cell>0.54</cell></row><row><cell>Al2O3</cell><cell>17.46</cell><cell>16.87</cell></row><row><cell>MgO</cell><cell>3.53</cell><cell>3.36</cell></row><row><cell>CaO</cell><cell>3.12</cell><cell>3.04</cell></row><row><cell>Na2O</cell><cell>4.11</cell><cell>3.91</cell></row><row><cell>K 2 O</cell><cell>3.57</cell><cell>3.92</cell></row><row><cell>Notes:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Run conditions and calculated diffusion coefficients for O and Si discussed in this study</figDesc><table><row><cell>P</cell><cell cols="2">T ( o C) Run duration</cell><cell>D* 0 (m 2 /s)</cell><cell>D* Si</cell><cell>(m 2 /s)</cell></row><row><cell>(GPa)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(min)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>1355</cell><cell>1160</cell><cell>6.45 ± 0.65×10 -14</cell><cell cols="2">1.45 ± 0.45×10 -14</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>1410</cell><cell>760</cell><cell>1.10 ± 0.11×10 -13</cell><cell cols="2">3.75 ± 1.13×10 -14</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>1460</cell><cell>720</cell><cell>1.42 ± 0.14×10 -13</cell><cell cols="2">4.80 ± 1.44×10 -14</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>1561</cell><cell>690</cell><cell>7.02 ± 0.70×10 -13</cell><cell cols="2">5.77 ± 1.73×10 -13</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>1662</cell><cell>180</cell><cell>1.77 ± 0.18×10 -12</cell><cell cols="2">9.56 ± 2.87×10 -13</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>1410</cell><cell>420</cell><cell>2.43 ± 0.24×10 -13</cell><cell cols="2">1.02 ± 0.31×10 -13</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>1460</cell><cell>180</cell><cell cols="3">4.01 ± 0.40×10 --13 1.20 ± 0.36×10 -13</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>1561</cell><cell>270</cell><cell>1.45 ± 0.15×10 -12</cell><cell cols="2">6.36 ± 1.91×10 -13</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>1662</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>2.57 ± 0.26×10 -12</cell><cell cols="2">1.39 ± 0.42×10 -12</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>1460</cell><cell>92</cell><cell cols="3">2.85 ± 0.29×10 -12 1.57 ± 0.47×10 --12</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>1561</cell><cell>76</cell><cell>4.82 ± 0.48×10 -12</cell><cell cols="2">2.86 ± 0.86×10 -12</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>1662</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>8.77 ± 0.89×10 -12</cell><cell cols="2">5.13 ± 1.54×10 -12</cell></row><row><cell>5.2</cell><cell>1612</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>4.01 ± 0.40×10 -12</cell><cell cols="2">2.23 ± 0.67×10 -12</cell></row><row><cell>5.2</cell><cell>1637</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>7.80 ± 0.78×10 -12</cell><cell cols="2">4.95 ± 1.49×10 -12</cell></row><row><cell>5.7</cell><cell>1662</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>5.60 ± 0.56×10 -12</cell><cell cols="2">2.80 ± 0.28×10 -12</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>9.36</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>18 O/ΣO (*10 3 )</cell><cell>2 4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>9.28 9.32 28 Si/ΣSi (*10) 9.24</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>-400 -200</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>400</cell><cell>9.20</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Distance (µm)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">FIGURE 2. Isotopic profiles for 28 Si ( 28 Si/ΣSi, squares) and 18 O ( 18 O/</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">ΣO, circles) for a sample run at 2 GPa and 1410 °C for 420 minutes.</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Isotopic abundances were measured using the Cameca 3f ion</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">microprobe at the Center for Solid State Science, Arizona State</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Regression coefficients calculated for activation volumes (∆V a ) and energies (E a ), and for pre-exponential factors (lnD 0 ) discussed in this study</figDesc><table><row><cell>Oxygen</cell></row></table><note><p>-15.9 ± 2.3 Coefficients for multiple linear regression Dacite -11.1 ± 0.7 280 ± 12 -10.6 ± 0.8 -12.0 ± 1.0 341 ± 19 -7.4 ± 1.3 Basalt -8.1 ± 1.8 179 ± 13</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>Ion microprobe analyses were performed at the <rs type="institution">Center for Solid State Science, Arizona State University</rs>. The authors thank <rs type="person">Rick Hervig</rs> for his hospitality and expertise in making these measurements. Comments from <rs type="person">F.J. Spera</rs> and an anonymous reviewer improved the manuscript. The authors also acknowledge comments and editorial assistance from <rs type="person">Mike Toplis</rs>. This work was supported by <rs type="funder">NSF</rs><rs type="grantNumber">/EAR-94-19382</rs> (CEL).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_QCN46ey">
					<idno type="grant-number">/EAR-94-19382</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the temperature dependence of cooperative relaxation properties in glass-forming liquids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Adam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gibbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Chemical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Melting of gold, silver, and copper-Proposal for a new high-pressure calibration scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Akella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4969" to="4977" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pressure enhancement of ion mobilities in liquid silicates from computer simulation studies to 800 kilobars</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Angell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cheeseman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tamaddon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">218</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="885" to="887" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ion dynamics studies of liquid and glassy silicates, and gas-in-liquid solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Angell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Scamehorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Phifer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kadiyala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cheeseman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics and Chemistry of Minerals</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Akimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Block</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Holzapfel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Manghnani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Nicol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stishov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Another step toward an international practical pressure scale: 2nd AIRAPT IPPS task group report</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="54" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Silicate melts: The &quot;anomalous&quot; pressure depen-Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM dence of the viscosity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bottinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Richet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2725" to="2731" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The viscosity of magmatic silicate liquids: A model for calculation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bottinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Weill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">272</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="438" to="475" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Apparatus for phase equilibrium measurements at pressures up to 50 kilobars and temperatures up to 1750 °C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>England</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="741" to="748" />
			<date type="published" when="1960">1960</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pressure dependence of self-diffusion in the NaAlO 2 -SiO 2 system: Compositional effects and mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bryce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<publisher>American Mineralogist</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="356" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Structure, Dynamics, and Properties of Silicate Melts</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mcmillan</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dingwell</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Mineralogical Society of America</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="503" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Mathematics of Diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Crank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">414</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics simulation of the structure of aluminosilicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dempsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kawamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Progress in Experimental Petrology at National Environmental Research Council</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="56" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spinel lherzolite xenoliths from Lorena Butte, Simcoe Mountains, southern Washington (USA)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Draper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="766" to="776" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen diffusion in three silicate melts along the join diopsideanorthite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2292" to="2299" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The nature of the glass transition in a silica-rich oxide melt</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Farnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">265</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1206" to="1209" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in natural silicate melts: a critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics of Magmatic Processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hargraves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics simulations of SiO 2 melt and glass: ionic and covalent models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kubicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lasaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Mineralogist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="941" to="955" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics and diffusion in silicate melts</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Diffusion, Atomic Ordering, and Mass Transport</title>
		<title level="s">Advances in Physical Geochemistry</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ganguly</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="50" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscosity, density, and structure of silicate melts at high pressures, and their petrological applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Physics of Magmatic Processes</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hargraves</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton; New Jersey</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="120" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aluminum in glasses and melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lacy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics and chemistry of glasses</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermodynamic properties of silicate liquids with emphasis on density, thermal expansion and compressibility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S E</forename><surname>Carmichael</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Modern Methods of Igneous Petrology</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nicholls</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Mineralogical Society of America</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="64" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Washington, D.C</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self diffusion of network formers (silicon and oxygen) in naturally occurring basaltic liquid</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lesher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hervig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tinker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="413" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in silicate melts: I. Self diffusion in CaO-Al 2 O 3 -SiO 2 at 1500 °C and 1 GPa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4353" to="4367" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusive motion in alkali silicate melts: an NMR study at high temperature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pines</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3653" to="3664" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationships between silicate melt structure and petrologic processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth Science Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">281365</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics simulations of molten CaAl2Si2O8: Dependence of structure and properties on pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nevins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Mineralogist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1220" to="1230" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen diffusion in liquid silicates and relation to their viscosity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Oishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Terai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ueda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mass Transport Phenomena in Ceramics</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Heuer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="310" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Plenum</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Silicon and oxygen self-diffusivities in silicate liquids measured to 15 gigapascals and 2800 Kelvin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Poe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mcmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rubie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yarger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Diefenbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">276</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1245" to="1248" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen self diffusion in Na 2 Si 4 O 9 liquid up to 10 GPa and estimation of high-pressure melt viscosities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rubie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Elphick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Mineralogist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="574" to="582" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics of liquid SiO 2 under high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rustad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yuen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review, section A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2081" to="2089" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscosities of magmatic silicate liquids: An empirical method of prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">272</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="870" to="893" />
			<date type="published" when="1972">1972</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusivity of oxygen in jadeite and diopside melts at high pressures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shimizu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1295" to="1303" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mobility of Mg, Ca, and Si in diopside-jadeite liquids at high pressures</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Physical Geochemistry</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Perchuk</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kushiro</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="212" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NMR evidence for five-coordinated silicon in a silicate glass at atmospheric pressure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">351</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="638" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Five-and six-coordinated Si in K 2 Si 4 O 9 glass quenched from 1.9 GPa and 1200° C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mcmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Mineralogist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="965" to="968" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics simulations of liquids and glasses in the system NaAlSiO 4 -SiO 2 : methodology and melt structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Spera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Mineralogist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative links between microscopic properties and viscosity of liquids in the system SiO 2 -Na 2 O</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Toplis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chemical Geology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peraluminous viscosity maxima in Na2O-Al2O3-SiO2 liquids: The role of triclusters in tectosilicate melts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Toplis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dingwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lenci</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2650" to="2612" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion of calcium and silicon in a lime-alumina-silica slag</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Towers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chipman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transactions AIME</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">209</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="769" to="773" />
			<date type="published" when="1957">1957</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lubrication, gasketing, and precision in multianvil experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Mineralogist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1092" to="1100" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular dynamics study of the transport properties of perovskite melts under high temperature and pressure conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wasserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yuen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rustad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth and Planetary Science Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="384" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion in magmas at depth in the earth: the effects of pressure and dissolved H 2 O</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Earth and Planetary Science Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pressureinduced silicon coordination and tetrahedral structural changes in alkali oxidesilica melts up to 12 GPa: NMR, raman, and infrared spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stebbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kanzaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mcmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Poe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Mineralogist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In situ observation of the olivine-spinel phase transformation in Fe 2 SiO 4 using synchrotron radiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Akaogi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Shimomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Akimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6207" to="6213" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Al coordination changes in high-pressure aluminosilicate liquids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Yarger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nieman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Diefenbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Poe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mcmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">270</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1964" to="1967" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen diffusion in multicomponent glass-forming silicates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yinnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics and Chemistry of Glasses</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In situ x-ray observations of the coesite-stishovite transition: reversed phase boundary and kinetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Utsumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Liebermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics and Chemistry of Minerals</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MANUSCRIPT ACCEPTED SEPTEMBER 19, 2000 PAPER HANDLED BY MICHAEL TOPLIS Brought to you by | New York University Bobst Library Technical Services Authenticated Download</title>
		<idno>Date | 7/1/15 1:28 PM</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>MANUSCRIPT RECEIVED DECEMBER 14</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
