<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A refractory Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 high-entropy alloy with excellent structural stability and tensile properties</title>
				<funder ref="#_8eaaPnH">
					<orgName type="full">Program for ChangJiang Scholars and Innovative Research Team in University</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_jngTNQt">
					<orgName type="full">National Natural Science Foundation of China</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_NqPRm2u #_YAF2nKG">
					<orgName type="full">State Key Laboratory for Advanced Metals and Materials, USTB</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_PECbqDj">
					<orgName type="full">National Nature Science Foundation of China</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-05-28">28 May 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory for Advanced Metals and Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology Beijing</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100083</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">PR China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory for Advanced Metals and Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology Beijing</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100083</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">PR China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory for Advanced Metals and Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology Beijing</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100083</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">PR China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Si</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory for Advanced Metals and Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology Beijing</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100083</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">PR China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory for Advanced Metals and Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology Beijing</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100083</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">PR China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory for Advanced Metals and Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology Beijing</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100083</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">PR China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory for Advanced Metals and Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Science and Technology Beijing</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100083</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">PR China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A refractory Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 high-entropy alloy with excellent structural stability and tensile properties</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-05-28">28 May 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">433B87675215BFDB217FE061815100C2</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.matlet.2014.05.134</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 16 April 2014 Accepted 21 May 2014</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>High-entropy alloy Metals and alloys Plasticity Microstructure</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>A novel refractory Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 high entropy alloy (HEA) with single body centered cubic (BCC) structure was prepared by copper mold cast method. This HEA still holds the single BCC phase even after furnace cooling from homogenization at 1573 K for 6 h. The fracture strength and plastic strain of this HEA reach about 969 MPa and 14.9%, respectively. There is significant work hardening effect in this HEA, which is considered as resulting from the movement and multiplication of dislocations.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>High entropy alloys (HEAs) are basically defined as those alloys which contain multi-principal elements in equal or near equal atomic percentage <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Recently, great attention has been paid to HEAs due to their high strength, high hardness, excellent softening resistance, wear and corrosion resistance etc. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Two types of HEA systems with the face centered cubic (FCC) and body centered cubic (BCC) crystal structure, respectively, have been developed. The FCC type of HEAs which is represented by FeCoNiCrMn HEA alloys exhibits high thermodynamic stability and excellent malleability, but has medium high tensile strength <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>. In contrast, the BCC type of HEAs has high strength, but shows high brittleness and low ductility. Very recently, Senkov et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> prepared a series of BCC structure refractory HEAs with high hardness and compressive yield strength up to 1300 MPa. However, most of these refractory HEAs only show low compressive plastic strain at room temperature. It has been also noted that no tensile properties have been reported for BCC structure HEAs. However, tensile properties are more valuable for engineering application of HEAs. In this letter, a new BCC Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 HEA with excellent structural stability at high temperature, and the combination of high tensile strength and plasticity is presented for the first time. The structural stability, deformation and fracture feature for this HEA are examined. The strengthening mechanism for the excellent tensile properties of this HEA is discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental</head><p>Alloy ingots with a nominal composition of Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 (at%) were prepared by arc-melting a mixture of pure metals (purity 499.8 wt%) in a Ti-gettered high-purity argon atmosphere. The ingots were flipped and remelted five times to ensure the chemical homogeneity. The melted alloys were then drop-cast into a watercooled copper mold with dimensions of 10 mm Â 10 mm Â 60 mm. The as-cast bar was sealed in a vacuum quartz tube and subsequently homogenized in a tubular furnace at 1573 K for 6 hours in flowing Ar atmosphere and subsequently furnace-cooled to room temperature. The phase formation and stability was characterized by X-ray diffraction (XRD) and Differential scanning calorimeter (DSC) at the heating rate of 20 K/min, respectively.</p><p>The room temperature mechanical properties were evaluated using CMT4105 universal electronic tensile testing machine at the strain rate of 1 Â 10 À 3 s À 1 . Dog-bone shape specimens with gauge geometry of 1 mm Â 5 mm Â 10 mm were used in the test. The microstructure and fracture morphologies of the samples were investigated by using scanning electron microscope (SEM) Auriga produced by Zeiss (BRD). The refined microstructures of as-cast and fractured samples were examined by FEI G 2 F20 type of transmission electron microscope (TEM). The TEM samples were prepared by ion milling after mechanical grounding down to 40 μm of thickness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head><p>The XRD and DSC patterns of as-cast and homogenized samples are presented in Fig. only peaks of single BCC phase. Both the DSC curves don't have exothermic or endothermic phase transformation peaks below 1200 . The secondary electron (SE) image of the as-cast sample (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>) reveals a homogeneous dendrites microstructure. After homogenization (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>) at 1573 K for 6 h, the dendritic structure disappeared and the grains have grown to the size of $1 mm, indicating that the microstructure is still composed of the single solid solution phase. This illustrates that the HEA has high structural stability even with furnace cooling.</p><p>So far, several parameters have been proposed to predict the structural stability and phase formation of HEAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>. Zhang et al. proposed a criterion for the formation of solid-solution phases in HEAs based on the enthalpy of mixing ðΔH mix Þ and atomic radius difference ðδÞ <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. To further include the mixing entropy effect, an additional parameter ðΩÞ was also proposed as Ω¼T m ΔS mix /|ΔH mix |, where T m is the average melting temperature and ΔS mix the entropy of mixing of an alloy. From available data, it was concluded that the criteria for the formation of HEAs with single solid solution phase are ΩZ1:1 and δr6:6% , respectively. As for current HEA, the values of Ω and δ are calculated to be 10.75 and 4.86%, respectively, which are perfectly in accordance with the above mentioned criteria.</p><p>Guo et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref> proposed another parameter named valence electron concentration (VEC) according to the electronic structure theory to predict the phase stability of HEAs. Guo's statistics analysis indicates that BCC solid-solution phases were found to be stable as the VEC value is lower than 6.87. The VEC value of current HEA is calculated to be 4.25, which is in the range of VEC of the stable phase.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows the tensile true stress-stain curve of Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 alloy. It can be derived that this HEA has the yield strength (YS) of $879 MPa, the ultimate tensile strength (UTS) of $ 969 MPa, and the elastic and plastic elongation of $ 0.9%, and $ 14.9%, respectively. The fracture strength of this HEA is much higher than most of reported FCC type of HEAs, which may attributed to the formation of single BCC phase with strong bonding inherited from the refractory elements and the high solution hardening effect of whole-solute matrix. Meanwhile, this HEA exhibits very large plastic strain, which has been seldom found for BCC type of HEAs.</p><p>The SEM images of the fracture surface for this HEA alloy are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>. Obvious necking near the fracture surface and the twirling and surface relief effect of crystalline grains can be found from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(a)</ref>, demonstrating that typical plastic deformation took place before fracture. Multiple slip bands can be clearly observed on the grains in the necking surface (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(b)</ref>). The grain boundaries have been seriously distorted. From the SEM image  of fracture surface (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3(c)</ref> and<ref type="figure">(d)</ref>), it is seen that there are obvious vein patterns inside crystal grains. Dimples with size smaller than 100 μm distribute densely on the fracture surface. Some tearing took place across grain boundaries, and tiny dimples with size smaller than 5 μm distribute densely around the tearing ridges. All these features indicate that the fracture behavior is of typical ductile fracture, which is accordance with the high plastic strain as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</p><p>In this work, TEM analysis was also performed to clarify the strengthening mechanism. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>(a), no secondary phase precipitated in the microstructure. The dark fringes near the edge are actually the contrast difference induced by the mechanical stress which was generated during ion milling process. The selected area diffraction pattern (SADP) of the corresponding area, as shown in inset of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>(a), further confirms that the structure is of a single BCC structure with the lattice constant of 0.3519 nm. The structure of this HEA after fracture has been remarkably changed. From Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>(b), it is seen that a large amount of short curved dislocation lines distributes in the whole area of the sample. No secondary phase was formed even undergoing severe deformation. It is deduced that during the deformation process, dislocation motions are gradually retarded, then tangled and finally accumulate around grain boundaries and slip bands. Therefore, the dislocation strengthening via dislocation multiplication is considered to be the main mechanism for the large plasticity and significant work hardening of this HEA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p>In summary, a novel refractory HfNbTiZr high-entropy alloy with a single BCC phase has been successfully developed. This new HEA alloy exhibits excellent phase stability at high temperature and no phase separation during furnace cooling from 1573 K homogenization. In the as-cast state, tensile YS is 879 MPa, UTS is 969 MPa, and the plastic elongation is 14.9%. The YS and UTS  obtained in tensile tests are much higher than most of reported FCC type of HEAs. The remarkable tensile elongation is seldom found in BCC HEAs. The TEM study confirms that dense dislocations have been formed during the deformation, resulting in large plasticity and significant work hardening for this HEA.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. (a) XRD patterns, (b) DSC heating curves, (c) and (d) SEM images of as-cast and homogenized Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 alloys.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,111.86,58.64,361.92,325.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Tensile true stress-strain curve of Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 alloy.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,333.48,414.30,187.68,144.43" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. SEM images of Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 alloy after tensile tests. (a) low and (b) high magnification images of the specimen surfaces; (c) low and (d) high magnification images of the fracture surfaces.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,119.95,58.64,365.28,275.18" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. TEM bright-field images and the corresponding selected area diffraction pattern of (a) as-cast and (b) tensile-tested Hf 25 Nb 25 Ti 25 Zr 25 alloy.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,137.44,372.46,330.24,160.13" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1. Both the XRD patterns show that there are Contents lists available at ScienceDirect journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/matlet</figDesc><table><row><cell>Materials Letters</cell></row></table><note><p><p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.matlet.2014.05.134 0167-577X/&amp; 2014 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. n Corresponding author. Tel.: þ 86 10 68918758; fax: þ 86 10 62333447. nn Corresponding author. Tel.: þ 86 10 62333066; fax: þ86 10 62333447.</p>E-mail addresses: ydwang@bit.edu.cn (Y.D. Wang), xdhui@ustb.edu.cn (X.D. Hui).</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This research was supported by <rs type="funder">National Natural Science Foundation of China</rs> (No. <rs type="grantNumber">51271018</rs>), in part by <rs type="funder">National Nature Science Foundation of China</rs> (No. <rs type="grantNumber">51010001</rs>), 111 project (<rs type="grantNumber">B07003</rs>) and <rs type="funder">Program for ChangJiang Scholars and Innovative Research Team in University</rs>, and the proprietary program of the <rs type="funder">State Key Laboratory for Advanced Metals and Materials, USTB</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">2011Z-01</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">2012Z-01</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_jngTNQt">
					<idno type="grant-number">51271018</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PECbqDj">
					<idno type="grant-number">51010001</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_8eaaPnH">
					<idno type="grant-number">B07003</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_NqPRm2u">
					<idno type="grant-number">2011Z-01</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_YAF2nKG">
					<idno type="grant-number">2012Z-01</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Shun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Eng Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="303" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cantor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ith</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Knight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ajb</forename><surname>Vincent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Sci Eng: A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="218" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scripta Materialia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="526" to="529" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Otto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dlouhý</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Somsen</forename><surname>Ch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Eggeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5743" to="5755" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Tung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2993" to="3001" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kuznetsov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shaysultanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Sci Eng: A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">533</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Alloys Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">509</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6043" to="6048" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Sci Eng: A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">565</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1545" to="1557" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1758" to="1765" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Sci Eng: A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater Chem Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pk</forename><forename type="middle">Eng</forename><surname>Liawadvanced</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mater</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="534" to="538" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog Nat Sci: Mater Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="446" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Appl Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">103505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
