<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Compositional variation effects on the microstructure and properties of a refractory high-entropy superalloy AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</title>
				<funder ref="#_qSQNGup">
					<orgName type="full">Air Force</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">ONS</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_wFpKVFM">
					<orgName type="full">Air Force Research Laboratory</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_jsmUCez">
					<orgName type="full">UES, Inc.</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-11-21">21 November 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Materials and Manufacturing Directorate</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Air Force Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>45433</postCode>
									<settlement>Wright-Patterson AFB</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Center for the Accelerated Maturation of Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Ohio State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1305 Kinnear Rd</addrLine>
									<postCode>43212</postCode>
									<settlement>Columbus</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pilchak</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Materials and Manufacturing Directorate</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Air Force Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>45433</postCode>
									<settlement>Wright-Patterson AFB</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Materials and Manufacturing Directorate</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Air Force Research Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>45433</postCode>
									<settlement>Wright-Patterson AFB</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Center for the Accelerated Maturation of Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Ohio State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1305 Kinnear Rd</addrLine>
									<postCode>43212</postCode>
									<settlement>Columbus</settlement>
									<region>OH</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Compositional variation effects on the microstructure and properties of a refractory high-entropy superalloy AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-11-21">21 November 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">0B9F2738D05A244ED6AD8F725E2C804C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.matdes.2017.11.033</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 14 September 2017 Received in revised form 19 October 2017 Accepted 17 November 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>High entropy alloy Superalloy Microstructure Mechanical properties</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>A BCC-based analog to superalloy microstructures is sought with a ductile BCC matrix and coherent ordered B2 nano-precipitates.</p><p>• AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr has a brittle B2 matrix, coherent BCC nano-precipitates and coarse HCP particles at grain boundaries. • Sequential composition changes removed BCC and HCP phases in some alloys but the B2 phase remained continuous. • Deformation inverted the microstructure into a continuous BCC matrix and discrete B2 precipitates.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>High entropy alloys (HEAs) are one of the most recent developments in material science, which open a vast, unexplored area of alloy compositions and the potential to influence solid solution phase stability through control of configurational entropy <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref>. Using the HEA concept, several refractory high entropy alloys (RHEAs) have recently been reported as promising alternatives to Ni-based superalloys <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref>. RHEAs with a low density and high strength are among the most promising recent achievements in this field <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>. The reported densities of these new RHEAs are in the range of 5.9 to 8.4 g/cm 3 and their specific strengths are often superior to Ni-based superalloys <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref>. Some of these alloys consist of very fine, nano-scale mixtures of disordered BCC and ordered B2 phases with similar lattice parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref>, which may be responsible for their high strengths. Among these RHEAs, AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr has impressive yield strength of 745 MPa and good compressive ductility (N50% height reduction) at 1000 °C. Detailed analysis of the microstructure and crystal structure of this alloy using advanced transmission electron microscopy (TEM) and atom probe tomography (APT) techniques revealed a nano-scale, modulated mixture of an ordered B2 matrix and coherent, cuboidal precipitates of a disordered BCC phase <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref>. Based on these microstructural features, which are typical to superalloys, complex composition and the high strength at temperatures from 25 °C to 1200 °C, this two-phase alloy was named a "refractory high entropy superalloy" <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>.</p><p>Despite showing exceptionally good high-temperature properties, the AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr superalloy has very limited ductility at temperatures ≤ 600 °C, which has been explained by the presence of brittle, coarse intermetallic precipitates at grain boundaries <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20]</ref>. It was found that these grain-boundary (GB) precipitates have a hexagonal (P63/mcm) crystal structure and are predominantly composed of Al and Zr with an overall composition (in at.%) of ~Al 37 Mo 2 Nb 8 Ta 2 Ti 9 Zr 42 <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>. Based on model γ/γ′ superalloys, an 'ideal' microstructure of refractory superalloys would consist of two nanometer-scale, ordered/ disordered coherent phases, one of which is a disordered BCC matrix and another is ordered B2 precipitates, while the deleterious hexagonal intermetallic grain-boundary phase is completely removed. In some cases, heat treatment and/or hot working processing are used to remove intermetallic particles from grain boundaries, but annealing at 1000-1400 °C and water quenching of AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr revealed this phase to be stable over a large range of temperatures <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>.</p><p>In this work, an attempt has been made to remove the coarse, GB intermetallic phase, while maintaining the equiaxed grain microstructure comprised of the nano-scale interpenetrating phases, by adjusting the composition of the base AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr superalloy. Based on the large number of intermetallic phases that form in the Al-Zr binary system and the large electronegativity difference compared to other constituent elements in the HEA composition, the effects of reducing Al and Zr on the HEA microstructure were first investigated and characterized. In addition, the effect of removing Mo on the alloy phase composition, strength and ductility was also explored.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental procedures</head><p>HEA ingots with the compositions AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr (base composition, alloy #1), AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 (reduction of Zr by ½ molar ratio, alloy #2), AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 (reduction of Zr by ½ molar ratio and removal of Mo, alloy #3), Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr (reduction of Al by ½ molar ratio, alloy #4), and Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr (reduction of Al by ¾ molar ratio and replacement of Mo with Ta, alloy #5) were prepared by vacuum arc melting in an inert gas atmosphere. The samples were then hot isostatic pressed (HIP'd) for 2 h at 1400 °C and 207 MPa to remove any porosity and annealed in a flowing argon furnace at 1400 °C for 6 h followed by a furnace cool to room temperature with the initial cooling rate of 20 °C/ min.</p><p>A Bruker D2 Phaser X-ray diffractometer, at Cu Kα radiation, was used to identify the crystal structure of main phases in the alloys. The microstructure was characterized using scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) techniques. SEM was equipped with backscattered electron (BSE) and electron backscatter diffraction (EBSD) detectors. BSE and EBSD image processing and analysis was performed using the Materials Image Processing and Automated Reconstruction (MIPAR) software package <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>.</p><p>Samples for TEM analysis were extracted at site specific locations from the bulk sample using an FEI Helios NanoLab 600 Dual-Beam focused ion beam (DB-FIB) instrument. The FIB lift-out and thinning procedures are described elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref>. The thinned FIB lamellae were characterized using conventional bright-field (BF) and dark-field (DF) TEM imaging in an FEI CM200. Scanning transmission electron microscopy (STEM) high-angle annular dark-field (HAADF) micrographs were taken with an FEI Probe-Corrected Titan 80-300 STEM operating at 300 kV and a camera length of 115 mm. The convergence semiangle of the electron beam was 11.4 mrad and the inner and outer collection angles of the HAADF detector were 34.8 and 230.0 mrad, respectively. X-ray energy dispersive spectroscopy (XEDS) was performed using an FEI Image-Corrected Titan 60-300 STEM equipped with a Super-X™ XEDS detector system. The TEM was operated with an accelerating voltage of 300 kV and an electron beam convergence semiangle of 25 mrad. Cliff-Lorimer quantification and analysis of Super-X™ XEDS data was performed using standardless native k-factors in the Bruker Esprit software.</p><p>A Vickers microhardness unit was used to measure room temperature microhardness. Ten measurements were collected and averaged for each sample using a 1000 g load applied for 15 s. Room temperature compression tests were conducted using a servo-hydraulic MTS machine operating at a constant ram speed of 0.008 mm/s and silicon carbide dies. A thin (~50 μm) teflon foil was used as a lubricating material between the die and sample contacting surfaces. The initial sample dimensions were 5 mm × 5 mm × 8 mm, giving an initial strain rate of 0.001 s -1 . Sample deformation was monitored and synced with the load output from the test frame using a Video Displacement and Image Correlation System (Correlated Solutions Inc.), which also provided a visual record of individual specimen deformation response.</p><p>Compression tests at 1000 °C were conducted in a computercontrolled Instron mechanical testing machine outfitted with a Brew vacuum furnace and silicon carbide dies covered by boron-nitride powder to reduce friction. The specimen dimensions were 5 mm × 5 mm × 8 mm. Prior to each test, the furnace chamber was evacuated to 10 -6 Torr. The sample was then heated to the test temperature over a period of ~45 min and soaked at 1000 °C for 15 min under 22 N load control, and then compressed to fracture or to a 55% height reduction, whichever occurred first, at a constant ram speed of 0.008 mm/s that provided an initial strain rate of 0.001 s -1 . Load versus frame displacement responses were registered without specimens and these displacement values were subtracted from the frame displacements measured during the specimen compression at every registered load value. This procedure allowed measurements of deformation of the specimens only and excluded the elastic responses of the dies, machine frame and load cell.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">X-ray diffraction analysis and alloy density</head><p>X-ray diffraction (XRD) patterns of the four modified alloys after HIP and annealing at 1400 °C are given in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The diffraction peaks in these alloys correspond to a single-phase BCC crystal structure, with the lattice parameter changing with composition (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). XRD of the base AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr alloy conducted in previous work clearly showed the presence of two BCC phases <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref>. Detailed TEM and APT phase analysis in AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr revealed that one is a disordered BCC (A2) phase enriched with Nb and Ta with the lattice parameter a = 326.9 pm, and another is an ordered B2 phase enriched with Al and Zr with a = 330.4 pm <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref>. Reducing the amount of Zr in the AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 alloy resulted in a single BCC crystal structure with a = 326.9 pm (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>). Additional removal of Mo (AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 alloy) retained a single-phase BCC structure, but with an increased lattice parameter a = 330.6 pm (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>). According to the X-ray diffraction analysis, the reduced Al content alloy (Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr) also contained a single BCC phase with a lattice parameter a = 323.3 pm (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>), which is the average value of the lattice parameters of the BCC and B2 phases in the base AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr alloy. Finally, the alloy with a reduced Al and Mo content replaced with Ta (Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr) has a BCC crystal structure with a = 330.0 pm, similar to the Al, Zr-rich phase in the base alloy.</p><p>The alloy density was measured using a helium pycnometer and the results are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. The density values calculated using the rule of mixtures of pure elements, Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>), are also given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> for comparison.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ρ calc ¼ X c i M i = X c i V i<label>ð1Þ</label></formula><p>In Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>), c i , M i and V i are the atomic fraction (taken from Table <ref type="table">2</ref>), atomic mass, and atomic volume of element i, respectively. The measured density is always higher than the calculated density, which is an indication that the average atomic volume of the elements in each of the alloys is smaller than the average atomic volume of the pure elements, i.e. the elements experience some constraints (shrinkage) in the studied alloys. The atomic volume reduction is ~1% in these alloys. The atomic volume reduction is an indication of formation of some degree of covalency in the bonds between the elements and may also indicate ordering. The microstructure of the base AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr alloy was reported in detail elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref>. SEM-BSE images show the microstructure consisted of equiaxed grains, with low-angle subgrain boundaries inside the grains and coarse intermetallic particles at grain boundaries (GBs) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2a</ref>). The chemical composition of the alloy, matrix grains and GB particles is given in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. The GB particles are rich in Al and Zr while the matrix grains are slightly depleted with these elements, relative to the alloy composition. The volume fraction of the GB particles was estimated to be ~6-12%, depending on the location in the alloy. A detailed analysis using converged beam electron diffraction (CBED) revealed that the GB intermetallic particles have an ordered hexagonal crystal structure (space group P6 3 /mcm) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>. A very fine, basket-weave nano-lamellar structure was identified at high magnifications inside the grains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2b</ref>). It consists of continuous channels of an ordered B2 phase and cuboidal and/or plate-like disordered A2 (BCC) phase between the channels (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). These phases are coherent with each other and exhibit continuous lattice registry with a cubeon-cube orientation relationship described by 〈100〉 BCC //〈100〉 B2 , {001} BCC //{001} B2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref>. The precipitate dimensions in two orthogonal directions parallel to the precipitate edges vary from ~10 to ~55 nm and from ~25 to ~55 nm, respectively. The width of the B2 channels is ~7.0 ± 1.0 nm. The volume fraction of the disordered BCC phase was estimated to be 62 ± 2% <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>.</p><p>3.2.2. AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 SEM-BSE micrographs of the annealed AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 alloy are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>. The low magnification microstructure looks similar to that from the base alloy, AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr. It consists of equiaxed grains and dark-contrast second-phase GB particles (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4a</ref>). However, unlike AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZ, the higher magnification BSE images do not show contrast modulations inside the grains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4b</ref>), suggesting that the matrix grains are likely single-phase. XEDS analysis reveals that the GB particles have high concentrations of Al and Zr and their composition is similar to the GB particles in the base alloy (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). The composition of the grains is only slightly different from the composition of the alloy.</p><p>A STEM-HAADF micrograph taken from the interface between a darker contrast GB precipitate phase and a lighter contrast intragranular (matrix) phase is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>. The intragranular region is a single phase. A selected area diffraction analysis revealed that this phase has an ordered B2 crystal structure. For example, the (100) super-lattice reflections indicating ordering are clearly seen in the [001] zone axis of the B2 (intragranular) phase (inset in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>). A low-angle boundary consisting of an array of dislocation can also be seen inside the matrix grain in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>.</p><p>Super-X™ XEDS composition maps were acquired from the region of the AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 thinned foil indicated by the HAADF micrograph in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>. The XEDS spectra were only used to describe general trends in composition. As shown in the elemental maps, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6</ref>, the GB particle has a higher concentration of Al and Zr and reduced  concentrations of other elements relative to the matrix (B2) phase, which is in agreement with SEM/EDS (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). The regions on both sides of a subgrain boundary inside the matrix show the same composition as the matrix phase, further indicating a single B2 phase matrix microstructure.</p><p>3.2.3. AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 SEM BSE images of annealed AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref>. Low magnification micrographs of this Mo-free alloy reveal a coarse-grained (mm size scale), equiaxed single-phase microstructure and complete absence of coarse GB precipitates typical in AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 RHEAs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7a</ref>). Higher magnification micrographs show no evidence of the modulated two-phase structure inside the equiaxed grains. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7b</ref> shows a triple point and grain boundaries between three large grains. A dark contrast phase with a thin, serrated morphology is present uniformly along the grain boundaries. The dark contrast and jaggedness of the grain boundary look similar to intergranular cracks. However, a TEM FIB sample extracted and thinned along a similar grain boundary verified that the contrast was caused by a second phase with a lower average atomic number, and no voids or inter-granular cracks were detected along GBs.</p><p>A STEM-HAADF micrograph of a GB region showing two adjacent matrix grains and a darker contrast, second phase along the GB in shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8</ref>. The matrix grains are single phase with an ordered B2 crystal structure, based on the inset selected area diffraction pattern of a [001] zone axis of the B2 phase. Element ordering is revealed by the presence of faint (100) super-lattice reflections. XEDS composition maps from the same region are also shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8</ref>. Qualitatively, the darker contrast GB phase was rich in Al and Zr compared with the B2 intra-granular phase. The overall composition of the GB phase in this modified alloy is similar to the composition of the ordered hexagonal phase in the base alloy. This Al-Zr intermetallic is surrounded by a region deficient in Al and Zr and higher in Ta, which appears as a brightcontrast layer in the HAADF images. Despite the reduction in Zr and Mo concentration, the microstructure still contains a thin layer of the secondary intermetallic Al-Zr phase along high-angle grain boundaries. The effect on the microstructure by reducing Al was very different from reducing Zr. SEM BSE micrographs of Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr (Al was decreased by half relative to the base alloy) are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9</ref>. The low magnification BSE image shows an equiaxed grain microstructure with needle-like features inside the grains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9a</ref>). A lamellar eutectic-like two-phase microstructure is present along high-and low-angle GBs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9b</ref>). High magnification images of the grain interior revealed an orthogonally aligned nanoscale microstructure of two distinct phases (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9c</ref>), nearly identical to the base alloy nanoscale microstructure. Subgrain boundaries within the equiaxed grains are also present and look similar to those in the AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr base alloy. The needle-like features inside grains consist of three phases with distinct Z contrasts (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9d</ref>). The core of the needles consists of a bristle of a dark phase surrounded by a bright phase. This core is surrounded by another dark phase, which also contains fine spherical bright particles at the boundary with the matrix (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9d</ref>). XEDS chemical analysis of the bright-and dark-contrast phases inside the needle-like features and at grain/subgrain boundaries (i.e. in the locations containing coarse particles of these phases) shows that the bright phase is enriched in Mo, Nb and Ta, while the dark phase is rich in Al and Zr. The dark core bristle is heavily rich in Zr.</p><p>STEM-HAADF micrographs of Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10</ref>. An edge of a needle-like precipitate surrounded by the twophase nanoscale microstructure is seen at the top of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10a</ref>. The nanoscale microstructure consists of a higher average atomic number phase of rounded cuboidal precipitates aligned along 〈100〉 orientations in a lower average atomic number continuous matrix (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10b</ref>). The inset SADP shows (100) superlattice reflections indicating sublattice ordering in at least one of the nanoscale phases. The nanoscale precipitate phase  was of the same size scale of the disordered BCC cuboidal precipitates in the base alloy microstructure but was not as periodic, and only a single precipitate morphology was present.</p><p>XEDS elemental maps acquired near the needle-like precipitate are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11</ref>. The lighter contrast phase (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">10</ref>) has a composition higher in Mo, Nb, and Ta compared to the darker contrast matrix phase rich in Al and Zr. The partitioning of elements in the nanoscale phases is similar to the as-received base alloy microstructure in which BCC precipitates (rich in Mo, Nb, and Ta) are present in a continuous B2 matrix (rich in Al and Zr). Bright-field and dark-field micrographs of the nanoscale microstructure revealed that, in similar fashion to the base RHEA, the precipitate phase is a disordered solid solution A2 (BCC) phase while the continuous matrix is an ordered B2 phase. The phases in the needle-like precipitate (at the top and in the center of the XEDS scan) have the same composition as the nano-scale intra-granular phases, with the exception of the acicular feature in the center, which has a high concentration of Zr (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">11</ref>). It is possible that bristles of almost pure Zr precipitated inside grains in the annealed alloy, which are nuclei for the formation of the needle-like two-phase precipitates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.5.">Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr</head><p>The Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr RHEA has even less Al than the previous alloy and all Mo is replaced with Ta. SEM/BSE micrographs of this alloy are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">12</ref>. The lower magnification BSE images reveal a microstructure consisting of equiaxed grains and a well-developed subgrain structure inside the grains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">12a</ref>). No coarse GB particles are present. Higher magnification micrographs show a two-phase nanoscale interpenetrating microstructure, with the two phases coarsened at grain/ subgrain boundaries (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">12b</ref>), similar to the base alloy.</p><p>A STEM-HAADF micrograph of a thin foil, which was extracted from a grain interior by FIB, is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">13</ref>. The nanoscale microstructure consists of brighter contrast cuboidal and plate-like precipitates in a darker contrast continuous matrix. The lighter contrast precipitates coalesce together to form larger structures but remain aligned along cube face directions. Complimentary BF and DF micrographs were acquired with the electron beam parallel to the [001] zone axis of the nanoscale microstructure and are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_16">14</ref>. The inset [001] SADP taken with a large selected area aperture over both phases is consistent with a BCC crystal structure. The contrast observed in the dark-field micrograph indicates that the continuous channels of the matrix phase are an ordered B2 structure while the cuboidal precipitates are a disordered BCC solid solution phase. While the morphology of the BCC precipitates is slightly different from the periodic plate and cube structure in the base RHEA composition, the phases present in the nanoscale microstructure are the same. A region of the nanoscale microstructure and grain boundary was compositionally mapped using Super-X™ TEM  XEDS. Similar to the nanoscale microstructure of the base alloy, the ordered continuous matrix is rich in Al and Zr while the disordered precipitate phase has a higher concentration of Nb and Ta (no Mo in this modified composition). The coarser precipitates at subgrain/grain boundaries, similar to those shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">12b</ref>, have the same composition and the BCC and B2 crystal structures as in the respective intragranular nanoscale phases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Mechanical properties 3.3.1. Hardness and compression properties at room temperature</head><p>Room temperature Vickers hardness and compression properties of the alloys are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> and typical stress-strain curves are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">15a</ref>. The base AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr alloy has rather high hardness (Hv = 5.8 GPa), yield (σ 0.2 = 2197 MPa) and fracture stress  (σ f = 2370 MPa), but relatively low fracture strain (ε f = 4.1%). A decrease in the amount of Zr (AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 ) increases Hv to 6.2 GPa but makes the alloy brittle and fracture occurs during elastic loading at a relatively low fracture stress (σ f = 1320 MPa, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). An additional removal of Mo (AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 ) slightly improves compression ductility, but this alloy has low σ 0.2 = 1352, σ f = 1357 MPa and Hv = 5.0 GPa. A decrease in the amount of Al in Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr RHEA slightly decreases the compression ductility (ε f = 3.2%) but noticeably increases σ 0.2 (= 2350 MPa), σ f (= 2460 MPa) and Hv (=6.4 GPa) relative to the base alloy. Finally, Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr, which has even lower Al and completely replaced Mo with Ta, drops σ 0.2 to 1745 MPa, σ f to 1830 MPa and Hv to 4.9 GPa, while having ε f = 3.8%.</p><p>The Young's modulus E is highest (≈132-133 GPa) for AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 and Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr RHEAs. These are about 10 GPa higher than the Young's modulus of the base, AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr, alloy. Alloys without Mo (AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 and Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr) have reduced Young's moduli of 124 GPa and 118 GPa, respectively (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</p><p>These results indicate that Al and Zr reductions strengthen the alloys while Mo reductions soften the alloys considerably. Therefore, the room temperature strength of the base alloy can be improved by increasing the amount of Mo and/or by decreasing the amount of Al. The results also show that a decrease in Zr makes the alloy more brittle. This simple analysis does not address the influence of compositional changes on microstructure, which will be considered in the Discussion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.2.">Compression properties at 1000</head><p>°C During compression deformation at 1000 °C all five RHEAs had good ductility and showed no evidence of fracture when deformation stopped upon reaching a compression strain of 55%. Typical engineering stress vs. engineering strain curves for these alloys are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">15b</ref> and the characteristic properties are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref>. After plastic yielding, all the alloys show a rapid stress increase to a peak value (σ p ) followed by a flow softening stage. This flow softening stage switched to a steady-state stage with a nearly constant flow stress in the  AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 alloys, or replaced by a hardening stage in the AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 alloy, or continued up to about 30% compression strain in the Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr alloys (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">15b</ref>). A stress increase after ~30% compression strain, observed in all samples, was due to friction between the contact surfaces of the specimens and the dies.</p><p>The AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 RHEA (with a reduced amount of Zr) was the strongest one at 1000 °C, having σ 0.2 = 935 MPa and σ p = 1019 MPa. This alloy also showed a steady-state flow, with the steadystate flow stress of ~910 MPa. These stress values are noticeably higher than those shown by the base alloy. Additional removal of Mo resulted in a significant decrease in σ 0.2 to 535 MPa and σ p to 542 MPa in the AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 RHEA. The Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr alloy (with a reduced amount of Al) has σ 0.2 = 579 MPa and σ p = 646 MPa. The Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr RHEA, which has even less Al and no Mo, shows the smallest strength at 1000 °C: σ 0.2 = 366 MPa, σ p = 408 MPa. After reaching the peak stress at ε p ≈ 1.6-2.0% these two alloys started losing strength continuously, and after 20% compression strain they had a flow stress σ 20 = 312 MPa and 162 MPa, respectively. It can be clearly seen that Mo has a strong strengthening effect in these RCCAs. The presence of Al is likely also beneficial for the high-temperature strength, while Zr has an opposite effect.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.3.">Microstructure after compression deformation at 1000</head><p>°C After 55% compression deformation at 1000 °C, grains retained nearequiaxed shapes and their average size was almost the same as before deformation (Figs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>. Characteristic electron channeling contrast features in the form of bands, spots and/or protrusions were found on the BSE images of many deformed grains (e.g. Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">17a,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">18a,</ref><ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">19a</ref>). These channeling contrast features reveal the presence of internal stresses and local rotations of the crystal lattice inside the deformed grains <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>. The matrix grains in alloys with reduced Zr retain their single-phase B2 structure (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">16b</ref>). A few former GB precipitates in the AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 alloy are located inside the grains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">16a</ref>), which could indicate a high mobility of grain boundaries and their unpinning from GB particles during deformation at 1000 °C. Submicron-sized, dynamically recrystallized grains are present at the boundaries of deformed grains in the AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 alloy (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">17b</ref>). Dynamic recrystallization broke up a continuous layer of the Al-Zr rich phase observed at grain boundaries before deformation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7b</ref>). After deformation, this secondary phase is present in the form of fine, individual particles mixed with the recrystallized grains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_19">17b</ref>).</p><p>The alloys with reduced Al (Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr) retained their two-phase nano-structure inside grains (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">18</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">19</ref>). However, in both the alloys the nano-scale precipitates coarsened during deformation and the BCC phase (bright in the BSE images) became continuous, while formerly continuous B2 channels broke into separate elongated particles (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">18d</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">19c</ref>). No noticeable coarsening of the needle-like features common to the annealed Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr alloy (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9</ref>) occurred during deformation at 1000 °C, they became hardly visible on the low-magnification images (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">18a</ref>) but could be identified at high magnifications as long chains of elongated B2 particles covered by a layer of the BCC phase (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">18c</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.1.">Alloys with a reduced amount of Zr</head><p>The results of this work show that a ½ decrease in the molar ratio of Zr relative to the base alloy does not remove the hexagonal GB phase from the RHEA microstructure. Moreover, the average particle size and the volume fraction of this phase are not affected. However, the nano-scale disordered BCC precipitates disappear and the matrix grains have an ordered single-phase B2 crystal structure. The B2 phase has a composition close to the overall composition of the modified alloy (AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 ). The fully ordered state explains the lack of ductility of this alloy at room temperature and the highest plastic flow stress among the studied alloys at 1000 °C (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">15</ref>).</p><p>When Mo is additionally removed (AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 ), the coarse GB particles disappear and are replaced by a thin, continuous GB layer of  the ordered hexagonal phase. This Mo-free alloy is essentially a singlephase ordered B2 crystal structure. Mo is present in the hexagonal GB phase in a very small amount and removing this element from the alloy was not expected to affect the nature of the GB phase. Mo may facilitate formation of the GB particles by restricting solubility of Al in the matrix phase. When Mo is removed, the solubility of Al in the B2 phase may increase, leaving no extra Al to form the coarse (Al, Zr)-rich GB particles. However, the amount of Al in AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 alloy probably still exceeds the maximum solubility, which results in the formation of a thin, Al-Zr-rich layer at grain boundaries. The removal of Mo slightly improves ductility of this alloy (relative to the completely brittle AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 ) at room temperature, which may indicate that the coarse GB particles do deteriorate RT ductility. The removal of Mo also considerably decreases the plastic flow stress at 1000 °C, indicating that Mo is a strong solid solution strengthening element in this alloy system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.2.">Alloys with a reduced amount of Al</head><p>Reducing the amount of Al in Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr RHEAs is much more effective for removing the ordered hexagonal GB phase. This phase is absent in both of the Al-lean alloys, supporting our earlier suggestion that excessive Al is likely responsible for the formation of this GB phase. Similar to the base alloy, those with the reduced Al consist of two coherent phases: an ordered (Al and Zr rich) B2 matrix and a disordered (Nb, and Ta rich) BCC phase with spherical (in Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr) or cuboidal (in Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr) nano-scale morphologies. Additionally, Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr RHEA contains needle-like features that are evenly distributed in the alloy. These features consist of coarser BCC lamellae nucleated on Zr-rich bristles. This indicates that reducing Al in Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr produces Zr supersaturation and forms Zr-rich bristles in a BCC solid solution phase present at high temperatures. These bristles become nucleation sites for a lower-temperature, Mo-Nb-Ta-rich BCC phase leading to local coarsening relative to homogeneously nucleated nano-scale particles in other regions. After substituting Mo with Ta and an additional Al decrease in the Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr RHEA, Zr-rich bristles do not form and the needle-like features disappear. This RHEA has the most homogeneous and refined microstructure among the five studied alloys. This suggests that Mo reduces the solubility of not only Al but also Zr in the hightemperature BCC phase. Both the Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr RHEAs have high strength and some ductility at room temperature, although substitution of Mo with Ta decreases the RT strength by ~600 MPa and the 1000 °C strength by ~150-200 MPa. The most dramatic effect from decreasing the amount of Al (and Mo removal) is observed during compression testing at 1000 °C. These alloys soften continuously after reaching the peak stress at the beginning of plastic deformation, and the flow stress drops by ~50% after 20% plastic strain. The flow softening is likely due to coarsening and coalescence of the BCC nano-scale particles (compare Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">18</ref> with Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">19</ref> with Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">12</ref>). As a result, these BCC nano-particles transform to a continuous matrix phase, while the formerly continuous channels of the ordered B2 phase fragment and become embedded inside the BCC  matrix (see Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">18d</ref> and<ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">19c</ref>). Eventually, the microstructure containing the continuous disordered BCC matrix is softer and more ductile than that with continuous ordered B2 matrix phase.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.3.">The mechanism of formation of nanometer-scaled B2/BCC microstructure</head><p>The mechanism of formation of the coherent, two-phase nanoscaled microstructure inside the matrix grains of this refractory alloy system has not been well understood <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref>. Results of the present work suggest that Zr is somehow responsible for the formation of this two-phase nano-structure. Decreasing the concentration of this element suppresses the phase separation resulting in an ordered singlephase B2 crystal structure. On the other hand, Al does not seem to play important role in the phase separation, although its presence is likely responsible for the formation of the ordered B2 phase <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24]</ref>.</p><p>The refractory elements Mo, Nb and Ta are completely miscible in both liquid and solid states, and in the solid state they form continuous BCC solid solutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>. Ti also forms continuous BCC solid solutions with these three refractory elements at high temperatures, but a twophase range, BCC + HCP, can be present below 880 °C with the refractory elements suppressing the HCP solvus temperature. In the Ti-Zr system, a continuous BCC solid solution region is present at high temperatures and an HCP solid solution region is present at lower temperatures. Zr forms continuous BCC solid solutions with Nb and Ta at high temperatures. At lower temperatures, a two-phase, BCC + HCP region is present at the concentrations of Nb and Ta below 19% and. 6.5%, respectively. At higher Nb and Ta concentrations, i.e. 19-92.2% Nb or 6.5-91% Ta, a miscibility gap is present in the temperature range of 620-977 °C in Nb-Zr or 800-1760 °C in Ta-Zr systems, where the high-temperature BCC phase separates in two BCC phases, one of which is rich with Nb or Ta and another with Zr <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>. Finally, both Nb-Zr and Ta-Zr experience eutectoid reactions (at 620 °C or 800 °C, respectively) during which the Zr-rich BCC phase transforms to Zr-rich HCP and Nb-or Ta-rich BCC phases. In the Mo-Zr system, Zr has the maximum solubility of ~10% in BCC-Mo and Mo has a maximum solubility of ~41% in BCC-Zr. Beyond these solubility limits, a Laves Mo 2 Zr phase forms, while Zr-rich alloys also experience an eutectoid transformation BCC → HCP + Laves at 738 °C <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>.</p><p>Al forms numerous binary intermetallic compounds with all the elements in the studied alloy systems; however, none of these binary compounds has an ordered B2 crystal structure. B2 ordering has, however, been observed in ternary or higher order Al-Ti-X and Al-Zr-X systems, where X is Mo, Nb, Ta or the combination of these elements <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>.</p><p>Using this information on phase relationships, it is suggested that Nb, Ta and Zr are responsible for the formation of the two-phase, nano-scale microstructure inside the matrix grains. The matrix grains represent a high-temperature BCC phase, which, during cooling, separates into two BCC phases due to the presence of the miscibility gap. One phase is rich in Nb and Ta and another phase is rich in Zr. Ti seems to be neutral in this reaction and is distributed almost evenly between these two phases. Mo prefers the Nb and Ta rich phase due to its complete solubility with these elements. On the other hand, Al prefers the Zr-rich BCC phase due to a higher solubility and the highest negative enthalpy of mixing between Al and Zr, relative to those with other alloying elements <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>. The presence of Nb and Ta in the Al-Zr rich BCC phase allows the disorder-order transformation (BCC → B2) during cooling, without formation of other Al-containing phases. It is likely that a decrease in the amount of Al in the Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr RHEAs decreases the disorder-order transformation temperature below 1000 °C, which explains the reduced strength and noticeable deformation softening in these Al lean alloys during deformation at 1000 °C. A decrease in the amount of Zr moves the alloy composition outside the miscibility gap and the Zr-rich BCC phase does not form. In this case, the interaction of Al with other elements in the hightemperature BCC phase results in ordering and complete transformation of this phase in the ordered B2 phase upon cooling. It is likely that ordering in this case occurs at temperatures above 1000 °C, because these Zr-lean alloys show high strength, no softening and no evidence of the phase transformations during deformation at 1000 °C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.4.">Mechanical properties</head><p>Single-phase B2 RHEAs show the highest (AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 ) and next-to-lowest (AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 ) yield strengths at 1000C, suggesting that this phase can be intrinsically strong at high temperatures, and that solid solution hardening (Mo-induced in this case) plays a significant role. However, these are the most brittle alloys and show essentially no plastic deformation in room temperature compression. The B2 phase typically deforms either by ½ 〈111〉 or by 〈100〉 dislocations. The former provides 5 independent strains needed for plasticity in polycrystalline materials and the latter do not. The present results suggest that the B2 phase studied here may deform by 〈100〉 dislocations at room temperature. However, some B2 compounds that deform by ½ 〈111〉 slip can still be brittle <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref>, and so TEM studies are required to determine which type of dislocations operate in these RHEAs.  The two-phase intragranular microstructure in the base AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr RHEA and in the Al-lean alloys Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr and Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr can be thought of as analogous to the γ/γ′ microstructure in superalloys. In those microstructures, a relatively soft and ductile disordered FCC continuous phase (γ) surrounds nanometer-sized, coherent precipitates of the ordered FCC Ni 3 Al intermetallic phase. It might therefore be expected that the BCC/B2 (or β/β′) microstructures in these three alloys may have potential to provide a balance of strength and ductility. Supporting this view, these alloys have the highest compressive strengths at room temperature and the base alloy is the second strongest at 1000 °C. However, the present microstructures are reversed from the γ/γ′ stereotypethe strong but brittle B2 phase is continuous and the disordered BCC precipitates are discontinuous. This may explain the poor room temperature ductility of these alloys. The BCC phase does become continuous during deformation at 1000 °C. This transition is accompanied by extensive compressive ductility and a continuous drop in flow stress, which could result from the rather high volume fraction of the BCC phase (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">18d</ref>). These results also indicate that the low ductility B2/BCC structure can be transformed in a more ductile BCC/B2 structure by extensive hot working, such as forging and/or rolling. The concept of designing a BCC/B2 analog to the γ/γ′ microstructure of superalloys thus requires further study to provide a balance of room temperature ductility and high temperature strength.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Summary and conclusions</head><p>Compositional adjustments of the base AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr refractory high entropy superalloy were made to improve mechanical properties  Analysis of available phase diagrams suggests that Nb, Ta and Zr are likely responsible for the decomposition of a high-temperature BCC phase in two BCC phases during cooling due to a miscibility gap in the studied alloy system. When the amount of Zr is reduced, the alloy composition is moved outside the miscibility gap and no phase separation occurs. Strong interaction of Al with Zr in the presence Nb and Ta is likely responsible for the BCC → B2 ordering of a Zr-rich phase upon cooling.</p><p>The ordered intermetallic B2 phase is strong when Mo is present, but is brittle at room temperature causing brittleness or low ductility of the studied RHEAs. In the two-phase B2/BCC RHEAs the disordered BCC phase becomes continuous during deformation at 1000 °C, and this transformation is accompanied by extensive compressive ductility and a progressive drop in flow stress. It is suggested that the transformed microstructure consisting of the disordered BCC matrix and ordered B2 nanometer-sized precipitates would have room temperature ductility sufficient for engineering applications. Additional work is suggested to engineer two-phase BCC/B2 microstructures with a balance of room temperature tensile ductility and high temperature strength.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. X-ray diffraction patterns of (a) AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 , (b) AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 , (c) Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr, and (d) Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>3. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Microstructure of the annealed alloys 3.2.1. AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. STEM-HAADF images of the nano-phase structure present inside the grains of AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr. (a) Cuboidal and plate-like precipitates of a disordered BCC phase are separated by continuous channels of an ordered B2 phase. (b) The fast Fourier transforms (shown inside the red squares) reveal an ordered B2 structure for the dark channels and a disordered A2 (BCC) structure for the cuboidal precipitates.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,116.90,517.89,370.42,191.06" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr: (a) Low-magnification SEM BSE micrograph showing grains, a subgrain structure inside the grains and dark intermetallic particles at grain boundaries. (b) High magnification BSE image revealing a two-phase, basket-weave nano-lamellar structure inside the grains.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,116.90,53.18,370.42,171.21" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>3. 2 . 4 .</head><label>24</label><figDesc>Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 : (a) Low-magnification BSE micrograph showing grains and dark intermetallic particles at grain boundaries. (b) High magnification BSE image revealing a single-phase structure inside the grains.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,108.11,53.18,370.42,147.74" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 : STEM-HAADF image acquired along the [001] zone axis of the intragranular B2 phase bordering an ordered intermetallic GB particle. The selected area diffraction pattern (SADP) shown in the insert was taken from the area indicated by the arrow.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,38.72,459.35,241.26,239.83" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. SEM BSE micrographs of AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 showing (a) equiaxed grain structure and (b) a secondary phase present at grain boundaries.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,117.07,579.52,370.07,146.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Super-X™ XEDS compositional maps acquired at the boundary between the intermetallic precipitate and the intragranular phase in annealed AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 .</figDesc><graphic coords="6,117.01,53.18,370.22,243.89" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. BSE images of Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr showing (a) equiaxed grains with needle-like precipitates inside the grains, (b) eutectic-like microstructure at grain/subgrain boundaries, (c) nanoscale interpenetrating two phase microstructure and a low-angle boundary, and (d) a needle-like particle.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,108.28,426.22,370.07,291.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. STEM-HAADF micrograph of grain boundary precipitates between two B2 phase regions with associated SADP taken from the area indicated by the arrow (HAADF) and super-X™ XEDS compositional maps acquired across a high angle grain boundary in annealed AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 .</figDesc><graphic coords="7,108.23,53.18,370.22,243.21" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. XEDS compositional maps acquired at a lamellar precipitate surrounded by a two phase nanoscale microstructure in Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,116.79,481.66,370.55,244.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. STEM-HAADF micrographs of the Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr alloy showing the two phase nanoscale microstructure along with (a) a coalesced precipitate and (b) an inset SADP acquired from the two phase region.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,117.07,53.18,370.07,189.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Fig. 13. STEM-HAADF micrograph of Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr showing a nanoscale two phase microstructure.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,45.07,490.39,228.30,227.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. BSE images of Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr showing (a) equiaxed grains and low-angle grain boundaries inside the grains and (b) a two phase interpenetrating nanoscale microstructure inside the grains and coarser particles at a subgrain boundary.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,108.23,53.18,370.22,146.67" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Fig. 15 .</head><label>15</label><figDesc>Fig. 15. Engineering stress vs. engineering strain curves obtained during (a) room temperature (T = 25 °C) and (b) elevated temperature (T = 1000 °C) compression testing of AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr (alloy #1), AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 (#2), AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 (#3), Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr (#4) and Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr (#5).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Fig. 14. TEM (a) BF and (b) DF images of a nano-phase structure of Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr acquired with the transmitted and (100) superlattice reflection, respectively, as indicated by the circles in the SADP insets.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,116.90,53.18,370.42,189.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Fig. 16 .</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Fig. 16. Microstructure of AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 after 55% compression at 1000 °C.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,108.28,577.76,370.07,148.31" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 18 .</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Fig. 18. Microstructure of Al 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr after 55% compression at 1000 °C: (a) Equiaxed grain structure, (b) subgrain and nano-phase structures inside a grain, (c) needle-like features consisting of a B2 core and a BCC shell and (d) a high magnification image illustrating that the BCC phase (bright) is a matrix phase and the B2 phase is discontinuous after the compression deformation.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,117.07,408.76,370.07,300.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Fig. 17 .</head><label>17</label><figDesc>Fig. 17. Microstructure of AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5 after 55% compression at 1000 °C: (a) heavily deformed grains and (b) dynamically recrystallized grains and second-phase particles (dark) at a grain boundary.</figDesc><graphic coords="12,120.47,53.18,363.19,145.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="13,108.28,53.18,370.07,298.77" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Lattice parameters of the BCC phase, a, alloy density, ρ (measured vs. calculated), Vickers micro-hardness, Hv, and room temperature compression properties (Young's modulus, E, yield stress, σ 0.2 , fracture stress, σ f , and fracture strain, ε f ) of the studied RHEAs.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Alloy no.</cell><cell>Alloy ID</cell><cell>a</cell><cell>ρ</cell><cell>Hv</cell><cell>E</cell><cell>σ 0.2</cell><cell>σ f</cell><cell>ε f</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>pm</cell><cell>g/cm 3</cell><cell>GPa</cell><cell>GPa</cell><cell>MPa</cell><cell>MPa</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</cell><cell>326.9/330.4</cell><cell>7.4/7.31</cell><cell>5.8 ± 0.1</cell><cell>122</cell><cell>2197</cell><cell>2370</cell><cell>4.1</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5</cell><cell>326.9</cell><cell>7.4/7.32</cell><cell>6.2 ± 0.1</cell><cell>133</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1320</cell><cell>1.0</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5</cell><cell>330.6</cell><cell>7.1/7.02</cell><cell>5.0 ± 0.1</cell><cell>124</cell><cell>1352</cell><cell>1357</cell><cell>1.3</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>A l 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</cell><cell>328.3</cell><cell>8.1/7.96</cell><cell>6.4 ± 0.1</cell><cell>132</cell><cell>2350</cell><cell>2460</cell><cell>3.2</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>A l 0.25 NbTaTiZr</cell><cell>330.0</cell><cell>9.4/9.27</cell><cell>4.9 ± 0.1</cell><cell>118</cell><cell>1745</cell><cell>1830</cell><cell>3.8</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Compression properties of the compositionally modified RHEAs at 1000 °C (Young's modulus, E, yield stress, σ 0.2 , peak stress, σ p , peak strain at peak stress, ε p , stress at 10% strain, σ 10 , and stress at 20% strain, σ 20 ).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Alloy no.</cell><cell>Alloy ID</cell><cell>E</cell><cell>σ 0.2</cell><cell>σ p</cell><cell>ε p</cell><cell>σ 10</cell><cell>σ 20</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>GPa</cell><cell>MPa</cell><cell>MPa</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>MPa</cell><cell>MPa</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr [11]</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>745</cell><cell>792</cell><cell>1.9</cell><cell>735</cell><cell>727</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5</cell><cell>76</cell><cell>935</cell><cell>1019</cell><cell>2.0</cell><cell>907</cell><cell>912</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>AlNbTa 0.5 TiZr 0.5</cell><cell>53</cell><cell>535</cell><cell>542</cell><cell>1.4</cell><cell>433</cell><cell>483</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>A l 0.5 Mo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>579</cell><cell>646</cell><cell>2.0</cell><cell>461</cell><cell>312</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>A l 0.25 NbTaTiZr</cell><cell>63</cell><cell>366</cell><cell>408</cell><cell>1.6</cell><cell>288</cell><cell>162</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>O.N. Senkov et al. / Materials and Design 139 (2018) 498-511</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>Work by <rs type="funder">ONS</rs> was supported through the <rs type="funder">Air Force</rs> on-site contract <rs type="grantNumber">FA8650-15-D-5230</rs> managed by <rs type="funder">UES, Inc.</rs>, Dayton, Ohio and through the <rs type="institution">Air Force Research Laboratory, Materials and Manufacturing Directorate, Lab Director</rs>'s funds. JKJ acknowledges the financial support of the <rs type="grantName">Dayton Area Graduate Studies Institute</rs> (<rs type="programName">DAGSI) program</rs> of the State of Ohio and the <rs type="funder">Air Force Research Laboratory</rs>, grant number <rs type="grantNumber">RX0(1)-OSU-13-4</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_qSQNGup">
					<idno type="grant-number">FA8650-15-D-5230</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_jsmUCez">
					<orgName type="grant-name">Dayton Area Graduate Studies Institute</orgName>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">DAGSI) program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_wFpKVFM">
					<idno type="grant-number">RX0(1)-OSU-13-4</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Murty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ranganathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">High Entropy Alloys</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Butterworth-Heinemann</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A critical review of high entropy alloys and related concepts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="448" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Microstructure of Al 0.25 NbTaTiZr after 55% compression at 1000 °C: (a) Equiaxed grain structure, (b) a junction of three grains, (c) nano-phase structures inside a grain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date>19</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fundamental deformation behavior in high-entropy alloys: an overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Diao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dahmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opinion Solid State Mater. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="252" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical properties of Nb 25 Mo 25 Ta 25 W 25 and V 20 Nb 20 Mo 20 Ta 20 W 20 refractory high entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and properties of a refractory NbCrMo 0.5 Ta 0.5 TiZr alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and elevated temperature properties of a refractory TaNbHfZrTi alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Meisenkothen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4062" to="4074" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase composition and solid solution strengthening in TiZrNbMoV high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Si</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="651" to="660" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and mechanical properties of Co 2 Mo x Ni 2 VW x eutectic high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="546" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of Ti additions on mechanical properties of NbMoTaW and VNbMoTaW refractory high entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical properties of lowdensity, refractory multi-principal element alloys of the Cr-Nb-Ti-V-Zr system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">565</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and properties of aluminum-containing refractory high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2030" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of aluminum on the microstructure and properties of two refractory high entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and mechanical properties of a light-weight AlNbTiV high entropy alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shaysultanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An AlNbTiVZr 0.5 high-entropy alloy combining high specific strength and good ductility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yurchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sokolovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of Al addition on mechanical properties and microstructure of refractory AlxHfNbTaTiZr alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-M</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Juan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-H</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloys Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">624</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and mechanical properties at elevated temperatures of a new Al-containing refractory high-entropy alloy Nb-Mo-Cr-Ti-Al</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kauffmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gorr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schliephake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Seemuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heilmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloys Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">661</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="206" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and mechanical properties of B2 ordered refractory AlNbTiVZrx (x = 0-1.5) high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yurchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Zherebtsov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">704</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Welk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E A</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Viswanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Characterization of the microstructure of the compositionally complex alloy AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZr</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of a refractory high entropy superalloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Isheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Seidman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pilchak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Entropy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Characterization of a High Strength, Refractory High Entropy Alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<pubPlace>Columbus, OH, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>The Ohio State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>AlMo 0.5 NbTa 0.5 TiZrPhD Dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and application of MIPAR™: a novel software package for two-and three-dimensional microstructural characterization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Welk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Integr. Mater. Manuf. Innov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Newbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Joy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Echlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Flori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Advanced Scanning Electron Microscopy and X-ray Microanalysis</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Plenum Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design of quaternary Ir-Nb-Ni-Al refractory superalloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yamabe-Mitarai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metall. Mater. Trans. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the relationship between the enthalpy of formation and the disorder parameter of intermetallic phases with the B2 structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ipser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scr. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="917" to="922" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Okamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Phase Diagrams for Binary Alloys</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Materials Park, Ohio</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ASM International</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermodynamic reassessment of the Ti-Al-Nb system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cupid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Fabrichnaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Rios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ebrahimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Seifert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Mater. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ordering scheme in N-B aluminides with the B2 crystalstructure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scr. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">617</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Materials Science International Team, Al-Ta-Zr Ternary Phase Diagram Evaluation. Phase Diagrams, Crystallographic and Thermodynamic data: Datasheet from MSI Eureka in SpringerMaterials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Lysova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://materials.springer.com/msi/literature/docs/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">sm_msi_r_10_022102_01MSI Materials Science International Services GmbH</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mixing enthalpy of liquid phase calculated by Miedema&apos;s scheme and approximated with sub-regular solution model for assessing forming ability of amorphous and glassy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Takeuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Inoue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1779" to="1789" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vedula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Feal</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fe</forename><forename type="middle">3</forename><surname>Al</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Intermetallic Compounds: Principles and Practice</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Westbrook</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fleischer</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ltd., West Sussex, England</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="209" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
