<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Ductile W0.4MoNbxTaTi refractory high-entropy alloys with excellent elevated temperature strength</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_jfGAzFg">
					<orgName type="full">International Science and Technology Cooperation Program of China</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2021-03-26">26 March 2021</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wenchao</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Material Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing University of Aeronautics and Astronautics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210016</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tao</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Material Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing University of Aeronautics and Astronautics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210016</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chunyu</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Material Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing University of Aeronautics and Astronautics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210016</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Meng</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Material Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing University of Aeronautics and Astronautics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210016</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yunpeng</forename><surname>Nie</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Material Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing University of Aeronautics and Astronautics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210016</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jun</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Material Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing University of Aeronautics and Astronautics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210016</postCode>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Ductile W0.4MoNbxTaTi refractory high-entropy alloys with excellent elevated temperature strength</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2021-03-26">26 March 2021</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D6AFD05FFB2E9BED13378A6B6922DF26</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.matlet.2021.129753</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 1 February 2021 Received in revised form 11 March 2021 Accepted 21 March 2021</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Refractory high entropy alloy Microstructure Mechanical properties Specific strength</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In order to obtain refractory alloys with both high strength and good ductility simultaneously, the novel W0.4MoNbxTaTi high entropy alloys were developed, of which the crystal structure, microstructure, and compression properties were investigated as well. The as-cast alloys had a single BCC phase structure with dendritic substructure in coarse polygon crystal grains. The alloys exhibited outstanding mechanical properties at testing temperatures. The optimal yield strength and fracture strain were 1334 MPa and 38.9% in W0.4MoNb1.3TaTi alloy at ambient temperature. Furthermore, its yield strength decreased to 1125, 905, and 425 MPa at 1073, 1273, and 1373 K, respectively. And it showed high specific yield strength at elevated temperature. The compression performances of the W0.4MoNb1.3TaTi alloy were superior in comparison with other refractory high entropy alloys.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Recently, there has been a growing interest in HEAs owing to their potential use in extremely high temperature applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. However, there is a severe limitation of refractory HEAs applications for the poor coordination of favorable strength at high temperature and good plasticity at ambient temperature <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. For instance, NbCrMo0.5Ta0.5TiZr <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, AlMo0.5NbTa0.5TiZr <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> and Al0.4Hf0.6NbTaTiZr <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> exhibit exceptional hightemperature strength but limited room-temperature ductility, while TaNbHfZrTi <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> and Ti40Al10V20Nb20Mo10 <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> possess excellent plasticity at ambient temperature but relatively low strength at elevated temperature. At present, it is a challenge for refractory HEAs to achieve good matching of strength and plasticity at room temperature (RT) while still maintaining high strength at elevated temperatures. Generally, HEAs composed of refractory elements (such as W, Mo, Nb, Ta, and Ti) have the potential for high temperature applications due to their high melting point. For example, the WNbMoTaTi with an excellent yield strength of 1455 Mpa holds potentials for applications as high temperature materials, but its plasticity is only 11.5% at RT <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. In order to improve the ductility, according to the negative effect of W and the positive effect of Nb on plasticity, measures had been taken to reduce W content and increase Nb content <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. Therefore, novel W0.4MoNbxTaTi (x = 1.1, 1.3, 1.5) refractory HEAs demon-strated excellent high-temperature strength and a good combination of distinguished strength and good ductility at RT were designed. The phase composition, microstructure, as well as mechanical properties of the alloys, are discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental procedures</head><p>The refractory HEAs with a nominal composition of W0.4MoN-bxTaTi (x = 1.1, 1.3, and 1.5 in a molar ratio, denoted as Nb1.1, Nb1.3, and Nb1.5, respectively) were prepared using vacuum arc melting. The ingots were re-melted five times to improve the chemical homogeneity. Crystal structures were measured via an X-ray diffractometer. The microstructure and chemical compositions of the resulted cast alloys were investigated by SEM and EDS. An initial strain rate of 0.001 s À1 was applied to the compressive process. Cylindrical specimens (U 4*6 mm) were tested on a universal testing machine for room temperature compression testing. For high temperature testing, the samples (U 6*9 mm) were performed on a thermal simulator at 1073, 1273, and 1373 K. The heating rate was 300 K/min and the holding time was 300 s. Density of the alloys was measured via hydrostatic weighting. The hot-compressed specimens were cut parallel to the compression direction from the cylindrical samples after high temperature compression. Microstructural observations of the hot-compressed samples were analyzed by SEM. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> illustrates information on structure of the as-cast W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys. The XRD patterns showing in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1a</ref> demonstrate that the alloys have a single phase with BCC lattice according to Bragg's equation. The position of the diffraction peak of the solid solution deviates from the one of the elements, which is caused by severe lattice distortion.</p><p>SEM images (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1b-d</ref>) manifest large grains with dendritic structures inside. The results of EDS suggest that the dendrite was enriched with W and Ta, while the interdendrite was enriched with Ti, and Nb/Mo were evenly distributed. During cooling, the high-temperature BCC phase rejected Ti into the interdendrite, resulting in (W, Ta)-rich dendrite and Ti-rich interdendrite.</p><p>The true compression stress-strain curves of the W0.4MoN-bxTaTi alloys at different temperatures are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref>. The resulting yield strength (r 0.2 ) and fracture strain (e f ) are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. The alloys showed good ductility at room temperature as fracture strain ranging from 32% to 39%. The yield strengths of the alloys were 1412 MPa (Nb1.1), 1334 MPa (Nb1.3), and 1312 MPa (Nb1.5), respectively. Prominent work hardening stages were observed after yielding. The yield stress exhibited a pronounced decrease as the testing temperature increased to 1073 K and 1273 K, which was attributed to the energy provided by the high temperature. The higher energy would promote the movement of dislocations and even grain boundaries, leading to the reduction of yield strength.</p><p>Further increase of testing temperature to 1373 K resulted in a further decrease in yield strength. the alloys still exhibited high yield strength (585 MPa for Nb1.1, 425 MPa for Nb1.3, and 503 MPa for Nb1.5) even if the testing temperature was 1373 K. After reaching the yield point, pronounced steady-state flow stages were observed on the true stress-strain curves. The poor plasticity of Nb1.5 alloys at 1073 and 1273 K may be attribu-ted to the fact that the higher Nb content in this temperature interval leads to partial segregation of Nb and the formation of precipitated phases of M-Nb at grain boundaries, which weakens the high-temperature plasticity of the alloys <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref> also demonstrates the hot-compressed microstructure of the W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys corresponding to different temperatures. As the picture shows, the cracks were initiated at the grain boundaries (GBs) and then propagated along the GBs, meanwhile, some cracks expanded into the grains. As the temperature elevated, the propagation of cracks was suppressed. During the deformation process, stress concentration occurred, which caused a sharp increase in local energy. When the stress concentration reached a certain value, crack propagation began to appear, releasing energy. As the testing temperature increases, the atomic activity and dislocation migration rate rise significantly. Therefore, the local stress concentration could be effectively alleviated, which would inhibit crack initiation and propagation.</p><p>The produced refractory alloys, Nb1.1, Nb1.3 and Nb1.5, have densities of q = 10.7, 10.6 and 10.5 g/cm3, respectively. The comparison of mechanical properties and specific yield strength (SYS) between the W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys and previously reported HEAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref> are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. For the convenience of comparison, all e f greater than 50% were represented by 50%. Fig. <ref type="figure">3a</ref> demonstrates a comparison of mechanical properties at ambient temperature. The reference HEAs can be classified into two categories: (i) high strength but brittle alloys, having yield strength (YS) &gt;1400 MPa and e f &lt; 12%; (ii) ductile but soft HEAs, possessing YS &lt; 1000 MPa and ductility of 50%. It could be found that there is a typical tradeoff between strength and plasticity in these alloys. Noticeably, the W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys (marked with a red circle) displayed high YS above 1300 MPa and good ductility with e f greater than 32%, which perfectly combined the superiorities of the aforementioned two types of HEAs. Furthermore, the mechanical properties of the W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys at elevated temperatures were even more surprising (Fig. <ref type="figure">3b-c</ref>). The level of YS revealed by the studied alloys at 1073 K and 1273 K was superior to most reference alloys; only HfMoTaTiZr and HfMoNbTaTiZr alloy were comparable to them. However, these two reported alloys have poor room-temperature ductility. Compared with the other alloys, Nb1.3 not only possessed the highest strength but also had fine compressive plasticity. Fig. <ref type="figure">3d</ref> presents the SYS of the aforementioned alloys. Excluding the SYS of soft AlNbTiV and brittle NbCrMo0.5Ta0.5TiZr at 1073 K, Nb1.3 has the highest SYS at 1073 and 1273 K among all alloys. Thus, W0.4MoNb1.3TaTi has great potential in high-temperature applications over 1073 K.</p><p>The high-strength W0.4MoNbxTaTi HEAs benefit from severe lattice distortion caused by different elements randomly occupying lattice positions. The shear stress of dislocation slip increases due to the hindrance of lattice distortion, which reveals the high yield stress of HEAs. The addition of Nb reduces the chance of mismatch, alleviating the lattice distortion. Moreover, as the Nb content increases, the number of strong bonds such as W-M and Mo-M decreases. These illustrate the decrease in strength as Nb increas-ing. Correspondingly, the plasticity of HEAs would be improved. Furthermore, the increase in Nb content can reduce the degree of element segregation, which also contributes to the high ductility of W0.4MoNbxTaTi HEAs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p>The microstructure and mechanical properties of W0.4MoN-bxTaTi (x = 1.1, 1.3, 1.5) alloys were investigated thoroughly in present paper. The as-cast alloys are composed of single BCC structures with large polygon grains containing dendritic substructure. At room temperature, the alloys possess excellent yield strengths exceeding 1312 MPa and high fracture strains above 32%. At elevated temperatures, the W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys present preeminent yield strengths as well. The compressive properties of the W0.4MoNb1.3TaTi alloy are superior to previously reported high-temperature HEAs at both room and higher temperatures, and its specific yield strength at high temperature is excellent, making it a promising candidate for high-temperature applications. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CRediT authorship contribution statement</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Declaration of Competing Interest</head><p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matlet.2021.129753 0167-577X/Ó 2021 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. ⇑ Corresponding author. E-mail address: taowang@nuaa.edu.cn (T. Wang). Materials Letters 295 (2021) 129753 Contents lists available at ScienceDirect Materials Letters j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / m l b l u e</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Structure of the W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys in as-cast conditions: (a) XRD patterns; (b-d) SEM-BSE images: (b) Nb1.1; (c) Nb1.3; (d) Nb1.5.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,97.12,442.09,397.10,296.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Wenchao Wei: Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Investigation, Writing -original draft. Tao Wang: Conceptualization, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Writing -review &amp; editing. Chunyu Wang: Formal analysis, Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. Meng Wu: Writing -review &amp; editing, Supervision, Formal analysis. Yunpeng Nie: Writing -review &amp; editing, Supervision, Resources. Jun Peng: Resources, Writing -review &amp; editing, Supervision.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. True stress-strain curves and SEM images of the W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys at different temperatures.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,68.77,67.92,453.77,260.73" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="4,97.12,67.92,397.10,325.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Compression mechanical properties of W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Alloy</cell><cell>T (K)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Nb1.1</cell><cell>293</cell><cell>1412</cell><cell>32.1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1073</cell><cell>1027</cell><cell>21.7</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1273</cell><cell>664</cell><cell>34.4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1373</cell><cell>585</cell><cell>&gt;50</cell></row><row><cell>Nb1.3</cell><cell>293</cell><cell>1334</cell><cell>38.9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1073</cell><cell>1125</cell><cell>44.7</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1273</cell><cell>905</cell><cell>37.2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1373</cell><cell>425</cell><cell>48.3</cell></row><row><cell>Nb1.5</cell><cell>293</cell><cell>1312</cell><cell>37</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1073</cell><cell>986</cell><cell>21.3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1273</cell><cell>764</cell><cell>20.6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1373</cell><cell>503</cell><cell>40.9</cell></row></table><note><p><p>r 0.2 (MPa)</p>e f (%)</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgments This work was supported by the <rs type="funder">International Science and Technology Cooperation Program of China</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">2018YFE0194100</rs>) and the <rs type="funder">Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_jfGAzFg">
					<idno type="grant-number">2018YFE0194100</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shaysultanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yurchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sokolovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">228</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Juan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">565</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Meisenkothen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4062" to="4074" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">529</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">755</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="318" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Nat. Sci. Mater. Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2030" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Luan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">712</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="380" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fus. Eng. Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Tseng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Juan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Entropy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">736</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="148" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Comparison of mechanical properties (r 0.2 vs e f ) at different temperatures and specific yield strength (SYS) between the W0.4MoNbxTaTi alloys and other HEAs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
