<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Novel BCC VNbTa refractory multi-element alloys with superior tensile properties</title>
				<funder ref="#_ms2mVjn #_brTpUbx">
					<orgName type="full">Natural Science Basic Research Plan in Shaanxi Province, China</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_UsF6a8K">
					<orgName type="full">Key Research and Development Plan of Shaanxi Province, China</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2021-08-17">17 August 2021</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zhenhua</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
							<email>hanzhenhua@xaut.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xi&apos;an University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>710048</postCode>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lingkun</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xi&apos;an University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>710048</postCode>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jungang</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Changqing Downhole Technology Company</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chuanqing Drilling Engineering Co., Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>710021</postCode>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xi&apos;an University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>710048</postCode>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gang</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<email>liugang@xaut.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xi&apos;an University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>710048</postCode>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ran</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Zhengzhou University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>450001</postCode>
									<settlement>Zhengzhou</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Guojun</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xi&apos;an University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>710048</postCode>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">School of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Xi&apos;an University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>710048</postCode>
									<settlement>Xi&apos;an</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Novel BCC VNbTa refractory multi-element alloys with superior tensile properties</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2021-08-17">17 August 2021</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">90A59CD43710B2A6304E72174F9EB315</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.msea.2021.141908</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 9 July 2021; Received in revised form 13 August 2021; Accepted 14 August 2021</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Refractory multi-element alloys High entropy alloys Tensile plasticity Microstructure</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The refractory VNbTa alloys with single body centered cubic (BCC) structure were prepared. The proceed alloy exhibited excellent combination of strength and plasticity. The underlying mechanism was related to the solid solution strengthening effect caused by large atomic size misfit of elements among Nb, Ta and V.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Refractory high entropy alloys (RHEAs) with a simple body centered cubic (BCC) structure have been widely studied in recent years because of their high strength, hardness and thermal stability <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. However, the insufficient plasticity at room temperature limits their widespread engineering applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. Therefore, great works have been made to obtain an excellent combination of strength and plasticity in RHEAs. For example, the introducing high dislocation density, the transformation and natural-mixing of composition are all the well-known means to induce plasticity of RHEAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. However, it is noted that the strength relatively decreased when the plasticity was obtained of above RHEAs. The element V is considered to be the effective alloying elements for tailoring deformation behavior of some HEAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>. The underlying mechanism is ascribed to its atomic volume, large in FCC HEAs and small in BCC HEAs, which can cause a large misfit of atomic size, resulting in severe lattice distortion in both structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. For example, VCoNi HEA with single FCC structure exhibited excellent combination of strength and ductility <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. VNbTa RHEA with single BCC structure was predicted that the screw dislocations were closely related to deformation behavior of alloy at different temperatures, which could obtain an excellent combination of strength and ductility <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. However, the macroscopic mechanical properties of VNbTa RHEA remains unclear. Therefore, in the present study, the bulk VNbTa RHEA was prepared by vacuum arc melting, the microstructure and tensile properties were investigated. The corresponding intrinsic deformation mechanism was discussed in detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental</head><p>Alloy ingots with nominal compositions of VNbTa (at. %) were prepared by vacuum arc melting of equimolar pure metals (purity&gt;99.5%, total weight = 65g) in a Ti-gettered high-purity argon atmosphere. The pure metals were melted into alloy ingot with current of 450 A. To improve the homogeneity of all constituent elements, the ingots were remelted and flipped at least eight times. The melting alloy was drop casted into a water-cooled copper mold with dimensions of 10 mm × 20 mm × 30 mm. The phase of as-cast sample was identified by Xray diffraction (XRD) with a scanning speed of 4 deg/min. The microstructure was characterized by a field emission scanning electron microscope (SEM) equipped with electron backscattered diffraction (EBSD) and energy dispersive spectroscopy (EDS) detector. The details of the EBSD measurements can be discovered in our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. The flat dog-bone-shaped samples with gauge section of 6 mm (length) × 2.5 mm (width) × 1.5 mm (thickness) were sliced from rectangular samples using electric discharge machine. The geometry of tensile specimen can be seen in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">s1</ref>. The tensile tests were conducted using a testing machine with an initial strain rate of 2.5×10 -3 s -1 at room temperature, which were repeated 3 times to obtain reproducible properties. The fracture surface of tensile samples was observed by SEM.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Microstructure characterization</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref> exhibits the EBSD inverse pole figure (IPF) of as-cast VNbTa alloy. The random growth direction and irregular shape of grains can be observed in specimen, and the average grain sizes are nearly 44.28 μm (inset of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>). The EBSD phase figure of alloy is presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>. Only BCC phase can be detected, which is in accordance with the XRD pattern (inset of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>). Moreover, the crystal lattice parameter a is 3.230 A, which was measured by XRD pattern. This is close to the theoretical value of 3.214 A, which can be calculated by rule of mixtures: a mix = ∑ n i=1 c i a i <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Obviously, the lattice parameter of alloy obeys the rule of mixtures, and all elements are randomly distributed in BCC phase. However, for present alloy, the homogeneous distribution of all elements is difficult because the composition segregation is inevitable in the casting process. The elements distribution mappings of specimen are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>. It can be seen that Nb and Ta elements are distributed homogeneously on the whole specimen compared with V, which are concentrated distribution in grain boundaries. This is because the melting point of V element is much lower than Nb and Ta element, which results in the segregation of V element during casting process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Tensile mechanical properties of VNbTa alloy at room temperature</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">2a</ref> shows the tensile engineering stress-strain curve of VNbTa alloy. The corresponding data of mechanical properties are summarized in Table <ref type="table">s1</ref> and s2. It can be seen that present alloy exhibits the average yield strength (σ ys ) of ～925 MPa, ultimate tensile strength (σ ts ) of ～ 1050 MPa and fracture elongation (ε te ) of ～26%, respectively. Fig. <ref type="figure">2b</ref> shows the tensile true stress-strain curve and the corresponding strain hardening rate (ω) -true strain curve of specimen. The alloy exhibits obvious strain hardening after yielding, and has the average strain hardening exponent of ～0.62, uniform elongation (ε ue ) of ～12%. It is obvious that the present VNbTa alloy presents an excellent combination of strength and fracture elongation compared to the traditional BCC RHEAs under tensile deformation at room temperature (as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>. The SEM image of the fractography view of the specimen after tensile deformation is exhibited in the inset of Fig. <ref type="figure">2b</ref>. It can be seen that sample exhibits typical dimple patterns, implying a ductile failure, which is consistent with the results from the stress-strain curve (Fig. <ref type="figure">2a</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p>In general speaking, the solid solution strengthening has been treated as an effective way to tailor the mechanical properties of traditional solid solution alloy. The solid solution strengthening can be induced by lattice distortion, which is closely related to the misfit of atomic size. Fig. <ref type="figure">4a</ref> and<ref type="figure">b</ref> display the atomic size mismatch parameter (δ ri ), the shear modulus mismatch parameter (δ Gi ), and the mismatch parameter (f i ) of corresponding constituent elements of VNbTa alloy, respectively. It can be seen that the δ ri and f i of V are all maximum (|δ rV |= 0.06, f V = 0.545), which can be ascribed to small atomic size of V compared with Nb and Ta. That is to say, V can cause significant misfit of atomic size and further lead to severe lattice distortion, which could eventually result in a strong solid solution strengthening effect in present alloy. Theoretically, the yield strength of solid solution alloy can be estimated as <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>: σ cal 0.2 = Δσ +σ mix 0.2 , where Δσ is the solid solution strengthening effect of alloy, which can be estimated as <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Δσ = ( ∑ Δσ 3/2 i ) 2/3</formula><p>. And σ mix 0.2 can be calculated by the rule of mixtures:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">σ mix 0.2 = ∑ n i=1 c i (σ 0.2 ) i</formula><p>, where (σ 0.2 ) i is the yield strength of constituent elements.</p><p>The σ mix 0.2 and Δσ of VNbTa alloy can be calculated to be ～240 MPa and ～751 MPa, respectively. It can be seen that the Δσ of VNbTa alloy is higher than most of reported alloys (Fig. <ref type="figure">4c</ref>). That is to say, the solid solution strengthening plays a key role on strengthening VNbTa alloy.</p><p>The σ cal 0.2 is estimated to be 991 MPa, which is slightly higher than σ exp 0.2 (925 MPa). This is related to the defects and elements segregation during casting, which can also be observed in other RHEAs (Fig. <ref type="figure">4d</ref>). In addition, the severe lattice distortion can also result an obvious elastic interaction between the local stress field of solute atoms and dislocations, which leads to the changes of deformation behavior of alloy <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>As previous report, the cross-kinks dominated screw dislocations movement, and the strength characteristic at room temperature was screw dislocations self-pinning in presented VNbTa alloy <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusions</head><p>In summary, the room temperature tensile properties of refractory VNbTa alloy with BCC single phase has been studied. And the results showed an excellent combination of strength and plasticity of present alloy, which can be attributed to the solid solution strengthening effect caused by lattice distortion. Calculation results revealed that atomic size misfit among constituent elements was responsible for the severe lattice distortion of VNbTa alloy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CRediT authorship contribution statement</head><p>Zhenhua Han: designed the study and wrote the manuscript. Lingkun Meng: performed the mechanical testing and EBSD experiments. Jun Yang: Formal analysis. Gang Liu: contributed to prepare the alloys. Jungang Yang: Formal analysis. Ran Wei: conducted SEM experiments. Guojun Zhang: Formal analysis. All the authors contributed to discussion of the results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Declaration of competing interest</head><p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. (a) Tensile engineering stress-strain curve of as-cast VNbTa alloy at room temperature. Making the scale lines along the gage lengths of sample, using the variation of the distance between the scale lines to calculate the engineering strain. The details of the plastic strain measurements can be discovered in our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>; (b) the corresponding true stress-strain curve and strain hardening rate-true strain curve (the inset shows SEM image of fracture surface). </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. (a) EBSD inverse pole figure (the inset shows grain size distribution), (b) phase figure (the inset shows XRD pattern) and (c) the corresponding compositional mapping of as-cast VNbTa alloy.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,84.36,55.40,426.53,321.26" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Strength-ductility properties of recently developed RHEAs at room temperature.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,308.58,55.39,247.97,176.26" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="4,98.65,55.40,398.02,307.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This work was supported by the <rs type="funder">Natural Science Basic Research Plan in Shaanxi Province, China</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">2021JM-327</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">2020JM-455</rs>), and <rs type="funder">Key Research and Development Plan of Shaanxi Province, China</rs> (No. <rs type="grantNumber">2018ZDXM-GY-123</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_ms2mVjn">
					<idno type="grant-number">2021JM-327</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_brTpUbx">
					<idno type="grant-number">2020JM-455</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_UsF6a8K">
					<idno type="grant-number">2018ZDXM-GY-123</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A. Supplementary data</head><p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.msea.2021.141908. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Raabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Ritchie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="515" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Refractory highentropy alloys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1758" to="1765" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Intermetallics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">-high strainrate strengthening in ductile refractory high entropy alloys upon dynamic loading</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">106699</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<pubPlace>Ultra</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phasetransformation ductilization of brittle high-entropy alloys via metastability engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>An</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1701678</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical properties of Nb25Mo25Ta25W25 and V20Nb20Mo20Ta20W20 refractory high entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A refractory Hf25Nb25Ti25Zr25 high-entropy alloy with excellent structural stability and tensile properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Si</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural-mixing guided design of refractory high-entropy alloys with ascast tensile ductility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Furuhara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Tasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1175" to="1181" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vanadium is an optimal element for strengthening in both fcc and bcc high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Maresca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Curtinet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">188</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="486" to="491" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultrastrong medium-entropy singephase alloys designed via severe lattice distortion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kwiatkowski Da Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ikeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kormann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ponge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Neugebauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Raabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1807142</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic precipitation-induced the negative strain rates sensitivity in VCoNi medium-entropy alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">290</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">129480</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross-kinks control screw dislocation strength in equiatomic bcc refractory alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Marian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">116875</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and room temperature properties of a high-entropy TaNbHfZrTi alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloys Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">509</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6043" to="6048" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elastic and plastic properties of as-cast equimolar TiHfZrTaNb high-entropy alloy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dirras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lilensten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Djemia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Laurent-Brocq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tingaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Couzinié</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Perrière</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chauveau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Guillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">654</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical properties of refractory high-entropy alloys: experiments and modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hawk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloys Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">696</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1139" to="1150" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel HfNbTaTiV high-entropy alloy of superior mechanical properties designed on the principle of maximum lattice distortion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>An</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Substitutional solution hardening</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fleischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Metall</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="1963">1963</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
