<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Precipitation-strengthened refractory Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 high entropy alloy</title>
				<funder ref="#_hZ5d3xP">
					<orgName type="full">Russian Science Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
							<email>stepanov@bsu.edu.ru</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Bulk Nanostructured Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Belgorod State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>308015</postCode>
									<settlement>Belgorod</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">Yu</forename><surname>Yurchenko</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Bulk Nanostructured Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Belgorod State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>308015</postCode>
									<settlement>Belgorod</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Panina</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Bulk Nanostructured Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Belgorod State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>308015</postCode>
									<settlement>Belgorod</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">National Science Center &quot;Kharkov Institute of Physics and Technology&quot; NAS of Ukraine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>61108</postCode>
									<settlement>Kharkov</settlement>
									<country key="UA">Ukraine</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Zherebtsov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Bulk Nanostructured Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Belgorod State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>308015</postCode>
									<settlement>Belgorod</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">N.D. Stepanov) Laboratory of Bulk Nanostructured Materials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Belgorod State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Pobeda 85</addrLine>
									<postCode>308015</postCode>
									<settlement>Belgorod</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Precipitation-strengthened refractory Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 high entropy alloy</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">EF32FA45C6AFD345A70A364835297922</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.matlet.2016.11.030</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received date: 19 September 2016 Revised date: 26 October 2016 Accepted date: 8 November 2016</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Materials Letters High entropy alloy</term>
					<term>metals and alloys</term>
					<term>cast</term>
					<term>crystal structure</term>
					<term>mechanical properties</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Structure and mechanical properties of a new Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 high entropy alloy in the as-cast and annealed at 1200°C for 24 hours conditions are reported. In the as-cast condition the alloy has single body-centered cubic (bcc) phase structure. After annealing relatively fine and homogeneously distributed particles of Laves phase form in the bcc matrix. The precipitation of the second phase particles is accompanied by an increase in the yield strength and decrease in ductility determined in compression at room temperature. With increase of the testing temperature to 1000°C, the strength of the alloy decreases and ductility increases. The experimental phase composition of the alloy is compared with predicted equilibrium phases and possible ways to tailor the structure of the alloy to increase the mechanical properties further are discussed.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The so-called high-entropy alloys (HEAs), usually defined as alloys composed of multiple (≥5) principle elements with concentrations close to equiatomic (5-35 at.%), have attracted considerable attention in recent years particularly due to their encouraging mechanical properties <ref type="bibr">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. Earlier efforts in the alloy development were mostly focused on obtaining a single solid solution phase structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. However, it was suggested that the HEAs for high-performance structural applications require strengthening by second phases <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. Based on a Co-Cr-Fe-Ni-Mn system, several precipitation-strengthened HEAs with high mechanical properties were developed <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. Another an attractive class of HEAs is the refractory element based alloys which can be used at elevated temperatures <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. A lot of the refractory HEAs contain second phases and demonstrate high strength at elevated temperatures; however, most of these alloys have limited ductility at ambient temperature <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. A balanced combination of properties can be achieved in those alloys, where the second phase particles can be precipitated in a controlled way in an initially single phase structure. Although such possibility has been predicted by CALPHAD (CALculation of PHAse Diagrams) calculations in some alloys <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>, it has never been realized experimentally. Here we report structure and properties of a novel precipitationstrengthened Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 high entropy alloy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and methods</head><p>The alloy with a nominal composition of Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 (the subscripts indicate atomic fractions) was produced by arc melting of the high-purity (≥99.9 at.%) elements in an argon atmosphere inside a water-cooled copper cavity. The produced ingot with dimensions of 6×12×40mm 3 was re-melted 5 times. The actual chemical composition of the alloy is given in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. The cast alloy was annealed at 1200°C for 24 hours in vacuum and cooled down on air. The structure and properties of the Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 alloy were studied in the as-cast and annealed conditions. Samples for the structural investigations via x-ray diffraction (XRD) analysis and scanning electron microscopy (SEM) were prepared by mechanical polishing. The XRD analysis was performed using a RIGAKU diffractometer and Cu Kα radiation. SEM investigations were carried out on a Quanta 600 FEG microscope equipped with energydispersive (EDS) detector used for chemical composition measurements. The density of the alloy was measured via hydrostatic weighting. Compressive tests were performed rectangular specimens with dimensions of 6×4×4mm 3 on an Instron 300LX machine equipped with a radial furnace. The initial strain rate was 10 -4 s -1 and the temperatures were 22°C, 600°C, 800°C and 1000°C. For high-temperature testing, only the annealed specimens were used. The specimens were placed in the preheated furnace and held for 10 minutes before testing. The testing was performed until reaching a height reduction of 50%. CALPHAD modeling of the equilibrium phase diagram was conducted using Thermo-Calc (version 5) software employing TTTI3 (titanium alloys) database.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>The structure of the Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 alloy is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The XRD data for the as-cast condition (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>) suggests single body-centered cubic (bcc) phase structure in the alloy that is confirmed by the SEM observations (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>). Inside the bcc grains with size of ~100-300µm, dendritic segregations are observed; however, deviations from actual composition of the alloy are insignificant (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). After annealing at 1200°C for 24 hours, XRD detects the presence of a second phase (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>) identified as a hexagonal close packed (hcp) C14 Laves phase. The C14 Laves phase was already observed in an Al-Cr-Nb-Ti-V-Zr HEA system <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. SEM image (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>) shows that the Laves phase precipitates are mostly located inside the bcc grains as homogeneously distributed rectangular particles with an average length and width of 8 and 5µm, respectively, and the volume fraction of 5%. Some individual Laves phase particles are found on bcc grain boundaries. Note that thin continuous layer of a second phase observed in grain boundaries is, most probably, the same Laves phase. Chemical analysis (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>) demonstrates that the Laves phase particles are composed mostly of Cr, Nb, and Ti. The as-cast alloy has the yield strength of 1240 MPa and a pronounced strain hardening capacity, which results in a good ductilitythe alloy survives 50% reduction without any signs of fracture. Annealing at 1200°C for 24 hours significantly affects the room temperature compression behavior of the Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 alloy (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>); the yield strength reaches 1340MPa, but the alloy becomes less ductile and fractures after 18.5% height reduction. At 600°C, the annealed alloy demonstrates yield strength of 930 MPa and ductility ~30%. Taking into account the measured density of the alloy (5.76g/cm 3 ), the specific strength of the annealed alloy is 233 kPam 3 kg -1 at room temperature and 163 kPam 3 kg -1 at 600°C. At higher temperatures of 800 and 1000°C the alloy softens considerablythe respective values of the yield strength are 445MPa and 90MPa. It becomes very ductile and can be compressed to 50% reduction without fracture. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3</ref> demonstrates the simulated equilibrium phase diagram of the Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 alloy. The diagram suggests that the alloy solidifies through a single bcc phase; the solidus temperature is 1558°C. A Laves phase precipitates at temperatures 1146°C. Its volume fraction increases with a decrease in temperature. Finally, at T&lt;700°C, a Ti 3 Al phase appear. The predictions correlate with the experimental findings (like the single bcc structure in the as-solidified condition (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref> and<ref type="figure">b</ref>)) nicely. The comparison of the simulated phase diagram and the structure of the alloy annealed at 1200°C suggests that the Laves phase observed after annealing (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref> and<ref type="figure">c</ref>) has precipitated during cooling from the annealing temperature. Nevertheless, note that the thermodynamic predictions usually do not provide quantitatively accurate results in the case of HEAs due to the limitations of the existing databases <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. The presented data shows that the annealing at 1200°C has a pronounced effect on the structure and mechanical properties of the as-cast Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 alloy. Namely, it precipitates the relatively fine Laves phase particles (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>) which are likely to impede the dislocation motion in the bcc matrix of the alloy and thus increases strength (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>). However, the alloy becomes less ductile, probably, due to the presence of the second phase on the bcc grain boundaries. According to simulate phase diagram (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">3</ref>) the alloy can be heat treated in the single-phase field (homogenization; the annealing temperature and cooling conditions required to obtain the single phase structure after cooling are yet to be identified) and then annealed in two-phase field ("aging") to precipitate Laves phase particles. A high ductility of the alloy in the singe phase (ascast or homogenized) condition suggests that it can be cold-worked, thus providing additional nucleation sites for precipitates. By changing process parameterscold working strain, annealing temperature, duration, cooling condition etc, it seems possible to vary the parameters of the produced structure, including bcc grain size, fraction, morphology and dimensions of Laves precipitates and to modify the mechanical properties of the alloy in a wide range.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>In this work, structure and mechanical properties of the Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 high entropy alloy were examined. In the initially (in as-cast condition) single bcc phase alloy relatively fine, homogeneously distributed C14 Laves phase particles precipitate as a result of annealing at 1200°C for 24 hours. The precipitation of Laves phase particle increased room temperature compression yield strength of the alloy from 1240 MPa to 1340 MPa, but at a cost of a reduced ductility. The yield strength of the annealed alloy decreases to 910, 445 and 90 MPa with an increase in testing temperature to 600, 800 and 1000°C, respectively. Reasonable correlation between the experimental phase composition of the alloy and the predicted equilibrium phase diagram was established. Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. Chemical composition of the structural constituents of the Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 alloy determined using SEM-EDS. The corresponding constituents are identified with numbers in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref> and<ref type="figure">c</ref>      </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Structure of the Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 alloy in the as-cast (a, b) and 1200°C annealed (a, c) conditions: a -XRD patterns; b, c -SEM-BSE images. Fig. 2. Compression stress-strain curves of the Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 alloy in the as-cast condition (black line) and after annealing at 1200°C for 24 hours (colored lines). Fig. 3. Simulated equilibrium phase diagram of the Al 0.5 CrNbTi 2 V 0.5 alloy.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,95.00,53.26,406.22,713.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>5 9. 0 Highlights</head><label>0</label><figDesc>Fig. 1a</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 1b</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 1b</figDesc><graphic coords="6,85.05,407.19,226.85,208.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 1c</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 1c</figDesc><graphic coords="6,95.00,53.26,406.22,713.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2</figDesc><graphic coords="7,95.00,53.26,406.22,713.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3</figDesc><graphic coords="7,85.05,510.30,226.85,183.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>.</figDesc><table><row><cell>№</cell><cell>Constituents designation</cell><cell>Al</cell><cell>Element, at.% Cr Nb Ti</cell><cell>V</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">As-cast</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 Bright areas</cell><cell cols="3">11.9 18.4 22.1 38.8 8.8</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2 Dark areas</cell><cell cols="3">11.3 20.8 18.2 40.6 9.1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Annealing at 1200°C for 24 hours</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 Matrix</cell><cell cols="3">12.3 18.4 20.0 40.1 8.9</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2 Particles (C14 Laves)</cell><cell cols="3">3.3 48.8 20.3 18.3 9.3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Alloy composition</cell><cell cols="2">11.7 19.6 20.2 39.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors acknowledge the support from the <rs type="funder">Russian Science Foundation</rs> (Grant <rs type="grantNumber">14-19-01104</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_hZ5d3xP">
					<idno type="grant-number">14-19-01104</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructures and Properties of High-entropy Alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dahmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Mater. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-entropy alloys: a critical assessment of their founding principles and future prospects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pickering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. Mater. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fracture-resistant high-entropy alloy for cryogenic applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gludovatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hohenwarter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Catoor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Ritchie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">345</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1153" to="1158" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploration and development of high entropy alloys for structural applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Uchic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tiley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Entropy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="494" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerated exploration of multiprincipal element alloys with solid solution phases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6529</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A precipitation-hardened high-entropy alloy with outstanding tensile properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>An</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of carbon content and annealing on structure and hardness of the CoCrFeNiMn-based high entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yurchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloys Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">687</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical properties of Nb25Mo25Ta25W25 and V20Nb20Mo20Ta20W20 refractory high entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanical properties of lowdensity, refractory multi-principal element alloys of the Cr-Nb-Ti-V-Zr system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Sci. Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">565</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and properties of aluminumcontaining refractory high-entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2030" to="2042" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and mechanical properties of the AlCrxNbTiV (x= 0, 0.5, 1, 1.5) high entropy alloys</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Yurchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Skibin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloys Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">652</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An AlNbTiVZr0.5 high-entropy alloy combining high specific strength and good ductility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yurchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sokolovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="139" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low-density, refractory multiprincipal element alloys of the Cr-Nb-Ti-V-Zr system: Microstructure and phase analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1545" to="1557" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructure and mechanical properties of a refractory HfNbTiVSi0.5 high-entropy alloy composite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Effect of Al content on structure and mechanical properties of the Al x CrNbTiVZr</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Yurchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Shaysultanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tikhonovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Salishchev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>x = 0; 0.25</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Charact</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
