<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Precipitation strengthening in a hot-worked TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 refractory high entropy alloy</title>
				<funder ref="#_Y2GrhCC">
					<orgName type="full">National Natural Science Foundation of China</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_X6cWp9X">
					<orgName type="full">Special Funds for Future Industrial Development of Shenzhen, China</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_B4zzZCs">
					<orgName type="full">Project of Innovation for Postgraduate of Hunan Province</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2019-03-19">19 March 2019</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yuankui</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Lab of Powder Metallurgy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central South University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410083</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yong</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<email>yonliu@csu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Lab of Powder Metallurgy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central South University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410083</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yunping</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bin</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<email>binliu@csu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Lab of Powder Metallurgy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central South University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410083</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jiawen</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Lab of Powder Metallurgy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central South University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410083</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Meng</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Lab of Powder Metallurgy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central South University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410083</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ruiping</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Lab of Powder Metallurgy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central South University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>410083</postCode>
									<settlement>Changsha</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">YuanMeng Precision Technology (Shenzhen) Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518055</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Precipitation strengthening in a hot-worked TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 refractory high entropy alloy</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2019-03-19">19 March 2019</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">CC4E34959050A1B5A0A950D91F8AFF99</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.matlet.2019.03.075</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 27 February 2019 Received in revised form 17 March 2019 Accepted 18 March 2019</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Metals and alloys High entropy alloys Hot forging Phase transformation Mechanical property</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>A TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 refractory high entropy alloy was prepared by powder metallurgy and subsequently subjected to hot forging and annealing. Precipitation behavior and mechanical properties of the hotworked TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy were investigated. Results show that the hot forging leads to a formation of (Zr, Al)-rich HCP precipitates in the initial BCC matrix. The precipitates have significant strengthening effect on the TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy after annealing at 1000 °C for 2 h. Owing to the precipitation strengthening, the hot-worked TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy exhibits a high compressive yield strength of 1740 MPa with a compressive stain of 20%. It is interesting that annealing at lower or higher temperatures than 1000 °C causes a degradation in compression properties, mainly due to the decomposition of the BCC matrix and the coarsening of the HCP precipitates.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Refractory high entropy alloys (RHEAs) are a new class of multicomponent materials that have recently received much attention because of their attractive elevated-temperature mechanical properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. RHEAs are generally based on five or more refractory metals, but may also contain other low density elements, and typically have a BCC crystal structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Generally, RHEAs exhibit high strength and hardness, mainly due to solid-solution strengthening and severe lattice distortion effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Further strengthening methods of RHEAs are usually associated with alloying, work hardening, grain-boundary strengthening and precipitation strengthening. Among these strategies, precipitation strengthening is considered as the most effectively method <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>However, precipitation process of high entropy alloys is very slow due to sluggish diffusion effect. For example, the precipitation of a HCP phase in HfNbTaTiZr RHEA occurs after annealing for about 100 h <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, and the precipitation of a Cr-rich r phase in CrMnFeCoNi alloy needs an annealing time above 500 days <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Recently, it is reported that thermal mechanical processing can stimulate precipitation in high entropy alloys <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. During deformation, crystalline defects such as vacancies, dislocations and stacking faults formed, promoting diffusion and leading to an earlier formation of precipitates <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Besides, hot deformation can eliminate casting defects and refine microstructures, and thus, improve mechanical properties of RHEAs. But up to now, there is very few research focusing on precipitation behavior of hotworked RHEAs. In this work, a TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 RHEA was prepared by powder metallurgy and subsequently subjected to hot forging and annealing. The precipitation behavior and its effects on mechanical properties were analyzed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental procedure</head><p>The as-sintered TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy was prepared by powder metallurgy. The details of preparation process have been reported in our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Samples with a diameter of 30 mm and a height of 45 mm were machined from the as-sintered bulks, and then underwent hot forging at 1200 °C. The columnar samples were put in stainless steel cans to avoid severe oxidation during hot forging. The total height reduction is about 50%. After hot forging, the samples were annealed in vacuum at 600 °C $ 1200 °C for 2 h.</p><p>The phase analysis was performed by X-ray diffraction analyses (XRD, Advance D8) with Cu Ka radiation. The microstructures were observed by using a scanning electron microscope (SEM, Helios Nanolab G3 UC). The chemical composition was analyzed by energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDX). Specimens for SEM and EPMA were prepared from longitudinal cross-sections of the deformed samples. The details of microstructures were studied by using a transmission electron microscope (TEM, Titan G2 60-300). Specimens for TEM were prepared by using focused ion beam (FIB) apparatus. Compression tests were conducted on a hydraulic testing machine (Instron 8802) with a strain rate of 0.001 s À1 . Cylindrical specimens with dimension of 6 mm in diameter and 9 mm in height were used for compression tests.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head><p>The XRD patterns of the TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy in different status are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. The as-sintered alloy presents a BCC single phase structure. The lattice parameter of the BCC phase is determined to be 3.355 Å. A second phase with HCP crystal structure can be found after hot forging and subsequent annealing. Fig. <ref type="figure">1b</ref> is the enlarged area of 30 $ 45 degree range of the XRD patterns. It should be noted that the BCC phase decomposes into BCC and BCC2 phases after annealing at 800 °C for 2 h. Similar decomposition behavior has been reported in RHEAs subjected to hot deformation at 800 °C <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows the microstructures of the TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy. The single phase structure of the as-sintered TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy is confirmed by the SEM observation (Fig. <ref type="figure">2a</ref>). After hot forging, precipitates can be clearly found. The precipitates were identified as (Zr, Al)-rich phase (analyzed by EDX). Accompanied with the precipitation, a slight dynamic recrystallization (DRX) is also found. The alloy almost retained the hot-worked microstructures after annealing at 600 °C. But, annealing at 800 °C leads to a significant decomposition of the BCC matrix. The matrix transformed to single BCC phase when annealing at high temperatures (&gt;1000 °C), however, the precipitates became coarser at higher annealing temperatures. The details of the precipitates were investigated by TEM as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. The grain size of the precipitates is about 1 lm.</p><p>The crystal structures of the precipitates (HCP) and DRX grains (BCC) are further verified by selected-area electron diffraction (SAED) as show in Fig. <ref type="figure">3c</ref> and<ref type="figure">d</ref>. The BCC2 phase is plate-like with a size of about 50 nm, and is enriched in Ta and Nb.</p><p>According to the binary diagrams and the enthalpy of mixing between each two elements in Ti-Nb-Ta-Zr-Al system, Ta and Nb can form a BCC solid-solution phase at both low and high temperatures, while Zr and Al has a strong trend to form intermetallic phases <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>. As mentioned above, annealing at intermediate temperatures or thermal mechanical processing can stimulate precipitation in high entropy alloys. Therefore, the (Zr, Al)-rich HCP precipitates and the BCC2 phase could form either during hot forging or annealing. In addition, the HCP precipitates form continuous phase along grain boundaries with annealing temperatures increasing from 600 °C to 800 °C. But, when annealing at temperatures above 1000 °C, the precipitates become discontinuous again. This phenomenon is associated with the reversible wetting behavior, which has been also observed in a Cu-In system <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. The formation of the network of brittle HCP phase may lead to limited ductility of the RHEA <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>The compressive curves of the TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. The alloy is brittle after hot forging or annealing at 600 °C, possibly due to the insufficiently recrystallized microstructures. The alloy shows high yield strength after annealing at 800 °C, but, still has limited plasticity, because of the brittleness of the decomposed matrix. Apparently, annealing at 1000 °C for 2 h results in the best compression properties. The yield strength is 1740 MPa with a total strain of about 20%. In this condition, the precipitates are fine and distribute homogenously, while the matrix has been fully recrystallized with a single BCC solid solution. Annealing at higher temperature causes a degradation in both strength and plasticity. The coarsening of the HCP precipitates is responsible for the degraded properties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusion</head><p>Precipitation behavior and compression properties of the hotworked TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy were investigated. The as-sintered alloy has a single BCC phase structure. The hot forging leads to a formation of (Zr, Al)-rich HCP precipitates. Owing to the precipitation strengthening, the hot-worked TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy exhibits a high compressive yield strength of 1740 MPa with a total stain of 20% after annealing at 1000 °C for 2 h. Annealing at lower or higher temperatures than 1000 °C causes a degradation in compression properties, mainly due to the decomposition of the BCC matrix and the coarsening of the HCP precipitates.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Contents lists available at ScienceDirectMaterials Lettersj o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / m l b l u e</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. XRD patterns of the TiNbTa 0.5 ZrAl 0.5 alloy: (a) XRD patterns in different status; (b) the enlarged area of 30 $ 45 degree.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,73.70,299.34,454.30,176.49" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="3,92.24,67.92,397.13,298.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Y.Cao  et al. / Materials Letters 246 (2019) 186-189</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This work was supported by the <rs type="funder">National Natural Science Foundation of China</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">51671217</rs>), the <rs type="funder">Project of Innovation for Postgraduate of Hunan Province</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">CX2017B047</rs>), and the <rs type="funder">Special Funds for Future Industrial Development of Shenzhen, China</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">HKHTZD20140702020004</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Y2GrhCC">
					<idno type="grant-number">51671217</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_B4zzZCs">
					<idno type="grant-number">CX2017B047</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_X6cWp9X">
					<idno type="grant-number">HKHTZD20140702020004</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p>The authors declared that they have no conflicts of interest to this work.</p><p>We declare that we do not have any commercial or associative interest that represents a conflict of interest in connection with the work submitted.  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1758" to="1765" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dahmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Mater. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">563</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="546" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="448" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloy. Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">776</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="428" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Tseng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Poplawsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scripta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Otto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dlouhy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">´</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Pradeep</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kube ˇnová</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Raabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Juan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloy. Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">624</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Stepanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Yurchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Zherebtsov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">211</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Straumal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kogtenkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Kolesnikova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JETP Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="535" to="539" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Straumal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Kucheev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Efron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Eng. Perform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="667" to="670" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
