<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Strengthening mechanisms and microstructural evolution of ductile refractory medium-entropy alloy Hf 20 Nb 10 Ti 35 Zr 35</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_a36aptB">
					<orgName type="full">High Entropy Materials Center</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Wallace Academic Editing</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_Mh3gs5X">
					<orgName type="full">Higher Education Sprout Project of the Ministry of Education (MOE)</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Scripta</forename><surname>Materialia</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">I-An</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30 0 044</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ko-Kai</forename><surname>Tseng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30 0 044</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jien-Wei</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
							<email>jwyeh@mx.nthu.edu.tw</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30 0 044</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">High Entropy Materials Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30 0 044</postCode>
									<settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Badr</forename><surname>El-Sayed</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Petroleum Marine Services Co</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="EG">Egypt</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Materials Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Graduate Studies and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Alexandria University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="EG">Egypt</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chia-Heng</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mechanical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Taiwan Ocean University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>202301</postCode>
									<settlement>Keelung</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Shing-Hoa</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<email>shwang@email.ntou.edu.tw</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Mechanical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Taiwan Ocean University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>202301</postCode>
									<settlement>Keelung</settlement>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Strengthening mechanisms and microstructural evolution of ductile refractory medium-entropy alloy Hf 20 Nb 10 Ti 35 Zr 35</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8D63A23F2AD232A9A3C183CFDCED282E</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.scriptamat.2021.114225</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 18 July 2021 Accepted 17 August 2021</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-09-11T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>X-ray diffraction (XRD) Refractory metals Plastic deformation Phase transformations Entropy alloy</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>A metastable β-type medium-entropy refractory alloy, Hf20Nb10Ti35Zr35, was designed to have a ductile BCC structure in the as-solution-treated state. The alloy was aged to achieve the combinations of strength and ductility. The strengthening mechanisms included transformation-induced plasticity, twinning-induced plasticity and precipitation strengthening. These multiple strengthening mechanisms can serve as a basis for alloy design and the improvement of the mechanical properties of alloys.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In 2004, Yeh et al. proposed the concept of high-entropy alloys (HEAs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> . Since then, many HEAs have been designed and studied, such as refractory HEAs, eutectic HEAs, high-entropy superalloys, and high-entropy bulk metallic glasses <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> . In 2010, Senkov and Miracle first reported the creation of refractory HEAs MoNbTaW and MoNbTaVW <ref type="bibr">[ 3 , 4 ]</ref>. These two alloys possess bodycentered cubic (BCC) structures and excellent high-temperature yield strength of approximately 400 MPa at 1600 °C. However, they are extremely dense ( ρ = 13.76 and 12.36 g/cm 3 , respectively), and their room-temperature compressive ductility is poor ( &lt; 1%). In 2011, the same authors established the equiatomic composition of HfNbTaTiZr, a material with a low density ( ρ = 9.94 g/cm 3 ), high compression yield strength (929 MPa), and high ductility ( ε &gt; 50%) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> . Since then, many papers on refractory HEAs have been published. Although high-entropy tends to thermodynamically enhance solid solution phases, its effect is not limited to one phase.</p><p>For example, the multielement solution-type B2, Laves, σ , and L12 phases may be formed in alloys, especially at low temperatures. Based on this understanding, a two-phase refractory alloy with high strength and ductility was prepared using metastability engineering. Ta x HfZrTi ( x = 1, 0.6, 0.5, and 0.4) medium-entropy alloys (MEAs) possessing high capacity for work hardening and high ductility were developed by exploiting transformation-induced plasticity (TRIP) during the transformation from a BCC to a hexagonal close-packed (HCP) structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> . Therefore, increasing the configurational entropy may help to design refractory alloys-HEAs or MEAs-that exhibit TRIP and therefore possess a desirable combination of strength and ductility.</p><p>In this study, TRIP, twinning-induced plasticity (TWIP), and aging treatment were utilized to improve the strength and ductility of refractory alloys. Hf, Ti, Zr were selected for preparing an equiatomic HfTiZr refractory MEA because these elements belong to the same group in the periodic table and possess similar chemical and physical properties. Moreover, for alloying, Nb ( ρ = 8.57 g/cm 3 ) was used instead of the expensive Ta ( ρ = 16.69 g/cm 3 ) to stabilize the BCC phase, and the Hf ( ρ = 13.07 g/cm 3 ) content is reduced to lower the weight and cost of the final alloy. In this manner, we designed the refractory MEA Hf 20 Nb 10 Ti 35 Zr 35 (named Nb10). Nb10 has a high strain-hardening rate in the as-solutiontreated state because of the composite strengthening mechanisms of TRIP and TWIP. After aging treatment, the alloy undergoes a special precipitation sequence involving the orthorhombic ( αʺ), ω, and α phases, which are found in a few narrow compositions of Ti alloys such as the near-β-type Ti alloys of Ti-9Mo (in at.%) and Ti-6Cr-5Mo-5V-4Al (in wt.%) <ref type="bibr">[ 7 , 8 ]</ref>. This is closely related to the variation in tensile strength and ductility. The aforementioned phenom-ena are discussed to providing a design route for refractory MEAs and HEAs with excellent mechanical properties.</p><p>Nb10 was prepared in a water-cooled copper crucible by vacuum arc melting, and its ingots were remelted four or more times to achieve chemical homogeneity. The purity of each alloying element was &gt; 99.99%. The rectangular small cast ingots were coldrolled until their thickness was reduced by 65%. Thereafter, specimens cut from the strip were subjected to rapid heat treatment (RHT) at 900 °C for 1 min in a furnace and subsequently to water quenching to obtain recrystallized fine grains. The specimens were then sealed in a vacuum quartz tube to prevent oxidation. The specimens were then aged at 400 °C for 12 h, 450 °C for 1, 12, 18, 24 and 36 h, and 500 °C for 15 min and 1, 3, 6, and 12 h.</p><p>For microstructural investigation, the specimens were ground, polished, and etched with a solution composed of 3% HF + 10% H 2 NO 3 + H 2 O. The etched samples were placed in a scanning electron microscope (SEM) (model JSM-IT100, Jeol) to observe their microstructures and any precipitates. The various constituent phases were identified by using X-ray diffractometry (XRD) (model D2 PHASER, Bruker) and varying the scanning angle from 20 °to 100 °at a scanning rate of 4 °/min. Electrolytic polishing was performed to avoid any deformation effects arising from grinding and polishing before electron backscatter diffraction (EBSD) observations. An immersed area of 15-25 mm 2 was electrochemically polished at -20 to -10 °C with a voltage of -25 V for 15-20 s in a perchloric acid-methanol (1:9) solution. A Zeiss Supra 55 SEM equipped with an Oxford AZtechHKL for EBSD and operated at 20 kV was used for crystallography.</p><p>Hardness tests were conducted using a Vickers hardness tester (Mitutoyo 810-420 HV-114) with a loading of 5 kg. Tensile tests were conducted using an Instron 4468 machine with a strain rate of 10 -3 s -1 , and the Young's moduli of the specimens were measured by attaching them to a 10-mm extensometer. Dog-boneshaped tensile test specimens with gauge length of 20 mm, thickness of 1.5 mm, and width of 3 mm were prepared through wire electrical discharge machining.</p><p>The as-cast s Nb10 alloy exhibited a unique BCC structure in the XRD analyses, as depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> . The HCP + BCC mixed crystalline structure was formed after the specimens were coldrolled to a 65% reduction in thickness. This indicated that part of the material in the BCC phase was transformed to the HCP structure through martensitic transformation during deformation. A previous study reported deformation-induced phase transformation from the face-centered cubic (FCC) to the HCP structure at cryogenic temperatures in a FeCoCrNi HEA due to the gliding of Shockley partial dislocations on every other {111} FCC plane <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> ; the formation of the HCP phase improved the strength and workhardening rate of the material by restricting dislocation slip and accommodating plastic deformation. Similarly, in the present study, the deformation-induced phase transformation from the BCC to HCP phase may have resulted in increased strain hardening and ductility. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> illustrates only one BCC phase after 1 min of RHT at 900 °C. This indicated that the cold-rolling-induced HCP phase was completely reverted to the BCC phase.</p><p>The tensile stress-strain curve of BCC Nb10 after RHT at 900 °C for 1 min is depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2 (a)</ref>, and the material properties are listed in Table . 1 . As-solution-treated Nb10 exhibited high strain hardening and ductility. Its hardness was 252 HV5, and its tensile properties were as follows: E = 70.5 GPa, yield strength (YS) = 524 MPa, ultimate tensile strength (UTS) = 704 MPa, and elongation (EL) = 17.5%. Moreover, the strain-hardening rate versus true strain curve in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2 (b</ref>) can be divided into five stages based on slope changes. To identify the dominant mechanism in each stage, XRD pattern analyses were performed for the constituent phases. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> , Nb10 subjected to RHT at 900 °C for 1 min was composed of only the BCC phase, whereas in the deformed state after tensile testing, the material comprised both the BCC and HCP phases. This demonstrated that a strain-induced phase transformation from the BCC phase to a combination of BCC and HCP phases occurred through martensitic transformation during tensile strain. The results of the EBSD analyses are depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> . Fig.s 3 (a) and 3(b) reveal that before tensile deformation, the specimen was composed almost entirely of the BCC phase (99.4% area), with a small amount of an orthorhombic phase called αʺ martensite (yellow spots in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> . The grain size was approximately 10 μm.</p><p>After tensile deformation, a blue HCP structure was observed, as depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3 (c</ref>) and the magnified image in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3 (d)</ref>. In addition, the HCP phase was distributed uniformly throughout the matrix after tensile deformation. The magnified EBSD inverse pole Fig. <ref type="figure">(IPF</ref>) image in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> (e) reveals that half of the BCC grains, denoted by the dotted white circle in the upper left corner, were transformed into HCP laths. The orientation relationship of these circled grains was identified during the strain-induced transformation from the BCC (111) plane (blue) to the HCP (0 0 01) plane (red) from the IPF shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3 (f)</ref>. The overall phase ratio of BCC: HCP: αʺ: unresolved phase was approximately 19: 74: 3: 4. Notably, many twins appeared in the HCP grain. These are within the dotted white circle in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> (g) and indicated by the dotted black line in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3 (h</ref>). The circled grains had the same phase structure but contained parallel crystals with a misorientation of approximately 60 °. This phenomenon is attributable to the fact that the twin shear strain is 0.707 for FCC and BCC structures but only approximately 0.2 for HCP structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> . Thus, the low stress or strain induced by twinning in the HCP phase explains the ease of twin forma-  tion. Accordingly, deformation twinning tended to occur when the newly formed HCP grains were further strained.</p><p>Based on the microstructural observations, we determined the possible deformation mechanisms in the five strain-hardeningrate stages in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2 (b</ref>). The first stage was dislocation dominant. When dislocations gradually accumulated in the grains and piled up at the grain boundaries, continuous cross-slip leading to dynamic recovery occurred in the regions with higher dislocation density, causing overall softening. In the second stage, the strainhardening rate increased substantially because of the formation of the martensite HCP phase from the BCC matrix. In addition, a small amount of the αʺ orthorhombic martensite phase was formed. In the third stage, the curve exhibited a downward trend due to gradual saturation and thus a deceleration in the phase transformation from the BCC to the HCP structure. The fourth stage was a plateaulike period indicating the dominance of some hardening mechanism. This phenomenon occurred because the stress accumulated in the newly formed HCP phase reached the critical shear magnitude for triggering twin formation and result a certain amount of strain hardening. Finally, in the fifth stage, the strain-hardening rate decreased until fracture because of the dynamic dislocation recovery that occurred as the deformation-induced phase transformation and twin formation reached their limits. In brief, the composite action of the TRIP and TWIP effects was observed in the deformation of Nb10.</p><p>All of the XRD patterns and phase analysis results of the Nb10 aged at 400 °C (12 h), 450 °C (1, 12, 18, 24, 30, and 36 h), and 500 °C (15 min and 1, 3, 6, and 12 h) are presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> and summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> . The Ti 2 ZrO structure was determined to be in the ω phase on the basis of the JCPDS (Joint Committee on Powder Diffraction Standards) database entry for Ti 2 ZrO. The crystal had an ordered hexagonal structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> . The intensity of the ω phase was strong in the specimens treated at 400 °C (12 h), 450 °C (1, 12, 18, 24, 30, and 36 h), and 500 °C for 15 min and 1 h, and the specimen treated at 500 °C for 15 min exhibited asymmetrical peaks, with the left shoulder contributed by the early transition structure of the ω phase called embryonic ω <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> . However, the ω phase was not found for the specimens treated at 500 °C for 3, 6, and 12 h. Instead, the HCP phase ( α phase) was observed in the specimens treated at 450 °C (1, 12, 18, 24, 30, and 36 h) and 500 °C for 1, 3, 6, and 12 h. This demonstrated that the ω phase was formed at temperatures lower than 500 °C. Through up to 36 h at 450 °C, a large portion of the structure was in the ω phase in addition to some formed α phase. However, the ω phase almost disappeared and was replaced by the α phase after treatment at 500 °C for 3 h.</p><p>In addition, a comparison of the specimens treated at 400 °C for 12 h, 450 °C for 1 h, and 500 °C for 1 h revealed that no α phase was formed at 400 °C (12 h). This revealed the precipitation sequence of the present alloy: from a supersaturated BCC ( β) phase to the ω phase and then to the HCP ( α) phase. In addition, the transformation rate increased as the temperature increased.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref> shows the SEM images of the specimens treated at 500 °C for 15 min and for 1 and 3 h. Fine and dense spheroids of ω phase were dispersed in the matrix of the specimen treated for 15 min.</p><p>The particle size was approximately 0.06 μm. The ω phase (light gray) coarsened to a particle size of approximately 0.29 μm, and α particles measuring approximately 0.2 × 0.4 μm were formed in platelets in the specimen treated at 500 °C for 1 h. The ω phase was mostly replaced by α platelets in the specimen treated at 500 °C for 3 h; the platelets coarsened to a size of approximately 0.2 × 0.8 μm. According to a previous study, α particles tend to nucleate at the interface between the ω phase and β matrix and then digest the ω phase <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> . Li et al. studied the phase transformations in the near-β Ti alloy Ti-6Cr-5Mo-5V-4Al (in wt.%) and found that the O-rich regions present at the ω/ β interface were hot spots for α formation <ref type="bibr">[ 7 , 8 ]</ref>. In addition, the compositional partitioning of solutes in the ɷ and α phases indicated that the transformation from ɷ to α involved rapid lattice reconstruction at the ω/ α interface.  Summarizing from the observation of phase evolution, we could depict the TTT curves for the present alloy, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5 (d)</ref>.</p><p>The concluding remark is as follows, the α'' martensite with orthorhombic structure is formed in small amount by water quenching from high-temperature solution treatment firstly, and the following-up aging treatment at different temperatures causes sequential precipitates, ω and α phases. The phase transformation with increasing time evolves: supersaturated β + small amount α''</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">martensite → β + ω → β + α + ω → β + α.</formula><p>The mechanical properties of the specimens aged at 450 °C for 36 h and 500 °C for 15 min and 1, 3, and 12 h were obtained from the stress-train curve in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> (a) and are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> .</p><p>The specimen aged at 450 °C for 36 had a hardness of 346 HV5 and the following tensile properties: E = 104.6 GPa, YS = 1031 MPa, UTS = 1085 MPa, and EL = 3%. Compared with that of the specimen just after RHT discussed in Section 3.2, the E value was approximately 50% higher, YS was nearly doubled, and EL correspondingly decreased. As mentioned in the section 3.3, this state had a three-phase composite microstructure. The considerable strengthening was related to the fine ω and α precipitates dispersed in the β matrix, whereas the considerable stiffening was related to the decreased volume fraction of the low-Young's-modulus β phase and increased interfaces between the ω and β phases and between the α and β phases. The peak hardness of the specimen aged at 500 °C for 15 min was 312 HV5, and its E , YS, UTS, and EL were 90.3 GPa, 952 MPa, 984 MPa, and 2%, respectively; these values are inferior to those of the specimen aged at 450 °C for 36 h. This is reasonable because the specimen aged at 450 °C for 36 h state already contained α precipitates, whereas that aged at 500 °C for 15 min only contained ω phase. The specimen aged at 500 °C for 12 h had a hardness value of 274 HV5 and the following tensile properties: E = 88.6 GPa, YS = 855 MPa, UTS = 892 MPa, and EL = 6%. The mechanical properties improved with the aging time because, although a little strength was sacrificed, the EL increased by several times. Because the precipitates were mainly of the α phase in the specimens treated for 3, 12, and 36 h, the transformation of ω precipitates to α precipitates was beneficial for improving the ductility of the material. Therefore, longer aging to obtain α precipitates is the key to obtain a desirable combination of mechanical properties. MPa, UTS = 1085 MPa, and EL = 3%. The combination of mechanical properties improved with the aging time. The specimen treatment at 500 °C for 36 h had the following properties: hardness = 274 HV5, E = 88.6 GPa, YS = 855 MPa, UTS = 892 MPa, and EL = 6%. Prolonged aging transformed ω precipitates into α precipitates, which was beneficial for improving the ductility of the material. 4 Nb10 was designed to have a ductile BCC structure in the assolution-treated state and to form fine precipitates after aging under various conditions. The strengthening mechanisms included the TRIP and TWIP effects in deforming the β phase and precipitation strengthening induced by aging treatment. These multiple strengthening mechanisms could provide a basis for alloy design and the improvement of the mechanical properties of similar refractory alloys.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. XRD patterns of various states of Nb10.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,324.12,56.76,216.00,345.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. (a) Engineering stress-strain curve and (b) strain-hardening rate-true strian curve of single β-phase sample subjected to RHT at 900 • C for 1 min and water quenched.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,55.13,193.82,216.00,320.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. EBSD results of Nb10 specimen after RHT. (a) Phase map before tensile test showing recrystallized BCC structure, (b) enlarged phase map, (c) phase map after tensile test, (d) enlarged phase map after tensile test, (e) IPF image showing that (111)BCC transformed into (0 0 01)HCP after tensile test, (f) orientation map of BCC and HCP phases after tensile test, (g) phase map showing twin formation after tensile test, and (h) IPF image after tensile test (only HCP displayed).</figDesc><graphic coords="4,103.13,84.26,388.56,600.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. XRD patterns of specimens subjected to different aging treatments: (a) 450 °C for 1, 12, 18, 24, 30, and 36 h; (b) 500 °C for 15 min, 1, and 3 h; (c) 500 °C for 3, 6, and 12 h; and (d) comparison of specimens treated at 400 °C for 12 h, 450 °C for 1 h, and 500 °C for 1 h.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,55.13,57.22,216.00,177.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>1Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. SEM microstructures of specimens subjected to different aging treatments: (a) 500 °C for 15 min, (b) 500 °C for 1 h, and (c) 500 °C for 3 h. (d) TTT curves and related processes for Nb10. Line 1: RHT + 400 °C for 12 h; Line 2. RHT + 500 °C for 15 min; Line 3: RHT + 500 °C for 1 h; Line 4. RHT + 500 °C for 3 h.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,117.62,476.73,360.00,243.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Mechanical properties (E, YS, UTS, EL, and HV 5 ) and phases of Nb10 samples subjected to different processing conditions.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Treatments</cell><cell>E (GPa)</cell><cell>YS (MPa)</cell><cell>UTS (MPa)</cell><cell>El (%)</cell><cell>HV5</cell><cell>Phase</cell></row><row><cell>RHT (900 °C/min)</cell><cell>70.5</cell><cell>524</cell><cell>704</cell><cell>17.5</cell><cell>252</cell><cell>BCC + α''</cell></row><row><cell>RHT + 400 °C/12h</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>470</cell><cell>BCC + α'' + ω</cell></row><row><cell>RHT + 450 °C/1h</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>397</cell><cell>BCC + ω+ α</cell></row><row><cell>RHT + 450 °C/36h</cell><cell>104.6</cell><cell>1031</cell><cell>1085</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>346</cell><cell>BCC + ω+ α</cell></row><row><cell>RHT + 500 °C/15min</cell><cell>90.3</cell><cell>952</cell><cell>984</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>312</cell><cell>BCC + embryonic ω</cell></row><row><cell>RHT + 500 °C/1h</cell><cell>91.6</cell><cell>877</cell><cell>913</cell><cell>4.5</cell><cell>270</cell><cell>BCC + ω+ α</cell></row><row><cell>RHT + 500 °C/3h</cell><cell>88.8</cell><cell>844</cell><cell>883</cell><cell>8.7</cell><cell>275</cell><cell>BCC + α</cell></row><row><cell>RHT + 500 °C/12h</cell><cell>88.6</cell><cell>855</cell><cell>892</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>274</cell><cell>BCC + α</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This work was financially supported by the <rs type="funder">High Entropy Materials Center</rs> under the <rs type="programName">Featured Areas Research Center Program</rs> within the framework of the <rs type="funder">Higher Education Sprout Project of the Ministry of Education (MOE)</rs> and by the project <rs type="grantNumber">MOST 109-2634-F-007-024</rs> of the <rs type="funder">Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan</rs>. This manuscript was edited by <rs type="funder">Wallace Academic Editing</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_a36aptB">
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">Featured Areas Research Center Program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Mh3gs5X">
					<idno type="grant-number">MOST 109-2634-F-007-024</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Declaration of Competing Interest</head><p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Shun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tsau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Eng. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="303" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cham, Switzerland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Liaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1758" to="1765" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intermetallics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="706" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Senkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Senkova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Miracle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Woodward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alloys Compd</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">509</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6043" to="6048" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>An</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1701678</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Stephenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Ceguerra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ringer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dargusch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cairney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Mater</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="366" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kolli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A. Devaraj, Metals</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">506</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>An</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mater. Res. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Reed-Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Abbaschian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Comp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Boston</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">853</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hickman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mater. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="554" to="563" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
